<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Project syndicate</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://github.com/c4droid/" />
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/C4droid/rss/main/atom.xml"/>
  <updated>2021-08-28T16:25:56+08:00</updated>
  <id>https://github.com/c4droid/rss</id>
  <author>
     <name>linkong</name>
     <uri>http://github.com/c4droid</uri>
  </author>

  <entry>
    <title>Free Trade Can’t Bring Peace</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/onpoint/dangerous-myth-that-free-trade-brings-peace-by-benn-steil-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/onpoint/dangerous-myth-that-free-trade-brings-peace-by-benn-steil-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-14T00:00:30+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-14T00:00:30+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default onpoint" data-url="dangerous-myth-that-free-trade-brings-peace-by-benn-steil-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="6916fd785066fcca0d0a6bb0" data-entity-link-name="dangerous-myth-that-free-trade-brings-peace-by-benn-steil-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/onpoint/dangerous-myth-that-free-trade-brings-peace-by-benn-steil-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/onpoint/dangerous-myth-that-free-trade-brings-peace-by-benn-steil-2025-11" title="Free Trade Can’t Bring Peace"><span class="u-tos">Free Trade Can’t Bring Peace</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/8137f546f148f372206b4775756354f8.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/8137f546f148f372206b4775756354f8.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/8137f546f148f372206b4775756354f8.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/8137f546f148f372206b4775756354f8.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="onpoint/dangerous-myth-that-free-trade-brings-peace-by-benn-steil-2025-11">Free Trade Can’t Bring Peace</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 14, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="benn-steil" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/benn-steil" data-language="english" href="columnist/benn-steil">Benn Steil </a>
shows that globalization always depended on global security, not the other way around.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default onpoint" data-url="dangerous-myth-that-free-trade-brings-peace-by-benn-steil-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="6916fd785066fcca0d0a6bb0" data-entity-link-name="dangerous-myth-that-free-trade-brings-peace-by-benn-steil-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/onpoint/dangerous-myth-that-free-trade-brings-peace-by-benn-steil-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/onpoint/dangerous-myth-that-free-trade-brings-peace-by-benn-steil-2025-11" title="Free Trade Can’t Bring Peace"><span class="u-tos">Free Trade Can’t Bring Peace</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/8137f546f148f372206b4775756354f8.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/8137f546f148f372206b4775756354f8.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/8137f546f148f372206b4775756354f8.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/8137f546f148f372206b4775756354f8.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="onpoint/dangerous-myth-that-free-trade-brings-peace-by-benn-steil-2025-11">Free Trade Can’t Bring Peace</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 14, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="benn-steil" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/benn-steil" data-language="english" href="columnist/benn-steil">Benn Steil </a>
shows that globalization always depended on global security, not the other way around.        </p>
</header>
</li>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="3849ea48f52246e98b6cd44fe6c56427"> NEW YORK – In his <a href="https://archive.org/details/the-memoirs-of-cordell-hull-volume-one-1948/page/n5/mode/2up">1948 memoirs</a>, Cordell Hull wrote that during his 12 years as US President Franklin D. Roosevelt’s secretary of state, he was guided by the idea that “unhampered trade dovetailed with peace.” Tariff walls and battle lines rose together, he believed; tear down the first, and the second would fall. </p><p data-line-id="9d5d0f65cb2542a28c8002e047d3dbb2"> Hull’s conviction that commerce fosters peace reflected a venerable liberal tradition stretching back to the 18th-century German philosopher Immanuel Kant and the 19th-century British politician Richard Cobden. In his 1795 book <a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/50922/50922-h/50922-h.htm"><em>Perpetual Peace</em></a><em>, </em>Kant argued that republics bound by trade and law would naturally forswear war, while Cobden, a free-trade evangelist, held that economic interdependence rendered armed conflict materially ruinous and therefore irrational. US President Woodrow Wilson, who had lectured on Kant as a professor at Princeton University, carried this idealist notion into the 20th century. </p><p data-line-id="314b456180b34f53b4dc025644e8e47a"> Faith in the pacifying effects of commerce became political orthodoxy in the United States following passage of the Reciprocal Trade Agreements Act of 1934. Drafted by Hull, the bill reversed decades of Republican protectionism dating back to 1890. In the wake of the Smoot-Hawley Tariff Act of 1930 and the retaliatory spiral it provoked, it seemed almost self-evident that tariffs bred wars, and that free trade would therefore bring peace. </p><p data-line-id="9827a29285cd4d39ad196d7f70d4fbf3"> The geopolitical case for free trade, however, rested on little more than wishful thinking. To be sure, Tennesseans like Hull, who decried the harm that Northern manufacturing tariffs inflicted on Southern farm exports, had legitimate economic reasons to champion freer markets. But in reality, the causal arrow points in the opposite direction. It is peace that makes trade possible – a crucial distinction for understanding both globalization and its current retreat. </p><div data-classes="newsletter--bg newsletter--yellow newsletter--branding newsletter--compact newsletter--label newsletter--admin" data-consent="true" data-description="Every Thursday in PS Economics, we offer a concise selection of essential reading on the most important issues related to economics and finance." data-label="Sign up for our weekly newsletter, PS Economics" data-link-name="newsletter-economics" data-newsletter="prosyn-economics-newsletter" data-newsletter-subscribe-form="true"></div><p data-line-id="c94e1b2cc190491ea113d061a0166194"> Consider Britain’s ascent to imperial dominance in the 17th and 18th centuries. Its naval and colonial expansion was accompanied by mercantilist policies designed to draw in bullion to finance wars and suppress foreign competition. The Navigation Act of 1651 restricted trade to English ships and ports; colonial monopolies such as the East India Company consolidated imperial control; and tariffs, together with production “bounties,” like those paid under the Corn Laws of 1815, reinforced the system. </p><p data-line-id="1beb56e4b233456c9b70c061bc9b97e8"> Only after Britain established uncontested control of the seas did mercantilism lose its appeal. By the mid-19th century, the country needed cheap food and raw materials and sought new markets for its manufactures. Low tariffs and reciprocal trade agreements complemented new policies, such as the gold standard, that made London the world’s financial center. Britain’s ability to impose “peace” thus paved the way for its embrace of free trade. </p><p data-line-id="f9242859142c46bf80ad1573ec887dd7"> The US found itself in a similar position after the end of World War II. As the new global hegemon, it had both the power and the incentive to promote free trade and monetary stability, using low tariffs and fixed exchange rates to expand markets for its mass-produced goods. </p><p data-line-id="a09c1d516f8e4974becf5016e9261b37"> The result was the creation of the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade, designed to reduce import barriers, and the International Monetary Fund, established to stabilize currencies and stop competitive devaluations. The ensuing <em>Pax Americana</em> seemed to validate Hull’s belief that economic nationalism had caused the geopolitical breakdown of the 1930s. In fact, it had been one of its symptoms.  </p><p data-line-id="57f9513b201b406ebe70288311e0ed91"> Had the US not provided its trading partners with security guarantees, most notably through NATO, the postwar revival of trade and investment would never have been possible. Both France and the United Kingdom had initially resisted American efforts to promote European economic integration through the Marshall Plan, insisting that national self-sufficiency was necessary in the absence of US protection. The so-called liberal order was thus not spontaneous but deliberately constructed by the US and sustained by its military and monetary dominance. </p><h2 data-line-id="c86a3adb60204f779377c4232517765e"><strong>The Hull Doctrine’s Demise</strong></h2><p data-line-id="515a679424be48e6910b3b26241c7923"> The eras of <em>Pax Britannica</em> and <em>Pax Americana</em> revealed that peace does not come from disarmament or treaties prohibiting war, such as the 1928 Kellogg-Briand Pact, but from the presence of a global power willing and able to guarantee security. The European Coal and Steel Community, the precursor to the European Union, was founded on the premise that economic interdependence would make another continental war impossible. Europe’s postwar peace, however, rested less on markets than on American deterrence. It was an iron fist, and not an invisible hand, that safeguarded the global advance of free trade. </p><p data-line-id="ec35ce9ebc90449d8f0bd206f6a4da0d"> At the end of the Cold War, the US sought to deepen and expand trade flows further, both regionally and globally. Defending the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) in 1993, President Bill Clinton <a href="https://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/documents/remarks-signing-the-north-american-free-trade-agreement-implementation-act">argued</a> that it was as much about spreading peace as about spreading prosperity. “For this new era,” he declared, US national security “will be determined as much by our ability to pull down foreign trade barriers as by our ability to breach distant ramparts.” </p><p data-line-id="2ce4a31feebf454bbb4bd4d4cd788974"> But the connection between trade and security proved far weaker than Clinton’s rhetoric implied. Although NAFTA was followed by limited security cooperation between the US, Canada, and Mexico, that cooperation was driven largely by shared concerns over law enforcement and migration rather than by trade itself. </p>

<p data-line-id="135274bec8814819b1f9d2171fd6bc44"> The relationship between the US and China is a case in point. Between China’s accession to the World Trade Organization in 2001 and the election of avowed protectionist Donald Trump in 2016, US-China trade <a href="https://www.census.gov/foreign-trade/balance/c5700.html">increased fivefold</a>. Yet over the same period, their security relationship deteriorated amid rising tensions over China’s aggressive behavior in the South China Sea, its growing cyberespionage operations, and America’s “pivot to Asia” defense strategy. </p><p data-line-id="18266ff931f34bc89d42c0a3dfbb0049"> Sino-American ties, of course, soured further when Trump began to impose tariffs and sanctions in 2018, even as bilateral trade rose by 4%. Since then, the two countries have become economically intertwined to a degree that deeply worries both governments: China struggles to overcome its dependence on US semiconductors, while the US is scrambling to reduce its reliance on Chinese rare-earth metals. Far from easing strategic anxieties, economic interdependence has amplified them, leaving each side increasingly vulnerable to disruptions in strategically important sectors. </p><p data-line-id="995a7a2c416241c99d6d949500303796"> In short, the Hull Doctrine is dead – drowned in the South China Sea. While the liberal belief that trade raises the cost of war contains a kernel of truth, it is equally true that interdependence can just as easily breed mistrust and rivalry. </p><p data-line-id="864f43aa8c714995b4eca97d66424360"> Among Roosevelt’s contemporaries, no one understood the tension between commerce and peace better than Wendell Willkie, his 1940 Republican challenger. After visiting wartime China in 1942, Willkie pointedly <a href="https://archive.org/details/dli.ernet.527921">asked</a>: “Can we develop enormous trade relations with China ... unless today we are able to develop a joint military strategy with China?” In other words, could the US hope to expand trade without first building mutual trust? Were not the benefits of trade dependent on cooperation and a shared sense of security? </p><p data-line-id="917e9380961b4fe2ba82effaca7f9212"> Willkie also recognized how perilous it would be to integrate market economies with state-directed ones. When global prices fail to reflect supply-and-demand dynamics, they distort production and trade flows, killing off more efficient enterprises, fueling imbalances, and breeding resentment. As he <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1944/06/17/archives/revision-of-tariff-urged-by-willkie-policy-of-international.html">put it</a> in a 1944 <em>New York Times</em> article: </p><p data-line-id="e4b3aa033dea4b5ca531fe7813ee0efa"> “If after the war the industrial and commercial life of most of the countries of the world is either State-owned or controlled, then the whole problem of the survival of a free economic system, even in the United States, will be complicated. Certainly the pattern of our foreign trade policy will have to be fashioned to Government supervision, allocations and perhaps even price-fixing. For State-controlled economies can sell without regard to costs. In other words, prices can become political.” </p><p data-line-id="1f3c0a72a1b04892b540a756e96a022f"> And when anything becomes political, as the Nazi crown jurist Carl Schmitt <a href="https://www.foreignaffairs.com/guest-pass/redeem/lYvTVFkbQXE">famously observed</a>, it inevitably becomes adversarial. </p><h2 data-line-id="3860964f6a6b4c4ebd83469034d14230"><strong>No Trade Without Security</strong></h2><p data-line-id="f556774037af46d499c22498a03cfb3a"> What lessons can we draw from this history? The liberal order – and, in particular, faith in the steady expansion of global trade – was underpinned by US security guarantees. Although the Soviet Union and its satellites remained outside that system during the Cold War, they played only a marginal role in the world economy. The leading industrial powers, especially those of Western Europe and Japan, embraced liberalization under the protection of the US security umbrella. </p><p data-line-id="38acc3a7e44049b981c970e65cf44a9c"> While economic globalization accelerated after the end of the Cold War, China’s trajectory since joining the WTO has vindicated Willkie’s warning that the fusion of markets and state power would distort and politicize global prices. Rather than liberalizing, the Chinese regime used its newfound access to international markets to strengthen its state-industrial complex. </p><p data-line-id="84c09b9adc924a6eb0af76d6efc70629"> State-owned enterprises’ share of industrial output has risen sharply under President Xi Jinping, whose government directs massive amounts of capital into sectors deemed strategically vital through plans such as <a href="https://www.cfr.org/backgrounder/made-china-2025-threat-global-trade">Made in China 2025</a> and <a href="https://www.china-briefing.com/news/china-standards-2035-strategy-recent-developments-and-their-implications-foreign-companies/">China Standards 2035</a>. Meanwhile, subsidized overcapacity in steel, solar panels, and electric vehicles has turned trade itself into an instrument of geopolitical ambition. Willkie’s observation that “prices can become political” perfectly captures the current reality of global commerce. In the spirit of Clausewitz, trade has become war by other means. </p><p data-line-id="638386ba82e84df98044d093e7cb3f9f"> China’s economy today is roughly <a href="https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/NY.GDP.MKTP.CD?locations=CN">14 times larger</a> than it was when it joined the WTO, and its official defense budget has increased more than tenfold in nominal dollar terms (the real figure is likely far higher). Its growing military power, together with Russia’s revanchist ambitions and America’s profound disillusionment with the globalization project, has severely undermined the security foundation on which the liberal order rests. And even though world leaders continue to proclaim their commitment to globalization, it is far from clear that the multilateral trading system can endure without the security guarantees that sustained it. </p><p data-line-id="9837ab09ae9f4c599095e51b36fb9695"> As that foundation erodes, deglobalization will be anything but smooth. Efforts to decouple the US and Chinese economies will likely drive a surge in transshipments as exporters seek to conceal the origins of targeted products. The detection – or even the suspicion – of such practices will then trigger a cascade of new tariffs and secondary sanctions. </p><p data-line-id="6d9470996843445fb6c521b3593f6bea"> Three developments will further undermine efforts to preserve rules-based trade. The first is the growing use of “national security” exceptions at the WTO, since trade barriers justified on security grounds are treated by the US and others as beyond legal review. The second development is the continued paralysis of the WTO’s Appellate Body, which has been inquorate since 2019, owing to America’s refusal to approve new judges. Lastly, the most-favored-nation principle is being severely eroded, as more and more countries are forced to violate it in order to reach temporary trade truces with the Trump administration. </p><p data-line-id="cf9bffb89b7a42ccab7328caacffc29a"> When the Russian threat receded after 1991, Europeans convinced themselves that the project of economic and political integration championed by the EU’s architects – together with the broader drift toward liberal democracy – had rendered traditional geopolitics obsolete. But Russia’s invasion of Ukraine in 2022 revealed how completely peace had depended on the presence of the US as a security guarantor. America’s reluctance to continue in this role reflects the growing belief among its electorate that the costs of sustaining a liberal world order now outweigh the benefits. Absent a sharp change in that conviction, and an increase in the capacity of America’s postwar allies to buttress the security architecture, that order appears irretrievably lost. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How Indigenous Peoples Will Drive Progress at COP30</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/cop30-indigenous-peoples-land-protection-tenure-commitments-by-sonia-guajajara-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/cop30-indigenous-peoples-land-protection-tenure-commitments-by-sonia-guajajara-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-13T00:00:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-13T00:00:29+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="cop30-indigenous-peoples-land-protection-tenure-commitments-by-sonia-guajajara-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="6915f33b41290944d45faa58" data-entity-link-name="cop30-indigenous-peoples-land-protection-tenure-commitments-by-sonia-guajajara-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/cop30-indigenous-peoples-land-protection-tenure-commitments-by-sonia-guajajara-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/cop30-indigenous-peoples-land-protection-tenure-commitments-by-sonia-guajajara-2025-11" title="How Indigenous Peoples Will Drive Progress at COP30"><span class="u-tos">How Indigenous Peoples Will Drive Progress at COP30</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/230254b4014f29395dc83955feae1cb0.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/230254b4014f29395dc83955feae1cb0.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/230254b4014f29395dc83955feae1cb0.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/230254b4014f29395dc83955feae1cb0.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/cop30-indigenous-peoples-land-protection-tenure-commitments-by-sonia-guajajara-2025-11">How Indigenous Peoples Will Drive Progress at COP30</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 13, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="sonia-guajajara" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/sonia-guajajara" data-language="english" href="columnist/sonia-guajajara">Sonia Guajajara </a>
anticipates major breakthroughs for territorial protection and land tenure at this month’s climate conference.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="cop30-indigenous-peoples-land-protection-tenure-commitments-by-sonia-guajajara-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="6915f33b41290944d45faa58" data-entity-link-name="cop30-indigenous-peoples-land-protection-tenure-commitments-by-sonia-guajajara-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/cop30-indigenous-peoples-land-protection-tenure-commitments-by-sonia-guajajara-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/cop30-indigenous-peoples-land-protection-tenure-commitments-by-sonia-guajajara-2025-11" title="How Indigenous Peoples Will Drive Progress at COP30"><span class="u-tos">How Indigenous Peoples Will Drive Progress at COP30</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/230254b4014f29395dc83955feae1cb0.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/230254b4014f29395dc83955feae1cb0.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/230254b4014f29395dc83955feae1cb0.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/230254b4014f29395dc83955feae1cb0.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/cop30-indigenous-peoples-land-protection-tenure-commitments-by-sonia-guajajara-2025-11">How Indigenous Peoples Will Drive Progress at COP30</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 13, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="sonia-guajajara" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/sonia-guajajara" data-language="english" href="columnist/sonia-guajajara">Sonia Guajajara </a>
anticipates major breakthroughs for territorial protection and land tenure at this month’s climate conference.        </p>
</header>
</li>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="24a28a6b8d1f4391a0dd11b3c468e62b"> BELÉM – This year’s United Nations Climate Change Conference (COP30) in Belém, Brazil, has been eagerly awaited worldwide. A COP in the Amazon raises expectations for all those who recognize the urgency of climate change and its impact on our lives and environment. That is why Brazilian President <a href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/columnist/luiz-inacio-lula-da-silva">Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva</a> is calling this the “COP of Truth.” </p>
<p data-line-id="eadaf355bb6c43378c71f937a6a7cf2c"> As co-hosts for this COP, the Indigenous peoples and local communities of Brazil’s Amazon region understand what is at stake. We are among those who suffer the most from climate change, since our lives and livelihoods are directly connected to the natural ecosystems and biodiversity that global warming threatens. We are also among those who can provide some of the most powerful responses to the problem. For example, territories managed by Indigenous peoples and local communities have deforestation rates up to 50% lower than other <a href="https://www.un.org/development/desa/indigenouspeoples/wp-content/uploads/sites/19/2021/03/State-of-Worlds-Indigenous-Peoples-Vol-V-Final.pdf">areas</a>. </p>
<p data-line-id="cffbf45b510b4ceb92ab4992c0645694"> This is no accident. We are spiritually connected to nature; by relying on traditional knowledge to safeguard our territories, we also protect crucial carbon sinks and ecosystem services that benefit everyone.  </p>
<p data-line-id="426218a180b44600a8df03173721d411"> To meet the urgent goals enshrined in the Paris climate agreement, everyone must recognize the contributions of Indigenous peoples in formulating climate policies. That means recognizing territorial protection and land-tenure policies as inherently effective climate measures.  </p>
<p data-line-id="f89247fee10941029a0a8e8fe45dc2da"> Such recognition also highlights another issue. Historically, Indigenous peoples have received the fewest resources in the flow of climate and environmental finance: <a href="https://www.speciesconservation.org/blog/mbzf-backed-global-study-on-indigenous-peoples-climate-contributions-reaches-a-key-milestone/">less than 1%</a> of all funding actually reaches these territories, which is both inefficient and unjust. That is why the Brazilian government, working closely with other countries and Indigenous organizations, has gone to great lengths to ensure that COP30 benefits those who protect forests. </p>
<div data-classes="newsletter--bg newsletter--yellow newsletter--branding newsletter--compact newsletter--label newsletter--admin" data-consent="true" data-description="Go beyond the headlines to understand the issues, forces, and trends shaping the US presidential election – and the likely implications of its outcome." data-label="Sign up for our weekly newsletter, PS Politics" data-link-name="newsletter-politics" data-newsletter="prosyn-above-the-fold" data-newsletter-subscribe-form="true"></div>
<p data-line-id="1e8f6cceeafb4d70b89cf560e8f06f02"> Among the measures needed to make this a reality is the Intergovernmental Land Tenure Commitment, announced at the COP30 World Leaders Summit on November 6. The goal is to recognize and secure a predefined amount of land or territories managed by Indigenous peoples and local communities by 2030. Such a historic agreement is not only ambitious; it is also the first global commitment on land tenure. Brazil has worked with the Forest and Climate Leaders’ Partnership, a coalition of 36 governments and the European Union, to advance this vital commitment, setting the stage for COP30 to become a defining moment in the global climate agenda. </p>
<p data-line-id="1fd17c989a6a41528b523657ae7b3489"> Moreover, donor governments and philanthropic institutions will renew a 2021 <a href="https://news.mongabay.com/2025/10/cop26-forest-pledge-to-support-indigenous-local-rights-was-just-met-what-was-learned/">commitment</a> (initially made at COP26 in Glasgow) to allocate another $1.7 billion over the next five years to programs that strengthen land tenure and forests. The original commitment exceeded the initial target, and <a href="https://carbon-pulse.com/436950/">$1.86 billion</a> has already been mobilized. By renewing it, governments and civil society are signaling that they remain as committed as ever to this critical dimension of climate action. </p>
<p data-line-id="c3ef01ffd5da4659b75b7e71f11310c5"> After being announced by heads of state and government, these commitments will be formally signed on November 17 at an event showcasing the COP30 Action Agenda, a central theme of which is to achieve a “<a href="https://cop30.br/en/brazilian-presidency/cop-30-circles/global-ethical-stocktake">global ethical balance</a>.” For example, only around 10% of that $1.86 billion is estimated to have been transferred directly to Indigenous peoples and local communities. With the “Pledge 2.0,” and as part of the COP30 Action Agenda, we aim to increase this percentage substantially. Those who manage their territories more effectively deserve to manage a greater share of the resources allocated for territorial protection. </p>
<p data-line-id="dc4d63b3728b4c05bd96312aac863487"> Following the announcement at the World Leaders Summit, the land tenure and financial commitments will be officially launched at an event in the Blue Zone that I will lead on November 17. I will be joined by ministers and officials from other tropical countries, donors, philanthropic institutions, and, of course, Indigenous leaders. </p>
<p data-line-id="7bf8e29713474310892d1780b07b2540"> Moreover, these commitments will serve as the foundation for another major initiative at this COP: the launch of the Tropical Forest Forever Facility. Since Indigenous peoples and local communities are essential to guaranteeing the successful implementation of this facility, they will manage at least 20% of the funds it mobilizes.  </p>
<p data-line-id="b25c3aa3b5b14ef08e698bef40d735b2"> These are major breakthroughs, and it is important to remember that they were made possible only because Indigenous peoples and local communities have demanded a voice in decision-making processes. Participation is crucial to recognition. That is why we have a Ministry of Indigenous Peoples in Brazil, and it is why COP30 will elevate our unique voices and insights. Through my ministry, Indigenous organizations, and other partners, we are making possible the COP Village, an accommodation for three thousand Indigenous people who will be the heart of this COP.  </p>
<p data-line-id="1bf0ff3791e04de1a3b68b93c1b3dae9"> We will also have the largest number of Indigenous people in the world accredited in the Blue Zone, thanks to the COP30 presidency’s creation of a People’s Circle. By offering better forms of participation and advocacy, Brazil has created the conditions for Indigenous peoples and local communities to be heard like never before. </p>
<p data-line-id="7d3af3ae9bbf40b2905de78435fc8848"> Brazil invites all governments, donors, and development institutions to join the Intergovernmental Land Tenure Commitment and to contribute to the renewed Land and Forest Pledge. Only by working together can we protect the world’s ecosystems, strengthen land tenure and the rights of Indigenous peoples and local communities, and invest in people as the foundation for resilient development, a just transition, and lasting climate stability. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Scaling the Ocean Economy</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/how-to-unlock-financing-necessary-to-scale-the-ocean-economy-by-prince-albert-ii-of-monaco-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/how-to-unlock-financing-necessary-to-scale-the-ocean-economy-by-prince-albert-ii-of-monaco-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-13T00:00:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-13T00:00:28+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="how-to-unlock-financing-necessary-to-scale-the-ocean-economy-by-prince-albert-ii-of-monaco-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="6915fd8a41290944d49e6e2e" data-entity-link-name="how-to-unlock-financing-necessary-to-scale-the-ocean-economy-by-prince-albert-ii-of-monaco-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/how-to-unlock-financing-necessary-to-scale-the-ocean-economy-by-prince-albert-ii-of-monaco-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/how-to-unlock-financing-necessary-to-scale-the-ocean-economy-by-prince-albert-ii-of-monaco-2025-11" title="Scaling the Ocean Economy"><span class="u-tos">Scaling the Ocean Economy</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/d0807f35c311ea7975de25fdcaf0764c.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/d0807f35c311ea7975de25fdcaf0764c.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/d0807f35c311ea7975de25fdcaf0764c.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/d0807f35c311ea7975de25fdcaf0764c.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/how-to-unlock-financing-necessary-to-scale-the-ocean-economy-by-prince-albert-ii-of-monaco-2025-11">Scaling the Ocean Economy</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 13, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="prince-albert-ii-of-monaco" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/prince-albert-ii-of-monaco" data-language="english" href="columnist/prince-albert-ii-of-monaco">Prince Albert II of Monaco </a>
proposes building blocks for a coordinated strategy to deliver sustained “blue” investment.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="how-to-unlock-financing-necessary-to-scale-the-ocean-economy-by-prince-albert-ii-of-monaco-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="6915fd8a41290944d49e6e2e" data-entity-link-name="how-to-unlock-financing-necessary-to-scale-the-ocean-economy-by-prince-albert-ii-of-monaco-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/how-to-unlock-financing-necessary-to-scale-the-ocean-economy-by-prince-albert-ii-of-monaco-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/how-to-unlock-financing-necessary-to-scale-the-ocean-economy-by-prince-albert-ii-of-monaco-2025-11" title="Scaling the Ocean Economy"><span class="u-tos">Scaling the Ocean Economy</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/d0807f35c311ea7975de25fdcaf0764c.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/d0807f35c311ea7975de25fdcaf0764c.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/d0807f35c311ea7975de25fdcaf0764c.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/d0807f35c311ea7975de25fdcaf0764c.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/how-to-unlock-financing-necessary-to-scale-the-ocean-economy-by-prince-albert-ii-of-monaco-2025-11">Scaling the Ocean Economy</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 13, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="prince-albert-ii-of-monaco" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/prince-albert-ii-of-monaco" data-language="english" href="columnist/prince-albert-ii-of-monaco">Prince Albert II of Monaco </a>
proposes building blocks for a coordinated strategy to deliver sustained “blue” investment.        </p>
</header>
</li>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="d003c030d9b64e53b7eb2e55a3d31d51"> MONACO – Two major events this summer – the Blue Economy and Finance Forum (BEFF) in Monaco, and the third United Nations Ocean Conference in Nice – reflected the growing recognition that protecting the ocean is not only an environmental issue, but also a political, economic, financial, and social imperative. The challenge now is to translate this rapidly emerging consensus into concrete, sustained action. </p>
<p data-line-id="f33d82cca0914bc8a44aec0e18cb83d3"> Covering over two-thirds of our planet and accounting for 97% of its biosphere, the ocean is a critical ally in our efforts to tackle climate change, ensure food security, and support livelihoods. Without a healthy ocean, sustainable development will remain a distant dream. But protecting and restoring marine ecosystems costs money, and financial flows are falling far short of need. To close this gap, ocean protection must be regarded not as charity, but as an opportunity – a high-value investment in our collective future. </p>
<p data-line-id="4c2b4bc615c940e99fcbb31180300760"> The vision of a thriving ocean economy that offers both short-term profit and long-term value in terms of food security, employment, and resilience galvanized the political leaders, entrepreneurs, investors, philanthropists, and representatives of multilateral organizations and civil society at the BEFF. The event delivered on its goal of unlocking funding for ocean-positive projects, including through innovative instruments like blue bonds and blended-finance vehicles, which combine public, private, and philanthropic resources. It thus represented an important first step toward anchoring ocean protection where it counts: within the financial industry. </p>
<p data-line-id="b464fa7a0037435d9947718dde8c810d"> But the new “blue” investment announced by public, private, and philanthropic actors at the BEFF – amounting to some <a href="https://beff2025monaco.org/images/ANBilanBlue%20Economy%20and%20Finance%20ForumVDEF_11.06.pdf">€8.7 billion ($10.1 billion)</a> – represents only a fraction of what is needed to meet global targets. Moreover, isolated commitments, however ambitious, do not necessarily lead to <a>the sustained</a>, coordinated investment that scaling the blue economy demands. A more strategic approach, which focuses on leveraging public and philanthropic capital to de-risk investment in ocean-positive projects and attract long-term private finance, is urgently needed.  </p>
<div data-classes="newsletter--bg newsletter--yellow newsletter--branding newsletter--compact newsletter--label newsletter--admin" data-consent="true" data-description="Every Thursday in PS Economics, we offer a concise selection of essential reading on the most important issues related to economics and finance." data-label="Sign up for our weekly newsletter, PS Economics" data-link-name="newsletter-economics" data-newsletter="prosyn-economics-newsletter" data-newsletter-subscribe-form="true"></div>
<p data-line-id="bd39ba97d2114d03bbbdac8fd103568e"> Three imperatives stand out. The first is to create a robust pipeline of investable projects. As it stands, many promising initiatives remain stuck at the pilot stage. A lack of early-stage financing, technical assistance, or enabling policies means that they never get to a point where they are appealing to private investors. </p>
<p data-line-id="e7d9975eaa8f43f386a2c1bb81401b08"> Monaco is doing its part to bridge this gap. The ReOcean Fund – an ocean-focused private equity fund, co-managed by the Prince Albert II of Monaco Foundation (of which I am president) and Monaco Asset Management – has <a href="https://www.fpa2.org/en/news/successful-raise-of-73-million-dollars-for-the-reocean-fund-08499">raised</a> $73 million to invest in companies pioneering technologies that promise to advance critical goals like restoring marine ecosystems and decarbonizing shipping. But the responsibility for sustaining a pipeline of bankable projects ultimately falls to governments and development banks, which must use public finance to redefine investment risk so that it reflects the real economic returns of protecting marine ecosystems. </p>
<p data-line-id="1de5d44a4869400d8c5148f50685caad"> The second imperative is to create enabling conditions for investment. If ocean-relevant sectors – such as shipping, fisheries, coastal infrastructure, and tourism – are to align their activities with the blue-economy vision, they must be guided (and constrained) by net-zero and nature-positive targets that are ambitious and credible. Governments must not only develop and enforce the right rules of the game, including regional marine spatial plans, but also lead by example. That means eliminating poorly designed and harmful government subsidies, such as those driving exploitation of overfished stocks, and using those public resources to finance ocean-positive projects and cover transition costs for ocean-dependent sectors. With WTO Agreement Fish 1 now in force, the world has taken a historic first step toward curbing illegal, unreported, unregulated fishing and protecting vulnerable stocks, while negotiations continue over Fish 2, which will tackle overfishing capacities. </p>
<p data-line-id="10a4515255794ddf8a3ca99688f0e83e"> Public development banks must also do their part to strengthen investor confidence and catalyze market-wide change. At the BEFF, more than 20 public development banks endorsed the Finance in Common Ocean Coalition <a href="https://financeincommon.org/the-fics-ocean-coalition-releases-a-joint-statement-at-the-blue-economy-and-finance-forum-in-monaco">joint statement</a>, which articulated a collective ambition to scale up ocean finance, align portfolios with a regenerative and sustainable blue economy, and support pipeline development by sharing tools and methodologies. These institutions must follow through on these commitments, and their peers must join them. </p>
<p data-line-id="bb7571346fc24f8f83db95f86c060f54"> Finally, financial flows throughout the economy must be aligned with climate, biodiversity, and equity goals. For governments, this means integrating environmental and social externalities into public budgets, with national accounting systems factoring in both the value of ecosystem services and the financial risks arising from environmental degradation. </p>
<p data-line-id="ba9c916fad064506b1893269148bc39c"> Financial actors – including institutional investors, corporations, asset managers, and insurers – also have a critical role to play, not only as funders, but also by stepping up as core architects of a regenerative and sustainable blue economy. To this end, they must create clear taxonomies and metrics, which support consistent decision-making and prevent greenwashing. Blended-finance mechanisms and biodiversity credits and certificates can help provide the right incentives, aligning private finance with measurable sustainability outcomes. </p>
<p data-line-id="768d2f70837042889aa9de1bba80fc3d"> The ocean economy is beginning to take shape. The BEFF laid important foundations, and promising instruments – such as venture capital funds targeting ocean innovation, guarantee facilities supporting small and medium-sized enterprises dedicated to delivering ocean-positive outcomes, and sovereign blue bonds – are gaining traction. But the momentum from the summer must not be squandered. It must be translated into a clear and coordinated strategy for the decade. </p>
<p data-line-id="794275fc17fb449980e4c99b04dbf300"><em>This commentary is signed by </em><em><strong>Pascal Lamy</strong></em><em>, Co-Chair, Blue Economy and Finance Forum; </em><strong><em>H.E. Bernard Fautrier</em></strong><em>, Minister Plenipotentiary, Special Advisor to HSH the Sovereign Prince on environmental issues; </em><strong><em>Robert Calcagno</em></strong><em>, CEO, Monaco Oceanographic Institute; </em><em> </em><strong><em>Olivier Wenden</em></strong><em>, Vice-Chairman &amp; CEO, The Prince Albert II of Monaco Foundation;</em><em> </em><strong><em>Razan Al Mubarak</em></strong><em>, President, International Union for Conservation of Nature; </em><em> </em><strong><em>Dona Bertarelli</em></strong><em>, Executive Chair, Dona Bertarelli Philanthropy; </em><em> </em><strong><em>Thierry Deau</em></strong><em>, CEO, Meridiam;</em><em> </em><strong><em>Dame Amelia Fawcett</em></strong><em>, Co-Chair, International Advisory Panel on Biodiversity Credits; </em><strong><em>Sylvie Goulard</em></strong><em>, Co-Chair, International Advisory Panel on Biodiversity Credits; </em><strong><em>Pradeep Kurukulasuriya</em></strong><em>, Executive Secretary, United Nations Capital Development Fund; </em><strong><em>Sanda Ojiambo</em></strong><em>, CEO, United Nations Global Compact; </em><strong><em>Frederik Paulsen</em></strong><em>, Emeritus Chairman, Ferring; </em><strong><em>Thomas Thune Andersen</em></strong><em>, Chair, Lloyd’s Register Foundation; </em><strong><em>Célia Berche</em></strong><em>, Partnership Manager, Blue Alliance; </em><strong><em>Angelique Brathwaite</em></strong><em>, Director Science &amp; Conservation, Blue Alliance; </em><strong><em>Martin Callow</em></strong><em>, Acting Portfolio Lead – Nature Bonds, The Nature Conservancy; </em><strong><em>Alberto Cappato</em></strong><em>, Vice-President, International Association Cities and Ports; </em><strong><em>Isabelle De Cremoux</em></strong><em>, CEO, Seventure Partners; </em><strong><em>Vassilios Demetriades</em></strong><em>, Chief Strategy Officer, UW Group; </em><strong><em>Marisa Drew</em></strong><em>, Chief Sustainability Officer, Standard Chartered; </em><strong><em>Ambroise Fayolle</em></strong><em>, Vice-President, European Investment Bank; </em><strong><em>Daniela V. Fernandez</em></strong><em>, Founder &amp; CEO, Velamar; </em><strong><em>Melissa Garvey</em></strong><em>, Senior Advisor – Transformative Management &amp; Protection, The Nature Conservancy; </em><strong><em>Jean-Pierre Gattuso</em></strong><em>, Research Director, CNRS; </em><strong><em>Alfredo Giron</em></strong><em>, Head of Ocean, World Economic Forum; </em><strong><em>François Houllier</em></strong><em>, President &amp; CEO, Ifremer; </em><strong><em>Joe Kramek</em></strong><em>, President &amp; CEO, World Shipping Council; </em><strong><em>Gianpiero Leoncini</em></strong><em>, Executive Vice President, CAF – Development Bank of Latin America and the Caribbean; </em><strong><em>Nicolas Pascal</em></strong><em>, CEO, Blue Alliance; </em><strong><em>Francesco Prazzo</em></strong><em>, General Manager, SBM Offshore; </em><strong><em>Daniela Raik</em></strong><em>, Acting CEO, Conservation International; </em><strong><em>Kristin Rechberger</em></strong><em>, CEO, Dynamic Planet &amp; Revive Our Ocean; </em><strong><em>Rémy Rioux</em></strong><em>, Chairman, Finance in Common; </em><strong><em>Jean-Jacques Risso</em></strong><em>, President, Monaco Scientific Center; </em><strong><em>Karen Sack</em></strong><em>, Executive Director &amp; President, Ocean Risk and Resilience Action Alliance; </em><strong><em>James Scriven</em></strong><em>, CEO, IDB Invest.</em></p>
<p data-line-id="794275fc17fb449980e4c99b04dbf300"><em>This commentary is part of  <a data-sk="tooltip_parent" data-stringify-link="https://www.project-syndicate.org/topic/the-ocean-imperative" href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/topic/the-ocean-imperative" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">The Ocean Imperative</a>  debate, brought to you in part by The Ocean Risk and Resilience Action Alliance and AXA.</em><br/></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Turning Point for Clean Energy</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/accelerating-energy-transition-essential-to-economic-prosperity-by-agnes-dasewicz-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/accelerating-energy-transition-essential-to-economic-prosperity-by-agnes-dasewicz-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-13T00:00:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-13T00:00:27+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="accelerating-energy-transition-essential-to-economic-prosperity-by-agnes-dasewicz-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="6915f38c41290944d462e693" data-entity-link-name="accelerating-energy-transition-essential-to-economic-prosperity-by-agnes-dasewicz-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/accelerating-energy-transition-essential-to-economic-prosperity-by-agnes-dasewicz-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/accelerating-energy-transition-essential-to-economic-prosperity-by-agnes-dasewicz-2025-11" title="A Turning Point for Clean Energy"><span class="u-tos">A Turning Point for Clean Energy</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/c048b7cdf1aac36ce0acb52e1f091bd5.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/c048b7cdf1aac36ce0acb52e1f091bd5.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/c048b7cdf1aac36ce0acb52e1f091bd5.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/c048b7cdf1aac36ce0acb52e1f091bd5.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/accelerating-energy-transition-essential-to-economic-prosperity-by-agnes-dasewicz-2025-11">A Turning Point for Clean Energy</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 13, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="agnes-dasewicz" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/agnes-dasewicz" data-language="english" href="columnist/agnes-dasewicz">Agnes Dasewicz </a>
urges policymakers to build on recent progress and redouble efforts to expand access to renewables.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="accelerating-energy-transition-essential-to-economic-prosperity-by-agnes-dasewicz-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="6915f38c41290944d462e693" data-entity-link-name="accelerating-energy-transition-essential-to-economic-prosperity-by-agnes-dasewicz-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/accelerating-energy-transition-essential-to-economic-prosperity-by-agnes-dasewicz-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/accelerating-energy-transition-essential-to-economic-prosperity-by-agnes-dasewicz-2025-11" title="A Turning Point for Clean Energy"><span class="u-tos">A Turning Point for Clean Energy</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/c048b7cdf1aac36ce0acb52e1f091bd5.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/c048b7cdf1aac36ce0acb52e1f091bd5.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/c048b7cdf1aac36ce0acb52e1f091bd5.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/c048b7cdf1aac36ce0acb52e1f091bd5.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/accelerating-energy-transition-essential-to-economic-prosperity-by-agnes-dasewicz-2025-11">A Turning Point for Clean Energy</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 13, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="agnes-dasewicz" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/agnes-dasewicz" data-language="english" href="columnist/agnes-dasewicz">Agnes Dasewicz </a>
urges policymakers to build on recent progress and redouble efforts to expand access to renewables.        </p>
</header>
</li>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="c90a5bc5c2334abfb1cd75ab0f0b3478"> WASHINGTON, DC – This year marks a historic milestone: for the first time, global renewable-energy production has surpassed coal. In the first half of 2025, renewables accounted for <a href="https://ember-energy.org/latest-insights/global-electricity-mid-year-insights-2025/global-analysis/">more than 34%</a> of the world’s electricity, while coal’s share fell to just above 33%. Notably, these gains were largely driven by emerging economies. </p><p data-line-id="b683da6a2990429a8fb63a49d6f12e18"> As the world’s attention turns to the United Nations Climate Change Conference in Brazil (COP30), this milestone serves as a powerful reminder that the clean-energy transition is already underway. Having led investments at the US International Development Finance Corporation and now serving as chief investment officer at the Global Energy Alliance for People and Planet, I know a promising business opportunity when I see one.  </p><p data-line-id="2b2fd1f87363409aa6f9c5c2f6bf8bf4"> According to the International Renewable Energy Agency (IRENA), <a href="https://www.irena.org/News/pressreleases/2025/Jul/91-Percent-of-New-Renewable-Projects-Now-Cheaper-Than-Fossil-Fuels-Alternatives">91% of new renewable-energy projects</a> are now cheaper than their fossil-fuel counterparts. This finding provides clear evidence that, despite the <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2025/oct/22/global-use-of-coal-hit-record-high-in-2024">ongoing growth</a> in coal and oil use, renewables are both economically and technically viable throughout much of the world. </p><p data-line-id="e076b008dff7475bb5aafa597e398444"> We cannot afford to let today’s momentum slip away. </p><p data-line-id="77be2c69b72b464483331d01d56f58ed"> To reduce climate pollution, promote sustainable economic growth, and strengthen energy resilience where it is needed most, we must build on these achievements. As we approach the tenth anniversary of the Paris climate agreement, meaningful global climate action is still possible, even in the face of escalating geopolitical tensions and competing national priorities. </p><div data-classes="newsletter--bg newsletter--yellow newsletter--branding newsletter--compact newsletter--label newsletter--admin" data-consent="true" data-description="Every Thursday in PS Economics, we offer a concise selection of essential reading on the most important issues related to economics and finance." data-label="Sign up for our weekly newsletter, PS Economics" data-link-name="newsletter-economics" data-newsletter="prosyn-economics-newsletter" data-newsletter-subscribe-form="true"></div><p data-line-id="590dc0d4fbc24a05a5c3425c32f397f2"> Yet such progress is inherently fragile. All too often, clean-energy adoption stalls once the infrastructure is in place. Solar projects, for example, can <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/01/27/climate/africa-world-bank-solar-electricity.html">fail</a> when communities lack the necessary tools and financing to make full use of the electricity they produce.  </p><p data-line-id="dab5f5f65cb744239dea984a7ab7bcc7"> Providing solar panels is not enough. To lock in the benefits of renewables, governments must invest not only in power generation but also in systems, training, and equipment – such as electric mills and water pumps – that enable communities and countries to harness clean energy for business growth and job creation. </p><p data-line-id="67ecf75476db48668f04b1999473b840"> When implemented effectively, such investments deliver benefits across the board. Climate goals advance as renewables replace costly, polluting fuels. Communities gain access to affordable power, enabling them to improve education and health care, create jobs, and raise incomes. And with energy companies profiting from rising demand, emerging economies can <a href="https://www.reuters.com/sustainability/climate-energy/why-our-clean-energy-future-depends-emerging-economies--ecmii-2025-09-18/">attract new investment</a>.  </p><p data-line-id="edc7abef78534a79ab2425e938cbd7b6"> The challenge is enormous, but so is the opportunity. The World Bank projects that <a href="https://www.devcommittee.org/content/dam/sites/devcommittee/doc/documents/2025/Final_DC2025-0002.pdf">1.2 billion young people</a> in developing economies will reach working age over the next decade, but that only 420 million new jobs will be created by then. Access to clean energy, and the opportunities it brings, offers a way to bridge this gap before it becomes a global crisis. The World Economic Forum <a href="https://www.weforum.org/stories/2023/07/investment-emerging-economies-energy-transition">estimates</a> that the renewables industry alone could generate <a href="https://www.weforum.org/publications/the-future-of-jobs-report-2023/in-full/2-drivers-of-labour-market-transformation/">more than 30 million jobs</a> and mobilize $2.2-2.8 trillion annually. Embedding renewable technologies into other downstream sectors such as industry and agriculture could create <a href="https://www.rockefellerfoundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/Transforming-a-Billion-Lives-The-Job-Creation-Potential-from-a-Green-Power-Transition-in-the-Energy-Poor-World.pdf">a further 500 million new jobs</a> and improve the quality of 700 million existing ones. </p><p data-line-id="b3d1c1e16ae9431d809b268d431e0277"> To succeed, we must align energy policies with broader development objectives, integrate renewables into local industries, and accelerate investment in the equipment and training needed to use it effectively.  </p><p data-line-id="a98d519e906b4c1e9fec6980e86971d9"> Across Africa, this approach is already delivering tangible results. In Nigeria, farmers and traders are increasingly using solar-powered irrigation pumps, cold-storage facilities, and mills. These investments, in turn, have fueled a <a href="https://issuu.com/geapp/docs/global_energy_alliance_2025_impact_report/90">wave of distributed renewable-energy projects</a> that are rapidly transforming local power systems.  </p><p data-line-id="12d0e0b09f134a1e9d485bfe11a8f3b3"> In the Amazon, where COP30 is underway, the government of Brazil is investing $800 million to expand energy access and transition away from reliance on diesel. My organization is <a href="https://energyalliance.org/brazil/">helping</a> to ensure that this new renewable energy creates jobs and powers sustainable economic development for thousands of farmers and entrepreneurs.  </p><p data-line-id="9d446d1c88e441b5916de1116299a0aa"> India offers a useful model for emerging economies seeking to strengthen their power grids and absorb growing renewable capacity. In New Delhi, the country’s first <a href="https://www.devex.com/news/this-battery-storage-fix-offers-a-blueprint-for-systems-level-solutions-110853">commercial, utility-scale battery-energy storage system</a> – the largest in South Asia – now guarantees a reliable supply of clean electricity to 100,000 low-income households and businesses. Meanwhile, solar plants in Rajasthan provide steady daytime power to 40,000 farmers. And in Uttar Pradesh, a women’s entrepreneurship program aims to help 500,000 women-owned businesses adopt clean-energy technologies by 2030. </p><p data-line-id="49a0740bed5649d68d265a6cde18f0fb"> Together, these examples show that the clean-energy transition is within reach. But with <a href="https://www.who.int/news/item/12-06-2024-progress-on-basic-energy-access-reverses-for-first-time-in-a-decade">685 million people</a> worldwide lacking electricity, and more than a billion relying on unaffordable or unreliable supply, there is still a long way to go.  </p><p data-line-id="07d66246906c493591e5797a175eb737"> The choice before us is clear: continue investing in renewables or slide back into fossil-fuel dependence. By making clean energy the foundation for job creation and economic opportunity, we can turn today’s milestones into a future where clean power drives growth and ensures prosperity for all. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How to Measure Climate Progress</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/measure-climate-progress-in-lives-improved-by-gernot-wagner-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/measure-climate-progress-in-lives-improved-by-gernot-wagner-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-13T00:00:26+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-13T00:00:26+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="measure-climate-progress-in-lives-improved-by-gernot-wagner-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="6915e08b41290944d4f7e7b5" data-entity-link-name="measure-climate-progress-in-lives-improved-by-gernot-wagner-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/measure-climate-progress-in-lives-improved-by-gernot-wagner-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/measure-climate-progress-in-lives-improved-by-gernot-wagner-2025-11" title="How to Measure Climate Progress"><span class="u-tos">How to Measure Climate Progress</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a9a3938065e6f1c4ed3b549dbf62e95f.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a9a3938065e6f1c4ed3b549dbf62e95f.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a9a3938065e6f1c4ed3b549dbf62e95f.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a9a3938065e6f1c4ed3b549dbf62e95f.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/measure-climate-progress-in-lives-improved-by-gernot-wagner-2025-11">How to Measure Climate Progress</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 13, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="gernot-wagner" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/gernot-wagner" data-language="english" href="columnist/gernot-wagner">Gernot Wagner </a>
thinks tackling the problem is justified on social and economic grounds, not existential ones.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="measure-climate-progress-in-lives-improved-by-gernot-wagner-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="6915e08b41290944d4f7e7b5" data-entity-link-name="measure-climate-progress-in-lives-improved-by-gernot-wagner-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/measure-climate-progress-in-lives-improved-by-gernot-wagner-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/measure-climate-progress-in-lives-improved-by-gernot-wagner-2025-11" title="How to Measure Climate Progress"><span class="u-tos">How to Measure Climate Progress</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a9a3938065e6f1c4ed3b549dbf62e95f.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a9a3938065e6f1c4ed3b549dbf62e95f.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a9a3938065e6f1c4ed3b549dbf62e95f.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a9a3938065e6f1c4ed3b549dbf62e95f.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/measure-climate-progress-in-lives-improved-by-gernot-wagner-2025-11">How to Measure Climate Progress</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 13, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="gernot-wagner" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/gernot-wagner" data-language="english" href="columnist/gernot-wagner">Gernot Wagner </a>
thinks tackling the problem is justified on social and economic grounds, not existential ones.        </p>
</header>
</li>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="803af9d4ef1d492dbe147e74c7a22f01"> NEW YORK – Try putting yourself in <a href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/columnist/bill-gates">Bill Gates</a>’s shoes. You could spend your days on what made you one of the world’s richest people while also deploying your wealth to do the most good. You could invest in for-profit ventures pursuing things like clean-energy breakthroughs, or in effecting changes in policy. And to mark your 70th birthday, you could publish an essay that would quickly become a global news story. </p><p data-line-id="8596414728b2426ebefbbac21e4c6cd5"> Gates has done it all. His essay, “<a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/home/home-page-topic/reader/three-tough-truths-about-climate">Three Tough Truths About Climate</a>,” sent a shockwave through the climate movement on the eve of this year’s United Nations Climate Change Conference (COP30) in Belém, Brazil. But the essay is less blueprint than Rorschach test, because anyone can selectively quote from its 5,000 words to support a wide variety of viewpoints. </p><p data-line-id="037f7cd06aee4fbc9a3a071ae25f25fd"> Like many such documents, this one begins with a strawman. In a move more typical of the Breakthrough Institute, a California-based group founded on the premise that environmentalism harms the climate cause, Gates rejects the “doomsday” argument that “nothing matters more than limiting the rise in temperature.” Little does – but Gates chose to go with “nothing,” a much stronger word. </p><p data-line-id="9c4b22c37a5f4c189966267642b4665c"> He then argues that climate change, though a “serious” problem, “will not be the end of civilization.” But supercharged storms and other climate-driven disasters are already upending lives and livelihoods. Of the five recorded storms severe enough to warrant the proposed “<a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/does-hurricane-melissa-show-its-time-for-a-category-6-designation/">category 6</a>” classification, all have happened in the past 15 years. </p><p data-line-id="87fd6f8c7d8d48cb91d52d0368dd9521"> Moreover, we are not dealing only with massive, headline-grabbing extremes and <a href="http://www.gwagner.com/tipping-economics">global tipping points</a> (irreversible planetary changes). There are also the pernicious, often hidden “<a href="https://press.princeton.edu/books/hardcover/9780691221038/slow-burn">slow burn</a>” effects, like the <a href="https://gwagner.com/hle">0.04% loss</a> in annual payroll for one additional day above 32°C (90°F) in any given year. Such costs add up quickly. To point out that we can still live with average global warming <a href="https://business.columbia.edu/insights/climate/investment-decarbonization-trillions-climate-costs">below 3°C</a> is hardly reassuring, especially for the poor and vulnerable who already suffer the most. </p><div data-classes="newsletter--bg newsletter--yellow newsletter--branding newsletter--compact newsletter--label newsletter--admin" data-consent="true" data-description="Every Thursday in PS Economics, we offer a concise selection of essential reading on the most important issues related to economics and finance." data-label="Sign up for our weekly newsletter, PS Economics" data-link-name="newsletter-economics" data-newsletter="prosyn-economics-newsletter" data-newsletter-subscribe-form="true"></div><p data-line-id="afea525eb5294f3d822b61f71c73fcf4"> Gates’s reasoning on this socioeconomic dimension is understandable. His second and third tough truths focus on human suffering and prosperity, and these are indeed the criteria against which climate progress should be measured. Annual greenhouse-gas emissions, their atmospheric concentrations, the resulting warming, and effects like rising seas and more devastating storms are all ultimately proxies for lives that will be disrupted or even ended prematurely. </p><p data-line-id="a292d52f9fba402a8a6d3747c8200cb8"> Climate change kills. Economists can now calculate the <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-021-24487-w">mortality cost of carbon</a>. Each ton of CO<sub>2</sub> emitted today kills around 0.0002 people. Again, such costs can add up quickly. The lifetime emissions generated by every 3.5 Americans today will kill one person by the end of the century. </p><p data-line-id="5a84976b6fcd4877979596f787721a6e"> True, many people already die from other preventable causes. Gates himself has called out US President Donald Trump’s administration for cutting aid funding in ways that will <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/culture/the-new-yorker-documentary/the-shutdown-of-usaid-has-already-killed-hundreds-of-thousands">kill children</a> in some of the poorest parts of the world. In an effort to make up for some of the shortfall with his own foundation and personal wealth, Gates <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/03/12/climate/bill-gates-breakthrough-energy-cuts.html">has reduced his giving</a> for climate programs and investments, both in the US and globally. </p><p data-line-id="19bd406446e94130b513ae094ed5cf3d"> No one doubts that there are only so many philanthropic dollars to go around. But climate finance goes well beyond charity, as Gates shows by his own actions. His own total <a href="https://www.axios.com/2025/11/04/climate-bill-gates-memo">public health and climate funding have increased</a> over time. “Funding,” in this case, includes support for Breakthrough Energy (which has no relation to the Institute), which has invested in more than 150 companies that need help scaling up climate technologies by driving down the “<a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/introducing-the-green-premiums">green premium</a>” (the added costs of low-carbon technologies relative to high-carbon ones that pay nothing for their negative externalities). </p><p data-line-id="81f276dfe091491d8bb1569f5d093b2f"> Reducing this premium is necessary for many early-stage startups that have yet to climb the learning curve and benefit from economies of scale. Fortunately, there are plenty of other climate technologies that are already in the money. Solar power’s rapid growth over the past half-decade is the result of economics, not benevolence. The same goes for battery prices, which have <a href="https://business.columbia.edu/insights/climate/energy-storage">fallen by about 50%</a> since 2010. </p><p data-line-id="169ccd29f02242df87ebcd09e120ccb2"> While other low-carbon technologies still command a green premium, most are <a href="https://www.mckinsey.com/capabilities/sustainability/our-insights/what-would-it-take-to-scale-critical-climate-technologies">trending toward profitability</a>. Still, we need creative thinking to help them get there. Co-production helps. A company focused on a single product might lose against incumbents, but spreading the green premium across two or more products can cut costs significantly. The Gates-funded company Brimstone, for example, focuses both on <a href="https://gwagner.com/ft-cement">producing lower-carbon cement</a> and on making money from the alumina extracted in the production process. <a href="http://gwagner.com/years-sublime">Sublime</a>, a rival cement startup, is pursuing a similar strategy. (I recently co-authored a <a href="https://gwagner.com/coproduction">study</a> with Brimstone’s CEO, Cody Finke, and a half-dozen colleagues, including an employee of another Gates-funded venture, on precisely this point.) </p><p data-line-id="2c7d9abc8948446092ad6d7a01f708b9"> Patience helps, too. Back when Canadian Prime Minister Mark Carney was the governor of the Bank of England, he poignantly described the climate as a “<a href="https://www.bankofengland.co.uk/speech/2015/breaking-the-tragedy-of-the-horizon-climate-change-and-financial-stability">tragedy of the horizon</a>.” Too many businesses feel compelled to focus on short-term earnings, just as political leaders are unable to think beyond election cycles. But some of Gates’s climate investments, like those in the <a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/work/accelerate-energy-innovation/reader/the-future-of-energy-is-subatomic">next-generation nuclear</a> company TerraPower, and especially his investments in Commonwealth Fusion, are deliberately structured to yield returns years or even decades from now. </p><p data-line-id="77f97b353b024e5dafc93fc082fda226"> Supportive policies help, such as the explicit carbon prices and <a href="https://climate.ec.europa.eu/eu-action/climate-strategies-targets/2040-climate-target_en">decarbonization targets</a> in the European Union, or the <a href="https://business.columbia.edu/insights/climate/one-big-beautiful-bill-setback-clean-energy">subsidies</a> that are more prominent in the United States. The key, in each case, is to provide long-term investment certainty. This is an area where Gates’s essay is especially weak. While Gates fully recognizes the importance of policy, he has created an opening for those, like Trump, who put their personal, <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-11-05/why-the-us-economy-might-benefit-from-abandoning-clean-energy-goals">short-term gain</a> first. </p><p data-line-id="fac84665a9fe48e18baf04b99c503c9b"> But make no mistake: the benefits of shifting away from fossil fuels far outweigh the costs. Gates clearly understands that. Clean energy is about <a href="https://news.un.org/en/story/2025/07/1165460">sovereignty, energy security, equity</a>, and, yes, future competitiveness. Ending reliance on oil, coal, and gas, and embracing technologies that will only become better and cheaper over time, is not just smart climate policy. It is the best way to improve economic competitiveness and human prosperity for decades to come. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Trump’s Foreign Economic Policy in Disarray</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/argentina-and-china-show-disarray-of-trump-foreign-economic-policy-by-barry-eichengreen-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/argentina-and-china-show-disarray-of-trump-foreign-economic-policy-by-barry-eichengreen-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-12T00:00:25+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-12T00:00:25+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="argentina-and-china-show-disarray-of-trump-foreign-economic-policy-by-barry-eichengreen-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="6914addec97bf942c7d69d66" data-entity-link-name="argentina-and-china-show-disarray-of-trump-foreign-economic-policy-by-barry-eichengreen-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/argentina-and-china-show-disarray-of-trump-foreign-economic-policy-by-barry-eichengreen-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/argentina-and-china-show-disarray-of-trump-foreign-economic-policy-by-barry-eichengreen-2025-11" title="Trump’s Foreign Economic Policy in Disarray"><span class="u-tos">Trump’s Foreign Economic Policy in Disarray</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/61acba3822cf2a6dcbbd28bf9ab7b964.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/61acba3822cf2a6dcbbd28bf9ab7b964.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/61acba3822cf2a6dcbbd28bf9ab7b964.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/61acba3822cf2a6dcbbd28bf9ab7b964.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/argentina-and-china-show-disarray-of-trump-foreign-economic-policy-by-barry-eichengreen-2025-11">Trump’s Foreign Economic Policy in Disarray</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 12, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="barry-eichengreen" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/barry-eichengreen" data-language="english" href="columnist/barry-eichengreen">Barry Eichengreen </a>
says that in Argentina and China, the US has created two problems of its own making.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="argentina-and-china-show-disarray-of-trump-foreign-economic-policy-by-barry-eichengreen-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="6914addec97bf942c7d69d66" data-entity-link-name="argentina-and-china-show-disarray-of-trump-foreign-economic-policy-by-barry-eichengreen-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/argentina-and-china-show-disarray-of-trump-foreign-economic-policy-by-barry-eichengreen-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/argentina-and-china-show-disarray-of-trump-foreign-economic-policy-by-barry-eichengreen-2025-11" title="Trump’s Foreign Economic Policy in Disarray"><span class="u-tos">Trump’s Foreign Economic Policy in Disarray</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/61acba3822cf2a6dcbbd28bf9ab7b964.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/61acba3822cf2a6dcbbd28bf9ab7b964.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/61acba3822cf2a6dcbbd28bf9ab7b964.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/61acba3822cf2a6dcbbd28bf9ab7b964.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/argentina-and-china-show-disarray-of-trump-foreign-economic-policy-by-barry-eichengreen-2025-11">Trump’s Foreign Economic Policy in Disarray</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 12, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="barry-eichengreen" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/barry-eichengreen" data-language="english" href="columnist/barry-eichengreen">Barry Eichengreen </a>
says that in Argentina and China, the US has created two problems of its own making.        </p>
</header>
</li>
<div id="archive" style="margin: 20px; font-weight: bold; color:red;">Full article text:
 | <a href="https://archive.is?run=1&amp;url=https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/argentina-and-china-show-disarray-of-trump-foreign-economic-policy-by-barry-eichengreen-2025-11" target="_blank">archive.is</a></div>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary paywall english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="b609e6e5cfc04cf38eeed81bbf076aea"> MANCHESTER – When it comes to US foreign economic policy, President Donald Trump’s administration has two problems on its hands. Following what has become something of a pattern for this administration, both problems are of its own making. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Key to Unlocking Private Climate Finance</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/private-climate-finance-requires-policy-certainty-by-lynn-forester-de-rothschild-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/private-climate-finance-requires-policy-certainty-by-lynn-forester-de-rothschild-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-12T00:00:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-12T00:00:24+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="private-climate-finance-requires-policy-certainty-by-lynn-forester-de-rothschild-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="69148d90c97bf942c762e791" data-entity-link-name="private-climate-finance-requires-policy-certainty-by-lynn-forester-de-rothschild-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/private-climate-finance-requires-policy-certainty-by-lynn-forester-de-rothschild-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/private-climate-finance-requires-policy-certainty-by-lynn-forester-de-rothschild-2025-11" title="The Key to Unlocking Private Climate Finance"><span class="u-tos">The Key to Unlocking Private Climate Finance</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/985746892da40ba06638ff0c739308f2.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/985746892da40ba06638ff0c739308f2.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/985746892da40ba06638ff0c739308f2.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/985746892da40ba06638ff0c739308f2.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/private-climate-finance-requires-policy-certainty-by-lynn-forester-de-rothschild-2025-11">The Key to Unlocking Private Climate Finance</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 12, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="lynn-forester-de-rothschild" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/lynn-forester-de-rothschild" data-language="english" href="columnist/lynn-forester-de-rothschild">Lynn Forester de Rothschild </a>
urges international policymakers to ensure that the net-zero transition benefits workers and communities.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="private-climate-finance-requires-policy-certainty-by-lynn-forester-de-rothschild-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="69148d90c97bf942c762e791" data-entity-link-name="private-climate-finance-requires-policy-certainty-by-lynn-forester-de-rothschild-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/private-climate-finance-requires-policy-certainty-by-lynn-forester-de-rothschild-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/private-climate-finance-requires-policy-certainty-by-lynn-forester-de-rothschild-2025-11" title="The Key to Unlocking Private Climate Finance"><span class="u-tos">The Key to Unlocking Private Climate Finance</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/985746892da40ba06638ff0c739308f2.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/985746892da40ba06638ff0c739308f2.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/985746892da40ba06638ff0c739308f2.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/985746892da40ba06638ff0c739308f2.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/private-climate-finance-requires-policy-certainty-by-lynn-forester-de-rothschild-2025-11">The Key to Unlocking Private Climate Finance</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 12, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="lynn-forester-de-rothschild" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/lynn-forester-de-rothschild" data-language="english" href="columnist/lynn-forester-de-rothschild">Lynn Forester de Rothschild </a>
urges international policymakers to ensure that the net-zero transition benefits workers and communities.        </p>
</header>
</li>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="6822b0a9d9f645a1a67f6840fac66a1e"> LONDON – The United Nations Climate Change Conference (COP30), now underway in Brazil, marks a decade since 195 parties adopted the landmark Paris climate agreement at COP21. But what should be a moment of celebration is instead being overshadowed by rising uncertainty: the climate-finance gap still amounts to <a href="https://unfccc.int/news/from-billions-to-trillions-setting-a-new-goal-on-climate-finance">trillions of dollars</a>, while support among the developed countries for climate action is fracturing. </p><p data-line-id="eb5c4554993c48f687f8eec2e6367639"> The transition to a low-carbon global economy cannot succeed without the active participation of the private sector, yet businesses and investors are reluctant to commit funds amid uncertainty and instability. Above all, markets need predictability: coherent policy frameworks, clearly defined priority sectors, and practical strategies for managing the financial, environmental, and social risks. </p><p data-line-id="34a307d24aa944879780748e1f49e5c4"> The predictability and stability that investors and markets require, however, remain out of reach. The International Energy Agency has <a href="https://www.iea.org/news/promising-new-technologies-face-market-uncertainty-in-pivotal-moment-for-global-energy-innovation">warned</a> that policy uncertainty has stalled the development and usage of many promising clean-energy technologies that are ripe for scaling up. Excluding AI, venture-capital funding for energy innovation <a href="https://www.iea.org/reports/the-state-of-energy-innovation/executive-summary">declined</a> across sectors in 2023 and 2024. Meanwhile, most countries still lack the policy and investment mechanisms needed to mobilize private capital at scale. </p><p data-line-id="347f63bffcf34424a30931fef7c2d97b"> While tighter financial conditions and policy uncertainty play a major role, they are only part of the problem. A deeper, often overlooked reason for the slow pace of progress is that the global climate movement has largely failed to focus on the people most affected by the energy transition: workers, consumers, and local communities. </p><p data-line-id="aab6bbd009b443d1b086186935f021bc"> From its very inception, the <a href="https://www.inclusivecapitalism.com/">Council for Inclusive Capitalism</a> (which I lead) has argued that major economic transitions provide companies and investors with a unique opportunity to build a more inclusive society. Inspired by the late Pope Francis’s <a href="https://www.vatican.va/content/francesco/en/encyclicals/documents/papa-francesco_20150524_enciclica-laudato-si.html">call</a> to “hear both the cry of the earth and the cry of the poor,” we established a partnership with energy-intensive companies and investors to develop a framework for a <a href="https://www.inclusivecapitalism.com/just-energy-transition-home/">just climate transition</a>. </p><p data-line-id="0d90eabba43c4ff3871d27960c3b7c93"> Created in collaboration with BP, Reliance, the California Public Employees’ Retirement System, State Street, and others, this framework places people at the heart of the energy transition. It emphasizes universal access to clean energy, decent jobs that provide pathways for retraining and reskilling, support for local communities, and the need to strengthen supply chains. It also recognizes that investors’ capital-allocation strategies must align with these priorities through meaningful stakeholder engagement and sharing of best practices. </p><p data-line-id="224c98979fbe4b58a23fb16b5d1ddef0"> Together with the energy transition, the AI revolution is set to reshape labor markets. To this end, we co-hosted a <a href="https://www.inclusivecapitalism.com/unga-80-climate-week-2025/">meeting</a> with World Bank President <a href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/columnist/ajay-banga">Ajay Banga</a> at the recent UN Climate Week in New York to discuss how to learn from the mistakes of past transitions and ensure that no one is left behind. </p><p data-line-id="4da1854df1b545a69996894d3be336b1"> Turning ambition into action requires achievable national strategies. When implemented effectively, nationally determined contributions can serve as more than just climate pledges – they can guide investment and act as roadmaps for economic transformation. Brazil provides a useful model: a <a href="https://www.oecd.org/en/publications/investing-in-climate-for-growth-and-development_16b7cbc7-en.html">joint report</a> by the OECD and the UN Development Programme touts the country’s National Bank for Economic and Social Development as a leader in creating innovative financial instruments capable of attracting private capital at scale. </p><p data-line-id="ca81660fb7824eef8ccf5fa2e463447b"> Other emerging markets are also <a href="https://www.iea.org/news/global-renewable-capacity-is-set-to-grow-strongly-driven-by-solar-pv">making strides</a>. Wind and solar power are expanding rapidly across Asia, the Middle East, and Africa, with India on track to become the world’s <a href="https://etedge-insights.com/industry/energy/india-takes-giant-leap-to-become-worlds-second-largest-renewable-energy-market-by-2030-iea-report/">second-largest renewable-energy market</a> after China. For developing countries, <a href="https://www.inclusivecapitalism.com/news-insights/2025-steering-committee-meeting/">inclusive growth</a> is not a slogan but a socioeconomic imperative, particularly when it comes to ensuring access to energy and critical infrastructure. </p><p data-line-id="93976b0f0a5b4a96b0bd7bd9aef4936c"> Developed economies face a different set of challenges. In the United States, about 40% of energy and technology projects announced under former US President <a href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/columnist/joseph-biden-jr">Joe Biden</a>’s industrial and climate policies were already <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/afb729b9-9641-42b2-97ca-93974c461c4c">experiencing delays</a> even before President Donald Trump’s return to the White House. At the same time, rising energy costs are <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/ce32r5k43vwo">jeopardizing</a> the United Kingdom’s net-zero transition, while European manufacturers struggle to cut CO<sub>2</sub> emissions and stay profitable in a global market increasingly dominated by Chinese firms. </p><p data-line-id="5dcac16330fb42a392b930c20a72a6cc"> Even so, there are reasons for cautious optimism. Although Trump withdrew the US from the Paris agreement, energy affordability and AI competitiveness remain top national priorities. Institutional investors and private capital have both the means and the incentive to back emerging technologies – including carbon-free, scalable nuclear energy – that can sustain AI growth without driving up utility costs. </p><p data-line-id="9ffd97bb64624c649d91c194eee16faf"> The dozens of world leaders in Brazil for COP30 are meeting at a critical juncture. To build a just and sustainable future, we must bridge the divide between governments, financial institutions, civil society, and the private sector. Only by focusing on workers, communities, and consumers can we translate national targets into tangible progress that protects both people and the planet. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Halting Africa’s Deforestation</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/cop30-must-adopt-more-comprehensive-strategy-to-stop-deforestation-africa-by-hippolyte-fofack-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/cop30-must-adopt-more-comprehensive-strategy-to-stop-deforestation-africa-by-hippolyte-fofack-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-12T00:00:23+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-12T00:00:23+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="cop30-must-adopt-more-comprehensive-strategy-to-stop-deforestation-africa-by-hippolyte-fofack-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="69136844fb07afa2ca853813" data-entity-link-name="cop30-must-adopt-more-comprehensive-strategy-to-stop-deforestation-africa-by-hippolyte-fofack-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/cop30-must-adopt-more-comprehensive-strategy-to-stop-deforestation-africa-by-hippolyte-fofack-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/cop30-must-adopt-more-comprehensive-strategy-to-stop-deforestation-africa-by-hippolyte-fofack-2025-11" title="Halting Africa’s Deforestation"><span class="u-tos">Halting Africa’s Deforestation</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1c4d47d9ac1257448e075eb4a696ce04.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1c4d47d9ac1257448e075eb4a696ce04.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1c4d47d9ac1257448e075eb4a696ce04.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1c4d47d9ac1257448e075eb4a696ce04.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/cop30-must-adopt-more-comprehensive-strategy-to-stop-deforestation-africa-by-hippolyte-fofack-2025-11">Halting Africa’s Deforestation</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 12, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="hippolyte-fofack" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/hippolyte-fofack" data-language="english" href="columnist/hippolyte-fofack">Hippolyte Fofack </a>
calls for a commitment at COP30 to boosting crop yields and building sustainable cities on the continent.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="cop30-must-adopt-more-comprehensive-strategy-to-stop-deforestation-africa-by-hippolyte-fofack-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="69136844fb07afa2ca853813" data-entity-link-name="cop30-must-adopt-more-comprehensive-strategy-to-stop-deforestation-africa-by-hippolyte-fofack-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/cop30-must-adopt-more-comprehensive-strategy-to-stop-deforestation-africa-by-hippolyte-fofack-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/cop30-must-adopt-more-comprehensive-strategy-to-stop-deforestation-africa-by-hippolyte-fofack-2025-11" title="Halting Africa’s Deforestation"><span class="u-tos">Halting Africa’s Deforestation</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1c4d47d9ac1257448e075eb4a696ce04.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1c4d47d9ac1257448e075eb4a696ce04.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1c4d47d9ac1257448e075eb4a696ce04.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1c4d47d9ac1257448e075eb4a696ce04.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/cop30-must-adopt-more-comprehensive-strategy-to-stop-deforestation-africa-by-hippolyte-fofack-2025-11">Halting Africa’s Deforestation</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 12, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="hippolyte-fofack" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/hippolyte-fofack" data-language="english" href="columnist/hippolyte-fofack">Hippolyte Fofack </a>
calls for a commitment at COP30 to boosting crop yields and building sustainable cities on the continent.        </p>
</header>
</li>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="5fe51840c7a445e7a6d112dbcc1340c8"> WASHINGTON, DC – The international community is quick to highlight Africa’s development challenges and failures, often citing the continent’s limited progress on poverty reduction and climate action. </p>
<p data-line-id="945fc1e49d43480080419484efce9fca"> Consider the persistent focus on Africa’s massive climate-finance gap, estimated at around <a href="https://www.climatepolicyinitiative.org/publication/climate-finance-needs-of-african-countries/">$2.8 trillion</a> between 2020 and 2030, and its unsustainable debt burden, with Sub-Saharan Africa (SSA) now <a href="https://drgr.org/news/paying-for-the-past-or-investing-in-the-future-africas-debt-and-climate-dilemma/">spending more</a> on debt service than it receives in climate finance. Much attention has also been devoted to African countries’ disappointing progress toward the United Nations Sustainable Development Goals. The continent is on track to achieve <a href="https://sdg.iisd.org/news/report-makes-recommendations-to-accelerate-sdgs-in-africa-agenda-2063/">only 6%</a> of the 32 measurable SDG targets by 2030. </p>
<p data-line-id="6f5adafbf89b4547b1b0bab5b82a7b2e"> But these challenges are compounded by the lack of international development support. Nowhere is the gap between rhetoric and action more evident than in efforts to achieve <a href="https://sdgs.un.org/goals/goal15">SDG 15</a>, which aims to protect, restore, and promote the sustainable use of terrestrial ecosystems, including by combating deforestation. From 2010 to 2020, Africa had the world’s <a href="https://www.fao.org/interactive/forest-resources-assessment/2020/en/">largest annual rate of net forest loss</a>, averaging 3.9 million hectares. Given the scale of the problem, the UN Climate Change Conference (COP30) in Belém must adopt a more proactive and comprehensive strategy to prevent deforestation and curb related environmental risks. </p>
<p data-line-id="3beece83c58f45a1b1fe1b3765389077"> A wide array of proven interventions – many seen as beyond the realm of climate policy – could protect millions of hectares of forest in Africa each year, especially in the Congo Basin, one of the most essential global commons. Home to the world’s <a href="https://www.worldbank.org/en/news/press-release/2025/10/20/congo-basin-forests-hold-trillions-in-untapped-value-new-report-calls-for-strategic-global-investment">second-largest tropical rainforest</a>, the Congo Basin absorbs nearly <a href="https://www.unep.org/news-and-stories/story/critical-ecosystems-congo-basin-peatlands">1.5 billion tons</a> of carbon dioxide annually and is a biodiversity hotspot, with roughly <a href="https://www.worldwildlife.org/places/congo-basin/">10,000 species of tropical plants</a>, 30% of which are unique to the region. </p>
<div data-classes="newsletter--bg newsletter--yellow newsletter--branding newsletter--compact newsletter--label newsletter--admin" data-consent="true" data-description="Every Thursday in PS Economics, we offer a concise selection of essential reading on the most important issues related to economics and finance." data-label="Sign up for our weekly newsletter, PS Economics" data-link-name="newsletter-economics" data-newsletter="prosyn-economics-newsletter" data-newsletter-subscribe-form="true"></div>
<p data-line-id="53102ab4d2a0497bb2b4f76e04b24bde"> Preserving the Congo Basin is especially important because the insatiable global demand for Africa’s natural resources has decimated the continent’s forests. This process began in the 19th and early 20th centuries, as European imperial powers exported timber and cleared vast swaths of old-growth forest for cash crops such as cocoa, coffee, palm oil, tea, and rubber. It has continued and even intensified in recent years, driven by demographic pressures and rising Asian demand for raw materials. As a result, tropical Africa has lost <a href="https://www.chathamhouse.org/2023/05/deforestation-africa">around 22%</a> of its forested area since 1900 – comparable to the more widely publicized losses in the Amazon. </p>
<p data-line-id="70dfd877e3e34059acd921e9cbdb6258"> Deforestation is fast approaching a tipping point in the Congo Basin. Between 2002 and 2024, the Democratic Republic of the Congo, which contains <a href="https://www.rainforestfoundationuk.org/our-projects/where-we-work/drc/">about 60%</a> of the Congo Basin rainforest, lost <a href="https://www.globalforestwatch.org/dashboards/country/COD/">7.4 million hectares</a> of humid primary forest, which accounted for 36% of its total tree cover loss. If current deforestation rates persist, large portions of the Congo Basin <a href="https://www.forestsnews.org/79903/over-a-quarter-of-congo-basin-forests-at-risk-of-vanishing-by-2050">could disappear</a> by 2050, with dire consequences for global climate stability. </p>
<p data-line-id="ea15ae50fd644a079ab8039fac5a14b6"> Importantly, the world’s insatiable appetite for Africa’s natural resources is not the only driver of deforestation. Subsistence farming and increased housing demand, especially in rapidly growing urban areas, have also led to large-scale land-clearing, owing mainly to low agricultural productivity and poor territorial planning. </p>
<p data-line-id="bfc65c66b1034cf3a7f343d1ac9fe480"> In many African countries, crop yields reach <a href="https://news.unl.edu/article/yield-gap-study-highlights-potential-for-higher-crop-yields-in-africa">only 20-30%</a> of their potential because of the lack of irrigation (currently less than 5% of cultivated land in SSA is irrigated), sparse use of fertilizers and high-quality seed varieties, and <a href="https://www.ifpri.org/blog/feeding-africa-how-small-scale-irrigation-can-help-farmers-change-game/">inadequate access to technology</a>. To meet the nutrition needs of a fast-growing population that is expected to reach <a href="https://www.imf.org/en/Publications/fandd/issues/2023/09/PT-african-century">2.5 billion</a> by 2050, farmers often compensate for low crop yields by clearing more land and resorting to reduced fallow periods. </p>
<p data-line-id="c10f725c89cb47f8945726440ecddab2"> Unplanned urbanization is equally harmful. Poor housing standards and the proliferation of low-quality single-family homes that lack basic amenities have triggered urban sprawl. Many African cities – from Lagos and Douala to Kinshasa and Kibera – are <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0264837722000060">growing out, not up</a>, with millions of hectares of forest cleared to make room for such dwellings. Compounding these pressures is the fact that <a href="https://www.intechopen.com/chapters/72270">more than 70%</a> of households in SSA still use wood for cooking and heating, leading to even more environmental degradation. This amplifies the negative long-term effects that poor urban planning has on the climate. </p>
<p data-line-id="ac5278e45c364b1faba5d502ffaffd8d"> Although world leaders declared their commitment to halting and reversing forest loss and land degradation at <a href="https://www.ciwem.org/news/cop26-100-world-leaders-commit-to-halt-and-reverse-forest-loss-by-2030">previous COPs</a>, deforestation in Africa continues to outpace restoration efforts, including those by the <a href="https://www.wri.org/initiatives/african-forest-landscape-restoration-initiative-afr100">African Forest Landscape Restoration Initiative</a> and the <a href="https://www.unccd.int/our-work/ggwi">Great Green Wall Initiative</a>. And the European Union’s <a href="https://environment.ec.europa.eu/topics/forests/deforestation/regulation-deforestation-free-products_en">regulation on deforestation-free products</a>, while a worthy endeavor, is unlikely to fix the imbalance. </p>
<p data-line-id="10037d07f17e4fbdadfcc40c1bf82f6b"> That is because focusing solely on the rainforest is not sufficient to save it. Investments that boost agricultural productivity, raise housing standards, and improve territorial planning – with an emphasis on compact, upward growth rather than urban sprawl – are essential to preserve the Congo Basin rainforest and prevent ecosystem collapse. </p>
<p data-line-id="b13bd1417d1c4861a92b12fc1d967b4a"> Increasing crop yields and building better cities are not only among the most cost-effective strategies for climate-change adaptation; they also bring significant economic and social benefits. Moreover, by striking the right balance between immediate needs and long-term sustainability, investments in these areas can help Africa manage its demographic pressures without risking the planet’s future. </p>
<p data-line-id="8c8c0a94dbfd45f38b63d1d1a670c29a"> For decades, African governments relied on cash crops and timber exports to build their foreign-exchange reserves, valuing growth and macroeconomic stability over sustainable development. African households are increasingly taking a similar approach, prioritizing basic needs over climate and environmental considerations. But in an era defined by the global climate crisis, Africans should not be forced into such a Cornelian dilemma. </p>
<p data-line-id="1e38112a84754e81b09595db13256260"> As the continent faces rapid population growth, continuing down this path would be destructive for the planet and everyone on it. To reduce the risk of crossing climate tipping points, the world must improve living standards in Africa. It is a price that must be paid to avert a climate disaster. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What Democracy Means for a Society’s Bottom Line</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/democracy-key-to-human-development-and-economic-prosperity-by-aminata-toure-and-kevin-casas-zamora-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/democracy-key-to-human-development-and-economic-prosperity-by-aminata-toure-and-kevin-casas-zamora-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-12T00:00:22+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-12T00:00:22+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="democracy-key-to-human-development-and-economic-prosperity-by-aminata-toure-and-kevin-casas-zamora-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="6913733cfb07afa2cac596f8" data-entity-link-name="democracy-key-to-human-development-and-economic-prosperity-by-aminata-toure-and-kevin-casas-zamora-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/democracy-key-to-human-development-and-economic-prosperity-by-aminata-toure-and-kevin-casas-zamora-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/democracy-key-to-human-development-and-economic-prosperity-by-aminata-toure-and-kevin-casas-zamora-2025-11" title="What Democracy Means for a Society’s Bottom Line"><span class="u-tos">What Democracy Means for a Society’s Bottom Line</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/0f920158d75e6be505bab9dc8cc19261.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/0f920158d75e6be505bab9dc8cc19261.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/0f920158d75e6be505bab9dc8cc19261.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/0f920158d75e6be505bab9dc8cc19261.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/democracy-key-to-human-development-and-economic-prosperity-by-aminata-toure-and-kevin-casas-zamora-2025-11">What Democracy Means for a Society’s Bottom Line</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 12, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="aminata-toure" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/aminata-toure" data-language="english" href="columnist/aminata-toure">Aminata Touré </a> &amp; <a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="kevin-casas-zamora" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/kevin-casas-zamora" data-language="english" href="columnist/kevin-casas-zamora">Kevin Casas-Zamora </a>

reject the notion that political rights and socioeconomic welfare are separate or even competing goals.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="democracy-key-to-human-development-and-economic-prosperity-by-aminata-toure-and-kevin-casas-zamora-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="6913733cfb07afa2cac596f8" data-entity-link-name="democracy-key-to-human-development-and-economic-prosperity-by-aminata-toure-and-kevin-casas-zamora-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/democracy-key-to-human-development-and-economic-prosperity-by-aminata-toure-and-kevin-casas-zamora-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/democracy-key-to-human-development-and-economic-prosperity-by-aminata-toure-and-kevin-casas-zamora-2025-11" title="What Democracy Means for a Society’s Bottom Line"><span class="u-tos">What Democracy Means for a Society’s Bottom Line</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/0f920158d75e6be505bab9dc8cc19261.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/0f920158d75e6be505bab9dc8cc19261.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/0f920158d75e6be505bab9dc8cc19261.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/0f920158d75e6be505bab9dc8cc19261.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/democracy-key-to-human-development-and-economic-prosperity-by-aminata-toure-and-kevin-casas-zamora-2025-11">What Democracy Means for a Society’s Bottom Line</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 12, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="aminata-toure" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/aminata-toure" data-language="english" href="columnist/aminata-toure">Aminata Touré </a> &amp; <a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="kevin-casas-zamora" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/kevin-casas-zamora" data-language="english" href="columnist/kevin-casas-zamora">Kevin Casas-Zamora </a>

reject the notion that political rights and socioeconomic welfare are separate or even competing goals.        </p>
</header>
</li>
<div id="archive" style="margin: 20px; font-weight: bold; color:red;">Full article text:
 | <a href="https://archive.is?run=1&amp;url=https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/democracy-key-to-human-development-and-economic-prosperity-by-aminata-toure-and-kevin-casas-zamora-2025-11" target="_blank">archive.is</a></div>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary paywall english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="a8216c744e374d39893cb43563a439c9"> DAKAR/SAN JOSÉ – Democracy is in trouble. For nine consecutive years, <a href="https://www.idea.int/gsod/">more countries</a> have suffered a weakening of democratic institutions than have experienced improvement – the longest such decline in a <a href="https://www.idea.int/news/global-democracy-report-majority-countries-worsen-press-freedom-hits-50-year-low">half-century</a>. Around the world, citizens are losing faith in democracy, and demagogues have exploited their disillusionment. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Trumponomics Will End in Tears</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/trump-reject-republican-economic-policy-orthodoxy-will-end-in-disaster-by-desmond-lachman-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/trump-reject-republican-economic-policy-orthodoxy-will-end-in-disaster-by-desmond-lachman-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-12T00:00:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-12T00:00:21+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="trump-reject-republican-economic-policy-orthodoxy-will-end-in-disaster-by-desmond-lachman-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="69122b246e7cf0dd8e539352" data-entity-link-name="trump-reject-republican-economic-policy-orthodoxy-will-end-in-disaster-by-desmond-lachman-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/trump-reject-republican-economic-policy-orthodoxy-will-end-in-disaster-by-desmond-lachman-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/trump-reject-republican-economic-policy-orthodoxy-will-end-in-disaster-by-desmond-lachman-2025-11" title="Trumponomics Will End in Tears"><span class="u-tos">Trumponomics Will End in Tears</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/68b5666431e95d10f12f34dfcbf3c25a.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/68b5666431e95d10f12f34dfcbf3c25a.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/68b5666431e95d10f12f34dfcbf3c25a.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/68b5666431e95d10f12f34dfcbf3c25a.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/trump-reject-republican-economic-policy-orthodoxy-will-end-in-disaster-by-desmond-lachman-2025-11">Trumponomics Will End in Tears</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 12, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="desmond-lachman" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/desmond-lachman" data-language="english" href="columnist/desmond-lachman">Desmond Lachman </a>
sees a disaster brewing as US Republicans turn their backs on the economic principles they long championed.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="trump-reject-republican-economic-policy-orthodoxy-will-end-in-disaster-by-desmond-lachman-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="69122b246e7cf0dd8e539352" data-entity-link-name="trump-reject-republican-economic-policy-orthodoxy-will-end-in-disaster-by-desmond-lachman-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/trump-reject-republican-economic-policy-orthodoxy-will-end-in-disaster-by-desmond-lachman-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/trump-reject-republican-economic-policy-orthodoxy-will-end-in-disaster-by-desmond-lachman-2025-11" title="Trumponomics Will End in Tears"><span class="u-tos">Trumponomics Will End in Tears</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/68b5666431e95d10f12f34dfcbf3c25a.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/68b5666431e95d10f12f34dfcbf3c25a.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/68b5666431e95d10f12f34dfcbf3c25a.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/68b5666431e95d10f12f34dfcbf3c25a.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/trump-reject-republican-economic-policy-orthodoxy-will-end-in-disaster-by-desmond-lachman-2025-11">Trumponomics Will End in Tears</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 12, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="desmond-lachman" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/desmond-lachman" data-language="english" href="columnist/desmond-lachman">Desmond Lachman </a>
sees a disaster brewing as US Republicans turn their backs on the economic principles they long championed.        </p>
</header>
</li>
<div id="archive" style="margin: 20px; font-weight: bold; color:red;">Full article text:
 | <a href="https://archive.is?run=1&amp;url=https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/trump-reject-republican-economic-policy-orthodoxy-will-end-in-disaster-by-desmond-lachman-2025-11" target="_blank">archive.is</a></div>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary paywall english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="2d80cb89b87a40fb8f6501ae7adb9668"> WASHINGTON, DC – US President Donald Trump has suspended trade talks with Canada, and announced an additional 10% tariff on Canadian goods, over an Ontario-funded television ad that used audio of former President Ronald Reagan denouncing tariffs. The episode is telling. Yet again, Trump is pretending to defend the Republican Party’s longstanding economic principles, while pursuing policies that constitute a wholesale rejection of them. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Key to Unlocking Climate Progress</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/cop30-climate-finance-invest-in-state-capacity-to-turn-promises-into-progress-by-mariana-mazzucato-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/cop30-climate-finance-invest-in-state-capacity-to-turn-promises-into-progress-by-mariana-mazzucato-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-11T00:00:20+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-11T00:00:20+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="cop30-climate-finance-invest-in-state-capacity-to-turn-promises-into-progress-by-mariana-mazzucato-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="69135cb1fb07afa2ca598b93" data-entity-link-name="cop30-climate-finance-invest-in-state-capacity-to-turn-promises-into-progress-by-mariana-mazzucato-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/cop30-climate-finance-invest-in-state-capacity-to-turn-promises-into-progress-by-mariana-mazzucato-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/cop30-climate-finance-invest-in-state-capacity-to-turn-promises-into-progress-by-mariana-mazzucato-2025-11" title="The Key to Unlocking Climate Progress"><span class="u-tos">The Key to Unlocking Climate Progress</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/df4be4dbdcd8231b68128f57192ce4dc.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/df4be4dbdcd8231b68128f57192ce4dc.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/df4be4dbdcd8231b68128f57192ce4dc.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/df4be4dbdcd8231b68128f57192ce4dc.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/cop30-climate-finance-invest-in-state-capacity-to-turn-promises-into-progress-by-mariana-mazzucato-2025-11">The Key to Unlocking Climate Progress</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 11, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="mariana-mazzucato" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/mariana-mazzucato" data-language="english" href="columnist/mariana-mazzucato">Mariana Mazzucato </a>
sees a need for investments in state capacity to help countries follow through on their decarbonization plans.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="cop30-climate-finance-invest-in-state-capacity-to-turn-promises-into-progress-by-mariana-mazzucato-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="69135cb1fb07afa2ca598b93" data-entity-link-name="cop30-climate-finance-invest-in-state-capacity-to-turn-promises-into-progress-by-mariana-mazzucato-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/cop30-climate-finance-invest-in-state-capacity-to-turn-promises-into-progress-by-mariana-mazzucato-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/cop30-climate-finance-invest-in-state-capacity-to-turn-promises-into-progress-by-mariana-mazzucato-2025-11" title="The Key to Unlocking Climate Progress"><span class="u-tos">The Key to Unlocking Climate Progress</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/df4be4dbdcd8231b68128f57192ce4dc.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/df4be4dbdcd8231b68128f57192ce4dc.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/df4be4dbdcd8231b68128f57192ce4dc.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/df4be4dbdcd8231b68128f57192ce4dc.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/cop30-climate-finance-invest-in-state-capacity-to-turn-promises-into-progress-by-mariana-mazzucato-2025-11">The Key to Unlocking Climate Progress</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 11, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="mariana-mazzucato" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/mariana-mazzucato" data-language="english" href="columnist/mariana-mazzucato">Mariana Mazzucato </a>
sees a need for investments in state capacity to help countries follow through on their decarbonization plans.        </p>
</header>
</li>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="82e87751e23043c5b4e28b1f8e3cc4bc"> LONDON – <a href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/columnist/bill-gates">Bill Gates</a>’ <a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/home/home-page-topic/reader/three-tough-truths-about-climate">call</a> for the United Nations to pivot from climate action focused on temperature goals to vaccines has misread the challenge we face. Investments in climate mitigation and development are not competing priorities. On the contrary, with the World Health Organization <a href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/climate-change-and-health">projecting</a> that climate change will cause approximately 250,000 additional deaths per year between 2030 and 2050, climate action is also health action. </p><p data-line-id="d270650965bf44a78b2b978d31dffc25"> All those attending the UN Climate Change Conference (COP30) in Belém this week should keep this insight in mind. But Gates is right that we must deliver real solutions, and, as the Brazilian government has made clear, the goal for this “Solutions COP” is to bridge the gap between declarations and delivery, which will require allocating scarce resources effectively. This is not about trade-offs between climate and health: it is about getting serious about our goals. </p><p data-line-id="9845dc064a274cf9966c954c1543a2ae"> Progress at COP30 is far from assured. The United Kingdom has just <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2025/nov/05/uk-opts-out-of-flagship-fund-to-protect-amazon-and-other-threatened-tropical-forests">withdrawn</a> its funding for the proposed Tropical Forest Forever Facility, which is supposed to be formally adopted this month. Making matters worse, the European Union has just <a href="https://www.reuters.com/sustainability/cop/eu-eyes-weaker-climate-goal-scramble-deal-by-cop30-sources-say-2025-11-05/">weakened</a> its 2040 decarbonization target by allowing countries to buy foreign carbon credits rather than cutting domestic emissions. Meanwhile, <a href="https://www.un.org/sustainabledevelopment/blog/2023/07/press-release-un-warns-of-soaring-global-public-debt-a-record-92-trillion-in-2022-3-3-billion-people-now-live-in-countries-where-debt-interest-payments-are-greater-than-expenditure-on-health-or-edu/">3.3 billion people</a> live in countries that are spending more on interest payments than on health, implying that they are foregoing investments in climate resilience. </p><p data-line-id="9f1cf13094334c898833e9f1d5ef3548"> Ten years after COP21 in Paris, the world is not short of targets or stated commitments. Rather, what is missing is the ability to deliver fast, fair, and durable progress. From debt sustainability and climate change to the pursuit of inclusive growth, the common thread running through all our biggest challenges is public institutions’ inability to turn commitments into tangible outcomes. </p><div data-classes="newsletter--bg newsletter--yellow newsletter--branding newsletter--compact newsletter--label newsletter--admin" data-consent="true" data-description="Every Thursday in PS Economics, we offer a concise selection of essential reading on the most important issues related to economics and finance." data-label="Sign up for our weekly newsletter, PS Economics" data-link-name="newsletter-economics" data-newsletter="prosyn-economics-newsletter" data-newsletter-subscribe-form="true"></div><p data-line-id="1687ed8e42bb4b88b5b982e9da2a210d"> As a result, we are left treading water. Cutting debt while undermining investment-led growth will not bring about debt sustainability, but it will exacerbate the climate crisis. After all, the debt crisis is also an investment crisis – without investment, the productive capacity of countries does not increase, making them more dependent on foreign aid precisely when that aid is withering. </p><p data-line-id="a45ffb0d028f416885febfe27be3c055"> To find our way back to shore, we urgently need a new financial architecture that can provide the policy and fiscal space to support implementation and build state capacity. While the International Monetary Fund and the World Bank are attempting to reimagine themselves for the 21st century, they must move faster to accommodate carbon-related constraints and persistent development deficits. Here, too, ambition has outpaced execution: pledges abound, but governance and public-purpose finance are still bottlenecks. </p><p data-line-id="dfe01e1b093542a0ac2dc00f0e8c03cf"> Moreover, countries must commit to investing in their ability to administer and implement the much-needed industrial and financial strategies that can put the Nationally Determined Contributions (NDCs) at the center of economic development – such as by embedding climate goals in green industrial strategies and green financial policies. At COP30 this week, I will be presenting a way to use <a href="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/bartlett/publications/2025/nov/mission-oriented-country-platforms-engines-just-green-transition">country platforms</a> more effectively. More than just a tool for derisking the private sector, country platforms must be used in a way that makes government climate policy greater than the sum of its parts. </p><p data-line-id="2690ad71554143b9b55ccf95127d4976"> As I argue in a new report, “<a href="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/bartlett/publications/2025/nov/state-capacity-and-capabilities-just-green-world">State Capacity and Capabilities for a Just Green World</a>,” with Esther Dweck, Brazil’s minister of management and innovation in public services, governments must invest in their own capacity. This means ensuring all tools – including procurement policy, digital public infrastructure, and the design of state-owned enterprises – are fit for purpose. Building dynamic state capabilities means investing in policy labs, learning by doing, and becoming less reliant on outside consultants. Brazil’s <a href="https://www.bcb.gov.br/en/financialstability/pix_en">Pix payment system</a> and Rural Environmental Registry show what becomes possible when governments invest in the data collection, systems, and skills needed to turn plans into results. </p><p data-line-id="8023b27491bc4c6bae9a234e969cfa4a"> Most developing countries need additional support to build these capabilities and fulfill their NDCs, and a new financial architecture should be supportive of that objective. Investments in state capacity should be understood as among the most effective forms of climate policy. When designed as mission-oriented implementation hubs, country platforms can align public instruments behind clear goals, with state-owned enterprises, public development banks, and strategic procurement agencies working in concert. </p><p data-line-id="8acd53d1206d46778fb6a0e1e3513327"> Gates is right that temperature goals alone are not the best measure of human welfare. But he is wrong to turn away from bold climate action that emphasizes ambitious mitigation rather than passive adaptation. In the spirit of Brazil’s call for this to be a Solutions COP, climate finance must be spent on the right things: building the state capacity needed to implement green industrial strategies that align decarbonization with development, health, jobs, and resilience. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How COP30 Can Re-Energize Climate Action</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/cop30-brazil-re-energize-climate-action-by-jennifer-morgan-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/cop30-brazil-re-energize-climate-action-by-jennifer-morgan-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-11T00:00:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-11T00:00:19+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="cop30-brazil-re-energize-climate-action-by-jennifer-morgan-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="69134105fb07afa2cad5f15f" data-entity-link-name="cop30-brazil-re-energize-climate-action-by-jennifer-morgan-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/cop30-brazil-re-energize-climate-action-by-jennifer-morgan-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/cop30-brazil-re-energize-climate-action-by-jennifer-morgan-2025-11" title="How COP30 Can Re-Energize Climate Action"><span class="u-tos">How COP30 Can Re-Energize Climate Action</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1f72790855cb4c649ec32df5cbaa8b61.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1f72790855cb4c649ec32df5cbaa8b61.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1f72790855cb4c649ec32df5cbaa8b61.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1f72790855cb4c649ec32df5cbaa8b61.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/cop30-brazil-re-energize-climate-action-by-jennifer-morgan-2025-11">How COP30 Can Re-Energize Climate Action</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 11, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="jennifer-morgan" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/jennifer-morgan" data-language="english" href="columnist/jennifer-morgan">Jennifer Morgan </a>
explains what it will take to consider the United Nations Climate Change Conference in Belém a success.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="cop30-brazil-re-energize-climate-action-by-jennifer-morgan-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="69134105fb07afa2cad5f15f" data-entity-link-name="cop30-brazil-re-energize-climate-action-by-jennifer-morgan-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/cop30-brazil-re-energize-climate-action-by-jennifer-morgan-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/cop30-brazil-re-energize-climate-action-by-jennifer-morgan-2025-11" title="How COP30 Can Re-Energize Climate Action"><span class="u-tos">How COP30 Can Re-Energize Climate Action</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1f72790855cb4c649ec32df5cbaa8b61.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1f72790855cb4c649ec32df5cbaa8b61.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1f72790855cb4c649ec32df5cbaa8b61.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1f72790855cb4c649ec32df5cbaa8b61.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/cop30-brazil-re-energize-climate-action-by-jennifer-morgan-2025-11">How COP30 Can Re-Energize Climate Action</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 11, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="jennifer-morgan" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/jennifer-morgan" data-language="english" href="columnist/jennifer-morgan">Jennifer Morgan </a>
explains what it will take to consider the United Nations Climate Change Conference in Belém a success.        </p>
</header>
</li>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="ffec063a18b84136a6ef1d320b4ebeb3"> BERLIN – It is hard to imagine a more appropriate venue for this year’s United Nations Climate Change Conference (COP30). Delegations from around the world will gather in the equatorial Brazilian city of Belém, on the edge of the Amazon – one of the front lines of climate vulnerability. Some 40% of the city’s population lives below sea level, and around <a href="https://sumauma.com/en/na-belem-da-cop30-ate-a-sombra-e-desigual/">82% of residents</a> walk on streets with no shade. Heat and humidity define their daily life, and nature directly sustains their existence. </p>
<p data-line-id="34827b479a8e42e98a08aba7b19f6899"> But as COP30 gets underway, there is no point in pretending that governments are rising to the occasion. The UN Environment Programme’s latest emissions gap <a href="https://www.unep.org/resources/emissions-gap-report-2025">report</a> makes clear that without stronger governmental action, we will inevitably see temperature levels at which crops fail, cities overheat, economies falter, and the human toll soars. This is the reality that policymakers will confront in Belém, and they should feel a sense of collective responsibility to confront the alarming gap between what countries have put on the table and what is urgently required. Getting to climate safety will not be easy. But acknowledging how far we have come should inspire hope that we can make it the rest of the way. From 2005-15, oil, gas, and coal power generation met <a href="https://eciu.net/analysis/reports/2025/10-years-post-paris">68% of the growth</a> in global electricity demand. From 2015-25, renewables met <a href="https://eciu.net/analysis/reports/2025/10-years-post-paris">67% of the increase</a> in demand. </p>
<p data-line-id="e7374f2c2a1146ca84f02b712f24b82f"> In China, President Xi Jinping <a href="https://www.climateandcapitalmedia.com/clean-energy-is-the-cornerstone-of-xi-jinpings-five-year-plan/">says</a> he wants to use the upcoming 15th Five-Year Plan to “accelerate” the construction of a new energy system and promote the safe, reliable, and orderly replacement of fossil energy. In India, renewables met <a href="https://www.pib.gov.in/PressReleasePage.aspx?PRID=2183866">51.5% of total electricity demand in July</a> this year. And in the European Union, GDP grew by about 68% between 1990 and 2023, while net greenhouse-gas emissions decreased <a href="https://climate.ec.europa.eu/news-other-reads/news/eu-advances-towards-2030-climate-targets-continued-emissions-cuts-2025-11-06_en">by approximately 37%</a>, according to preliminary data. </p>
<p data-line-id="bf77d79c44fe49d3a5ffc22bbd5806b5"> The falling costs of renewable energy, electric vehicles, and battery storage clear the path for governments, civil society, and regional and municipal leaders to tackle the challenge of climate safety. The alternative, apathy and defeat, is no alternative at all. </p>
<div data-classes="newsletter--bg newsletter--yellow newsletter--branding newsletter--compact newsletter--label newsletter--admin" data-consent="true" data-description="Go beyond the headlines to understand the issues, forces, and trends shaping the US presidential election – and the likely implications of its outcome." data-label="Sign up for our weekly newsletter, PS Politics" data-link-name="newsletter-politics" data-newsletter="prosyn-above-the-fold" data-newsletter-subscribe-form="true"></div>
<p data-line-id="e4ceb10784de4fec86e7257f4a252672"> So, what needs to happen at COP30? First, governments must reaffirm the Paris agreement and its goal of keeping the global average temperature within 2°C, and preferably within 1.5°C, of the pre-industrial level. With the Trump administration actively working to slow the phaseout of fossil fuels, confirming this target will send an important signal to investors and planners around the world. </p>
<p data-line-id="6027a6b2edc5413aba429edc87440630"> Second, governments must accelerate implementation of what has already been agreed. The 2023 <a href="https://unfccc.int/topics/global-stocktake">Global Stocktake</a> in Dubai called on countries to triple renewable energy capacity, double energy efficiency, promote a just transition away from fossil fuels, and halt (and then reverse) deforestation by 2030. Agreement on these goals was hard-won; now they must be pursued with the necessary speed and scale. </p>
<p data-line-id="ccf3352151a54e1a9ddbdbdf011da20f"> As Brazilian President <a href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/columnist/luiz-inacio-lula-da-silva">Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva</a> suggested on the first day of COP30, governments <a href="https://www.gov.br/planalto/pt-br/acompanhe-o-planalto/discursos-e-pronunciamentos/2025/11/discurso-do-presidente-lula-na-abertura-da-cop30-em-belem-pa">could create a roadmap</a> detailing various pathways to a just transition away from fossil fuels, which would require an agreement on what a just transition must include. They could supplement this with initiatives to overcome barriers to renewables, such as commitments to invest in electric grids and battery storage. And a similar approach could lay out a path to achieving zero deforestation by 2030. </p>
<p data-line-id="840b90b6aa1a4d698967382127cf0764"> As the host of COP30, the Brazilian government is already <a href="https://cop30.br/en/news-about-cop30/cop30-action-agenda-calls-for-accelerating-the-implementation-of-the-global-stocktake">calling</a> for the summit to “accelerate the implementation of the Global Stocktake.” We need to turn that catchphrase into concrete progress by adopting a forward-looking game plan that identifies the pathways, policies, and supporting measures needed to close the gap to the Paris agreement’s 1.5°C target. </p>
<p data-line-id="5a3f789a98934cc9a4401c9278c68a51"> But redoubling our efforts is not only about accelerating progress where it is lagging; it is also about taking advantage of the pace of the transformation that is well underway – delivering jobs and economic growth – in many places. The progress made in recent years has been unmistakable: wind and solar power <a href="https://ember-energy.org/latest-insights/renewable-additions-in-2025-are-once-again-expected-to-surge-putting-tripling-within-reach/tracking-progress-towards-a-global-tripling-of-ren/">have more than tripled since 2015</a>, and EVs have grown from less than <a href="https://www.iea.org/reports/global-ev-outlook-2025/trends-in-electric-car-markets-2">1% back then to over 20%</a> today.  </p>
<p data-line-id="4fa909d1681d4fff8d693b95eaa17be0"> Third, countries should demonstrate how they intend to align the steps they are taking today with what is needed to reach net-zero emissions. This matters because several countries have recently offered new climate commitments that <a href="https://unfccc.int/process-and-meetings/the-paris-agreement/nationally-determined-contributions-ndcs/2025-ndc-synthesis-report">seem to fall short of meeting their own net-zero goals</a>, whether by 2050 or later. </p>
<p data-line-id="5e836f2f4ddc4b4296195098484b1cf5"> Of course, access to finance and investment remains essential for developing countries to decarbonize and bolster climate resilience. COP30 can make real progress by securing commitments to mobilize more resources for vulnerable countries to help them adapt to rising sea levels, strong storms, prolonged heat waves, and other consequences of climate change. </p>
<p data-line-id="b9a8f519b8164f34ab07968fa440abcc"> The Brazilian hosts have set an ambitious agenda, but the defining test will be whether the world takes steps to close the widening gap to the 1.5°C goal. For Lula, securing a win would solidify his legacy as a champion for the people around the world who stand to suffer the most if we fail. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What Bill Gates Overlooks About Climate Change</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/what-bill-gates-misses-in-essay-on-climate-change-by-peter-singer-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/what-bill-gates-misses-in-essay-on-climate-change-by-peter-singer-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-11T00:00:18+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-11T00:00:18+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="what-bill-gates-misses-in-essay-on-climate-change-by-peter-singer-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="69133626fb07afa2caa1c93a" data-entity-link-name="what-bill-gates-misses-in-essay-on-climate-change-by-peter-singer-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/what-bill-gates-misses-in-essay-on-climate-change-by-peter-singer-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/what-bill-gates-misses-in-essay-on-climate-change-by-peter-singer-2025-11" title="What Bill Gates Overlooks About Climate Change"><span class="u-tos">What Bill Gates Overlooks About Climate Change</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/7525c9ade500faa02871e57ca4f3329e.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/7525c9ade500faa02871e57ca4f3329e.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/7525c9ade500faa02871e57ca4f3329e.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/7525c9ade500faa02871e57ca4f3329e.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/what-bill-gates-misses-in-essay-on-climate-change-by-peter-singer-2025-11">What Bill Gates Overlooks About Climate Change</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 11, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="peter-singer" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/peter-singer" data-language="english" href="columnist/peter-singer">Peter Singer </a>
explains why a temperature increase of 2.9°C could indeed “be the end of civilization.”        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="what-bill-gates-misses-in-essay-on-climate-change-by-peter-singer-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="69133626fb07afa2caa1c93a" data-entity-link-name="what-bill-gates-misses-in-essay-on-climate-change-by-peter-singer-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/what-bill-gates-misses-in-essay-on-climate-change-by-peter-singer-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/what-bill-gates-misses-in-essay-on-climate-change-by-peter-singer-2025-11" title="What Bill Gates Overlooks About Climate Change"><span class="u-tos">What Bill Gates Overlooks About Climate Change</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/7525c9ade500faa02871e57ca4f3329e.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/7525c9ade500faa02871e57ca4f3329e.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/7525c9ade500faa02871e57ca4f3329e.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/7525c9ade500faa02871e57ca4f3329e.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/what-bill-gates-misses-in-essay-on-climate-change-by-peter-singer-2025-11">What Bill Gates Overlooks About Climate Change</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 11, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="peter-singer" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/peter-singer" data-language="english" href="columnist/peter-singer">Peter Singer </a>
explains why a temperature increase of 2.9°C could indeed “be the end of civilization.”        </p>
</header>
</li>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="df5e4b1de960450e88236e7b7b81fa32"> SINGAPORE – Ahead of this year’s United Nations Climate Change Conference (COP30), now underway in Belém, Brazil, Bill Gates, who chairs and funds the foundation that bears his name, released an essay entitled “<a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/home/home-page-topic/reader/three-tough-truths-about-climate">Three tough truths about climate</a>.” The first of these truths is: “Climate change is a serious problem, but it will not be the end of civilization.” </p>
<p data-line-id="663fe79e47c446c3b10dd5a846eea941"> Gates recognizes that climate change is “a very important problem,” that it “needs to be solved,” and that “[e]very tenth of a degree of heating that we prevent is hugely beneficial because a stable climate makes it easier to improve people’s lives.” Nevertheless, to say that climate change will not be the end of civilization must lessen our sense of the urgency of acting to mitigate it. So, we should ask whether this “truth” really is true. </p>
<p data-line-id="0dc2dc2fcb194771b3f1180fa37f0010"> Gates defends his flat statement that climate change “will not be the end of civilization” with a graph showing that even if countries do no more than continue what they are doing now, “Global warming will probably be less than 3°C by 2100.” More precisely, the graph suggests that by 2100, with countries continuing to do what they are doing now, the global average temperature will be 2.9°C above the pre-industrial level. </p>
<p data-line-id="a4bef354441d409d9c4bddd70a2be942"> Suppose we agree that, although a global temperature rise of 2.9°C would make some parts of our planet uninhabitable because of extreme heat or rising sea levels, enough will still be suitable for human habitation to allow civilization to continue. The question remains: Will the temperature rise stop at 2.9°C? </p>
<div data-classes="newsletter--bg newsletter--yellow newsletter--branding newsletter--compact newsletter--label newsletter--admin" data-consent="true" data-description="Go beyond the headlines to understand the issues, forces, and trends shaping the US presidential election – and the likely implications of its outcome." data-label="Sign up for our weekly newsletter, PS Politics" data-link-name="newsletter-politics" data-newsletter="prosyn-above-the-fold" data-newsletter-subscribe-form="true"></div>
<p data-line-id="1ead6d376d8d41629a1608ca05f7343f"> To make the case that it will, Gates gives a detailed account of technological innovations that, he believes, could enable us to move to zero emissions before the end of the century. But he misses something critically important. To see this, let’s take a step back. </p>
<p data-line-id="3e38dce1b22343af869688cabe718b87"> The United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC), which has been signed by 198 parties, including all United Nations member states, dates from the “Earth Summit” held in Rio de Janeiro in 1992. Article 2 of the convention states that its ultimate objective is to achieve “stabilization of greenhouse gases in the atmosphere at a level that would prevent dangerous anthropogenic interference with the climate system.” </p>
<p data-line-id="7f360c9d38594bb4b205a7d21e0ccc37"> The convention did not put any specific limit on how much global warming could be tolerated without dangerous anthropogenic interference with our climate. Countries had different views about that, and the science was still developing. </p>
<p data-line-id="2680ca37889d4241a10db087e413a9a3"> Eighteen years later, however, at the 16th Conference of the Parties to the UNFCCC (COP16), in Cancún, the science was sufficiently advanced for it to be agreed that to avoid danger, global warming must be limited to 2°C above pre-industrial levels. Then, in 2015, with further evidence showing the threat of sea-level rise to low-lying island states, the agreement was further refined at COP21 in Paris to hold the increase to “well below” 2°C while “pursuing efforts to limit the temperature increase to 1.5°C.” </p>
<p data-line-id="c19e518359874caaafbeb8ad096b1b5f"> All the criticism of the 2°C limit has been on the side of saying that it is too high. For example, a two-year expert review <a href="https://unfccc.int/resource/docs/2015/sb/eng/inf01.pdf">reported</a> to the UNFCCC in 2015 that “the ‘guardrail’ concept, in which up to 2°C of warming is considered safe, is inadequate, and would therefore be better seen as an upper limit, a defence line that needs to be stringently defended, while less warming would be preferable.” </p>
<p data-line-id="c0f2612b3f1e4d0fb8701e0ff7cfe086"> No major country, nor any authoritative expert body, has suggested that we could safely raise the 2°C limit. The main reason for this is not that civilization will be unable to survive in a world that is 2°C warmer than the pre-industrial world was, or that, as Gates points out, it is easier to improve people’s lives when the climate is stable. </p>
<p data-line-id="c51b6f5ac930400188f360626b3e0d44"> Instead, the main reason is that once global warming exceeds 2°C, the risk of activating positive feedback loops increases significantly. These loops may further increase global temperatures even if we have, thanks to the technological innovations Gates mentions, reduced to zero the emissions for which humans are directly responsible. </p>
<p data-line-id="93269eea2086424ba9623d33006dc678"> Three of these feedback loops are particularly important: </p>
<ul data-line-id="be94d1ef2fa44c6e81be01ecdf381a11"><ul><li>Immense quantities of carbon are locked up in organic matter, now frozen in arctic permafrost. Above 2°C, there is a high risk that the organic matter will thaw rapidly and decompose, releasing carbon dioxide and methane (a much more potent greenhouse gas), which would increase global warming and cause further thawing;</li><li>Ice, whether on land or the ocean, reflects the sun’s radiation. Once the ice sheets of Greenland, Antarctica, and the Arctic Ocean start to melt, the darker land and water surfaces that are exposed will absorb more of the sun’s warmth, causing more ice to melt;</li><li>The Amazon rainforest is another huge store of carbon. As temperatures rise above 2°C, the forest may begin to die, releasing its stored carbon into the atmosphere.<br/></li></ul></ul>
<p data-line-id="6229058b5e7a452ab690c6c52718e842"> When we include these and other reinforcing loops in our calculations, we cannot easily brush aside the threat climate change poses to the future of civilization. </p>
<p data-line-id="c8f19872c4164735b45d6fa645972ba5"> Gates seeks to de-emphasize the existential threat posed by climate change in order to “put human welfare at the center of our climate strategies.” But this doesn’t tell us how tolerant we should be of the risk of creating a climate that will be disastrous for human welfare for centuries to come. Tolerating 2.9°C of warming by 2100 may, in the long run, be far worse for human welfare than doing everything possible to keep warming below 2°C. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The AI Labor Shock Is Coming for Women</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/women-white-collar-workers-will-bear-brunt-of-ai-induced-job-displacement-by-noreena-hertz-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/women-white-collar-workers-will-bear-brunt-of-ai-induced-job-displacement-by-noreena-hertz-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-11T00:00:17+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-11T00:00:17+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="women-white-collar-workers-will-bear-brunt-of-ai-induced-job-displacement-by-noreena-hertz-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="69133bf9fb07afa2cabf63bd" data-entity-link-name="women-white-collar-workers-will-bear-brunt-of-ai-induced-job-displacement-by-noreena-hertz-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/women-white-collar-workers-will-bear-brunt-of-ai-induced-job-displacement-by-noreena-hertz-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/women-white-collar-workers-will-bear-brunt-of-ai-induced-job-displacement-by-noreena-hertz-2025-11" title="The AI Labor Shock Is Coming for Women"><span class="u-tos">The AI Labor Shock Is Coming for Women</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a8718624006a444d851f734a3b5013da.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a8718624006a444d851f734a3b5013da.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a8718624006a444d851f734a3b5013da.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a8718624006a444d851f734a3b5013da.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/women-white-collar-workers-will-bear-brunt-of-ai-induced-job-displacement-by-noreena-hertz-2025-11">The AI Labor Shock Is Coming for Women</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 11, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="noreena-hertz" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/noreena-hertz" data-language="english" href="columnist/noreena-hertz">Noreena Hertz </a>
warns that the latest wave of automation is likely to have a disproportionate impact on female workers.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="women-white-collar-workers-will-bear-brunt-of-ai-induced-job-displacement-by-noreena-hertz-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="69133bf9fb07afa2cabf63bd" data-entity-link-name="women-white-collar-workers-will-bear-brunt-of-ai-induced-job-displacement-by-noreena-hertz-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/women-white-collar-workers-will-bear-brunt-of-ai-induced-job-displacement-by-noreena-hertz-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/women-white-collar-workers-will-bear-brunt-of-ai-induced-job-displacement-by-noreena-hertz-2025-11" title="The AI Labor Shock Is Coming for Women"><span class="u-tos">The AI Labor Shock Is Coming for Women</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a8718624006a444d851f734a3b5013da.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a8718624006a444d851f734a3b5013da.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a8718624006a444d851f734a3b5013da.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a8718624006a444d851f734a3b5013da.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/women-white-collar-workers-will-bear-brunt-of-ai-induced-job-displacement-by-noreena-hertz-2025-11">The AI Labor Shock Is Coming for Women</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 11, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="noreena-hertz" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/noreena-hertz" data-language="english" href="columnist/noreena-hertz">Noreena Hertz </a>
warns that the latest wave of automation is likely to have a disproportionate impact on female workers.        </p>
</header>
</li>
<div id="archive" style="margin: 20px; font-weight: bold; color:red;">Full article text:
 | <a href="https://archive.is?run=1&amp;url=https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/women-white-collar-workers-will-bear-brunt-of-ai-induced-job-displacement-by-noreena-hertz-2025-11" target="_blank">archive.is</a></div>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary paywall english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="63ea0a96fc104973b834378faf1a4617"> LONDON – In 1986, “Anne” – a data entry clerk – watches an IBM PC land on her desk. Within a year, her job is gone. Four decades later, “Natalie” – a social-media manager – looks on as ChatGPT drafts the posts she once wrote. But her exit may come even faster than Anne’s.  </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A New Economic Playbook for Policymakers</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/successor-to-washington-consensus-must-get-politics-right-by-tim-besley-and-andres-velasco-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/successor-to-washington-consensus-must-get-politics-right-by-tim-besley-and-andres-velasco-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-11T00:00:16+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-11T00:00:16+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="successor-to-washington-consensus-must-get-politics-right-by-tim-besley-and-andres-velasco-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="69131ce5fb07afa2ca2b014a" data-entity-link-name="successor-to-washington-consensus-must-get-politics-right-by-tim-besley-and-andres-velasco-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/successor-to-washington-consensus-must-get-politics-right-by-tim-besley-and-andres-velasco-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/successor-to-washington-consensus-must-get-politics-right-by-tim-besley-and-andres-velasco-2025-11" title="A New Economic Playbook for Policymakers"><span class="u-tos">A New Economic Playbook for Policymakers</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/7a1697e95e0145673c9012df24979f50.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/7a1697e95e0145673c9012df24979f50.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/7a1697e95e0145673c9012df24979f50.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/7a1697e95e0145673c9012df24979f50.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/successor-to-washington-consensus-must-get-politics-right-by-tim-besley-and-andres-velasco-2025-11">A New Economic Playbook for Policymakers</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 11, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="tim-besley" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/tim-besley" data-language="english" href="columnist/tim-besley">Tim Besley </a> &amp; <a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="andres-velasco" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/andres-velasco" data-language="english" href="columnist/andres-velasco">Andrés Velasco </a>

tout a promising successor to the Washington Consensus that recognizes the importance of politics.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="successor-to-washington-consensus-must-get-politics-right-by-tim-besley-and-andres-velasco-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="69131ce5fb07afa2ca2b014a" data-entity-link-name="successor-to-washington-consensus-must-get-politics-right-by-tim-besley-and-andres-velasco-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/successor-to-washington-consensus-must-get-politics-right-by-tim-besley-and-andres-velasco-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/successor-to-washington-consensus-must-get-politics-right-by-tim-besley-and-andres-velasco-2025-11" title="A New Economic Playbook for Policymakers"><span class="u-tos">A New Economic Playbook for Policymakers</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/7a1697e95e0145673c9012df24979f50.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/7a1697e95e0145673c9012df24979f50.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/7a1697e95e0145673c9012df24979f50.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/7a1697e95e0145673c9012df24979f50.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/successor-to-washington-consensus-must-get-politics-right-by-tim-besley-and-andres-velasco-2025-11">A New Economic Playbook for Policymakers</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 11, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="tim-besley" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/tim-besley" data-language="english" href="columnist/tim-besley">Tim Besley </a> &amp; <a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="andres-velasco" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/andres-velasco" data-language="english" href="columnist/andres-velasco">Andrés Velasco </a>

tout a promising successor to the Washington Consensus that recognizes the importance of politics.        </p>
</header>
</li>
<div id="archive" style="margin: 20px; font-weight: bold; color:red;">Full article text:
 | <a href="https://archive.is?run=1&amp;url=https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/successor-to-washington-consensus-must-get-politics-right-by-tim-besley-and-andres-velasco-2025-11" target="_blank">archive.is</a></div>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary paywall english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="2d77b30f75ef4029a6972854e4dba867"> LONDON – Voters in many countries are furious. Democratic leaders, lacking a playbook, seem unable to address the causes of that fury. The only people benefiting from this vacuum are populists and wannabe strongmen. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Europe Must Close the Space Gap</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/europe-space-gap-ceding-markets-power-to-us-china-and-others-by-anders-fogh-rasmussen-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/europe-space-gap-ceding-markets-power-to-us-china-and-others-by-anders-fogh-rasmussen-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-10T00:00:15+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-10T00:00:15+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="europe-space-gap-ceding-markets-power-to-us-china-and-others-by-anders-fogh-rasmussen-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="69120f846e7cf0dd8eea613a" data-entity-link-name="europe-space-gap-ceding-markets-power-to-us-china-and-others-by-anders-fogh-rasmussen-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/europe-space-gap-ceding-markets-power-to-us-china-and-others-by-anders-fogh-rasmussen-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/europe-space-gap-ceding-markets-power-to-us-china-and-others-by-anders-fogh-rasmussen-2025-11" title="Europe Must Close the Space Gap"><span class="u-tos">Europe Must Close the Space Gap</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/485473de6de442cc4af452a829c0cc21.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/485473de6de442cc4af452a829c0cc21.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/485473de6de442cc4af452a829c0cc21.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/485473de6de442cc4af452a829c0cc21.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/europe-space-gap-ceding-markets-power-to-us-china-and-others-by-anders-fogh-rasmussen-2025-11">Europe Must Close the Space Gap</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 10, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="anders-fogh-rasmussen" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/anders-fogh-rasmussen" data-language="english" href="columnist/anders-fogh-rasmussen">Anders Fogh Rasmussen </a>
offers a roadmap for the bloc to address a serious threat to its economic security and sovereignty.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="europe-space-gap-ceding-markets-power-to-us-china-and-others-by-anders-fogh-rasmussen-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="69120f846e7cf0dd8eea613a" data-entity-link-name="europe-space-gap-ceding-markets-power-to-us-china-and-others-by-anders-fogh-rasmussen-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/europe-space-gap-ceding-markets-power-to-us-china-and-others-by-anders-fogh-rasmussen-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/europe-space-gap-ceding-markets-power-to-us-china-and-others-by-anders-fogh-rasmussen-2025-11" title="Europe Must Close the Space Gap"><span class="u-tos">Europe Must Close the Space Gap</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/485473de6de442cc4af452a829c0cc21.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/485473de6de442cc4af452a829c0cc21.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/485473de6de442cc4af452a829c0cc21.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/485473de6de442cc4af452a829c0cc21.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/europe-space-gap-ceding-markets-power-to-us-china-and-others-by-anders-fogh-rasmussen-2025-11">Europe Must Close the Space Gap</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 10, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="anders-fogh-rasmussen" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/anders-fogh-rasmussen" data-language="english" href="columnist/anders-fogh-rasmussen">Anders Fogh Rasmussen </a>
offers a roadmap for the bloc to address a serious threat to its economic security and sovereignty.        </p>
</header>
</li>
<div id="archive" style="margin: 20px; font-weight: bold; color:red;">Full article text:
 | <a href="https://archive.is?run=1&amp;url=https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/europe-space-gap-ceding-markets-power-to-us-china-and-others-by-anders-fogh-rasmussen-2025-11" target="_blank">archive.is</a></div>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary paywall english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="4e54be93c9c147c1b338010dc6efc600"> COPENHAGEN – It has been 56 years since Neil Armstrong, at the height of the Cold War, set foot on the moon and captured the world’s imagination. But space is no longer simply about exploration and innovation. It has become a front line for security, particularly for Europe. Just days after Russia’s invasion of Ukraine, a Russian <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/newsroom/cipr/items/740427/en">cyberattack</a> took down a satellite network providing critical connectivity to Europe. And now, both Russia and China are developing weapons to jam, overwhelm, and destroy Europe’s satellites. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>COP30 Must Do Good, Not Just Avoid Harm</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/cop30-should-give-indigenous-peoples-direct-access-to-climate-finance-by-eileen-mairena-cunningham-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/cop30-should-give-indigenous-peoples-direct-access-to-climate-finance-by-eileen-mairena-cunningham-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-10T00:00:14+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-10T00:00:14+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="cop30-should-give-indigenous-peoples-direct-access-to-climate-finance-by-eileen-mairena-cunningham-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="691200446e7cf0dd8eaed71d" data-entity-link-name="cop30-should-give-indigenous-peoples-direct-access-to-climate-finance-by-eileen-mairena-cunningham-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/cop30-should-give-indigenous-peoples-direct-access-to-climate-finance-by-eileen-mairena-cunningham-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/cop30-should-give-indigenous-peoples-direct-access-to-climate-finance-by-eileen-mairena-cunningham-2025-11" title="COP30 Must Do Good, Not Just Avoid Harm"><span class="u-tos">COP30 Must Do Good, Not Just Avoid Harm</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/d441dcafc024395638887214ab5045ff.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/d441dcafc024395638887214ab5045ff.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/d441dcafc024395638887214ab5045ff.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/d441dcafc024395638887214ab5045ff.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/cop30-should-give-indigenous-peoples-direct-access-to-climate-finance-by-eileen-mairena-cunningham-2025-11">COP30 Must Do Good, Not Just Avoid Harm</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 10, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="eileen-mairena-cunningham" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/eileen-mairena-cunningham" data-language="english" href="columnist/eileen-mairena-cunningham">Eileen Mairena Cunningham </a>
makes the case for giving indigenous peoples on the front lines of climate change direct access to finance.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="cop30-should-give-indigenous-peoples-direct-access-to-climate-finance-by-eileen-mairena-cunningham-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="691200446e7cf0dd8eaed71d" data-entity-link-name="cop30-should-give-indigenous-peoples-direct-access-to-climate-finance-by-eileen-mairena-cunningham-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/cop30-should-give-indigenous-peoples-direct-access-to-climate-finance-by-eileen-mairena-cunningham-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/cop30-should-give-indigenous-peoples-direct-access-to-climate-finance-by-eileen-mairena-cunningham-2025-11" title="COP30 Must Do Good, Not Just Avoid Harm"><span class="u-tos">COP30 Must Do Good, Not Just Avoid Harm</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/d441dcafc024395638887214ab5045ff.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/d441dcafc024395638887214ab5045ff.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/d441dcafc024395638887214ab5045ff.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/d441dcafc024395638887214ab5045ff.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/cop30-should-give-indigenous-peoples-direct-access-to-climate-finance-by-eileen-mairena-cunningham-2025-11">COP30 Must Do Good, Not Just Avoid Harm</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 10, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="eileen-mairena-cunningham" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/eileen-mairena-cunningham" data-language="english" href="columnist/eileen-mairena-cunningham">Eileen Mairena Cunningham </a>
makes the case for giving indigenous peoples on the front lines of climate change direct access to finance.        </p>
</header>
</li>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="f14483dffcc04ff79c04f9ae74f492b4"> MANAGUA – When indigenous peoples are mentioned in the context of climate change, my mind immediately goes to images of my grandmother’s roofless and flooded house, destroyed by a Category 5 hurricane and a Category 4 storm in quick succession. </p><p data-line-id="0dfed58470d04095a0251fa05eedc10e"> I also move beyond the personal, thinking of the extreme weather swings in the Andes that are damaging agricultural production; the Maasai families in Kenya and Tanzania watching their livestock die from droughts or, increasingly, massive floods; and the communities devastated by landslides in the Philippines’ Cordillera mountains. </p><p data-line-id="a665d13bf8cf4ef1b5f00eb9d31a0a43"> For indigenous peoples, climate change is more than figures and charts; it is a wound that festers, eating away at our land, resources, spirituality, and culture. The extreme weather events that are growing more frequent and severe <a href="https://desapublications.un.org/publications/state-worlds-indigenous-peoples-volume-vi-climate-crisis">disproportionately harm</a> our communities because we rely directly on natural ecosystems. </p><p data-line-id="78c3dbff41b043c981d744255bea8be4"> The decision to hold this year’s United Nations Climate Change Conference (COP30) in the Amazon region has raised our expectations significantly. To be sure, the road to Belém has not been easy. We are hopeful about the proceedings, while also approaching them with the caution and clarity that come from having taken part in climate negotiations many times before, only to be ignored. </p><p data-line-id="31f99bf184a94f2d85acca386e928666"> These summits are dominated by national policymakers. Still, we have always insisted that our voices be heard – even from the margins – and will continue to do so. Our aspiration is not only to be invited to the negotiating table and given a say in decision-making, but to help create a collective space where everyone can participate as a valued stakeholder. </p><div data-classes="newsletter--bg newsletter--yellow newsletter--branding newsletter--compact newsletter--label newsletter--admin" data-consent="true" data-description="Go beyond the headlines to understand the issues, forces, and trends shaping the US presidential election – and the likely implications of its outcome." data-label="Sign up for our weekly newsletter, PS Politics" data-link-name="newsletter-politics" data-newsletter="prosyn-above-the-fold" data-newsletter-subscribe-form="true"></div><p data-line-id="1c872c35c0a34cb0afb15fd1017eeb8f"> With <a href="https://www.euronews.com/green/2025/11/10/cop30-what-to-expect-from-this-years-un-climate-talks">more than 3,000</a> indigenous people from Africa, the Arctic, Asia, North America, Latin America and the Caribbean, the Pacific, and Eastern Europe expected to attend COP30, the Global Caucus of Indigenous Peoples on Climate Change has developed positions on the summit’s main themes. Whether discussing action on climate finance, adaptation, or mitigation, our rights to self-determination and free, prior, and informed consent concerning all matters affecting our lands, territories, and resources must be recognized. These are not favors or nice-to-haves, but the essential principles of a just climate transition. </p><p data-line-id="61b67b6c71ec4f66b873bab2ea2a31b8"> As COP30’s host, Brazil seeks to make it the “<a href="https://cop30.br/en/news-about-cop30/pre-cop-concludes-with-progress-toward-consensus-on-implementing-agreements-and-strengthening-adaptation">COP of implementation</a>,” which means translating commitments into robust action: capacity and technology transfers, as well as finance that actually reaches those on the front lines of climate change. </p><p data-line-id="b9eb56690d2b4cdba32d86a191cf5c7a"> For indigenous peoples, implementing climate policies requires direct access to predictable and sustainable finance. Instead of being forced to depend on intermediaries who leave us with crumbs, we should be trusted to manage the funds ourselves, allocating them based on our own needs, timelines, and knowledge systems. The problem with climate finance is not a lack of capacity but a lack of trust and political will. </p><p data-line-id="ccf14f783657485081c39da4b9b48197"> Moreover, multilateralism – touted as the path to climate salvation – is often skewed in favor of wealthy countries and influential stakeholders. We need partners who treat us as such, rather than as beneficiaries, who recognize our governance structures, support our initiatives, conduct cultural due diligence, and, above all, encourage genuine dialogue. </p><p data-line-id="6db1309904ad44e68083830f0cccefee"> In debates about how to ensure a just transition, we will continue to stress that clean-energy projects must not be built at the expense of our dispossession. Without strong safeguards, the decarbonization process risks becoming yet another <a href="https://eeb.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/Sacrifice-Zones-final-layout.pdf">cycle of extractivism</a>. Respect for indigenous peoples’ rights to land and resources must be at the heart of any climate policy. </p><p data-line-id="1575bda2cafb4a5385ecef3b968310ef"> Likewise, adaptation and mitigation must be approached holistically. We cannot continue to measure success only by carbon sequestration; we must also consider the effects of these efforts on livelihoods, <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1748-9326/ab68a9#erlab68a9s3">mental and spiritual health</a>, and the cultural continuity of indigenous peoples. </p><p data-line-id="d2e7a5ff5a024684aafb3e53bbed110e"> Governments and other institutions must be held accountable at COP30 for the promises they have made over the years. Words should become tangible commitments, particularly in regard to providing indigenous peoples with direct access to finance. This will require a decisive shift in mindset: climate action must do good, not merely avoid harm. </p><p data-line-id="62c3d94eebc44bfabcce130583d1595b"> Indigenous peoples, when viewed from this perspective, are part of the solution. Caring for the planet is embedded in our knowledge systems – restoring a forest, protecting a lagoon, and preserving traditional seeds are everyday tasks for us. But to carry out this work, we need real recognition and support from the international community. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Future of International Aid</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/international-aid-needed-rethink-even-before-us-cuts-by-david-miliband-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/international-aid-needed-rethink-even-before-us-cuts-by-david-miliband-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-10T00:00:13+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-10T00:00:13+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="international-aid-needed-rethink-even-before-us-cuts-by-david-miliband-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="6911b5956e7cf0dd8ea6c445" data-entity-link-name="international-aid-needed-rethink-even-before-us-cuts-by-david-miliband-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/international-aid-needed-rethink-even-before-us-cuts-by-david-miliband-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/international-aid-needed-rethink-even-before-us-cuts-by-david-miliband-2025-11" title="The Future of International Aid"><span class="u-tos">The Future of International Aid</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a02a63fb13fc8597433325697a74725e.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a02a63fb13fc8597433325697a74725e.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a02a63fb13fc8597433325697a74725e.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a02a63fb13fc8597433325697a74725e.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/international-aid-needed-rethink-even-before-us-cuts-by-david-miliband-2025-11">The Future of International Aid</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 10, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="david-miliband" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/david-miliband" data-language="english" href="columnist/david-miliband">David Miliband </a>
offers a plan to improve humanitarian and development efforts in the face of rising extreme poverty.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="international-aid-needed-rethink-even-before-us-cuts-by-david-miliband-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="6911b5956e7cf0dd8ea6c445" data-entity-link-name="international-aid-needed-rethink-even-before-us-cuts-by-david-miliband-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/international-aid-needed-rethink-even-before-us-cuts-by-david-miliband-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/international-aid-needed-rethink-even-before-us-cuts-by-david-miliband-2025-11" title="The Future of International Aid"><span class="u-tos">The Future of International Aid</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a02a63fb13fc8597433325697a74725e.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a02a63fb13fc8597433325697a74725e.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a02a63fb13fc8597433325697a74725e.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/a02a63fb13fc8597433325697a74725e.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/international-aid-needed-rethink-even-before-us-cuts-by-david-miliband-2025-11">The Future of International Aid</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 10, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="david-miliband" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/david-miliband" data-language="english" href="columnist/david-miliband">David Miliband </a>
offers a plan to improve humanitarian and development efforts in the face of rising extreme poverty.        </p>
</header>
</li>
<div id="archive" style="margin: 20px; font-weight: bold; color:red;">Full article text:
 | <a href="https://archive.is?run=1&amp;url=https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/international-aid-needed-rethink-even-before-us-cuts-by-david-miliband-2025-11" target="_blank">archive.is</a></div>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary paywall english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="406cf7297fab47c7879b36d181db5065"> NEW YORK – America’s role in international aid has been turned upside down since January, with institutions shuttered, policies upended, and funding slashed. It is now unclear what lies ahead for American policy, the international aid system, or the world’s poorest. All we know is that a massive gap needs to be filled. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Will AI Democratize Access to Equity Financing?</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/ai-can-expand-access-to-equity-finance-by-ricardo-hausmann-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/ai-can-expand-access-to-equity-finance-by-ricardo-hausmann-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-10T00:00:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-10T00:00:12+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="ai-can-expand-access-to-equity-finance-by-ricardo-hausmann-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="690f83b6d768d309a8bfb163" data-entity-link-name="ai-can-expand-access-to-equity-finance-by-ricardo-hausmann-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/ai-can-expand-access-to-equity-finance-by-ricardo-hausmann-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/ai-can-expand-access-to-equity-finance-by-ricardo-hausmann-2025-11" title="Will AI Democratize Access to Equity Financing?"><span class="u-tos">Will AI Democratize Access to Equity Financing?</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/e271999e2ebc9f214d74644dfacf4ac5.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/e271999e2ebc9f214d74644dfacf4ac5.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/e271999e2ebc9f214d74644dfacf4ac5.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/e271999e2ebc9f214d74644dfacf4ac5.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/ai-can-expand-access-to-equity-finance-by-ricardo-hausmann-2025-11">Will AI Democratize Access to Equity Financing?</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 10, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="ricardo-hausmann" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/ricardo-hausmann" data-language="english" href="columnist/ricardo-hausmann">Ricardo Hausmann </a>
explains how emerging applications of the technology can broaden ownership, spur innovation, and boost growth.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="ai-can-expand-access-to-equity-finance-by-ricardo-hausmann-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="690f83b6d768d309a8bfb163" data-entity-link-name="ai-can-expand-access-to-equity-finance-by-ricardo-hausmann-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/ai-can-expand-access-to-equity-finance-by-ricardo-hausmann-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/ai-can-expand-access-to-equity-finance-by-ricardo-hausmann-2025-11" title="Will AI Democratize Access to Equity Financing?"><span class="u-tos">Will AI Democratize Access to Equity Financing?</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/e271999e2ebc9f214d74644dfacf4ac5.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/e271999e2ebc9f214d74644dfacf4ac5.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/e271999e2ebc9f214d74644dfacf4ac5.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/e271999e2ebc9f214d74644dfacf4ac5.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/ai-can-expand-access-to-equity-finance-by-ricardo-hausmann-2025-11">Will AI Democratize Access to Equity Financing?</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 10, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="ricardo-hausmann" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/ricardo-hausmann" data-language="english" href="columnist/ricardo-hausmann">Ricardo Hausmann </a>
explains how emerging applications of the technology can broaden ownership, spur innovation, and boost growth.        </p>
</header>
</li>
<div id="archive" style="margin: 20px; font-weight: bold; color:red;">Full article text:
 | <a href="https://archive.is?run=1&amp;url=https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/ai-can-expand-access-to-equity-finance-by-ricardo-hausmann-2025-11" target="_blank">archive.is</a></div>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary paywall english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="a1365c645655469997635ab87b64bde2"> CAMBRIDGE – Economists around the world are rightly focused on how AI will reshape labor markets. But the next decade’s most consequential shift may unfold in a different market altogether: equity. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why Emerging Economies Are Embracing AI</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/emerging-economies-can-use-ai-to-advance-social-economic-goals-by-michael-spence-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/emerging-economies-can-use-ai-to-advance-social-economic-goals-by-michael-spence-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-10T00:00:11+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-10T00:00:11+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="emerging-economies-can-use-ai-to-advance-social-economic-goals-by-michael-spence-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="6911b2996e7cf0dd8e9d61d4" data-entity-link-name="emerging-economies-can-use-ai-to-advance-social-economic-goals-by-michael-spence-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/emerging-economies-can-use-ai-to-advance-social-economic-goals-by-michael-spence-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/emerging-economies-can-use-ai-to-advance-social-economic-goals-by-michael-spence-2025-11" title="Why Emerging Economies Are Embracing AI"><span class="u-tos">Why Emerging Economies Are Embracing AI</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/5d6d15c8d1a4522d692b2edc9a490f78.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/5d6d15c8d1a4522d692b2edc9a490f78.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/5d6d15c8d1a4522d692b2edc9a490f78.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/5d6d15c8d1a4522d692b2edc9a490f78.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/emerging-economies-can-use-ai-to-advance-social-economic-goals-by-michael-spence-2025-11">Why Emerging Economies Are Embracing AI</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 10, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="michael-spence" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/michael-spence" data-language="english" href="columnist/michael-spence">Michael Spence </a>
explains that countries do not need to be building models to make the most of the technology.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="emerging-economies-can-use-ai-to-advance-social-economic-goals-by-michael-spence-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="6911b2996e7cf0dd8e9d61d4" data-entity-link-name="emerging-economies-can-use-ai-to-advance-social-economic-goals-by-michael-spence-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/emerging-economies-can-use-ai-to-advance-social-economic-goals-by-michael-spence-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/emerging-economies-can-use-ai-to-advance-social-economic-goals-by-michael-spence-2025-11" title="Why Emerging Economies Are Embracing AI"><span class="u-tos">Why Emerging Economies Are Embracing AI</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/5d6d15c8d1a4522d692b2edc9a490f78.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/5d6d15c8d1a4522d692b2edc9a490f78.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/5d6d15c8d1a4522d692b2edc9a490f78.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/5d6d15c8d1a4522d692b2edc9a490f78.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/emerging-economies-can-use-ai-to-advance-social-economic-goals-by-michael-spence-2025-11">Why Emerging Economies Are Embracing AI</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 10, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="michael-spence" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/michael-spence" data-language="english" href="columnist/michael-spence">Michael Spence </a>
explains that countries do not need to be building models to make the most of the technology.        </p>
</header>
</li>
<div id="archive" style="margin: 20px; font-weight: bold; color:red;">Full article text:
 | <a href="https://archive.is?run=1&amp;url=https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/emerging-economies-can-use-ai-to-advance-social-economic-goals-by-michael-spence-2025-11" target="_blank">archive.is</a></div>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary paywall english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="6f66fb8fb69c42f99b3a52e818f7f0ca"> MILAN – During a recent trip to Kazakhstan, I was struck by people’s enthusiasm for AI. Virtually everyone I encountered – including academics, policymakers, and entrepreneurs – seemed convinced that the technology will help solve thorny challenges, from diversifying the economy away from dependence on natural resources to expanding access to critical services, particularly for remote populations. I had expected the diffusion of knowledge about AI to be slower, but perhaps their positivity should not have surprised me. After all, the rapid development of AI implies important opportunities for emerging economies. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Mamdani’s Big Bet</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/mamdani-democratic-socialists-and-us-political-realignment-by-slavoj-zizek-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/mamdani-democratic-socialists-and-us-political-realignment-by-slavoj-zizek-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-10T00:00:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-10T00:00:10+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="mamdani-democratic-socialists-and-us-political-realignment-by-slavoj-zizek-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="690fb947d768d309a888c9f4" data-entity-link-name="mamdani-democratic-socialists-and-us-political-realignment-by-slavoj-zizek-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/mamdani-democratic-socialists-and-us-political-realignment-by-slavoj-zizek-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/mamdani-democratic-socialists-and-us-political-realignment-by-slavoj-zizek-2025-11" title="Mamdani’s Big Bet"><span class="u-tos">Mamdani’s Big Bet</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/0548d754debaf835d5b38c908bcc9baf.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/0548d754debaf835d5b38c908bcc9baf.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/0548d754debaf835d5b38c908bcc9baf.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/0548d754debaf835d5b38c908bcc9baf.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/mamdani-democratic-socialists-and-us-political-realignment-by-slavoj-zizek-2025-11">Mamdani’s Big Bet</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 10, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="slavoj-zizek" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/slavoj-zizek" data-language="english" href="columnist/slavoj-zizek">Slavoj Žižek </a>
thinks New York’s incoming democratic-socialist mayor understands how American politics is changing.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="mamdani-democratic-socialists-and-us-political-realignment-by-slavoj-zizek-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="690fb947d768d309a888c9f4" data-entity-link-name="mamdani-democratic-socialists-and-us-political-realignment-by-slavoj-zizek-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/mamdani-democratic-socialists-and-us-political-realignment-by-slavoj-zizek-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/mamdani-democratic-socialists-and-us-political-realignment-by-slavoj-zizek-2025-11" title="Mamdani’s Big Bet"><span class="u-tos">Mamdani’s Big Bet</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/0548d754debaf835d5b38c908bcc9baf.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/0548d754debaf835d5b38c908bcc9baf.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/0548d754debaf835d5b38c908bcc9baf.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/0548d754debaf835d5b38c908bcc9baf.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/mamdani-democratic-socialists-and-us-political-realignment-by-slavoj-zizek-2025-11">Mamdani’s Big Bet</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 10, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="slavoj-zizek" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/slavoj-zizek" data-language="english" href="columnist/slavoj-zizek">Slavoj Žižek </a>
thinks New York’s incoming democratic-socialist mayor understands how American politics is changing.        </p>
</header>
</li>
<div id="archive" style="margin: 20px; font-weight: bold; color:red;">Full article text:
 | <a href="https://archive.is?run=1&amp;url=https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/mamdani-democratic-socialists-and-us-political-realignment-by-slavoj-zizek-2025-11" target="_blank">archive.is</a></div>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary paywall english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="5035c49c696b418cbeac1a55c00add48"> LJUBLJANA – Emancipatory movements around the world rightly rejoiced at Zohran Mamdani’s victory in the New York City mayoral race. Clearly, today’s populist right has no monopoly on the ability to mobilize crowds and attract new or disillusioned voters. Democratic socialists can do it, too. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Case for a European-Chinese Green Pact</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/eu-china-green-energy-technology-partnership-would-be-mutually-beneficial-by-jean-pisani-ferry-and-beatrice-weder-di-mauro-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/eu-china-green-energy-technology-partnership-would-be-mutually-beneficial-by-jean-pisani-ferry-and-beatrice-weder-di-mauro-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-07T00:00:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-07T00:00:09+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="eu-china-green-energy-technology-partnership-would-be-mutually-beneficial-by-jean-pisani-ferry-and-beatrice-weder-di-mauro-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="690e3713606380a659aedce6" data-entity-link-name="eu-china-green-energy-technology-partnership-would-be-mutually-beneficial-by-jean-pisani-ferry-and-beatrice-weder-di-mauro-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/eu-china-green-energy-technology-partnership-would-be-mutually-beneficial-by-jean-pisani-ferry-and-beatrice-weder-di-mauro-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/eu-china-green-energy-technology-partnership-would-be-mutually-beneficial-by-jean-pisani-ferry-and-beatrice-weder-di-mauro-2025-11" title="The Case for a European-Chinese Green Pact"><span class="u-tos">The Case for a European-Chinese Green Pact</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/622685ad20f6960922635517853bb189.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/622685ad20f6960922635517853bb189.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/622685ad20f6960922635517853bb189.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/622685ad20f6960922635517853bb189.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/eu-china-green-energy-technology-partnership-would-be-mutually-beneficial-by-jean-pisani-ferry-and-beatrice-weder-di-mauro-2025-11">The Case for a European-Chinese Green Pact</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 7, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="jean-pisani-ferry" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/jean-pisani-ferry" data-language="english" href="columnist/jean-pisani-ferry">Jean Pisani-Ferry </a> &amp; <a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="beatrice-weder-di-mauro" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/beatrice-weder-di-mauro" data-language="english" href="columnist/beatrice-weder-di-mauro">Beatrice Weder di Mauro </a>

think both sides have much to gain from pursuing closer economic ties through clean energy and technology.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="eu-china-green-energy-technology-partnership-would-be-mutually-beneficial-by-jean-pisani-ferry-and-beatrice-weder-di-mauro-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="690e3713606380a659aedce6" data-entity-link-name="eu-china-green-energy-technology-partnership-would-be-mutually-beneficial-by-jean-pisani-ferry-and-beatrice-weder-di-mauro-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/eu-china-green-energy-technology-partnership-would-be-mutually-beneficial-by-jean-pisani-ferry-and-beatrice-weder-di-mauro-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/eu-china-green-energy-technology-partnership-would-be-mutually-beneficial-by-jean-pisani-ferry-and-beatrice-weder-di-mauro-2025-11" title="The Case for a European-Chinese Green Pact"><span class="u-tos">The Case for a European-Chinese Green Pact</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/622685ad20f6960922635517853bb189.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/622685ad20f6960922635517853bb189.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/622685ad20f6960922635517853bb189.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/622685ad20f6960922635517853bb189.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/eu-china-green-energy-technology-partnership-would-be-mutually-beneficial-by-jean-pisani-ferry-and-beatrice-weder-di-mauro-2025-11">The Case for a European-Chinese Green Pact</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 7, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="jean-pisani-ferry" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/jean-pisani-ferry" data-language="english" href="columnist/jean-pisani-ferry">Jean Pisani-Ferry </a> &amp; <a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="beatrice-weder-di-mauro" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/beatrice-weder-di-mauro" data-language="english" href="columnist/beatrice-weder-di-mauro">Beatrice Weder di Mauro </a>

think both sides have much to gain from pursuing closer economic ties through clean energy and technology.        </p>
</header>
</li>
<div id="archive" style="margin: 20px; font-weight: bold; color:red;">Full article text:
 | <a href="https://archive.is?run=1&amp;url=https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/eu-china-green-energy-technology-partnership-would-be-mutually-beneficial-by-jean-pisani-ferry-and-beatrice-weder-di-mauro-2025-11" target="_blank">archive.is</a></div>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary paywall english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="790702c866b7450ea905d73d9c9c16b8"> GENEVA/PARIS – In early 2021, the European Union shelved the Comprehensive Agreement on Investment it had negotiated with China after the United States signaled its disapproval. At the time, deferring to the new US administration seemed prudent, because Europe was eager to rebuild transatlantic unity after Donald Trump’s first term. For a while, it looked like a wise move: US President <a href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/columnist/joseph-biden-jr">Joe Biden</a> soon rejoined the Paris climate agreement and proclaimed that “America is back.” </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Europe Must Find Its Own Way in Ukraine</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/ukraine-war-europe-should-cut-out-trump-talk-to-china-and-kremlin-by-zaki-laidi-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/ukraine-war-europe-should-cut-out-trump-talk-to-china-and-kremlin-by-zaki-laidi-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-07T00:00:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-07T00:00:08+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="ukraine-war-europe-should-cut-out-trump-talk-to-china-and-kremlin-by-zaki-laidi-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="690e0f0b606380a6593ab3bd" data-entity-link-name="ukraine-war-europe-should-cut-out-trump-talk-to-china-and-kremlin-by-zaki-laidi-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/ukraine-war-europe-should-cut-out-trump-talk-to-china-and-kremlin-by-zaki-laidi-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/ukraine-war-europe-should-cut-out-trump-talk-to-china-and-kremlin-by-zaki-laidi-2025-11" title="Europe Must Find Its Own Way in Ukraine"><span class="u-tos">Europe Must Find Its Own Way in Ukraine</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1898a61982935ae4fda3d1f03e865d39.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1898a61982935ae4fda3d1f03e865d39.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1898a61982935ae4fda3d1f03e865d39.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1898a61982935ae4fda3d1f03e865d39.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/ukraine-war-europe-should-cut-out-trump-talk-to-china-and-kremlin-by-zaki-laidi-2025-11">Europe Must Find Its Own Way in Ukraine</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 7, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="zaki-laidi" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/zaki-laidi" data-language="english" href="columnist/zaki-laidi">Zaki Laïdi </a>
sees no option but for European leaders to pursue new diplomacy with China and then Russia.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="ukraine-war-europe-should-cut-out-trump-talk-to-china-and-kremlin-by-zaki-laidi-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="690e0f0b606380a6593ab3bd" data-entity-link-name="ukraine-war-europe-should-cut-out-trump-talk-to-china-and-kremlin-by-zaki-laidi-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/ukraine-war-europe-should-cut-out-trump-talk-to-china-and-kremlin-by-zaki-laidi-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/ukraine-war-europe-should-cut-out-trump-talk-to-china-and-kremlin-by-zaki-laidi-2025-11" title="Europe Must Find Its Own Way in Ukraine"><span class="u-tos">Europe Must Find Its Own Way in Ukraine</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1898a61982935ae4fda3d1f03e865d39.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1898a61982935ae4fda3d1f03e865d39.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1898a61982935ae4fda3d1f03e865d39.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1898a61982935ae4fda3d1f03e865d39.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/ukraine-war-europe-should-cut-out-trump-talk-to-china-and-kremlin-by-zaki-laidi-2025-11">Europe Must Find Its Own Way in Ukraine</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 7, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="zaki-laidi" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/zaki-laidi" data-language="english" href="columnist/zaki-laidi">Zaki Laïdi </a>
sees no option but for European leaders to pursue new diplomacy with China and then Russia.        </p>
</header>
</li>
<div id="archive" style="margin: 20px; font-weight: bold; color:red;">Full article text:
 | <a href="https://archive.is?run=1&amp;url=https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/ukraine-war-europe-should-cut-out-trump-talk-to-china-and-kremlin-by-zaki-laidi-2025-11" target="_blank">archive.is</a></div>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary paywall english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="db5b0e03510c479e99f6da4e7096da48"> PARIS – Recent developments in the Donbas confirm that while the Russian army is indeed advancing, its progress is very slow and comes at a phenomenal cost in human lives and limbs. But if Russian President Vladimir Putin can shrug off the deaths of hundreds of thousands of his soldiers, does that mean Ukraine and Europe are destined to live with an endless conflict? </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Is Takaichi Sanae Japan’s Margaret Thatcher?</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/how-will-takaichi-sanae-address-inflation-gender-inequality-geopolitical-tensions-by-koichi-hamada-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/how-will-takaichi-sanae-address-inflation-gender-inequality-geopolitical-tensions-by-koichi-hamada-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-07T00:00:07+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-07T00:00:07+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="how-will-takaichi-sanae-address-inflation-gender-inequality-geopolitical-tensions-by-koichi-hamada-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="690e1269606380a659439df8" data-entity-link-name="how-will-takaichi-sanae-address-inflation-gender-inequality-geopolitical-tensions-by-koichi-hamada-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/how-will-takaichi-sanae-address-inflation-gender-inequality-geopolitical-tensions-by-koichi-hamada-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/how-will-takaichi-sanae-address-inflation-gender-inequality-geopolitical-tensions-by-koichi-hamada-2025-11" title="Is Takaichi Sanae Japan’s Margaret Thatcher?"><span class="u-tos">Is Takaichi Sanae Japan’s Margaret Thatcher?</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/e44dace9cfc7c2cf52fa41ed4b3a13c6.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/e44dace9cfc7c2cf52fa41ed4b3a13c6.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/e44dace9cfc7c2cf52fa41ed4b3a13c6.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/e44dace9cfc7c2cf52fa41ed4b3a13c6.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/how-will-takaichi-sanae-address-inflation-gender-inequality-geopolitical-tensions-by-koichi-hamada-2025-11">Is Takaichi Sanae Japan’s Margaret Thatcher?</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 7, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="koichi-hamada" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/koichi-hamada" data-language="english" href="columnist/koichi-hamada">Koichi Hamada </a>
thinks the answer will depend on her success in managing three key challenges.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="how-will-takaichi-sanae-address-inflation-gender-inequality-geopolitical-tensions-by-koichi-hamada-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="690e1269606380a659439df8" data-entity-link-name="how-will-takaichi-sanae-address-inflation-gender-inequality-geopolitical-tensions-by-koichi-hamada-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/how-will-takaichi-sanae-address-inflation-gender-inequality-geopolitical-tensions-by-koichi-hamada-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/how-will-takaichi-sanae-address-inflation-gender-inequality-geopolitical-tensions-by-koichi-hamada-2025-11" title="Is Takaichi Sanae Japan’s Margaret Thatcher?"><span class="u-tos">Is Takaichi Sanae Japan’s Margaret Thatcher?</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/e44dace9cfc7c2cf52fa41ed4b3a13c6.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/e44dace9cfc7c2cf52fa41ed4b3a13c6.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/e44dace9cfc7c2cf52fa41ed4b3a13c6.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/e44dace9cfc7c2cf52fa41ed4b3a13c6.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/how-will-takaichi-sanae-address-inflation-gender-inequality-geopolitical-tensions-by-koichi-hamada-2025-11">Is Takaichi Sanae Japan’s Margaret Thatcher?</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 7, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="koichi-hamada" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/koichi-hamada" data-language="english" href="columnist/koichi-hamada">Koichi Hamada </a>
thinks the answer will depend on her success in managing three key challenges.        </p>
</header>
</li>
<div id="archive" style="margin: 20px; font-weight: bold; color:red;">Full article text:
 | <a href="https://archive.is?run=1&amp;url=https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/how-will-takaichi-sanae-address-inflation-gender-inequality-geopolitical-tensions-by-koichi-hamada-2025-11" target="_blank">archive.is</a></div>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary paywall english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="eab8a16c6d9d43209dfac2a68e956f31"> NEW HAVEN – For the first time in its history, Japan’s parliament has selected a woman, Takaichi Sanae of the Liberal Democratic Party, to be prime minister. In this sense, Takaichi has already followed in the footsteps of her <a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/asia/japan/japan-sanae-takaichi-new-prime-minister-drummer-policies-b2849747.html">political idol</a>, Margaret Thatcher – the United Kingdom’s first female prime minister. But whether she is remembered as Japan’s own “Iron Lady” will depend on her ability to manage three key challenges: inflation, low female labor-force participation, and a fraught geopolitical environment. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why Climate Finance Is Not Enough</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/green-technology-transfers-must-accompany-climate-finance-by-laura-carvalho-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/green-technology-transfers-must-accompany-climate-finance-by-laura-carvalho-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-07T00:00:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-07T00:00:06+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="green-technology-transfers-must-accompany-climate-finance-by-laura-carvalho-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="690df886606380a659f18cc7" data-entity-link-name="green-technology-transfers-must-accompany-climate-finance-by-laura-carvalho-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/green-technology-transfers-must-accompany-climate-finance-by-laura-carvalho-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/green-technology-transfers-must-accompany-climate-finance-by-laura-carvalho-2025-11" title="Why Climate Finance Is Not Enough"><span class="u-tos">Why Climate Finance Is Not Enough</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/bd5355e07fe9c516febda2a3255ebfc9.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/bd5355e07fe9c516febda2a3255ebfc9.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/bd5355e07fe9c516febda2a3255ebfc9.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/bd5355e07fe9c516febda2a3255ebfc9.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/green-technology-transfers-must-accompany-climate-finance-by-laura-carvalho-2025-11">Why Climate Finance Is Not Enough</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 7, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="laura-carvalho" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/laura-carvalho" data-language="english" href="columnist/laura-carvalho">Laura Carvalho </a>
sees a need for a more accommodating intellectual-property regime to facilitate green technology transfers.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="green-technology-transfers-must-accompany-climate-finance-by-laura-carvalho-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="690df886606380a659f18cc7" data-entity-link-name="green-technology-transfers-must-accompany-climate-finance-by-laura-carvalho-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/green-technology-transfers-must-accompany-climate-finance-by-laura-carvalho-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/green-technology-transfers-must-accompany-climate-finance-by-laura-carvalho-2025-11" title="Why Climate Finance Is Not Enough"><span class="u-tos">Why Climate Finance Is Not Enough</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/bd5355e07fe9c516febda2a3255ebfc9.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/bd5355e07fe9c516febda2a3255ebfc9.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/bd5355e07fe9c516febda2a3255ebfc9.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/bd5355e07fe9c516febda2a3255ebfc9.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/green-technology-transfers-must-accompany-climate-finance-by-laura-carvalho-2025-11">Why Climate Finance Is Not Enough</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 7, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="laura-carvalho" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/laura-carvalho" data-language="english" href="columnist/laura-carvalho">Laura Carvalho </a>
sees a need for a more accommodating intellectual-property regime to facilitate green technology transfers.        </p>
</header>
</li>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="7b6f3215698f4a0eb30f2c6769efbf21"> SÃO PAULO – With the United Nations Climate Conference (COP30) in Belém, Brazil, approaching, it is clear that the world’s widely shared commitment to a just energy transition is falling by the wayside. In the year since governments signed on to the agreement at COP29 to scale up climate finance – with a goal of mobilizing $1.3 trillion annually by 2035 – wealthy countries have been retreating from their financial pledges. Worse, these signs of bad faith are coming just as the costs of climate adaptation and decarbonization in developing countries are mounting. </p>
<p data-line-id="fc5705a95e1c465cb8fdfa9e92fc5927"> If the Global North is no longer willing to meet its funding promises, as now seems certain, it can still demonstrate good faith, nonetheless, through another form of solidarity: sharing the knowledge, technology, and intellectual property that underpin the green transition. </p>
<p data-line-id="c9624c52476b4d388d9c0a2607779146"> This is not an issue that can be deferred. The shift to a green economy is already reproducing the same asymmetries that have long defined global trade. Instead of fostering inclusive development, climate policy is increasingly being shaped by protectionist measures and IP regimes that entrench technological monopolies in the Global North. For example, the European Union’s Carbon Border Adjustment Mechanism may be billed as a safeguard against carbon leakage; but it also illustrates how climate policy can be used to justify protectionist trade measures. </p>
<p data-line-id="1f2e87891de641b9aebd15b8d84cf63d"> Moreover, China’s recent <a href="https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/economy/foreign-trade/china-files-wto-complaint-against-india-over-ev-battery-subsidies-urges-new-delhi-to-rectify-wrongdoings/articleshow/124571889.cms">complaint</a> against India for its electric-vehicle and battery subsidies shows how green industrial policies are increasingly becoming grounds for trade disputes. Together, these developments signal a growing tension between climate goals and World Trade Organization rules. Could measures to address climate change soon become a new impetus for economic exclusion? </p>
<p data-line-id="93bf01789124457a821484db8d68aa0b"> At the heart of this issue lies a stark imbalance: larger powers like China, the United States, and the EU are producing high-value green technologies, while most developing countries are stuck exporting low-value green commodities – primarily critical minerals. This mirrors the colonial-era division of labor, whereby the Global South supplied raw materials, and the North supplied innovation, monopolized production, and reaped the largest profits. </p>
<div data-classes="newsletter--bg newsletter--yellow newsletter--branding newsletter--compact newsletter--label newsletter--admin" data-consent="true" data-description="Go beyond the headlines to understand the issues, forces, and trends shaping the US presidential election – and the likely implications of its outcome." data-label="Sign up for our weekly newsletter, PS Politics" data-link-name="newsletter-politics" data-newsletter="prosyn-above-the-fold" data-newsletter-subscribe-form="true"></div>
<p data-line-id="f43bc6c24e0b4c2ba6f23b66033106d0"> Data from the World Intellectual Property Organization <a href="https://www.wipo.int/edocs/pubdocs/en/wipo_pub_econstat_wp_44.pdf">underscore</a> the depth of this divide. Green patents (relating to renewable energy, energy efficiency, and climate adaptation) are overwhelmingly concentrated in a handful of countries, such as China, the US, Japan, and Germany. Between 2000 and 2024, the top ten economies accounted for nearly 90% of international patent filings in solar and wind technologies. Brazil, despite ranking sixth globally in installed wind capacity, contributed only 0.4% of global wind patents. For solar, its share was a mere 0.19%. </p>
<p data-line-id="f2f8211539cf44bcbc6b44ad4cb1fbf2"> This technological concentration is not accidental. It is the result of a global IP regime that privileges monopoly profits over public goods. Efforts to foster more global coordination, including through the <a href="https://www.wto.org/english/tratop_e/trips_e/trips_e.htm">Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights</a> (TRIPS) agreement, have failed to address the fundamental problem. </p>
<p data-line-id="b1e4bb04008646e1be5d1989d7171c9c"> Without access to affordable technologies, the Global South cannot fully participate in the climate transition. Worse, the current system risks locking developing countries into a new form of dependency, supplying the minerals for batteries and solar panels but lacking the means to produce them. </p>
<p data-line-id="6274447ec049417381b03bdedf9a4303"> Climate finance is not sufficient to break this cycle. Instead, technology transfers and reforms to the global IP regime must be at the center of climate negotiations. While the UN Framework Convention on Climate Change and the Paris climate agreement do acknowledge this, little progress has been made. </p>
<p data-line-id="7fae00315285470083be566db1f4ebd8"> Fortunately, there is a precedent for the necessary changes. Back in the 2000s, Brazil played a pivotal role in categorizing access to HIV/AIDS medicines as a public good, rather than as a commodity governed solely by IP rights. This shift was driven by a combination of legal, political, and civil-society actions that challenged the global pharmaceutical patent regime and put public health first. </p>
<p data-line-id="f92fb8141ad549fbb13305c57c33e2a0"> As the Nobel laureate economist <a href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/columnist/joseph-e-stiglitz">Joseph Stiglitz</a> has <a href="https://cgt.columbia.edu/news/stiglitz-wealth-health-intellectual-property-laws-facing-counterattack/">argued</a>, such mechanisms are essential to correct market failures and ensure equitable access to innovation. That is why the International Court of Justice, in its recent <a href="https://www.icj-cij.org/sites/default/files/case-related/187/187-20250723-pre-01-00-en.pdf">advisory opinion</a> on climate change, underscored the obligation of all states to cooperate – beyond the provision of finance – on the development and diffusion of green technologies, including by sharing knowledge and engaging in technology transfers.  </p>
<p data-line-id="3da193e1fd4c43dc88bb2d4b08cc0d5a"> The Technology Implementation Program that was agreed at COP28 offers a means to foster such cooperation. Under Brazil’s leadership at COP30, TIP can become a platform for strengthening national innovation systems, enabling countries to adapt technologies to local contexts and build capacity for climate solutions. The idea is to use a mix of public and private money to support trial projects, and then to scale those that prove effective. </p>
<p data-line-id="a2e001acf81445b5a88da182c39296eb"> For example, we could support a pilot that aims to produce low-carbon fertilizer using green hydrogen. Currently, ammonia – the key input for nitrogen fertilizers – is made using hydrogen from fossil fuels, which is why the sector is responsible for roughly <a href="https://www.carbonbrief.org/fertiliser-emissions-could-be-cut-to-one-fifth-of-current-levels-by-2050/">1-2% of global carbon dioxide emissions</a>. By replacing fossil-based hydrogen with renewable (green) hydrogen, the same ammonia output would produce far fewer emissions, as well as offering a scalable, locally adaptable solution. If the pilot succeeds in this hard-to-abate sector, it will create a replicable model for other countries. </p>
<p data-line-id="c9b63c1d0a614c9b874d378bffc672cb"> Brazil’s COP30 presidency can rally the Global South behind a vision of TIP that delivers climate justice through innovation. This is not just a technical agenda, but a political one. Only by empowering countries with access to green technologies can they build the capacity they need. And by helping the rest of the world decarbonize, wealthy countries will be helping themselves. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Toward Humanist Superintelligence</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/humanist-superintelligence-ai-must-be-designed-for-human-control-by-mustafa-suleyman-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/humanist-superintelligence-ai-must-be-designed-for-human-control-by-mustafa-suleyman-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-07T00:00:05+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-07T00:00:05+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="humanist-superintelligence-ai-must-be-designed-for-human-control-by-mustafa-suleyman-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="690df2f3606380a659e0a0ed" data-entity-link-name="humanist-superintelligence-ai-must-be-designed-for-human-control-by-mustafa-suleyman-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/humanist-superintelligence-ai-must-be-designed-for-human-control-by-mustafa-suleyman-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/humanist-superintelligence-ai-must-be-designed-for-human-control-by-mustafa-suleyman-2025-11" title="Toward Humanist Superintelligence"><span class="u-tos">Toward Humanist Superintelligence</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1cce4994c6d43f00c3672f42a044a4d9.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1cce4994c6d43f00c3672f42a044a4d9.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1cce4994c6d43f00c3672f42a044a4d9.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1cce4994c6d43f00c3672f42a044a4d9.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/humanist-superintelligence-ai-must-be-designed-for-human-control-by-mustafa-suleyman-2025-11">Toward Humanist Superintelligence</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 7, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="mustafa-suleyman" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/mustafa-suleyman" data-language="english" href="columnist/mustafa-suleyman">Mustafa Suleyman </a>
warns against the creation of entirely unbounded, autonomous advanced AI systems.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default" data-url="humanist-superintelligence-ai-must-be-designed-for-human-control-by-mustafa-suleyman-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="690df2f3606380a659e0a0ed" data-entity-link-name="humanist-superintelligence-ai-must-be-designed-for-human-control-by-mustafa-suleyman-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/commentary/humanist-superintelligence-ai-must-be-designed-for-human-control-by-mustafa-suleyman-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/commentary/humanist-superintelligence-ai-must-be-designed-for-human-control-by-mustafa-suleyman-2025-11" title="Toward Humanist Superintelligence"><span class="u-tos">Toward Humanist Superintelligence</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1cce4994c6d43f00c3672f42a044a4d9.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1cce4994c6d43f00c3672f42a044a4d9.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1cce4994c6d43f00c3672f42a044a4d9.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/1cce4994c6d43f00c3672f42a044a4d9.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="commentary/humanist-superintelligence-ai-must-be-designed-for-human-control-by-mustafa-suleyman-2025-11">Toward Humanist Superintelligence</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 7, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="mustafa-suleyman" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/mustafa-suleyman" data-language="english" href="columnist/mustafa-suleyman">Mustafa Suleyman </a>
warns against the creation of entirely unbounded, autonomous advanced AI systems.        </p>
</header>
</li>
<div id="archive" style="margin: 20px; font-weight: bold; color:red;">Full article text:
 | <a href="https://archive.is?run=1&amp;url=https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/humanist-superintelligence-ai-must-be-designed-for-human-control-by-mustafa-suleyman-2025-11" target="_blank">archive.is</a></div>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary paywall english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="34d232e329574485abffc0eb1da1b693"> REDMOND – For decades, the Turing test was AI researchers’ North Star. Today, it’s been quietly surpassed. With reasoning models and agentic capabilities emerging, and with the pace of AI infrastructure build increasing, we have crossed an inflection point on the journey to superintelligence: the point at which AI exceeds human-level performance at all tasks. </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>In Search of the AI Bubble’s Economic Fundamentals</title>
    <link href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/onpoint/will-ai-bubble-burst-trigger-financial-crisis-by-william-h-janeway-2025-11" />
    <id>https://www.project-syndicate.org/onpoint/will-ai-bubble-burst-trigger-financial-crisis-by-william-h-janeway-2025-11</id>
    <published>2025-11-07T00:00:04+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-11-07T00:00:04+00:00</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default onpoint" data-url="will-ai-bubble-burst-trigger-financial-crisis-by-william-h-janeway-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="690db1fed064fa643bf9b5fd" data-entity-link-name="will-ai-bubble-burst-trigger-financial-crisis-by-william-h-janeway-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/onpoint/will-ai-bubble-burst-trigger-financial-crisis-by-william-h-janeway-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/onpoint/will-ai-bubble-burst-trigger-financial-crisis-by-william-h-janeway-2025-11" title="In Search of the AI Bubble’s Economic Fundamentals"><span class="u-tos">In Search of the AI Bubble’s Economic Fundamentals</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/65eb8eaaaa686846b84ebce03dc96874.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/65eb8eaaaa686846b84ebce03dc96874.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/65eb8eaaaa686846b84ebce03dc96874.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/65eb8eaaaa686846b84ebce03dc96874.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="onpoint/will-ai-bubble-burst-trigger-financial-crisis-by-william-h-janeway-2025-11">In Search of the AI Bubble’s Economic Fundamentals</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 7, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="william-h-janeway" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/william-h-janeway" data-language="english" href="columnist/william-h-janeway">William H. Janeway </a>
explains why the sector might be better off if the reckoning comes sooner rather than after leverage piles up.        </p>
</header>
</li>]]></summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<li class="listing listing--default onpoint" data-url="will-ai-bubble-burst-trigger-financial-crisis-by-william-h-janeway-2025-11">
<a class="track-event overlay" data-entity-id="690db1fed064fa643bf9b5fd" data-entity-link-name="will-ai-bubble-burst-trigger-financial-crisis-by-william-h-janeway-2025-11" data-entity-type="document" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="/onpoint/will-ai-bubble-burst-trigger-financial-crisis-by-william-h-janeway-2025-11" data-language="english" href="/onpoint/will-ai-bubble-burst-trigger-financial-crisis-by-william-h-janeway-2025-11" title="In Search of the AI Bubble’s Economic Fundamentals"><span class="u-tos">In Search of the AI Bubble’s Economic Fundamentals</span></a>
<figure class="image listing__image image--ratio-list">
<picture>
<source media="--small" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/65eb8eaaaa686846b84ebce03dc96874.2-1-large.1.jpg"/>
<source media="--large" srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/65eb8eaaaa686846b84ebce03dc96874.4-3-medium.1.jpg"/>
<source srcset="https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/65eb8eaaaa686846b84ebce03dc96874.2-1-medium.1.jpg"/>
<img alt="" height="310" loading="lazy" src="https://pic1.xuehuaimg.com/proxy/https://webapi.project-syndicate.org/library/65eb8eaaaa686846b84ebce03dc96874.2-1-large.1.jpg" width="620"/>
</picture>
</figure>
<header class="listing__header">
<h2 class="listing__title">
<a href="onpoint/will-ai-bubble-burst-trigger-financial-crisis-by-william-h-janeway-2025-11">In Search of the AI Bubble’s Economic Fundamentals</a>
</h2>
<p class="listing__excerpt">
<span class="bl-pubdate vl-divider">Nov 7, 2025</span>
<a class="track-event listing__author author" data-entity-id="" data-entity-link-name="william-h-janeway" data-entity-type="member" data-event-action="click" data-href-original="columnist/william-h-janeway" data-language="english" href="columnist/william-h-janeway">William H. Janeway </a>
explains why the sector might be better off if the reckoning comes sooner rather than after leverage piles up.        </p>
</header>
</li>
<div id="archive" style="margin: 20px; font-weight: bold; color:red;">Full article text:
 | <a href="https://archive.is?run=1&amp;url=https://www.project-syndicate.org/onpoint/will-ai-bubble-burst-trigger-financial-crisis-by-william-h-janeway-2025-11" target="_blank">archive.is</a></div>
    <br/> <div class="article__body article__body--commentary paywall english" data-page-area="article-body" dir="ltr" itemprop="articleBody">
<p data-line-id="20efc78d05924d05b6c1e51366e9e1db"> CAMBRIDGE – In recent weeks, the notion that we are witnessing an “AI Bubble” has moved from the fringes of public debate to the mainstream. As <em>Financial Times</em> commentator Katie Martin <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/ce8bc257-5f06-4005-bd36-b094a9b91938">aptly put it</a>, “Bubble-talk is breaking out everywhere.” </p>
</div>]]></content>
  </entry>
</feed>
