<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>VOA Special English</title>
        <link>https://www.21voa.com/special_english/</link>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <itunes:category>ESL</itunes:category>
        <itunes:author>VOA</itunes:author>
        <description>美国之音（以下称VOA）的英语节目，按播音速度可分为两种：Standard English （标准英语）和 Special English（特别英语）。

Special English 又叫“慢速英语”，是VOA 专为全世界非英语国家初学英语的听众安排的一种简易、规范的英语广播节目。该节目创始于50年代末期，是VOA 的专家们研究如何与世界各地的英语学习者进行交际的产物。它正式开播于1959年10月。当时只面向欧洲和中东，但由于这个节目适合许多国家英语学习者的需要，所以它的广播对象不久就扩大到世界其他地区，并很快在全世界范围内产生了广泛的影响。现在这个节目对欧洲、非洲和拉丁美洲每晚广播一次，对加勒比地区每晚广播一次（星期天除外），对东南亚广播次数最多，每天上午两次，晚上三次。

30多年来，VOA 为了办好Special English节目，进行了大量的调查研究工作，对播音速度、内容及用词范围都作了具体规定，基本上达到了既能为英语学习者提供信息，又不损害英语本身风格的目的，使之成为VOA 独具特色，拥有最大量听众的节目。

美国著名词汇学家S. B. Flexmer 指明了Special English的三条标准，也就是它所“特别”的地方：

1、它是一种由美国人最常用的1500个基本单词为主体构成的美国英语；

2、它用简短、明晰的句子写作和广播；

3、它以每分钟90个单词的速度，即2/3的Standard English（标准英语）速度进行广播。

Special English的节目可分为两大类：一类是新闻节目；一类是专题节目。

1．新闻节目

VOA Special English 的新闻广播向听众提供世界范围内的政治、经济、军事、外交、国际关系、宗教、天气以及各种重大事件和珍闻奇事等各个方面的信息，每天向东南亚地区广播五次，早上两次，晚上三次，每逢半点播出。

Special English新闻节目每次长约十分钟，大都播出十条左右新闻，近一千个单词，每条新闻多为一分钟，但偶尔也有长达两分钟的要闻。除头条新闻外，每条新闻都由一个电头引导，这样显得结构分明，条理清晰，适宜初学英语的人收听。在节目结束之前，播音员常常用三四句话重播其中三条新闻的提要以加深听众对要闻的印象。

Special English新闻中70%左右的内容与同时整点播出的Standard English新闻相同，但相同新闻的先后次序有所变动。每次节目的开头和结尾大同小异，格式比较固定。

2．专题节目（一）

Special English的专题节目（Feature Programs）,从时间上看，可分为两大类：一是每五分钟一次的专题，二是每十五分钟一次的专题。本节先介绍每项五分钟一次的专题材节目。

Special English五分钟一次的专题材节目安排在Special English新闻节目之后和（或）每十五分钟一次的专题材节目之前播出，每星期播七次。根据内容，可分为三个小类，即：Science Report（科学报道），逢星期一、三、五播出，每天播六遍；Agriculture Report（农业报道），逢星期二、四播出，每天播六遍；Words And Their Stories（词语掌故），逢星期六和星期天播出，每天播五遍。这三个专题材各具特色，具有相对的独立性，听众每听完一个节目，都会获得一个完整的印象。

Science Report（科学报道）这一专题材节目每周向听众介绍三篇有关现代科学技术最新发展情况的报道，涉及物理、化学、天文至高无上理、生物、环卫、心理、教育、医学和计算机等方面。适宜理工科大学生和科技工作者收集信息，积累资料，学习科技英语。

Agriculture Report（农业报道） Agriculture Report是为农业科技工作者和生产者安排的一个专题。它专门报道世界各国，特别是美国现代农业生产的最新成文汇报总务科 学家对农业生产某一方面的研究进展，以及他们对影响农业生产的某一自然现象进行分析和研究的近况。此外，它还经常向听众介绍发展中国家家业生产的一些有益经验等内容。

Words And Their Stories（词语掌故）这一专题节目，旨在向学习英语的听众介绍美国英语中生动有趣的词语和惯用法，并从科学研究和通俗词源学的角度来解释它们的含意、产生的背景及其在使用过程中的演变情况等。它通过讲故事的形式讲解每一个词语。这是VOA Special English中的优秀节目之一，是学习美国英语的极好材料。通过收听这一节目，听众不仅能学到娓娓动听的掌故和地道的美国英语，而且能增加美国的社会文化背景知识，历史传统与现状的了解。

VOA 为了更好地办好这个节目，便于听众收听学习，于1978年编辑出版了一本名为Words And Their Stories的书，共收集一百篇故事，作者是Herbert Sutcliffe, Harold Bermen 及VOA 该节目的部分编辑人员。在每次的实际广播中，播音员都以此书为蓝本，再根据需要对原稿进行适当增删。按每周两个故事计算，此书的一百个故事还不能满足一年的播音需要。于是编辑们就是重播部分词语掌故的同时，不断增加许多新的词语掌故，及时将词源学家的最新研究成果和不断增加的新词汇介绍给听众。收听实践证明，初学者在收听过程中必然会遇到许多人名、地名和一些较难的句子，有时甚至在听完之后还很难理解所播词语的确切含义及其汉语意思，为此，听众可参看1983年由中国对外翻译出版公司出版的该书英汉对照本中的有关部分。

3．专题节目（二）

VOA Special English的专题节目，除上节谈的五分钟一次的以外，还有本节要介绍的每十五分钟一次的节目。这类节目共有七个不同的小专题，以星期为单位循环，每天分四次复播出一个专题，但星期日和星期六的两个专题材每晚只播三遍，每次节目约十分钟，继每次五分钟的专题节目之后播出。

这类专题节目的基本结构是，在特定的伴声中先报告当次节目的名称，并扼要介绍其主要内容，然后播送节目正文。最后，在伴乐声中报告节目主持人和撰稿人的姓名，以邀请听众在下周的这个时间继续收听该节目而结束。

People in America（美国人物志） 这是有关美国历史名人的一个专题节目，每逢星期天晚上播出。它向听众介绍在美国历史上产生过重大影响、起过重要作用、作出了突出贡献的科学、文学、政治、或其他各方面的历史人物。节目一般都对他们的生平事迹进行简要的叙述，对其贡献作出评介，类似人物小传。有的重要人物事迹很多，必须用两次或几次的节目时间进行联播。对这样的节目要坚持收听，才会获得完整的印象。

TThis is America（今日美国） This Is America向听众介绍美国人民的生活、学习、工作和娱乐情况，是英语学习者解美国社会的一条渠道。该专题大都一个节目一个整体，每逢星期一晚播出。

Science in the News（科学新闻） 这一专题材主要对新近的科学技术新闻进行综述或摘要广播。向听众介绍世界各国在自然、医学、疾病、原子能、航天等方面的科研动态、成果、突破性进展及存在的困难。涉及当今世界人们普遍关心的重大问题，如核事故、航天飞机爆炸、自然灾害、环境污染和爱滋病等等。每逢星期二播出，每次播一到五条新闻摘要。

Explorations（自然探索） 每逢星期三晚上，听众可以收听到Explorations这一专题节目。该专题既涉及人类遨游太空、探索原子、研究自身、改造自然的现代技术，也报道发展中国家开发新资源，利用新工艺改善人民生活等方面的成就，其侧重点在各种科技实验和简易实用技术方面。该节目一般安排一段时间播一个系列，每次播出一个主题，以便能将某项新技术的研究和应用的全过程介绍给听众，电台还乐意为感兴趣的听众提供所需的文字材料。

The Making of a Nation（建国史话） 这一专题节目向听众介绍美利坚合众国从十三个殖民地区域到现代工业国的孕育、诞生以及形成超级大国的历史过程，并以历史为线索，特定的历史时期为单位，以重大的历史事件为主题材来叙述各个党派、各届总统和政府的历史作用与贡献。这是每个英语学习者都应了解的基本知识。The Making of a Nation每逢星期四播出。这是个系列节目，坚持收听，则有助于系统了解美国的历史概况。

American Mosaic（美国万花筒） American Mosaic是一个radio magazine（广播杂志）节目。该节目题材广泛、内容丰，展示着美国社会文化生活中比较轻松愉快的生活画面；听众收听该节目就如同在阅读一本图文并茂的杂志。它每次有三到五个小节目，涉及音乐、图书、技术和教育等方面的内容。我们既可以从中欣赏到著名歌唱的优秀歌曲，对美国音乐有所了解，又可以获取一些生动有趣的现代美国社会生活知识，随着播音员那亲切悦耳的声音步入美国风景如画的大好河山；同时还能听到世界各地的听众提出的有关英语语方文学等方面的问题和电台的解答。

American Stories（美国故事） 这一专题材节目安排在每星期六晚上播出。这样能使听众在学习和工作之余，得以轻松一下头脑。我们可以通过这一美国文学的“窗口”，接触各种流派、各类名家的文学作品。了解美国英语的时代特色，欣赏、学习美国人民运用语方的技巧，并从那些佳作名篇中获得艺术享受。该节目对短篇故事采取一次播一篇的方式，对中、长篇小说则先进行简写加工，再分几次播出全文。在播出故事正文之前，播音员常常先介绍故事的主要情节。对需要分几次节目时间播出的中长篇，在播第二或以后各部分之前，主持人还先重述已播部分的故事梗概，以唤起听众的回忆，使故事听起来更加连贯。</description>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Use Ancient Genes to Estimate Contact Between Humans, Neanderthals  (2025/1/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/scientists-use-ancient-genes-to-estimate-contact-between-humans-neanderthals.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Scientists have used ancient genes to learn more details about contact between Neanderthals and humans tens of thousands of years ago.</p>
<p>Results of two recent studies estimate the two groups likely met and began mating about 45,000 years ago.</p>
<p>Modern humans – also known as Homo sapiens – began in Africa hundreds of thousands of years ago and later started spreading to Europe, Asia and other places. Scientists believe that at some point, they met and mated with Neanderthals. The mixing of these groups had a major influence on humans' <strong>genetic code</strong>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image provided by Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology shows an artist's illustration of ancient humans from Ranis, Germany and the Czech Republic traveling together 45,000 years ago.(Tom Bj&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;246;rklund/Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4146b084-23f5-4f15-a2b7-430df9e86fb5_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image provided by Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology shows an artist's illustration of ancient humans from Ranis, Germany and the Czech Republic traveling together 45,000 years ago.(Tom Bj<i>&amp;#</i>246;rklund/Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology via AP)</span></div>
<p>However, scientists do not know exactly when or how the two groups interacted. But the two new studies provide some additional details about the timing of this contact.</p>
<p>One group of scientists examined genetic material from three female and three male Homo sapien individuals who lived around 45,000 years ago. Reuters news agency reported that research involved the oldest genes from Homo sapiens ever examined, or sequenced.</p>
<p>Some of the genes came from bones found in a <strong>cave</strong> in the central German village of Ranis. Other material came from a woman believed to have lived at around the same time in a cave in a mountainous area of what is now the Czech Republic.</p>
<p>Researchers estimated the period of mixing between Neanderthals and humans at about 49,000 to 45,000 years ago. The findings were recently published in a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-08420-x">study</a> in <em>Nature</em>.</p>
<p>A second group of researchers examined genetic material from 300 present-day and ancient Homo sapiens. This included 59 individuals who lived between 2,000 and 45,000 years ago. That <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adq3010">study</a>, published in the journal <em>Science</em>, estimated the period of mixing at about 50,500 to 43,500 years ago.</p>
<p>The scientists said their new findings on the mixing and mating of the groups suggested the activities happened a little more recently than thought in the past. They believe the contact continued over many generations.</p>
<p>Priya Moorjani was co-writer of the study appearing in <em>Science</em>. She is an assistant professor of molecular and cell biology at the University of California, Berkeley. She told Reuters, “Genetic data from these <strong>samples </strong>really helps us paint a picture in more and more detail.”</p>
<p>The team noted that it is difficult to know the exact nature of the interactions between Homo sapiens and Neanderthals based on the examined data. The researchers also could not confirm exactly where the mixing and mating happened. However, they believe it was most likely somewhere in the Middle East.</p>
<p>The researchers noted most modern humans still have genetic material from Neanderthals that accounts for an estimated one to two percent of their DNA. They said modern-day genetic <strong>traits</strong> linked to skin color, hair color and even nose shape can relate back to the Neanderthals. Our genetic makeup also includes links to another group of human ancestors called Denisovans.</p>
<p>Moorjani noted that the history of Neanderthals living outside Africa for thousands of years likely gave them a greater ability to deal with climate and diseases in new environments. “Some of their genes may have been <strong>beneficial</strong> to modern humans,” she added.</p>
<p>Rick Potts is director of the Smithsonian Institution's Human Origins program. He was not involved in the new research. Potts told The Associated Press he hopes future genetic studies can help scientists learn even more details about the interactions of Neanderthals and modern humans.</p>
<p>He said, “Out of many really<strong> compelling </strong>areas of scientific investigation, one of them is: well, who are we?”</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters and Nature. </em></p>
<p><strong>_______________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>genetic code</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> information from DNA or RNA that is used to create an organism's proteins</p>
<p><strong>cave </strong><em>– n. </em>a large hole in the side of a mountain or underground</p>
<p><strong>sample </strong><em>– n. </em>a small amount of something that gives you information about the thing it was taken from</p>
<p><strong>trait</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n. </em>a quality, good or bad, in someone's character</p>
<p><strong>beneficial </strong><em>– adj. </em>helpful or useful</p>
<p><strong>compelling</strong> <em>– adj.</em> demanding attention</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>AI Tools Often Used for Fake Product Reviews  (2025/1/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/ai-tools-often-used-for-fake-product-reviews.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Artificial intelligence (AI) tools that permit people to produce online <strong>reviews </strong>have put sellers, service providers and buyers in unfamiliar territory, public protection groups and researchers say.</p>
<p>False, or fake, reviews have long appeared on many popular websites such as Amazon and Yelp. The reviews are often traded on private social media groups between fake review dealers and businesses willing to pay. Sometimes, businesses get good reviews in exchange for offering buyers rewards such as gift cards.</p>
<p>But AI tools, popularized by OpenAI's ChatGPT, permit people to produce reviews faster and in greater numbers, technology industry experts say.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Online customer reviews for a product are displayed on a computer on April 17, 2019 in New York.(AP Photo/Jenny Kane)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4854bda8-e5a7-4daa-9de2-c68a53e04021_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Online customer reviews for a product are displayed on a computer on April 17, 2019 in New York.(AP Photo/Jenny Kane)</span></div>
<p><strong>Where are AI-generated reviews appearing? </strong></p>
<p>Fake reviews are found across a wide range of industries, from e-commerce and travel to services such as home repairs, medical care and music lessons.</p>
<p>The Transparency Company is a technology company and public protection group that uses software to detect fake reviews. The company said it started to see AI-generated reviews appear in large numbers in mid-2023. The reviews have increased quickly ever since.</p>
<p>For a recently released report, The Transparency Company examined 73 million reviews in three areas: home, legal and medical services. Nearly 14 percent of the reviews were likely fake. The company expressed a “high degree of confidence” that 2.3 million reviews were partly or entirely AI-produced.</p>
<p>Last September, the Federal Trade Commission (FTC) took legal action against the company behind an AI writing tool and content producer called Rytr. The FTC accused Rytr of offering a service that could pollute the marketplace with fake reviews.</p>
<p>The FTC, which banned the sale or purchase of fake reviews in 2024, said some of Rytr's buyers used the tool to produce hundreds and perhaps thousands of reviews. The reviews appeared in support of garage door repair companies, sellers of copied designer handbags and other businesses.</p>
<p><strong>What are companies doing? </strong></p>
<p>Major companies are developing policies for how AI-generated content fits into their systems for removing fake reviews. Some companies already employ special programs and investigative teams to find and remove fake reviews. Still, the companies are giving users some ability to use AI.</p>
<p>Spokespeople for Amazon and Trustpilot, for example, said they would permit buyers to post AI-assisted reviews as long as the buyers represent their true experience. Yelp has taken a more cautious approach, saying its rules require reviewers to write their own reviews.</p>
<p>The Coalition for Trusted Reviews, which Amazon, Trustpilot, Glassdoor, Tripadvisor, Expedia and Booking.com launched last year, said that even though people may put AI to illegal use, the technology also presents “an <strong>opportunity</strong> to push back against those who seek to use reviews to <strong>mislead </strong>others.”</p>
<p>The FTC's rule banning fake reviews, which took effect in October, permits the agency to fine businesses and individuals who take part in fake reviews. Tech companies hosting such reviews are protected from the penalty. This is because they are not legally responsible under U.S. law for the content that outsiders post on their websites.</p>
<p>Tech companies, including Amazon, Yelp and Google, have <strong>sued</strong> fake review dealers they accuse of selling fake reviews on their sites. The companies say their technology has blocked or removed a large number of suspect reviews and suspicious accounts. However, some experts say they could be doing more.</p>
<p>“Their efforts thus far are not nearly enough,” said Kay Dean, a former federal criminal investigator who runs a public protection group called Fake Review Watch. “If these tech companies are so committed to eliminating review <strong>fraud</strong> on their platforms, why is it that I, one individual who works with no automation, can find hundreds or even thousands of fake reviews on any given day?”</p>
<p><strong>Finding fake reviews </strong></p>
<p>Consumers can try to find fake reviews by watching out for a few possible warning signs, researchers say. Overly good or bad reviews are suspect. Highly specialized terms that repeat a product's full name or model number are another possible <strong>clue.</strong></p>
<p>When it comes to AI, research done by Balázs Kovács, a Yale professor, has shown that people cannot tell the difference between AI-created and human-written reviews. Some AI <strong>detectors</strong> may also be fooled by shorter texts, which are common in online reviews, the study said.</p>
<p>However, there are some AI clues that online shoppers and service seekers should keep in mind. Panagram Labs says reviews written with AI are often longer, highly structured and include “empty descriptors.” Empty descriptors include general phrases and attributes or characteristics. The writing also often includes overused phrases or opinions like “the first thing that struck me” and “game-changer.”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p>And I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Haleluya Hadero reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>___________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>review </strong>-- n. an evaluation or assessment of a product or service</p>
<p><strong>opportunity </strong><em>-- n.</em> a good chance for progress</p>
<p><strong>mislead </strong>– v. to lead in a wrong direction or into a mistaken action</p>
<p><strong>sue </strong><em>-- v. </em><strong> </strong>to seek justice from someone by legal process</p>
<p><strong>fraud</strong> -- n. intentional changing of truth in order to get another person to part with something of value</p>
<p><strong>automation</strong> – n. automatically controlled operation of a system by and electronic device that takes the place of human labor</p>
<p><strong>clue </strong><em>-- n. </em>an idea; a piece of evidence that leads one toward a solution</p>
<p><strong>detect</strong><em>-- v. </em>to find or discover the true nature of something; to discover something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Some on Indonesian Islands Fear Mining Damage to Environment  (2025/1/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/some-on-indonesian-islands-fear-mining-damage-to-environment.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Indonesia has the world's largest known supply of nickel and major supplies of valuable minerals, including cobalt and bauxite. However, the mining industry there is being criticized for not protecting the environment and some Indonesian island people.</p>
<p>The Southeast Asian country is involved in mining that produces materials important to the manufacture of stainless steel and electric vehicle <strong>batteries</strong>, among other things.</p>
<p>Indonesia is aiming to expand its mining and processing industries. But the development could face opposition from international and local groups.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A nickel mine is visible on top of a hill above a village on Kabaena Island, Indonesia, Thursday, Nov. 14, 2024. (AP Photo/Yusuf Wahil)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/95ee8fb0-2641-46e1-bba3-362740d73267_cx0_cy7_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A nickel mine is visible on top of a hill above a village on Kabaena Island, Indonesia, Thursday, Nov. 14, 2024. (AP Photo/Yusuf Wahil)</span></div>
<p>Nickel processing centers are becoming more common in parts of Indonesia. Sometimes, the plants are near the sea where many boats line up to carry ore, a mineral combination that contains nickel. Sometimes, these plants are near schools or places where local people fish or farm.</p>
<p>The World Resources Institute, based in Washington D.C., says from 2001 to 2020, 1.4 million hectares of trees were cut down around the world. Indonesia is estimated to have had the highest loss.</p>
<p>Amanda Hurowitz is a director with Mighty Earth. The environmental group is also based in Washington, D.C. Hurowitz said that, on the island of Kabaena, mining companies have cleared 3,700 hectares of forest in the last 22 years.</p>
<p>Fishermen who used to fish off the island have said the waters are filled with sediment from the mines. People in farming communities also say they are affected. They say sugar cane, sugar palms and clove trees do not grow well anymore.</p>
<p>Amal Susanto is a sugar palm farmer. He said: “That's the effect: The growth of the sugar palm trees will not be as good because of the influence of mining.” Susanto lives in an area where permits have been approved but mining has not yet begun.</p>
<p>People living in the area have reported health problems. Some told the Associated Press (AP) that they suffered from itchy skin, <strong>sore</strong> throat and other difficulties.</p>
<p>The Indonesia-based nonprofit group Satya Bumi sent water, dust and shellfish from the area to a laboratory this year. The group said the results showed dangerous levels of nickel, lead and cadmium. These substances are linked to mining.</p>
<p>Kathrin Shilling is an assistant professor and biology researcher at Columbia University in New York City. She studied the lab results. Shilling told the AP, “If people on this island are using the river water as drinking water...you cannot escape basically any of the exposure to those <strong>toxic</strong> metals.”</p>
<p>Kabaena is not the only place affected. To the north, on a larger island, Torobulu is another place where mining damage can be seen.</p>
<p>The mining problems continue although Indonesia's constitutional court ruled in March of this year that small islands such as Kabaena should have special protection. However, a researcher from Satya Bumi said the government is still approving mining permits.</p>
<p>The group Mighty Earth said 150 hectares of forest have been cleared on Kabaena since April 1. And it said over half of that was on land controlled by the mining company Tonia Mitra Sejahtera. The company and Indonesia's Ministry of Energy and Mineral Resources did not answer requests for comment from the AP.</p>
<p>Amiruddin is a 53-year-old fisherman on Kabaena Island. He said the results of the government permits for mining have affected many people.</p>
<p>“All residents here have felt the impact,” he said.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Yusuf Wahil and Victoria Milko reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>__________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>batteries</strong> –n. a device that chemically stores power and can produce electrical current<br/>
<strong>sore</strong> –adj. painful<br/>
<strong>toxic</strong> –adj. something that is poisonous</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How Serious Is Bird Flu Outbreak?  (2024/12/31)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/how-serious-is-bird-flu-outbreak.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">30 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>California officials have declared a state of emergency over the spread of bird flu. It is affecting milk cows in that state and causing illnesses in some people in other U.S. states.</p>
<p>The avian influenza virus, or bird flu, has spread among wild birds, farm birds and many mammal <strong>species</strong>.</p>
<p>The virus is known as Type A H5N1. It was identified for the first time in U.S. milk cows in March. Since then, bird flu has been found in about one third of U.S. states.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This colorized electron microscope image released by the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases on March 26, 2024, shows avian influenza A H5N1 virus particles. (CDC/NIAID via AP, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1c9e72b8-5e9c-4427-bc4d-1024fc984586_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This colorized electron microscope image released by the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases on March 26, 2024, shows avian influenza A H5N1 virus particles. (CDC/NIAID via AP, File)</span></div>
<p>The U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) is following the number of cases and is reporting the latest details on its <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cdc.gov/bird-flu/situation-summary/index.html" target="_blank">website</a>. Most of the illnesses have been mild. Health officials said that one person in Louisiana was hospitalized with the nation's first known severe illness caused by the virus.</p>
<p>California Governor Gavin Newsom said he declared the state of emergency so state workers could take faster action.</p>
<p>California officials have been testing milk tanks. They said they have found the virus in hundreds of <strong>herds</strong>. The virus was recently found in Southern California <strong>dairy</strong> farms. It was found in the state's Central Valley in August.</p>
<p><strong>What is the risk to the general public?</strong></p>
<p>Officials with the CDC repeated that the public has a low risk of getting the virus. There are no reports of person-to-person infection and no signs that the virus has changed to spread easily among humans.</p>
<p>Flu experts say it is too soon to know how the situation will change. But some experts are worried because flu viruses are <strong>mutating</strong> all the time and small genetic changes could take place.</p>
<p><strong>Are cases becoming more serious?</strong></p>
<p>Health officials said the first known case of severe illness in the U.S. was found in a patient in Louisiana. The person is older than 65 and has other medical problems. Officials said the person showed severe breathing problems after being near a group of sick birds. The CDC said that the Louisiana case is the first confirmed U.S. infection connected with <strong>backyard</strong> birds, or birds kept near a home.</p>
<p>Almost all the earlier infections in the U.S. have been in farmworkers dealing with infected dairy cattle or birds. In two cases — an adult in Missouri and a child in California — health officials have not learned how they became infected.</p>
<p>Angela Rasmussen is a virus expert at the University of Saskatchewan in Canada. She said as more people become infected, more severe illnesses will be reported. Rasmussen said, "I <strong>assume</strong> that every H5N1 virus has the <strong>potential</strong> to be very severe and deadly."</p>
<p>The World Health Organization says on its website that from 2003 to November 2024 about 142 people died from the H5N1 virus around the world. Most of the deaths were in Southeast Asia.</p>
<p><strong>How can people protect themselves?</strong></p>
<p>People who have contact with dairy cows, commercial <strong>poultry</strong> or with backyard birds are at higher risk than other people. CDC and other experts said those people should use breathing, eye, and hand protection, especially if the animals appear ill or if they die.</p>
<p>The CDC said in July that it would buy $5 million in vaccines for farmworkers to protect against seasonal flu. If someone becomes infected with two flu types at the same time, it might permit the bird flu virus to mutate and to become more dangerous.</p>
<p><strong>How else is bird flu spread?</strong></p>
<p>The H5N1 virus can also be spread in raw, or <strong>unpasteurized</strong>, milk. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration says pasteurized milk is safe to drink because the heat treatment kills the virus.</p>
<p>But high levels of the virus have been found in unpasteurized milk. Health officials urge people to avoid drinking raw milk. It can spread other germs in addition to bird flu.</p>
<p>The U.S. Agriculture Department has increased its testing of raw milk across the country to identify and contain avian flu. Federal officials ordered milk testing which began this month in 13 states.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Jonel Aleccia reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>mild </strong><em>–adj.</em> having little effect on a person, not severe at all</p>
<p><strong>herd </strong><em>–n</em>. a group of animals such as cattle or sheep</p>
<p><strong>dairy</strong> <em>– adj.</em> of or relating to a type of farming that deals with the production of milk and foods made from milk</p>
<p><strong>mutate </strong>- <em>v</em>. to cause (a gene) to change and create an unusual characteristic in a plant or animal</p>
<p><strong>backyard</strong> – <em>n</em>. the general area near and around someone's home</p>
<p><strong>assume </strong><em>–v.</em> to take something as correct without confirming that it is correct or right</p>
<p><strong>potential</strong> – <em>n</em>. a chance or possibility that something will happen or exist in the future</p>
<p><strong>poultry</strong> – <em>n</em>. birds (such as chickens and ducks) that are raised on farms for their eggs or meat</p>
<p><strong>pasteurized</strong> – <em>adj</em>. put through a process in which a liquid (such as milk or cream) is heated to a temperature that kills harmful germs and then cooled quickly</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Top Technology Stories of 2024  (2024/12/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/top-technology-stories-of-2024.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Throughout 2024, we saw further development of artificial intelligence (AI) systems and new legal action brought against technology companies. Here is a look back at some of the biggest tech stories we covered in 2024.</p>
<p><strong>AI continues to expand</strong></p>
<p>During the year, companies continued developing and deploying new AI tools.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Google, Microsoft and Alphabet logos and AI Artificial Intelligence words are seen in this illustration from May 4, 2023. (REUTERS/Dado Ruvic/Illustration)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/3ae36539-6083-4186-917d-a0367dde2d0c_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Google, Microsoft and Alphabet logos and AI Artificial Intelligence words are seen in this illustration from May 4, 2023. (REUTERS/Dado Ruvic/Illustration)</span></div>
<p>Among these were a new set of AI offerings announced by American software company Microsoft. Officials <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/microsoft-s-ai-agents-aim-to-take-over-many-human-duties/7876418.html">explained</a> the new tools included “personal agents” designed to help users complete business activities with little or no human involvement.</p>
<p>Microsoft says it designed the agents to expand on so-called chatbots – AI tools that work by themselves to produce human-level writing or discussions. The company said it expects a full release of the agents sometime in 2025.</p>
<p>In September, technology company Apple <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/apple-launches-new-iphone-built-for-ai-/7780192.html">announced</a> it was launching several new iPhones equipped with special <strong>chips</strong> to support AI operations. Apple chief Tim Cook said the new models had been “designed for Apple Intelligence from the ground up.”</p>
<p>We reported in October about an effort by researchers to use AI to improve existing weather prediction models. One system works by combining past weather predictions with modern methods to provide the most complete picture of weather and climate data.</p>
<p><strong>More warnings AI's possible dangers</strong></p>
<p>In California, three legislative measures were <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/new-california-laws-aim-to-prevent-ai-harm-during-elections/7797015.html">enacted</a> to ban the use of AI tools to create false images and videos during election campaigns. One main goal was to fight deepfakes. These are pieces of video or audio created to make it appear that people in it are saying or doing things they never said or did. Deepfakes were used in several world election campaigns in 2024.</p>
<p>In May, an international gathering of major AI developers and top government officials in Seoul <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/business-political-leaders-agree-to-safely-develop-deploy-ai/7622826.html">agreed</a> on measures that aim to ensure that AI systems are safely built and deployed. Attendees from 16 different technology companies signed a promise to develop AI technology in ways that limit possible public harms.</p>
<p><strong>US legal moves against tech companies</strong></p>
<p>About one year ago, an American jury <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/jury-rules-google-app-store-operates-as-monopoly/7396589.html">found</a> that Google's app store operates as an illegal monopoly. Then in August 2024, a federal judge ruled that Google had violated trade laws by operating its search engine as a <strong>monopoly</strong>. The ruling accused Google of paying smartphone makers to ensure that its search engine was set as the <strong>default</strong> system on new devices.</p>
<p>As part of the case, the U.S. government proposed in November a series of measures to limit Google from anti-competition business activities. Google criticized the court's ruling as an example of government overreach. U.S. officials have long warned that TikTok presents national security concerns.</p>
<p>Earlier this month, video sharing service TikTok <a class="wsw__a" href="file:///C:/Users/ckweaver/Downloads/TikTok%20has%20asked%20a%20U.S.%20appeals%20court%20to%20temporarily%20block%20a%20law%20requiring%20its%20parent%20company,%20ByteDance,%20to%20divest%20itself%20of%20the%20popular%20video%20sharing%20service,%20or%20face%20a%20U.S.%20ban">asked</a> a U.S. appeals court to block a law requiring its Chinese parent, ByteDance, to <strong>divest</strong> itself of TikTok or face a U.S. ban. The request came after the same court had upheld a law forcing ByteDance to sell TikTok by January 19 or face the ban. Lawyers for ByteDance and TikTok are seeking to have the U.S. Supreme Court rule on the case.</p>
<p><strong>Self-driving tech</strong></p>
<p>In May, U.S.-based Aurora Innovation <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/driverless-trucks-set-to-hit-us-highways/7595728.html">said</a> it was preparing to launch a series of driverless trucks to transport goods on a major public highway. Company officials said it planned to begin the service in Texas, with 20 tractor-trailers transporting goods between Dallas and Houston. The company hopes to expand the service to thousands of tractor-trailers within three to four years.</p>
<p><strong>Flying taxis</strong></p>
<p>In October, the U.S. Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/us-agency-issues-final-rules-for-flying-air-taxis/7837729.html">announced</a> it had issued final rules for operating air taxis. It also set training and approval requirements for pilots. The FAA said air taxis belong to a kind of aircraft known as Advanced Air Mobility (AAM) flyers. They generally operate on their own on electrical power, with <strong>vertical</strong> take-off and landing abilities.</p>
<p>FAA Administrator Mike Whitaker said such aircraft represent “the first new <strong>category</strong> of aircraft in nearly 80 years.” He added that the new rules are meant to mark the beginning of possible widespread AAM operations across the U.S. in the future.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>chip </strong><em>– n. </em>a very small slice of silicon containing electronic circuits (as for a computer)<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>monopoly</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> complete control of the entire supply of goods or of a service in a certain area or market</p>
<p><strong>default </strong><em>– adj. </em>what exists or usually happens if no changes are made</p>
<p><strong>divest </strong><em>– v. </em>to sell something, especially a business or part of a business</p>
<p><strong>vertical</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj. </em>pointing straight up from a surface</p>
<p><strong>category </strong><em>– n. </em>a group of people of things of a similar kind</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Large Chilean Frog at Risk from Climate Change  (2024/12/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/large-chilean-frog-at-risk-from-climate-change.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A large frog <strong>species</strong> that lived alongside dinosaurs and is considered a "living fossil" is now losing ground in its native Chile.</p>
<p>Climate change and human actions are damaging the creature's living environment, or habitat.</p>
<p>The Helmeted Water Toad is one of the largest frogs in the world, growing up to over 30 centimeters in length and weighing up to one kilogram.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A Chilean frog (Calyptocephalella gayi) sits on a tree trunk in a wetland in the middle of a neighbourhood in the city of Quilpue, Chile, December 8, 2024. (REUTERS/Rodrigo Garrido)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a53e07d4-4c39-4163-8378-d60c5aa4e176_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A Chilean frog (Calyptocephalella gayi) sits on a tree trunk in a wetland in the middle of a neighbourhood in the city of Quilpue, Chile, December 8, 2024. (REUTERS/Rodrigo Garrido)</span></div>
<p>The <strong>amphibian</strong> has experienced little genetic change for millions of years. But now its future is at risk, scientists say.</p>
<p>"It's sad that a species that managed to coexist with dinosaurs, that managed to resist a mass <strong>extinction</strong>, is now threatened by human beings," said Melissa Cancino. Cancino is an animal doctor and founder of Proyecto Anfibia, a group that works on amphibian research and education in Chile.</p>
<p>The Helmeted Water Toad's environment covers a large part of the country, but its population is suspected to have decreased by at least 30 percent since 1990. The creature is identified as "<strong>vulnerable</strong>" on the International Union for Conservation of Nature's (IUCN) Red List.</p>
<p>Climate change, habitat changes, environmental decline and pollution have all caused the Helmeted Water Toad's numbers to decline, Cancino said. Poor water and waste management have also threatened the frog's living environment.</p>
<p>Matias Faundez, another member of Proyecto Anfibia, has seen the damage first hand.</p>
<p>"This <strong>estuary</strong> runs through the whole city, and has plenty of illegal run-offs," he said as he walked through a stream outside of Valparaiso. "Even so," he added, "the frog manages to survive."</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Rodrigo Gutierrez reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>species </strong><em>– n.</em> a class of animals having common attributes and a common name</p>
<p><strong>amphibian</strong><em> – n. </em>any of a class of cold-blooded animals (such as frogs) that have gilled aquatic young and air-breathing adult</p>
<p><strong>vulnerable</strong> <em>– adj.</em> open to attack or damage</p>
<p><strong>extinction</strong><em> – n.</em> the act of completely dying off</p>
<p><strong>estuary</strong><em> – n.</em> a part of the sea at the lower end of a river</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>A Guide to Recovering Overgrown Garden  (2024/12/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/a-guide-to-recovering-overgrown-garden.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>What is the best way to repair an overgrown <strong>garden</strong>?</p>
<p>Garden expert for the Associated Press Jessica Damiano believes she knows the answer.</p>
<p>Here are some of her suggestions for making big improvements. Planning in the autumn and winter months can help you see something much more beautiful next winter:</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This May 2023 image provided by Jessica Damiano shows a neglected, overgrown property on Long Island, New York. (Jessica Damiano via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1154133e-0c4a-4403-ba45-0462282d41c4_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This May 2023 image provided by Jessica Damiano shows a neglected, overgrown property on Long Island, New York. (Jessica Damiano via AP)</span></div>
<p><strong>Decide what to clear away</strong></p>
<p>First, take a notebook with you and walk around the garden. Look carefully at each part. Try to decide which plants can be saved, which to throw away, and which ones require attention. Make a list as soon as you can.</p>
<p>Dead plants, <strong>weeds</strong> and invasive plants should be first to go. If the weather permits, dig them out, removing as much of their root systems as possible. Otherwise, wait until spring to do this before planting.</p>
<p>Next, remove and give away healthy plants that you do not want. Online groups and neighborhood web pages are places to find people to receive the plants. Many people will even be willing to do the digging if it means getting a free plant.</p>
<p>If the garden is full of plants, shrubs, trees and vines that have grown wild, you might need to use a <strong>chainsaw</strong> or heavy machine.</p>
<p><strong>Define any new beds</strong></p>
<p>If there are a lot of weeds or if you want to create new garden beds, you can cover the existing <strong>vegetation</strong> rather than dig it up. Decide the size and shape of the area you want to make into a new bed.</p>
<p>Cover that area with <strong>cardboard</strong> or lots of newspaper. Put about seven centimeters of <strong>compost</strong> and five centimeters of <strong>mulch</strong> on top of it. You can start in the autumn and leave it there over the winter until planting time in the spring.</p>
<p>When it is time to plant, cut holes in the cardboard or paper big enough for the roots of your plants. The covering over the ground will keep most weeds from growing. Some weeds may break through and require pulling or more cardboard, Damiano said.</p>
<p><strong>How and when to prune</strong></p>
<p>Healthy but overgrown or unproductive deciduous <strong>shrubs</strong> can be brought back to life by <strong>pruning</strong>. “Deciduous” means that the plants lose their leaves during the winter season. The best time to prune many plants is when their branches are bare in late winter.</p>
<p>Choosing a pruning method will require weighing appearance against the time it will take to recover. The fastest and most severe method would be to cut the whole plant down just above ground level. Although extreme, many shrubs can deal with this form of pruning and will <strong>bounce back</strong> stronger.</p>
<p>If keeping the plant looking normal is important, prune each branch or stem individually at uneven heights. It is also possible to cut back one-third of the plant's branches each year for three years. That method would have the least severe effect but requires the most patience.</p>
<p>Evergreen trees and shrubs should only undergo light pruning such as the shortening of individual branches. Take care to avoid pruning too much or creating holes in evergreen plants and trees. With the exception of yews, they do not regrow from such damage.</p>
<p><strong>Looking to the dirt</strong></p>
<p>Now that you have taken care of pruning, turn your attention to the soil.</p>
<p>Test the soil's pH, or its acidity level. Do this to make sure the soil is good for the plants you plan to add. Test <strong>kits</strong> are available at local garden stores and online. In the United States, a cooperative extension service might provide soil testing and soil-amendment advice for a small cost. Cooperative extension services are part of a Department of Agriculture system that includes some universities. It aims to help farmers and people interested in plants.</p>
<p>If the soil is hard, break it up with a machine or hand tools. Finally, spread five to seven centimeters of compost over the area. As it breaks down, nutrients will work their way into the soil.</p>
<p><strong>Planting considerations</strong></p>
<p>After completing these steps, it will be time to plant your new garden. Choose new trees, shrubs or <strong>perennials</strong>, that will not grow wildly. Dig holes as deep as their roots but two times as wide and space them out to their expected full-grown sizes. Native plants are good because they need little added water or special care.</p>
<p>Plant groundcover – short, spreading plants – to cover the ground and keep weeds from growing and the soil from drying out. It might take one or two years, but a step-by-step approach will make gardening a joy again.</p>
<p>And, perhaps best of all, you will see something beautiful when you look outside from your home.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jessica Damiano reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>garden</strong> <em>– n.</em> a plot of ground where herbs, fruits, flowers, or vegetables are grown</p>
<p><strong>weed </strong><em>–n.</em> an undesirable plant that grows grow thickly and crowds out more desirable plants</p>
<p><strong>chain saw </strong><em>– n.</em> a tool with sharp metal teeth that cuts through wood</p>
<p><strong>vegetation </strong><em>–n.</em> <strong> </strong>plant life or total plant cover (as of an area)</p>
<p><strong>cardboard</strong> <em>– n.</em> a material made from cellulose fiber (as wood pulp) like paper but usually thicker</p>
<p><strong>compost</strong> <em>– n.</em> <strong> </strong>a mixture that consists largely of decayed organic matter and is used for fertilizing and conditioning land</p>
<p><strong>mulch </strong><em>– n.</em> a covering (as of straw or sawdust) spread over the ground to protect the roots of plants from heat, cold, or evaporation, prevent soil loss, control weeds, enrich the soil, or keep fruit (as strawberries) clean</p>
<p><strong>shrub</strong> <em>– n.</em> a woody plant that has several stems and is smaller than most trees</p>
<p><strong>prune </strong><em>– v. </em>to cut off the parts of a woody plant that are dead or not wanted</p>
<p><strong>bounce back </strong><em>–v. (phrasal)</em> to return quickly to a normal condition after a difficult situation or event</p>
<p><strong>kit </strong><em>–n.</em> a set of tools or supplies</p>
<p><strong>perennial </strong><em>– n.</em> a plant that lives for several years usually with new leafy growth produced from the base each year</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Expressions for New Year's Resolution  (2024/12/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/expressions-for-new-year-s-resolution.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>During a new year, many of us decide to try something new. With a new year's <strong>resolution</strong>, we resolve to do something we have not done in the past.</p>
<p>Sometimes new things are risk-free – like eating healthier food or getting more exercise.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Fireworks are seen over Victoria Harbour at midnight on New Years Sunday Jan. 1, 2023 in Hong Kong. (AP Photo/Anthony Kwan)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/022a0000-0aff-0242-fa57-08daeb62d345_cx5_cy7_cw91_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Fireworks are seen over Victoria Harbour at midnight on New Years Sunday Jan. 1, 2023 in Hong Kong. (AP Photo/Anthony Kwan)</span></div>
<p>Sometimes we decide to learn a new skill, like a language or a musical instrument. Again, these things are not risky, nor do they have bad <strong>consequences</strong>. If you do not learn how to play the guitar, nothing bad will happen — probably.</p>
<p>However, sometimes we need to <strong>shake up</strong> our lives and do something different that <em>does</em> have consequences. That means there are risks if things do not work out.</p>
<p>Such a change could involve moving to a new city, starting a new job, or ending a relationship. These new things<em> do</em> have a level of risk . Things could go wrong. On the other hand, things could go very right.</p>
<p>So, for these situations, we introduce two expressions that <strong>encourage</strong> you to take a chance.</p>
<p><strong>Nothing ventured, nothing gained.</strong></p>
<p>The first expression is <u>nothing <strong>ventured</strong>, nothing gained.</u></p>
<p>This means that without doing something risky or difficult, a bad situation will not improve. You could also sum it up this way: If you try something risky, you could fail. But if you do not try at all ... you will surely fail.</p>
<p>The word “venture” can be both a noun and a verb. As a verb, it means to proceed in a dangerous or risky plan. As a noun, it means an action that involves chance, risk, or danger.</p>
<p>For example, starting a new restaurant is a risky business venture these days. And venturing into an unknown area could be dangerous.</p>
<p>A friend of mine wanted to learn how to drive a stunt car and then move to Los Angeles to become a stunt car driver. A stunt car is a vehicle used in the movies to perform crashes and wild driving. There are not many women in this profession. So, I told her that her decision involved lots of risk. She said to me: “Well, <u>nothing ventured, nothing gained</u>.”</p>
<p><strong>Fortune favors the bold.</strong></p>
<p>Our second expression is <strong><u>fortune favors</u></strong><u> the <strong>bold</strong>.</u></p>
<p>“Fortune” usually means wealth or fame. But it can also mean being in a good situation. And, if you are bold, you are brave.</p>
<p>So, this expression means that people who are brave and take chances help themselves. Their bold, brave actions put them in a good place.</p>
<p>When using this expression, keep this in mind. The person who finds a fortune has done something to get it. It just doesn't happen to them by chance. So, if someone happens to win a lot of money in a lottery, you wouldn't use the expression <u>fortune favors the bold</u>.</p>
<p>However, let's say you quit your job and moved to a new city. That is a bold decision. But you are sure that it will be good for you. In the new city, you find your dream job. It might even pay more money than your old job. Here, you could definitely say, “<u>Fortune favors the bold</u>!”</p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>. For the start of 2023, I wish you and yours health and wealth.</p>
<p>Until next time ... I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>resolution </strong>–n. a promise to yourself to do something you believe you should do</p>
<p><strong>consequence </strong>–n. the result of an action usually that is meaningful or serious</p>
<p><strong>encourage </strong>–v. to make someone likely to take some action</p>
<p><strong>shake up </strong><em>–v. (phrasal</em>) to make a lot of changes or to make a big change</p>
<p><strong>venture </strong>–v. to do something that involves risk and reward</p>
<p><strong>fortune </strong>–n. wealth, fame or good conditions (often because of influences beyond direct control of an individual)</p>
<p><strong>favor</strong> –v. to approve of or to support</p>
<p><strong>bold </strong>–adj. not afraid of danger of difficult situations</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>1929 Books, Films, More to Enter Public Domain Next Month  (2024/12/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/books-films-more-to-enter-public-domain-next-month.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">27 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Popeye the Sailor and the Belgian boy reporter Tintin lead the class of <strong>characters</strong> and works of art to enter <strong>public domain</strong> in 2025.</p>
<p>On January 1, 2025, the U.S. copyright ends on creations from 1929. That means the early versions of the comic characters can be used without permission or payment.</p>
<p>They will be joined by the books <em>A Farewell to Arms</em> by Ernest Hemingway and <em>The Sound and the Fury</em> by William Faulkner. Other works coming into the public domain include songs from American artist Cole Porter, early films from Alfred Hitchcock and the Marx Brothers, and several more films starring Mickey Mouse, whose earliest version became public domain last year.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A helium-filled Popeye balloon appears in the 33rd Macy's Thanksgiving Day Parade in New York on Nov. 26, 1959. (AP Photo/File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/6fe94264-917f-4c8f-ba21-faaf698623e0_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A helium-filled Popeye balloon appears in the 33rd Macy's Thanksgiving Day Parade in New York on Nov. 26, 1959. (AP Photo/File)</span></div>
<p>“It's a<strong> trove</strong>! There are a <strong>dozen</strong> new Mickey <strong>cartoons</strong> — he speaks for the first time and <strong>dons</strong> the familiar white gloves,” said Jennifer Jenkins, director of the Center for the Study of the Public Domain, part of Duke University Law School in North Carolina.</p>
<p>“There are masterpieces from Faulkner and Hemingway, the first sound films from Alfred Hitchcock, Cecil B. DeMille, and John Ford, and amazing music from Fats Waller, Cole Porter, and George Gershwin. Pretty exciting,” she added.</p>
<p>Here is a closer look from the Associated Press at this year's crop of public domain works:</p>
<p><strong>Comics characters</strong></p>
<p>Popeye the Sailor, with his big arm muscles and fighting spirit, was created by E.C. Segar and made his first appearance in the newspaper <strong>comic strip</strong> <em>Thimble Theater</em> in 1929. His first words were, “'Ja think I'm a cowboy?” when asked if he was a sailor. It was supposed to be a one-time appearance for the character. Instead, he became the main character, and the strip would be renamed <em>Popeye</em>.</p>
<p>But as with Mickey Mouse last year and Winnie the Pooh in 2022, only the earliest version is free for reuse. Popeye did not become a film character until 1933 and that version remains under copyright.</p>
<p>The 1929 version of the character Tintin, the creation of Belgian artist Hergé, will also come into the public domain. The simply drawn teenager with dots for eyes and hair shaped like an ocean wave, was among the most popular characters in Europe for much of the 20th century.</p>
<p>However, in much of the world, Tintin will not become public property until 70 years after the 1983 death of his creator.</p>
<p><strong>Important American books</strong></p>
<p>The books entering the public domain this year read like a list for an American literature class.</p>
<p><em>The Sound and the Fury</em> is arguably William Faulkner's most famous book. Its special <strong>style</strong> of expression was a big hit although the book was widely considered difficult to read and understand. The story is set in the southern state of Mississippi, where Faulkner was born and lived most of his life. It tells about the ruin of a leading family there.</p>
<p>And Ernest Hemingway's <em>A Farewell to Arms</em> joins his earlier <em>The Sun Also Rises</em> in the public domain. The story about an ambulance driver is set in Italy during World War I. It was based in part on Hemingway's real life. It has been made into film, TV, and radio versions, and now can be done anew without permission.</p>
<p>American John Steinbeck's first novel, <em>A Cup of Gold</em>, will also enter the public domain.</p>
<p><strong>Movies</strong></p>
<p>Filmmaking was changing from silent to sound production during the late 1920s.</p>
<p>The famous moviemaker Alfred Hitchcock was still living in Britain when he made the film <em>Blackmail</em>. The movie began as a silent film but was turned to sound film during production. Two versions of Blackmail were released. One of the versions became Britain's and Hitchcock's first sound film.</p>
<p>American John Ford is probably best remembered for making the kind of films called Westerns. Those movies remain protected. But, Ford's first sound film, 1929's <em>The Black Watch</em>, enters the public domain next month. The action movie includes a young John Wayne who appears in a small part. Years later, Wayne was the star of many Ford films.</p>
<p>Another notable director, Cecil B. DeMille, already a Hollywood leader in silent films, made <em>Dynamite</em> his first sound film in 1929.</p>
<p>Groucho, Harpo, and the other Marx Brothers humor group had their first starring parts in 1929's <em>The Cocoanuts</em>. The brothers went on to make the popular comedies, <em>Animal Crackers</em> and <em>Duck Soup</em>.</p>
<p>And <em>The Broadway Melody</em> will also enter the public domain on January 1. It became the first sound film and the second film ever to win the Oscar for best picture — then called “outstanding production.”</p>
<p><strong>Music</strong></p>
<p>Songs from the last year of the 1920s are also about to become publicly available for use.</p>
<p>Cole Porter's <strong>compositions</strong> <em>What Is This Thing Called Love</em>? and <em>Tiptoe Through the Tulips</em> are among the highlights, as is the jazz <strong>classic</strong> <em>Ain't Misbehavin' </em>written by Fats Waller and Harry Brooks.</p>
<p>Different laws cover sound recordings. Those newly in the public domain date to 1924. They include a recording of <em>Nobody Knows the Trouble I've Seen</em> from star and civil rights <strong>icon</strong> Marian Anderson, and <em>Rhapsody in Blue</em> performed by its composer George Gershwin.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver. And I'm Dorothy Gundy.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press' Andrew Dalton reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>character</strong> <em>– n.</em> a person who appears in a book, movie, play or other artwork</p>
<p><strong>public domain</strong> <em>– n. (law)</em> when a creative product is outside of legal copyright protection and can freely be used and copied by the public</p>
<p><strong>trove</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a valuable collection</p>
<p><strong>dozen</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n. </em>twelve of something</p>
<p><strong>cartoon </strong>–n. a series of simple pictures that tell a story or a movie made from similar simple pictures</p>
<p><strong>don </strong><em>–v. </em><strong> </strong>to put on (a piece of clothing)</p>
<p><strong>comic strip </strong><em>–n.</em> a short series of simple pictures that tell a story that is often funny and that is published in a newspaper regularly</p>
<p><strong>style </strong><em>–n.</em> a way of doing something that has recognizable, distinctive elements</p>
<p><strong>composition </strong><em>–n.</em> a written musical work</p>
<p><strong>classic </strong><em>–adj.</em> something that is considered among the best examples of the group to which it belongs</p>
<p><strong>icon </strong><em>–n</em>. a person who is the representation of an idea or ideal</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Do People Still Say That?  (2024/12/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/do-people-still-say-that.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">27 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Emmanuel in France about how to know if an expression is still popular in English.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Add a title - 1" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/0ee9b47d-bdcb-418f-824a-ebbd6a140e4e_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Add a title - 1</span></div>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p>
<p>Sometimes when I am reading or watching the older films, I find some interesting expressions. But I do not know if the people are speaking them nowadays. How can I figure this out?</p>
<p>Thank you,</p>
<p>Emmanuel</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Emmanuel.</p>
<p>It can sometimes be very difficult for learners of English to know if a word or expression sounds like it belongs to an earlier time.</p>
<p>For example, if you watch an older American film from the 1930s, you might hear the expression:</p>
<p><em>Gee, that's swell!</em></p>
<p>The expression “that's swell” means that something is good, and that the speaker is pleased. But nowadays people do not commonly say that. And if they do say it, they are probably saying it in a joking way because they know the expression is rare and not currently used.</p>
<p>Here are some ways to help you find out if an expression belongs to an earlier time:</p>
<p><strong>Language exchange partners</strong></p>
<p>Find a native English language partner. Then you can ask him or her if expressions are no longer used very much. Our VOA Learning English article <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/five-tips-for-great-language-exchanges/5175780.html">“Five Tips for Great Language Exchanges”</a> gives advice on how you can do a language exchange.</p>
<p>Note, however, that native English speakers can have different opinions about what expressions are still popular. That is because people in different age groups use different expressions. For example, a 20-year-old person might not even know a few of the expressions that older people still use. And some older people do not know expressions that young people, such as teenagers, use. Also, some older people might not even know that expressions they use are becoming less popular over time.</p>
<p><strong>Using a corpus and dictionaries</strong></p>
<p>You can also use technology to get more information about expressions.</p>
<p>Language researchers have collected over one billion words in the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://nam10.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.english-corpora.org%2Fcoca%2F&amp;data=05%7C02%7CAndrewSmith%4021voa.com%7C749494b552994caa362908dcbcaf0592%7Cba99e87c673541c2b1c1354eee3a8659%7C0%7C0%7C638592707116585301%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=16C39dnI2Wx52MxTMBgizzwHDhiORhP4RHKn8Zsskn8%3D&amp;reserved=0">Corpus of Contemporary American English</a> (COCA). The examples come from American printed writing, video, and sound recordings.</p>
<p>You can use COCA to get information about how often an expression is used. It will not tell you if an expression sounds <strong>out-of-date</strong>. But an expression might rarely be used because it sounds old.</p>
<p>This VOA Learning English <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/use-a-language-corpus-to-improve-your-vocabulary/7189316.html">Education Tips article</a> gives information on how to use COCA.</p>
<p>Lastly, dictionaries will show if a word belongs to an earlier time by putting the word “<strong>archaic</strong>” before its definition.</p>
<p>Remember that it is more important to understand <strong>idiomatic</strong> expressions than to be able to use them. That's because you can always express your ideas without using idioms in simple language.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? We want to hear from you! Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please let us know where you are from, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>out-of-date </strong>–adj. old, not current, or no longer in use</p>
<p><strong>archaic </strong>–adj. from an earlier time, not used any longer</p>
<p><strong>idiomatic </strong>–adj. related to the use of idioms which are terms that do not mean what the words that form them would suggest</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Around Half of US Teens Always Online  (2024/12/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/study-around-half-of-us-teens-always-online.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Nearly half of American teenagers – children ages 13 to 17 - say they are online “<strong>constantly</strong>” despite concerns about the effects of social media and smartphones on their mental health.</p>
<p>The information comes from a report that was recently released by the Pew Research Center.</p>
<p>As in past years, YouTube was the most popular<strong> platform</strong> teenagers used. Around 90 percent said they watched videos on the website, down slightly from 95 percent in 2022. Nearly 75 percent of those questioned said they visit YouTube every day.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE — Isabella Cimato, 17, from left, Arianna Schaden, 14, and Sofia Harrison, 15, check their phones at Roosevelt Field shopping mall in Garden City, N.Y., on July 27, 2015. (AP Photo/Seth Wenig, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4e279598-ef5f-44c9-a7c2-9a4d352672e5_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE — Isabella Cimato, 17, from left, Arianna Schaden, 14, and Sofia Harrison, 15, check their phones at Roosevelt Field shopping mall in Garden City, N.Y., on July 27, 2015. (AP Photo/Seth Wenig, File)</span></div>
<p>There was a small downward change in several popular <strong>apps</strong> teens used. For example, 63 percent of teens said they used TikTok, down from 67 percent. Snapchat use went to 55 percent from 59 percent. This small decline could be due to pandemic-era restrictions easing up and kids having more time to see friends in person. But the change is probably not big enough to be truly meaningful.</p>
<p>X saw the biggest decline among teenage users. Only 17 percent of teenagers said they use X, down from 23 percent in 2022, the year Elon Musk bought the platform.</p>
<p>Reddit usage remained the same at 14 percent. About 6 percent of teenagers said they use Threads, Meta's answer to X that launched in 2023.</p>
<p>The report comes as countries around the world try to understand the effects of social media on young people's well-being.</p>
<p>Australia recently passed a law banning children under 16 from social networks. Still, it is unclear how the Australian government will be able to enforce the age limit. It is also unclear whether such a ban will come with unexpected or bad effects, such as <strong>isolating</strong> some children.</p>
<p>Meta's messaging service WhatsApp was different in that it saw the number of teenage users increase to 23 percent from 17 percent in 2022.</p>
<p>Pew also asked teenagers how often they use different online platforms. A small but notable number said they are on them “almost constantly.” For YouTube, 15 percent reported constant use, for TikTok, 16 percent, and for Snapchat, 13 percent.</p>
<p>As in previous public opinion studies, girls were more likely to use TikTok almost constantly while boys went to YouTube. There was no meaningful gender difference in the use of Snapchat, Instagram and Facebook.</p>
<p>Around 25 percent of Black and Hispanic teens said they visit TikTok almost constantly, compared with just 8 percent of white teenagers.</p>
<p>The report was based on a public opinion study of 1,391 U.S. teenagers that ran from September 18 to October 10, 2024.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Barbara Ortutay reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><em>______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>constantly</strong><em> – adv.</em> always, without change</p>
<p><strong>platform</strong> <em>– n.</em> a website or app that serves as a base from which a service is provided</p>
<p><strong>app </strong><em>– n. (short for application) </em>a program that performs a task or set of tasks</p>
<p><strong>isolate </strong><em>-- v. </em>to separate or set apart from others</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Grammar for Making New Year’s Resolutions  (2024/12/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/grammar-for-making-new-year-s-resolutions.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Alice Bryant</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>
The New Year can come on different dates for different cultures. Most of the Western world, for example, celebrates it on January 1st.</p>
<p>But one thing many cultures have in common is the idea of New Year's resolutions. A New Year's resolution is a personal goal to change unwanted behavior, make a life improvement or try something new.</p>
<p>Popular New Year's resolutions in the United States, for example, include losing weight, improving your finances, volunteering for a <strong>charity</strong> and spending less time on social media.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Grammar for Making New Year's Resolutions" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/eb5eec77-0504-472f-9d29-f61837300a69_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Grammar for Making New Year's Resolutions</span></div>
<p>On today's Everyday Grammar, we will show you how to talk about resolutions in English.</p>
<p><strong>Asking a question</strong></p>
<p>First, let's learn how to <em>ask</em> people about their resolutions.</p>
<p>Listen to a short <strong>conversation</strong>:</p>
<p><em>Hey there, Jill. Happy New Year! Great to see you.</em></p>
<p><em>Hi, Jonathan. Happy New Year to you too! How was yours? </em></p>
<p><em>It was crazy! We went to New York and watched the ball drop in Times Square. Really crowded and loud – but still really fun.</em></p>
<p><em>Sweet! <u>Do you have any New Year's resolutions</u>?</em></p>
<p>Jill asked Jonathan about resolutions simply by saying, “Do you have any New Year's resolutions?”</p>
<p>You can also say, “What are your New Year's resolutions?” to ask about more than one or “What is your New Year's resolution?” to ask about one.</p>
<p>Now, let's find out how to answer the question.</p>
<p><strong>Using phrasal verbs</strong></p>
<p>When we make statements about our resolutions, we often use <strong>phrasal verbs</strong>.</p>
<p>We can use the phrasal verb “take up” to say that we will start a new activity as a <strong>hobby</strong>.</p>
<p>Listen to Jill and Jonathan continue their conversation:</p>
<p><em>Sweet! Do you have any New Year's resolutions?</em></p>
<p><em>Yes, I do. I plan to <u>take up</u> kickboxing starting next week. I'm excited to finally do it rather than just talk about it! How about you?</em></p>
<p>Another phrasal verb for resolutions is “give up,” which is to stop doing or using something. We can use this verb to talk about ending bad <strong>habits</strong> or changing a behavior for a time.</p>
<p>Let's hear Jill respond using the verb “give up”:</p>
<p><em>How about you?</em></p>
<p><em>I am <u>giving up</u> sugar for the month of January. Then, for the rest of the year, I'm avoiding soft drinks.</em></p>
<p><strong><em>Impressive</em></strong><em>! I wish I could join you but kickboxing class starts soon. I'll probably want a sweet snack after class! </em></p>
<p>Another phrasal verb, “cut out,” has the same basic meaning as “give up.” For example, Jill could say, “I am cutting out sugar for the month of January.”</p>
<p>But in many situations, we do not need phrasal verbs to talk about resolutions, as you will soon see.</p>
<p><strong>Using future forms</strong></p>
<p>Next, let's talk about verb <strong>tenses</strong> and forms. Jonathan talked about his new kickboxing hobby using the verb “plan” followed by the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/getting-to-know-gerunds-and-infinitives/3111996.html" target="_blank">infinitive</a> verb form and Jill talked about giving up sugar using the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/everyday-grammar-present-progressive/3255195.html" target="_blank">present continuous</a> verb tense, also called “BE + ing.”</p>
<p>We can also use the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/everyday-grammar-fun-with-future-tenses/2935173.html" target="_blank">simple future</a> tenses: one with “will” and the other with “going to.” These tenses are especially useful when the New Year has not come yet.</p>
<p>Imagine it's the last week of the year and a few people are talking to each other about resolutions: Here are some things you might hear:</p>
<p><em>In 2020, I'<u>m going to visit</u> my parents every month.</em></p>
<p><em>By January 1, I <u>will end</u> a few unhealthy friendships.</em></p>
<p><em>In the new year, I'<u>m going to walk</u> 10,000 steps every day. </em></p>
<p>When we use simple future tenses to talk about resolutions, we're expressing that we are making a promise to or plan for ourselves. The noun “resolution” comes from the verb “resolve,” which means to make a serious decision to do something.</p>
<p><strong>Infinitives and gerunds</strong></p>
<p>You may have noticed that the statements so far today did not actually use the word “resolution.” That is because the subject was already known by the listeners. But it is still perfectly normal to start your statements with, “My New Year's resolution is...” or “My New Year's resolutions are...” An <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/everyday-grammar-gerunds-infinitives/2722827.html" target="_blank">infinitive verb or a gerund</a> must come after these phrases. Here is an example:</p>
<p><em>My New Year's resolution is <u>to call</u> my sister on video <strong>chat</strong> every week.</em></p>
<p>The infinitive verb here is “to call.”</p>
<p>You can also use a gerund, like this:</p>
<p><em>My New Year's resolution is <u>calling</u> my sister on video chat every week.</em></p>
<p>Well, that's all for today's program. Tell us about your New Year's resolutions in the comments below.</p>
<p>Happy New Year!</p>
<p>I'm Alice Bryant.</p>
<p><em>Alice Bryant wrote this lesson for Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>________________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>charity </strong>– n. an organization that helps people who are poor, sick, or otherwise in need</p>
<p><strong>conversation </strong>– n. an informal talk involving two people or a small group of people</p>
<p><strong>phrasal verb</strong> – n. a group of words that functions as a verb and is made up of a verb and a preposition or an adverb, or both</p>
<p><strong>hobby</strong> – n. an activity that a person does for pleasure when not working</p>
<p><strong>habit</strong> – n. something that a person does often in a regular and repeated way</p>
<p><strong>impressive </strong>– adj. deserving attention, admiration, or respect</p>
<p><strong>tense </strong>– n. a form of a verb that is used to show when an action happened</p>
<p><strong>chat </strong>– n. a talk held over the internet by people using a computer or phone</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What Were Google’s Top Searches in 2024?  (2024/12/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/what-were-google-s-top-searches-in-2024.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>As we near the end of 2024, we are looking back at the top terms people searched for on Google during the year.</p>
<p>Each year, Google releases its “Year in Search” report. It includes terms that saw the biggest rise in traffic compared to the year earlier.</p>
<p>Online marketing company Semrush <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.semrush.com/blog/google-search-statistics/">reports</a> Google controls about 92 percent of the worldwide internet search traffic. It also estimates the search engine completes up to 3 trillion requests per year.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This file image shows various Google logos displayed on a Google search, Monday, Sept. 11, 2023, in New York. (AP Photo/Richard Drew, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-62fc-08dcb71004ac_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This file image shows various Google logos displayed on a Google search, Monday, Sept. 11, 2023, in New York. (AP Photo/Richard Drew, File)</span></div>
<p>In an <a class="wsw__a" href="https://blog.google/products/search/google-year-in-search-2024/">announcement</a> on its news website, The Keyword, Google said 2024 was a very big year for web searches related to sporting events. Searches for information on soccer and cricket proved to be especially popular.</p>
<p>The top-searched soccer event was the Copa América competition, which took place in the United States this past summer. The next most-searched was the UEFA European Championship. That was followed by cricket's Men's T20 World Cup competition.</p>
<p>Imane Khelif led the list of top-searched sports stars during the year. Khelif is an Algerian female boxer who won a gold medal at the 2024 Olympic Games in Paris. An American boxer, Mike Tyson, came next on the list and Spanish soccer professional Lamine Yamal took the third place.</p>
<p>News was the other area receiving the most search requests during 2024. Topping the list for searches of events was the U.S. presidential election. That was followed by news stories about excessive heat experienced across many parts of the world. And finishing in third was news about the Paris Olympics.</p>
<p>U.S. President-elect Donald Trump topped searches in Google's people <strong>category</strong>. He was followed by Catherine, Princess of Wales. U.S. Vice President Kamala Harris, Trump's main opponent in the November presidential election, came in third on the list.</p>
<p>The most popular searches for people who died in 2024 included Liam Payne, Toby Keith and O.J. Simpson.</p>
<p>In the world of <strong>entertainment</strong>, Disney and Pixar's movie <em>Inside Out 2</em> was the top-searched movie of the year. In second place was Marvel's <em>Deadpool &amp; Wolverine</em>, followed by the comedy film <em>Saltburn</em>.</p>
<p>The top-searched television show was Netflix's <em>Baby Reindeer.</em> That was followed by Amazon's series <em>Fallout</em>. In third place was the action show <em>House of the Dragon</em>.</p>
<p>In music, Kendrick Lamar's <em>Not Like Us</em> topped song searches. Next on the list was <em>APT.</em>, a pop song by Rosé and Bruno Mars, followed by <em>Bling-Bang-Bang-Born</em> by Creepy Nuts.</p>
<p>The top Google search for a food <strong>recipe</strong> was for the Olympic village's chocolate muffin. The sweet treat was made famous by Norwegian swimmer Henrik Christiansen during the games.</p>
<p>The <em>New York Times </em>“Connections” <strong>puzzle</strong> topped game searches.</p>
<p>In searches on parks on Google Maps, New York City's Central Park was number one. At number two was Rizal Park in Manila, the Philippines, followed by Japan's Ohori Park in Fukuoka.</p>
<p>The California-based technology company said the 2024 search results were collected from January 1 through November 23. Users can find more top-searched terms at a special Google site found <a class="wsw__a" href="https://trends.withgoogle.com/year-in-search/2024/?utm_source=blog.google&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=yis2024">here</a>.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan adapted the report for VOA Learning English, with additional information from Google.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>category</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a group of people or things of a similar type</p>
<p><strong>entertainment </strong><em>– n.</em> movies, tv shows or other performances or activities that entertain people</p>
<p><strong>recipe</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a list of foods and instructions that tell how to cook something</p>
<p><strong>puzzle</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a game or activity in which you have to put pieces together or answer questions using skill</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Saturn’s Rings Might Be Much Older Than Had Been Thought  (2024/12/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/saturn-s-rings-might-be-much-older-than-had-been-thought.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Recent research suggests that Saturn's rings may be older than they look — and possibly as old as the planet itself.</p>
<p>Instead of being 400 million years old as some had thought, the icy rings could be the same age as Saturn: 4.5 billion years old.</p>
<p>A Japanese-led research team reported Saturn's rings may be in good condition not because they are young but because they are dirt-resistant.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This April 25, 2007 image made available by NASA shows a part of the rings of the planet Saturn, as seen from the Cassini spacecraft. (NASA/JPL-Caltech/Space Science Institute via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/0bff74ef-249a-4cfe-a18a-06add4adb790_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This April 25, 2007 image made available by NASA shows a part of the rings of the planet Saturn, as seen from the Cassini spacecraft. (NASA/JPL-Caltech/Space Science Institute via AP)</span></div>
<p>For many years, scientists had believed that Saturn's rings were between 100 million and 400 million years old. This idea came from more than 10 years of observations by NASA's Cassini spacecraft.</p>
<p>The spacecraft studied Saturn before its mission ended in 2017.</p>
<p>Images by Cassini showed no evidence of any darkening of the rings by <strong>impacts</strong> from micrometeoroids — space rock particles smaller than a grain of sand. The finding led scientists to believe the rings formed long after the planet.</p>
<p>Through computer <strong>modeling</strong>, the Institute of Science Tokyo's Ryuki Hyodo and his team showed that micrometeoroids become gas or small liquid drops once they hit the rings. As a result, little if any dark or dirty substances, or residue, remain.</p>
<p>Researchers found that the resulting charged particles are forced toward Saturn or out into space, keeping the rings clean. The findings dispute the idea that the rings are much younger than the planet. The resulting research appeared in the scientific publication Nature Geoscience.</p>
<p>Hyodo said it is possible Saturn's rings could be somewhere between the two extreme ages. For example, the rings could be around the halfway mark of 2.25 billion years old.</p>
<p>However, the solar system was much more<strong> chaotic</strong> during its early years. Large planetary-sized objects were moving around and affecting each other a lot at that time. It was just the sort of situation that might have produced Saturn's rings.</p>
<p>“Considering the solar system's <strong>evolutionary </strong>history, it's more likely that the rings formed closer to” Saturn's earliest times, Hyodo told the Associated Press in an email.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Marcia Dunn reported this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>impact</strong> <em>–n.</em> the result of at least two things colliding or striking one another</p>
<p><strong>model</strong> <em>– v.</em> to create a representation or simulation of something</p>
<p><strong>chaotic</strong> <em>– adj.</em> confused or disordered</p>
<p><strong>evolutionary</strong> <em>– adj.</em> of or pertaining to evolution (a process of change)</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Why Is SoftBank Investing in the US?  (2024/12/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/why-is-softbank-investing-in-the-us.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Japanese business leader Masayoshi Son and President-elect Donald Trump recently met at Trump's property, Mar-a-Lago, in the southeastern U.S. state of Florida. They announced plans for SoftBank Group to invest $100 billion in projects in the United States over the coming four years.</p>
<p>Trump said the investments in building artificial intelligence (AI) <strong>infrastructure</strong> would create 100,000 jobs. Reuters news agency reported that it was the second time that SoftBank's Son made a big promise to invest in U.S. projects. In 2016, Son announced $50 billion in investments with Trump after his election victory. The investments helped companies like Uber and WeWork.</p>
<p>Son is a founder and CEO, or chief executive officer, of SoftBank Group. SoftBank has investments in many new technology businesses, along with big companies like silicon <strong>chip</strong> maker Arm Holdings and Chinese online business Alibaba. Investor interest in AI has increased SoftBank's value, but it is unclear whether its investments will create that many jobs in the U.S.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="SoftBank Group CEO Masayoshi Son smiles with President-elect Donald Trump during a news conference at Mar-a-Lago, Monday, Dec. 16, 2024, in Palm Beach, Florida. (AP Photo/Evan Vucci)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/ba36a433-0c79-4072-9e27-0adf92f39a38_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">SoftBank Group CEO Masayoshi Son smiles with President-elect Donald Trump during a news conference at Mar-a-Lago, Monday, Dec. 16, 2024, in Palm Beach, Florida. (AP Photo/Evan Vucci)</span></div>
<p><strong>Son believes in the value of AI</strong></p>
<p>SoftBank investor meetings have supported the idea that AI will become profitable for the company. Son has said he believes AI will outdo human intelligence within 10 years, affecting every industry. He believes that companies and people working with AI will be the leaders of the next 10 to 20 years. SoftBank owns about 90 percent of Arm's publicly traded stock. This puts the Japanese company in a good position for expansion of AI <strong>applications</strong>. Arm says most mobile devices operate on small Arm-based processors.</p>
<p>Trump and Son said the $100 billion that SoftBank has promised to invest will go to building AI infrastructure, but the details remain unclear. The effect of AI on job creation remains an open question.</p>
<p><strong>What about the jobs?</strong></p>
<p>The announcement is like a promise Son made with then-President-elect Trump in December 2016 at Trump Tower in New York City. Then, Son said he would spend $50 billion and create 50,000 jobs. While that money was invested in businesses as time passed, it is unclear whether that many jobs were created.</p>
<p>Early in his first term, Trump announced a $10 billion investment by Foxconn in Wisconsin. Foxconn Technology Group is a Taiwan company best known for making Apple iPhones. In 2017, the company won Trump's praise for announcing that it would build a $10 billion factory. Foxconn said it would employ 13,000 people in a small town just south of Milwaukee. A much smaller investment there created fewer than 800 jobs.</p>
<p>Shutdowns during the COVID-19 pandemic starting in 2020 made job creation a more complex issue.</p>
<p>SoftBank itself says it had 65,352 employees as of March.</p>
<p><strong>Reaction in Japan</strong></p>
<p>Officials in Tokyo praised Son's effort, considering it a sign of friendship between the U.S. and Japan. There is concern over whether Trump will increase <strong>tariffs</strong> on some imports from allies like Japan, as well as China.</p>
<p>Yoji Muto is Japan's Trade and Industry minister. He said he was happy with the announcement. Muto said, "Generally speaking, I believe expansion of investment through steady <strong>accumulation</strong> of efforts between Japanese and U.S. companies would help further strengthen Japan-U.S. economic ties, so I find it delightful."</p>
<p>Trump called Son "one of the most <strong>accomplished</strong> business leaders of our time." SoftBank has been rebuilding its finances after the failure of its WeWork business and after investors turned away from some of its technology investments. After a decrease in share value between 2021 and 2023, SoftBank stock has recovered. The company's stock has increased sharply this year.</p>
<p>Amir Anvarzadeh studies Japanese businesses at Asymmetric Advisors, a company that advises on Japanese securities. Speaking of the SoftBank announcement, he said he did not think there was a firm plan. "The question arises, what are they going to buy?" Anvarzadeh asked. He said there were no remaining easily purchased companies in the industry.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jeff Mason and Steve Holland reported this story for Reuters and Elaine Kurtenbach reported on it for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>infrastructure</strong> – <em>n</em>. the basic equipment and structures (such as roads and bridges) that are needed for a country, region, or organization to function properly</p>
<p><strong>chip</strong> – <em>n</em>. a very small piece of hard material (called silicon) in a computer or other device that contains many electronic circuits</p>
<p><strong>application </strong>–n. the economic use of something: in this case, the use of artificial intelligence-based technology</p>
<p><strong>tariff</strong> – <em>n</em>. a tax on goods coming into or leaving a country</p>
<p><strong>accumulate</strong> – <em>v</em>. to gather or acquire (something) gradually as time passes</p>
<p><strong>accomplished</strong> – <em>adj</em>. very successful; having done or achieved many good or important things</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Mini Horses in Greece Bring Joy to Sick, Disabled  (2024/12/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/mini-horses-in-greece-bring-joy-to-sick-disabled.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">24 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A non-profit group in Greece uses small horses to provide pet <strong>therapy</strong> to sick and disabled people. But the organization is now considering its future after facing financial difficulties.</p>
<p>The Associated Press (AP) recently met members of the group, called Gentle Carousel Greece. The animals are brought to hospitals and care centers to give joy to the sick or those suffering physical limitations.</p>
<p>The horses are bred as <strong>miniature</strong> animals and stand about 72 centimeters tall. They are specially trained to provide comfort to disabled children, sick people, or older adults.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Elli Salma, a resident of an elderly care home, looks up as Ivi, a miniature horse used for therapy programs, visits her room, in Athens, Greece, on Friday, Nov. 22, 2024. (AP Photo/Thanassis Stavrakis)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f87ca07d-09b5-4ed1-abb4-34677ec07b42_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Elli Salma, a resident of an elderly care home, looks up as Ivi, a miniature horse used for therapy programs, visits her room, in Athens, Greece, on Friday, Nov. 22, 2024. (AP Photo/Thanassis Stavrakis)</span></div>
<p>One of the horses was recently brought to a school outside Athens for children with special needs. At the school, nine-year-old Josifina Topa Mazuch seemed drawn to a small, gray horse. She ended up leading the animal down a school hallway.</p>
<p>The horse, named Ivy, stood no taller than the girl's pink wheelchair. “I really want them to come again,” Josifina told the AP about Ivy and another visiting horse, Calypso. “They made me feel really happy,” she added.</p>
<p>Ivy and Calypso are two of nine miniature horses provided by the non-profit group. The organization is linked to an American group called Gentle Carousel Miniature Therapy Horses. The U.S. group is based in Ocala, Florida.</p>
<p>The organization said the horses complete at least two years of training. They are taught how to work in <strong>confined</strong> environments with children and adults with special health needs. Caregivers say the horses provide a form of pet therapy that offers valuable social interactions and new learning experiences.</p>
<p>But the leader of the Greek organization says her group has been financially struggling in recent years. Gentle Carousel Greece is run by 68-year-old Mina Karagianni. She said she now performs most of the group's duties herself. Karagianni also finances the group and cares for the nine miniature horses, mostly by herself.</p>
<p>Karagianni also told the AP she learned about the Florida-based organization over the internet while she was searching for information on a pony she had rescued. After learning about the group's activities, she got the idea to start her own operation.</p>
<p>“I was touched and I was moved, and I said: ‘OK, we have to bring this to Greece,'” Karagianni said. So, she decided to make changes to her land to be able to care for the horses. She said she turned her property into what she calls a “Magic Garden.” She has everything she needs to care for the horses. She also runs a small restaurant and party area.</p>
<p>Karagianni launched her Greek group in 2014. She said the organization has served about 12,000 children since it began until the pandemic led to restrictions in 2020.</p>
<p>The pandemic caused financial pressures and Karagianni herself faced a medical problem that hurt her ability to run the group. “I'm just starting to get myself back together again now,” she told the AP. “With a lot of financial difficulties. But what can I do? I'm trying.”</p>
<p>Karagianni said she had contacted businesses and non-profit groups about financial help but has not been successful. She plans to continue to seek help. “I'm making super-human efforts,” Karagianni said. “I'm doing what I can. But I can't do it alone,” she added.</p>
<p>Karagianni said she keeps going because she sees the great <strong>benefits</strong> the children and adults receive from the animals.</p>
<p>At the special needs school, teacher Eleni Volikaki said she sees “incredible” reactions from the children. “It's like something awakens their senses.” Volikaki noted the horses can often get students to make more progress than with other therapy methods.</p>
<p>“We saw things we didn't expect,” she said. “We saw children with autism, or children who are generally afraid of animals, coming very close, letting the (horses) get close to them.” Volikaki added.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>therapy</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> the work of treating mental or physical illness without using drugs or a medical operation</p>
<p><strong>miniature </strong><em>– n.</em> extremely small</p>
<p><strong>confine</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to prevent something from leaving a place or to prevent from spreading</p>
<p><strong>benefit</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> something good that helps you or gives a person an advantage</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers Hope to Bring Back American Chestnuts  (2024/12/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/researchers-hope-to-bring-back-american-chestnuts.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">23 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p><em>“Chestnuts roasting on an open fire,</em></p>
<p><em>Jack Frost nipping at your nose...”</em></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Chestnuts are displayed at a food vendor as a person dressed as Santa Claus offers rides, Thursday, Dec. 12, 2024, in New York. (AP Photo/Alyssa Goodman)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/935a29d6-0549-42a8-be7c-b6dfe073b3e9_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Chestnuts are displayed at a food vendor as a person dressed as Santa Claus offers rides, Thursday, Dec. 12, 2024, in New York. (AP Photo/Alyssa Goodman)</span></div>
<p>This classic song written by Bob Wells and Mel Tormé in 1944 has long brought to mind the image of Christmas for generations of Americans.</p>
<p>At one time, the American Chestnut was among the most common and largest trees in the eastern United States. The wood was used to cover the walls of homes and schools. The leaves helped add nutrients to the soil. And men on street corners sold chestnuts cooked on open fire.</p>
<p>However, in the late 19th century, some East Asian <strong>varieties</strong> of chestnut trees brought to the U.S. carried a <strong>fungus</strong> that killed almost all American chestnuts.</p>
<p><strong>Efforts to bring back the chestnut</strong></p>
<p>The American Chestnut Foundation (TACF) is a non-profit organization based in the eastern state of North Carolina. It has been working with researchers for over 30 years to bring the trees back to eastern U.S. forests.</p>
<p>American chestnuts now exist mostly as huge root systems that grow into small trees. The fungus harms them when the small trees start to develop fully. East Asian varieties, like those that brought the fungus in the first place, are resistant to the fungus.</p>
<p>Researchers have tried to save American chestnuts by cross-breeding, or mixing, them with one kind of Chinese chestnut that can fight off the fungus. Progress has been slow, however. The trees the researchers have grown could not resist the fungus well enough to become large and healthy trees.</p>
<p>That is why scientists are now trying to combine two methods: cross-breeding and genetically modifying, or changing, the genes of American chestnut trees. They hope this will improve the tree's ability to resist attack from the fungus.</p>
<p>But, progress was delayed by a recent mix-up involving two varieties of genetically modified American chestnuts. Scientists at the State University of New York (SUNY) had hoped to get approval for the new seed this year.</p>
<p><strong>Possible effects of climate change </strong></p>
<p>A changing climate and warmer temperatures may also make restoring the chestnut difficult in some areas.</p>
<p>A team at Virginia Tech University published a study this summer about this issue. They looked at projected future climates and then measured the shortest distance the trees would have to move to survive well in a new climate.</p>
<p>For now, researchers know their work might not be successful in their lifetimes. The process has been slow. And two of the first chestnut <strong>restoration</strong> experts, Bill Powell and Chuck Maynard, both died in the past 13 months.</p>
<p>Linda McGuigan helped support Powell's and Maynard's research for years at SUNY's College of Environmental Science and Forestry.</p>
<p>“The project moves on, lives on. And we honor their memory,” McGuigan said. “I want to do something good for the future, for my children.”</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Marina Walling wrote this story for The Associated Press. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p><p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>variety </strong><em>-n. </em>a kind or type of something</p>
<p><strong>fungus </strong><em>-n. </em>a mushroom or other plant that has no flowers, leaves, or green coloring</p>
<p><strong>restoration </strong><em>-n. </em>the bringing back of something to its former condition</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>New US Food Guidelines: Eat Less Meat, More Beans  (2024/12/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/new-us-food-guidelines-eat-less-meat-more-beans.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">23 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the Health &amp; Lifestyle report.</p>
<p>For a healthy diet, people should eat more beans, peas and lentils. They should eat less red meat and processed meats, as well as <strong>starchy</strong> vegetables, like potatoes. Also, they should continue to limit added sugars, sodium and saturated fat, an especially unhealthy kind of fat.</p>
<p>That is the latest advice released on December 10 by a <strong>panel</strong> of nutrition experts. This panel of experts is responsible for advising the U.S. government about the 2025 dietary guidelines. These guidelines will inform and shape federal food programs and policy.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - New U.S. food guidelines suggest eating less red meat and more beans, vegetables and healthy fats. In this Jan. 18, 2010 file photo, beef products are for sale at a food store in McLean, Virginia. (AP Photo/J. Scott Applewhite)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/21618652-914f-4a45-bb9c-5c1e8c22c4e6_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - New U.S. food guidelines suggest eating less red meat and more beans, vegetables and healthy fats. In this Jan. 18, 2010 file photo, beef products are for sale at a food store in McLean, Virginia. (AP Photo/J. Scott Applewhite)</span></div>
<p>But the 20-member panel did not advise on ultra-processed foods that some research findings link to health problems. The panel says there is not enough evidence to tell people to avoid them. And the group did not speak to possibly updating <strong>controversial</strong> guidance on drinking alcohol. They are leaving that issue to two independent reports expected to be released soon.</p>
<p>Overall, the <strong>recommendations</strong> for the 2025-2030 Dietary Guidelines for Americans sound familiar, said Marion Nestle. She is a food policy expert.</p>
<p>“This looks like every other set of dietary guidelines since 1980: eat your veggies and reduce <strong>consumption</strong> of foods high in salt, sugar and saturated fat,” she said in an email.</p>
<p>She also said the latest advice “says nothing about balancing calories, when overconsumption of calories, especially from ultra-processed foods, is the biggest <strong>challenge</strong> to the health of Americans.”</p>
<p><strong>What the scientific panel said about healthy diets</strong></p>
<p>The nutrition panel described a healthy diet for people beginning at two years old. It is high in vegetables, fruits, legumes, nuts, whole grains, fish and vegetable oils that are higher in unsaturated fat.</p>
<p>The recommended diet is lower in red and processed meats, sugar-sweetened food and drink, refined grains and saturated fat. It may also include fat-free or low-fat dairy and foods lower in sodium and may include plant-based foods.</p>
<p>This panel worked on the guidelines for almost two years. It was the first to consider dietary needs based on financial situation, race, ethnicity and culture.</p>
<p>Panelist Fatima Cody Stanford is an <strong>obesity</strong> expert and doctor at Massachusetts General Hospital. In an email, she said that considering these new elements will help make sure that the guidance “...<strong>reflects</strong> and includes <strong>various</strong> population groups."</p>
<p><strong>Missing from the guidelines</strong></p>
<p>The panel did not advise on two controversial food groups: ultra-processed foods or alcohol.</p>
<p>Ultra-processed foods make up about 60 percent of the American diet.</p>
<p>The panel considered more than 40 studies. Several of them showed links between ultra-processed foods and being overweight or obesity. But the nutrition experts had concerns with the quality of the research. So, they said the evidence was too limited to make recommendations.</p>
<p>The panel also did not change recommendations about alcohol. The current guidelines are two drinks or less a day for men and one drink or less a day for women.</p>
<p>The last time the guidance was updated was in 2020. At that time, the government rejected the advice of scientific advisers to recommend less alcohol consumption.</p>
<p>Two separate government groups expect to release reports in the coming months on the effects of moderate alcohol use to inform the guidelines.</p>
<p><strong>Do Americans follow dietary guidelines?</strong></p>
<p>The advisory panel said they know that the diets of most Americans do not meet the current guidelines. More than half of all adults in the country have one or more diet-related <strong>chronic </strong>health condition. And 18 million individuals and families have insecure sources of food, the report says.</p>
<p>The report adds that “...nutrition-related chronic health conditions” will continue “to threaten health through the lifespan.” It adds that this is not good “for the future of health in the United States.”</p>
<p><strong>What happens next?</strong></p>
<p>The scientific report informs the dietary guidelines which are updated every five years. These new recommendations now go to the U.S. Health &amp; Human Services (or HHS) and the U.S. Department of Agriculture (or USDA). Officials there will create the final guidance and release it next year.</p>
<p>As of December 11, the public has 60 days to comment on the guidance. HHS and USDA officials will hold a public meeting on January 16 to discuss the recommendations.</p>
<p>And that's the Health &amp; Lifestyle report.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>JoNel Aleccia reported this story for the Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>_______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>panel</strong> <em>– n.</em> a group of persons selected for some service (such as investigation or arbitration)</p>
<p><strong>controversial </strong><em>– adj. </em>something that causes a discussion marked especially by the expression of opposing views</p>
<p><strong>recommendation </strong><em>– n</em>. suggestions or advice on what is the best thing to do</p>
<p><strong>consumption</strong> <em>– n. </em>the act of eating or drinking something</p>
<p><strong>challenge </strong><em>– n. </em>a stimulating task or problem</p>
<p><strong>obesity</strong> <em>– n. </em>a condition that is characterized by excessive accumulation and storage of fat in the body and that in an adult is typically indicated by a body mass index of 30 or greater</p>
<p><strong>reflect </strong><em>– v. </em>to cause (something, such as honor or credit) to be attributed or associated —used with the words <em>on</em> or <em>upon</em></p>
<p><strong>various </strong><em>– adj. </em>of an indefinite number greater than one</p>
<p><strong>chronic</strong> <em>– adj. </em>continuing or occurring again and again for a long time</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Good Wintertime Meals Are Warm, Healthy and Tasty  (2024/12/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/good-wintertime-meals-are-warm-healthy-and-tasty.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">23 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p class="MsoBodyText">Winter is settling in across much of the United States, with dropping temperatures, snowfall and icy roads.</p>
<p class="MsoBodyText">But the cold season does not mean weeks of lifeless, colorless meals.</p>
<p>Diet and food experts say winter is a time to experiment. They suggest trying some of the season's vegetables to cook a healthy meal that tastes good.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Tomato vegetable soup is served at Madison Spring Hut in the White Mountains of New Hampshire, Monday, June 11, 2007. (AP Photo/Robert F. Bukaty, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/093305d7-ae75-41ef-a923-c5de07142c46_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Tomato vegetable soup is served at Madison Spring Hut in the White Mountains of New Hampshire, Monday, June 11, 2007. (AP Photo/Robert F. Bukaty, File)</span></div>
<p>“<strong>Embrace</strong> the cold, embrace the winter and <strong>appreciate</strong> the <strong>bounty</strong>,” said Kristen Rasmussen. Rasmussen is a dietician and cook who teaches at the University of California Berkeley.</p>
<p>Here are some suggestions from nutrition experts on how to “winterize” your meals:</p>
<p><strong>Fresh fruits and vegetables</strong></p>
<p>Any <strong>produce</strong> is good. Only one in 10 Americans eat the <strong>recommended</strong> amounts of fruits and vegetables each day, the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention says.</p>
<p><strong>Staple</strong> fruits and vegetables are available all year in American food stores. But winter is also “high season” for a few special kinds.</p>
<p>Citrus fruits, including lemons, limes and oranges, are among the fresh fruit available in U.S. stores in the winter. Other produce we connect with the cold weather are pumpkins and root vegetables like sweet potatoes, parsnips, beets and radishes.</p>
<p>And do not overlook winter's leafy greens. Rasmussen suggests including more chicory into your winter diet, like radicchio, escarole and endive. You can also try different kales and the leafy tops of root vegetables, like radish greens.</p>
<p>If fresh choices are limited, experts say <strong>canned</strong> and frozen fruits and vegetables still have a lot of nutritional value. Just do not overcook them. Also make sure these foods do not have a lot of added salt or fat.</p>
<p>Dried fruits, including apricots, dates and raisins, are good for winter meals. Nuts can also be tasty, nutritious and filling.</p>
<p>“Without a doubt, there's a lot of nutritional <strong>benefit</strong>, even in dried (fruits),” said Linda Van Horn, a clinical nutrition epidemiologist at Northwestern University in Illinois.</p>
<p><strong>Liquid meals: stew, soup or porridge</strong></p>
<p>Soups, stews and porridges are foods that have a long history and are eaten in many cultures. They often are made using just one cooking <strong>pot</strong> which can ease the whole process. They all can be frozen easily for a later meal.</p>
<p>And you can put just about anything in them.</p>
<p>“The benefit of it is that it's all contained,” Van Horn said. She noted that nutrients from the <strong>ingredients</strong> stay in the cooking liquid, or broth.</p>
<p>These meals are also a way to try out different beans and legumes, which Rasmussen called a “nutritional powerhouse.”</p>
<p>They are less costly than produce and provide an excellent source of protein and <strong>fiber </strong>said Alicia Henson. Henson is a dietician for children at the University of California San Francisco's Benioff Children's Hospital.</p>
<p>Porridges — in the morning or beyond — are a good way to try out different grains.</p>
<p>“You can make it <strong>savory</strong> or sweet, you can put leftovers on top...,” Rasmussen said, “...or an egg.”</p>
<p><strong>Cook for others to nourish mind and body</strong></p>
<p>Winter can be <strong>isolating</strong> for some people. So, join friends and family for meals even when it is not a holiday.</p>
<p>Eating foods that are “in season” can help people connect with the sources of their food and with their environment, experts say.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Devi Shastri reported this story for the Associated Press. Caty Weaver adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>embrace</strong><strong> </strong><em>–v.</em> to take up especially readily or gladly<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>appreciate</strong> <em>–n.</em> to understand the nature, worth, quality, or significance of</p>
<p><strong>bounty </strong><em>–n.</em> a lot of or a surplus of something good</p>
<p><strong>produce </strong><em>–n.</em> fresh fruit or vegetable</p>
<p><strong>recommend</strong><strong> </strong><em>–v.</em> suggest or advise</p>
<p><strong>staple </strong><em>–n.</em> something having widespread and constant use or appeal</p>
<p><strong>canned </strong><em>–adj.</em> put in a metal container called a can for long term storage</p>
<p><strong>benefit </strong><em>–n.</em> something that has value</p>
<p><strong>pot </strong><em>–n.</em> a container for cooking</p>
<p><strong>ingredient </strong>–n. one of the things that is put into a food to make it taste as it does</p>
<p><strong>savory </strong><em>–adj. </em>having a spicy or salty quality without sweetness</p>
<p><strong>fiber </strong><em>–n.</em> the part of food that cannot be digested</p>
<p><strong>isolate </strong><em>–v. </em>to set or keep apart from others</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Robot Leads Cattle to Greener Fields  (2024/12/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/robot-leads-cattle-to-greener-fields.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Researchers in Australia are using a robot powered by artificial intelligence (AI) to improve the way farmers raise cattle.</p>
<p>The robot has four wheels and is painted red.</p>
<p>Researchers have named the robot cow SwagBot. It can drive by itself and move cows from one field to another based on the condition of the soil and plant life.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="University of Sydney's autonomous robot 'SwagBot' moves around a field in Allynbrook, Australia, November 22, 2024. (REUTERS/Cordelia Hsu)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/600f9823-e6f4-40d9-8e2f-41b32f51e8bd_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">University of Sydney's autonomous robot 'SwagBot' moves around a field in Allynbrook, Australia, November 22, 2024. (REUTERS/Cordelia Hsu)
</span></div>
<p>Researchers at the University of Sydney in Australia said SwagBot is becoming the world's first “smart cow.” They believe it can make cattle farming more <strong>efficient</strong> and put less pressure on the environment.</p>
<p>Swagbot was first launched in 2016. At that time, it could only move around fields where cattle <strong>graze</strong>. Over time, scientists have added sensors and AI systems to the robot.</p>
<p>These systems help SwagBot judge the health, type, and thickness of grasses and plants in fields and to observe the health of the cattle.</p>
<p>The robot uses this information to move cattle to the best areas for grazing. The goal is to move cattle to a new grazing area before they have damaged the grass in a particular field. This can prevent damage to the soil. The robot can also send the information back to farmers.</p>
<p>Salah Sukkarieh is a professor of robotics and intelligent systems at the University of Sydney. His team made SwagBot. He said that once cattle feel at ease near the robot, they follow it around.</p>
<p>"You want to move the animals to the right part of the <strong>pasture</strong> where there is good protein, good <strong>carbs</strong>," he said. Sukkarieh added that it is important to move the cattle easily and without fences.</p>
<p>Australia is one of the world's biggest exporters of beef. It has around 30 million cattle spread across large areas that are often dry. As a result, some pastures are of low quality and do not have a lot of grass.</p>
<p>Farmers carefully <strong>assess</strong> how many animals their land can support. However, many farmers have little control over where the animals graze within large areas of land. Overgrazing can lead to poor soil that supports less plant and animal life.</p>
<p>Erin O'Neill is a part-time farmer who watched a recent demonstration of the robot in a field north of Sydney. She said the robot can help farmers get detailed information about the current condition of their fields.</p>
<p>She said the robot can tell farmers “what bits of pasture are most nutritious, particularly if you've got cattle like we do that are pregnant.” O'Neill added that pregnant cattle need high-quality pastures to aid them through pregnancy.</p>
<p>SwagBot is still in development. It is part of a growing movement in agriculture towards robotics. Farming experts hope robots can make production more efficient. Robots could also reduce the need for workers in places, like Australia, where finding workers in areas with a low population can be difficult.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Cordelia Hsu wrote this story for Reuters news agency. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>efficient </strong>–adj. something that does what it is supposed to do using the least resources possible</p>
<p><strong>graze </strong>–v. when certain animals, such as cattle, eat grass in a field</p>
<p><strong>pasture </strong>–n. a field used for feeding animals like cattle, sheep, goats, or other grazing animals</p>
<p><strong>assess </strong>–v. to take in information in the aim of making a judgement or determination about it</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>NASA Identifies Cause of Mars Helicopter’s Final Crash  (2024/12/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/nasa-identifies-cause-of-mars-helicopter-s-final-crash.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The American space agency NASA says it has found the likely cause of a crash that grounded its Mars helicopter Ingenuity.</p>
<p>The finding comes after NASA said it had carried out the “first aircraft accident investigation on another world.”</p>
<p>Ingenuity arrived on Mars along with NASA's Perseverance explorer, or rover, in February 2021. The experimental helicopter took its last flight, number 72, in January. That flight ended in a hard landing on the Martian surface.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="NASA's Ingenuity Mars Helicopter stands near a sand hill in an image taken by the Perseverance rover on Feb. 24, 2024, about five weeks after the aircraft's crash. (Image credit: Credit: NASA/JPL-Caltech/LANL/CNES/CNRS)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/21955213-579b-4598-bd5e-c0d60943f90e_cx70_cy8_cw29_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">NASA's Ingenuity Mars Helicopter stands near a sand hill in an image taken by the Perseverance rover on Feb. 24, 2024, about five weeks after the aircraft's crash. (Image credit: Credit: NASA/JPL-Caltech/LANL/CNES/CNRS)</span></div>
<p>In April 2021, Ingenuity became the first aircraft to complete a powered, controlled flight on another planet. The aircraft was built to test take-off, short flight and landing operations. The flights on Mars aimed to support NASA's efforts to build new aircraft that can fly in the atmospheres of other planets.</p>
<p>Engineers from NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory in California fully investigated Ingenuity's last flight on Mars. They found the cause of the crash was linked to the helicopter's <strong>navigation</strong> system. That camera-based system was not able to collect dependable data on elements of the Martian surface to support a safe landing.</p>
<p>A detailed, final report on the accident is to be issued in the coming weeks. But the engineers have already described their main findings <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.jpl.nasa.gov/news/nasa-performs-first-aircraft-accident-investigation-on-another-world/">in a statement</a> published online.</p>
<p>They said the helicopter's last flight saw the aircraft climb to about 12 meters, where it stayed, or hovered, while capturing images of the Martian surface. Data records show Ingenuity began its planned <strong>descent</strong> after about 19 seconds. By 32 seconds, the helicopter was back on the surface and was no longer sending communication signals.</p>
<p>The next day, Ingenuity team members reestablished communications and received images from its last flight. The images showed the aircraft suffered severe damage to its <strong>rotor blades</strong>.</p>
<p>NASA explained that Ingenuity's navigation system plays an important part in collecting data about the surface to ensure the aircraft can complete a smooth landing. The helicopter uses a camera that points downward, capturing information about what is below the craft.</p>
<p>In past flights, the engineers said the camera was able to find smooth, suitable landing possibilities. But NASA said during the final flight, the helicopter was traveling in an area with very few surface <strong>features</strong> for the camera to capture. This meant the aircraft's navigation system could not find enough of these features to choose a good landing spot.</p>
<p>At the time, Ingenuity was operating together with NASA's Perseverance rover in an area of Mars known as Jezero Crater.</p>
<p>The images recovered from Ingenuity suggested the navigation system's inability to pick up surface features made the helicopter descend too fast. The hard landing on a sand hill is believed to have caused the helicopter to turn over and roll.</p>
<p>The engineers said images showed that all four of Ingenuity's rotor blades broke at their weakest point. The damaged blades also caused the aircraft to shake. Events related to the crash led to increased power demand, which resulted in the loss of communications.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p>Although the crash ended Ingenuity's flight operations, NASA said it is still able to provide and send back weather information and other kinds of data. The space agency says this information could be helpful in designing future aircraft or other explorers to be sent to Mars.</p>
<p>Teddy Tzanetos is Ingenuity's project manager. He said in a statement one major thing the team learned was that future aircraft designed for space travel do not necessarily need to be large flying machines. Tzanetos added that Ingenuity's <strong>longevity</strong> suggests that “not everything needs to be bigger, heavier, and radiation-hardened” to work in the Martian environment.</p>
<p>With this in mind, NASA engineers have been testing smaller, lighter flying vehicles, with limited electronics, in order to produce future helicopters that can make a large number of smaller exploration trips.</p>
<p>Tzanetos shared details about one aircraft NASA is currently developing. It is called the Mars Chopper rotorcraft. Tzanetos said Chopper is about 20 times heavier than Ingenuity. Developers say it would be built to carry several kilograms of science equipment, while self-exploring distant areas of Mars. Chopper would also have a much longer travel ability, flying up to 3 kilometers in a day. Ingenuity's longest flight was 704 meters.</p>
<p>Tzanetos said that overall, “Ingenuity has given us the <strong>confidence </strong>and data to <strong>envision</strong> the future of flight at Mars.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English based on reports from NASA. </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>navigation</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> finding directions by using maps or other equipment</p>
<p><strong>rotor blade</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> thin, flat pieces of material that spin to make aircraft lift off the ground and travel</p>
<p><strong>descent </strong><em>– n. </em>the act or process of moving downward</p>
<p><strong>feature </strong><em>– n.</em> a common quality or important part of something</p>
<p><strong>longevity</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> surviving for a long time</p>
<p><strong>confidence</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> the feeling or belief that someone or some group is good or able to succeed at something</p>
<p><strong>envision</strong> <em>v. </em>to picture oneself</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>At Venezuela’s Hospital for Soft Toys, Old Toys Find New Life  (2024/12/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/at-venezuela-s-hospital-for-soft-toys-old-toys-find-new-life.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>One by one, volunteers rescue and repair <strong>toys</strong> that show the marks of use. They sew clothing and <strong>brush</strong> <strong>fur</strong> and hair, add filling and dress the toys. The workers are fixing them to again be given to children.</p>
<p>This is the work of the Hospital for Soft Toys, a project in Venezuela's capital, Caracas. The effort began with a mother's question: What do you do with all the toys once children <strong>outgrow</strong> them?</p>
<p>About 60 volunteers now meet at least twice a week. They work on Barbie <strong>dolls</strong>, toy bears and baby dolls that children have left behind. The group estimates it has <strong>recycled</strong> about 70,000 toys in the past seven years.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Volunteers restore used toys to donate them to vulnerable children as Christmas presents, at the non-profit foundation Hospital de los Peluches, or Hospital of Stuffed Animals, in Caracas, Venezuela, Thursday, Dec. 5, 2024. (AP Photo/Ariana Cubillos)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/c0b434e2-7f7b-4dd5-b26a-790d63668965_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Volunteers restore used toys to donate them to vulnerable children as Christmas presents, at the non-profit foundation Hospital de los Peluches, or Hospital of Stuffed Animals, in Caracas, Venezuela, Thursday, Dec. 5, 2024. (AP Photo/Ariana Cubillos)</span></div>
<p>Its volunteers work faster around the Christmas holiday. Mirady Acosta is a 63-year-old <strong>architect</strong> who represents the Hospital for Soft Toys. She said the idea came from a teacher named Lilian Gluck. In 2017, Gluck was looking for something to do with her children's toys as they grew older.</p>
<p>She did not want to throw them out or let them fall apart. She decided to wash them, fix them up and donate them to children staying in the University Hospital of Caracas.</p>
<p>The effort was popular. So, a few months later, she opened the Hospital for Soft Toys at her home. It is a nonprofit <strong>foundation</strong> that also collects and repairs other toys and educational games. The foundation receives donations from other countries that can include school supplies, <strong>diapers</strong>, shoes, food and candy.</p>
<p>All have been welcomed in a country that has seen years of economic crisis and renewed political unrest after July's election.</p>
<p>Silvia Heiber has volunteered for almost three years. She is 72 years old. She said that smoothing a soft toy's fur or fixing a doll's hair for another child to care for is also helpful for the volunteers.</p>
<p>"By doing this, all of us who come here are in <strong>therapy</strong>, a therapy of support for one another," Heiber said.</p>
<p>Mirna Morales is a 76-year-old teacher and volunteer. She called it "one of the best experiences I've ever had."</p>
<p>María Poleo, who is 84 years old, said the work is not difficult because all the volunteers know how to make or repair clothing.</p>
<p>On some days, it seems there are not enough toys to repair. But then someone arrives at the door with more boxes and bags full of toys.</p>
<p>The toys are delivered to hospitals and schools in poor areas, but also to homes for older people — anyone "who needs a little bit of <strong>affection</strong>," Heiber said.</p>
<p>Each restored doll comes with a message advising its new owner to recycle it when they no longer want it.</p>
<p>"Hello, I am your new friend," it says. "I am a doll with experience because I played with another girl. Love me and take care of me and I will do the same with you. When you grow up, give me to another girl who will love me and play with me like you."</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jorge Rueda and Juan Pablo Arráez reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>toy </strong>–n. an object for children to play with</p>
<p><strong>brush</strong> – <em>v</em>. to clean or smooth (something) with a brush</p>
<p><strong>fur</strong> – <em>n</em>. the hairy coat of an animal especially when it is soft and thick</p>
<p><strong>outgrow</strong> – <em>v</em>. to grow too large for (someone or something)</p>
<p><strong>recycle</strong> – <em>v</em>. to make something new from (something that has been used before)</p>
<p><strong>architect </strong>–n. a person whose job it is to design buildings</p>
<p><strong>foundation </strong>–n. an organization usually that administers money and support for a cause like health care or education</p>
<p><strong>diaper</strong> – <em>n</em>. a piece of cloth or other material that is placed between a baby's legs and fastened around the waist to hold body waste</p>
<p><strong>therapy</strong> – <em>n</em>. the treatment of physical or mental illnesses that does not use drugs</p>
<p><strong>affection</strong> – <em>n</em>. a feeling of liking and caring for someone or something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Expressions That ‘Stop You Cold’  (2024/12/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/expressions-that-stop-you-cold.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>In many parts of the world, temperatures are dropping for the winter season. But even for those in warm weather, our show on the word “cold” will help your English.</p>
<p>“Cold” is not just an adjective describing temperature. It can also describe stopping something suddenly and surprisingly. It also means starting or doing something without preparation.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A person walks in freezing cold temperatures in New York City on January 17, 2024. Temperature highs in the city are expected to hit 25F (-3.9C). (Photo by ANGELA WEISS / AFP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/46b1f25f-42db-42eb-bcb2-4e3f5147d26d_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A person walks in freezing cold temperatures in New York City on January 17, 2024. Temperature highs in the city are expected to hit 25F (-3.9C). (Photo by ANGELA WEISS / AFP)</span></div>
<p>These definitions give us several expressions and idioms.</p>
<p>When someone or something <u>stops cold,</u> it stops completely, suddenly, and perhaps with surprise. For example, I was surprised when my car <u>stopped cold</u> on a recent trip. I had just had it fixed! With this expression, we often say the thing or person being stopped. So, in that example, I could say engine trouble <u>stopped my car cold</u>.</p>
<p>When we <u>stop (someone) cold,</u> we completely stop them from doing something suddenly or immediately. Here's an example.</p>
<p><em>The sunset was so beautiful; it <u>stopped me cold</u>. </em></p>
<p>Sometimes, we add “in my <strong>tracks”</strong> to this expression, such as:</p>
<p><em>The sunset was so beautiful; it <u>stopped me cold in my tracks</u>.</em></p>
<p>Other <strong>variations</strong> of this expression include <u>to stop (someone) dead in their tracks</u> and <u>to stop (someone) on a <strong>dime</strong>.</u> They all mean the same thing – something or someone has come to a standstill. And we can use them the same way.</p>
<p>Now, let's talk about how we use <u>cold</u> in the business world.</p>
<p>Sometimes, we need to call someone who does not know us, and we do not know them. These are <u>cold calls</u>.</p>
<p>A <u>cold call</u> can also be a visit to a person or business. And usually we want to sell something. For example, a salesperson may have a <u>cold call</u> list to get new business.</p>
<p><u>Cold calls</u>, whether on the phone or in-person, are <strong>unsolicited</strong>. This means that no one asked or requested contact.</p>
<p>In business and also in life, if you <u>come to something cold</u> or <u>come into something cold</u>, you are not prepared. Here is an example:</p>
<p><em>Last week, I <u>came into the meeting cold</u>. I hadn't read any of the materials. </em></p>
<p>However, if you <u>come in from the cold</u>, you are in luck. It means you rejoin a group or a normal society again after being outside. We often use this expression to describe someone like a spy who was able <u>to come in from the cold</u> and enjoy a normal life.</p>
<p><u>Come in from the cold</u> can also be used when someone or something becomes popular, accepted, or active again after being unpopular, unaccepted, and inactive for a time.</p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>.</p>
<p>Until next time ... I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>track </strong><em>– n. </em>a mark left by something that has gone by</p>
<p><strong>variation</strong> <em>– n. </em>a change in form, position, or condition</p>
<p><strong>dime </strong><em>– n. </em>a coin of the U.S. worth <i></i>185;/<i></i>8321;<i></i>8320; dollar</p>
<p><strong>unsolicited </strong><em>– adj. </em>not asked for or requested</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Japanese Artist Finds Peace in Cutting Leaves  (2024/12/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/japanese-artist-finds-peace-in-cutting-leaves.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">20 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A Japanese artist who creates detailed designs on fallen leaves says the process gives the leaves new life and also helps keep him healthy.</p>
<p>The artist goes by the name Lito. He did not want to share his full name for personal reasons. Lito likes to cut, or carve, many different leaf designs. Examples of his work include a frog holding an <strong>umbrella</strong>, animals jumping happily, Japan's famous Mount Fuji and ocean waves.</p>
<p>Lito began making his leaf art in 2020. Now, he has many fans around the world who discovered his designs on social media.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Japanese leaf-cutting artist Lito looks at his freshly cut work during an interview in Tokyo on November 27, 2024. (AP Photo/Shuji Kajiyama)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/62b19150-68c8-4ee1-83bd-06a3284f9dc8_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Japanese leaf-cutting artist Lito looks at his freshly cut work during an interview in Tokyo on November 27, 2024. (AP Photo/Shuji Kajiyama)
</span></div>
<p>He recently told reporters from The Associated Press that his work also gives him peaceful feelings to help deal with a health issue. The condition Lito struggles with is called attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder, or ADHD. People with ADHD can experience difficulties such as mental <strong>focus</strong>, directing attention and organizing and controlling urges.</p>
<p>The 38-year-old Lito said that in addition to helping him deal with his own issues, he hopes his art can give other people enjoyment as well.</p>
<p>Lito likes working at night. In a demonstration of his process, he showed that he first treats several leaves with a chemical to keep them from drying out. Then, he chooses the one he wants to work on and places it on a cutting surface.</p>
<p>He begins by making a design on the leaf with a pen. He then uses a special design knife to cut the leaf. As he works slowly and carefully, one leaf begins to take the shape of a frog carrying an umbrella.</p>
<p>Some of Lito's more complex creations on a single leaf can take more than eight hours to complete. He said he likes to finish a leaf in one sitting. His leaf-cutting works include titles such as <em>Scrolls of Frolicking Animals</em>, <em>Leaf Aquarium</em>, and <em>Thirty-six Views of Mt. Fuji: The Great Wave off Kanagawa</em>. He often uses animals as his subject and each piece includes some of hisown personal elements.</p>
<p>Since his childhood, Lito says he has had high levels of <strong>concentration</strong> and <strong>patience</strong>. But no matter how hard he tried, he felt he could not meet expectations of behavior at school and work. He also struggled to understand others' feelings and to avoid conflict.</p>
<p>After years of difficulty, he went to a hospital at age 30 and was told he has ADHD, a <strong>diagnosis</strong> he felt explained why he has always done things differently.</p>
<p>Lito said he saw no reason to force himself to do things the same way as other people. So, he decided to change his way of living.</p>
<p>In early 2020, Lito learned about the art of leaf cutting. He saw it as the perfect use of his patience and concentration.</p>
<p>Word of his skill has spread far across social media, and he has published books on his leaf-cutting work. And almost every month, he holds a showing of his art in different places in Japan.</p>
<p>"If I can make people happy by doing what I am doing, I want to do more. That's my driving force for what's next," Lito said.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Mayuko Ono, Shuji Kajiyama and Mari Yamaguchi reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>umbrella</strong> – <em>n</em>. a device used to protect oneself from rain or sunlight</p>
<p><strong>focus</strong> – <em>n</em>. a state or condition permitting clear perception or understanding</p>
<p><strong>concentration</strong> – <em>n</em>. the ability to give your attention or thought to a single object or activity</p>
<p><strong>patient</strong> – <em>adj.</em> bearing pain or difficulty calmly or without complaint</p>
<p><strong>diagnosis</strong> – n. a medical finding of disease</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Kinds and Types  (2024/12/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/kinds-and-types.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">20 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Ann in Vietnam about four words that help describe what group something belongs to.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/90cdc02c-addc-4e42-88be-311d6c79a95b_w268_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>What are [the] differences among species, kinds, types, and genres? Which case [is] each word used for? Thank you,</p>
<p>Ann</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Ann.</p>
<p>We can use each of the words you ask about to describe what category something belongs in. A category is a group of things that share similar qualities.</p>
<p>For example, apples, bananas, and oranges all belong in the same category, which is fruit.</p>
<p><strong>Kind and type</strong></p>
<p>The words “kind” and “type” are synonyms. That means they each share the same meaning. And they have the most general meaning of the four words you ask about.</p>
<p>A “kind” or a “type” is a group that shares things in common. For example:</p>
<p><em>Electric cars are one <u>kind</u> of car, while gasoline-powered cars are another <u>type</u> (or <u>kind</u>) of car.</em></p>
<p>Notice that we commonly put the preposition “of” after the words “kind” or “type.”</p>
<p>The phrases “a kind of” and “a type of” are both very common in spoken English. We use the phrase “a kind of” more often than we use the phrase “a type of.”</p>
<p><strong>Species and genre</strong></p>
<p>The two words “species” and “genre” are more specific than the two words “kind” and “type.”</p>
<p>We use the word “species” to categorize living things. For example:</p>
<p><em>Elephants, cats, dogs, and mice are different <u>species</u> of animals. </em></p>
<p><em>Roses and lilies are different <u>species</u> of flowers. </em></p>
<p>Each species has a Latin scientific name. For example, the name of the species for human beings is <em>Homo sapiens</em>.</p>
<p>The word “genre” comes from the Latin word “genus,” which means “group.” We use “genre” to categorize styles of creative works. For example, music has many genres, such as rock, hip-hop, classical, and jazz. Genres of painting include Impressionism and Cubism. Likewise, film, dance, photography, literature, and theater each have their own genres.</p>
<p>The word “genre” is more formal than “kind of.” So, in everyday discussions, we might ask someone:</p>
<p><em>What <u>kind</u> of movies do you like?</em></p>
<p>However, in writing or more formal discussions, we might use the word “genre.”</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your favorite genres of creative works? And what are your questions about American English? We want to hear from you! Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please let us know where you are from, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Near a New Jersey Highway, a Large Statue of Buddha  (2024/12/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/near-a-new-jersey-highway-a-large-statue-of-buddha.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In the eastern American state of New Jersey, a large statue of Buddha has become a gathering place for people of many religious faiths.</p>
<p>The nine-meter-high statue has stood among the woods in Franklin Township since 2009. It was built under the leadership of the Venerable Hungampola Sirirathana Nayaka Thera, a Buddhist monk from Sri Lanka. He says his dream is to unite people of all faiths.</p>
<p>The statue is on the grounds of the New Jersey Buddhist Vihara and Meditation Center. The center has become a spiritual place for Buddhists, Hindus, and Christians.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Carol Kruhen lifts up her pressed palms next to a statue of the Buddha after meditating at the New Jersey Buddhist Vihara and Meditation Center in Franklin Township, N.J. on Sunday Nov. 30, 2024. (AP photo/Luis Andres Henao)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/3676030c-37ed-48be-b3eb-a86eb3c01bdd_cx6_cy2_cw87_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Carol Kruhen lifts up her pressed palms next to a statue of the Buddha after meditating at the New Jersey Buddhist Vihara and Meditation Center in Franklin Township, N.J. on Sunday Nov. 30, 2024. (AP photo/Luis Andres Henao)
</span></div>
<p>Among those who praise the center are a Princeton University professor who grew up in a Korean Christian church and who follows Tibetan Buddhism; a leader of the local Nepali community who organizes interfaith gatherings; and a woman who became a Buddhist after living near the statue.</p>
<p>“It just seems to be a <strong>nexus</strong> where a lot of people connect,” said Daniel Choi. He follows Tibetan Buddhism and teaches writing at Princeton. He has been <strong>meditating</strong> in front of the Buddha statue since 2015.</p>
<p>Choi said that the center is open to the public. He said that is unlike most Buddhist centers in the U.S. which are run by private organizations, “where you wouldn't be able to go in for open practice,” he said.</p>
<p>He also noted that the center is in an unexpected place. Thera built the statue and meditation center behind a house close to a highway.</p>
<p>“You hear traffic; you hear cars rushing by; you hear airplanes flying above...You hear the <strong>construction</strong> work going on,” Choi said.</p>
<p>The meditation center follows Theravada, the main form of Buddhism observed in Sri Lanka, Burma and Thailand. But it welcomes all Buddhist traditions and other faiths.</p>
<p>When Choi first visited, he was surprised to find a statue of Kuan Yin, the Buddhist goddess of <strong>compassion</strong>. The goddess is important in Mahayana Buddhism observed in China and Korea.</p>
<p>“For me that was very welcoming because I thought: 'OK, so there's something for me as well,'” Choi said.</p>
<p>Local students have painted a wall in the center with images showing different world religions, from Baha'i and Christianity to Sikhism and Zoroastrianism. All of these religions are practiced in New Jersey.</p>
<p>Tulsi Maharjan is director of the nonprofit organization Friends of Nepal - New Jersey. He has led projects involving more than one religion, including the wall painting and a peace garden.</p>
<p>He said that when he first came to New Jersey 35 years ago, he had to drive almost three hours to go to a Buddhist temple. But now, people from all over the world live near the Vihara Meditation center and statue.</p>
<p>“Now, within ten minutes...from my home, I can go to the Buddhist temple. But there are so many others,” he said listing nearby Jain, Sikh and Hindu temples that make him proud of the religious diversity in central New Jersey.</p>
<p>Maharjan said that anybody who comes to the temple “feels so <strong>calm and collected</strong> once they see that big Buddha.”</p>
<p>Carol Kuehn is a 76-year-old retired high school teacher who lives next to the Buddhist center. Kuehn said: “It's the first thing I look at in the morning.”</p>
<p>Kuehn grew up in a Christian family and became interested in Buddhism after reading Herman Hesse's novel <em>Siddhartha</em>.</p>
<p>She became a Buddhist after the leader of the temple arrived in 2002. Buddhism, she said, helped her deal with <strong>grief</strong> after the death of her husband.</p>
<p>“The whole point of Buddhism is to live in the moment,” she said.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Luis Andres Henao wrote this story for The Associated Press. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>nexus </strong><em>–n.</em> a point where people or things meet or join together</p>
<p><strong>meditate </strong><em>–v.</em> to spend time in quiet thought with the aim of easing tension or considering spiritual issues</p>
<p><strong>construction </strong><em>–n.</em> the process of building structures such as homes and buildings</p>
<p><strong>compassion </strong><em>–n.</em> a desire to help people who are suffering</p>
<p><strong>(cool,) calm and collected </strong><em>–adj.</em><em> (idiomatic) </em>to be at ease and thoughtful</p>
<p><strong>grief </strong><em>–n.</em> severe sadness usually because of a bad or difficult event</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Tech Tip: How to Protect Communications through Encryption  (2024/12/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/tech-tip-how-to-protect-communications-through-encryption.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>U.S. cybersecurity officials are advising people to use <strong>encryption</strong> in their communications after a major <strong>hacking</strong> campaign.</p>
<p>Federal officials released a list of security suggestions for U.S. telecommunications companies that were targeted.</p>
<p>The advice includes one suggestion that everyone can use: “Ensure that traffic is end-to-end encrypted to the maximum <strong>extent </strong>possible.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - An attendee at the Microsoft Ignite conference records an address on Nov. 19, 2024, in Chicago. (AP Photo/Charles Rex Arbogast, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/5ab9677b-ca52-4218-b328-45e322bc50da_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - An attendee at the Microsoft Ignite conference records an address on Nov. 19, 2024, in Chicago. (AP Photo/Charles Rex Arbogast, File)</span></div>
<p>End-to-end encryption, also known as E2EE, means that messages are protected so that only the sender and receiver can see them. If anyone else gets the message, all they will see is disordered information that cannot be understood without the <strong>key</strong>.</p>
<p>Law enforcement officials had until now resisted encryption. This resistance is because the encryption means the technology companies themselves will not be able to look at the messages. In addition, the companies will not be able to respond to law enforcement requests to turn the data over.</p>
<p>The Associated Press (AP) recently offered some ways that normal people can use for end-to-end encryption :</p>
<p><strong>Texting </strong></p>
<p>Officials said the hackers targeted the <strong>metadata</strong> of a large number of people. That included information on the dates, times and <strong>recipients </strong>of calls and <strong>texts</strong>. The hackers also got to see the information from texts from a much smaller number of people.</p>
<p>If you are an iPhone user, information in text messages that you send to someone else who also has an iPhone will be encrypted end-to-end. Look for the blue text bubbles which mean that the messages are encrypted iMessages.</p>
<p>The same goes for Android users sending texts through Google Messages. There will be a lock next to the timestamp on each message to show that the encryption is on.</p>
<p>But there is a weakness. When iPhone and Android users text each other, the messages are encrypted only using Rich Communication Services (RCS). That is a common method for messaging that has replaced the older SMS and MMS methods.</p>
<p>Apple notes that RCS messages “aren't end-to-end encrypted, which means they're not protected from a third party reading them while they're sent between devices.”</p>
<p>Samsung, which sells Android smartphones, also indirectly described the issue in a small area at the bottom of a press release last month. Samsung said about RCS, “Encryption only available for Android-to-Android communication.”</p>
<p><strong>Chat apps </strong></p>
<p>To avoid getting caught out when exchanging texts, experts recommend using encrypted messaging <strong>apps</strong>.</p>
<p>Privacy supporters are big fans of Signal, which uses end-to-end encryption on all messages and voice calls. Signal is an app that is run by an independent nonprofit group based in Mountainview, California. It promises never to sell customer data. The group has also made its source code publicly available so that it can be examined by anyone “for security and correctness.”</p>
<p>Signal's encryption method is so respected that it has been included into competitor WhatsApp.</p>
<p>End-to-end encryption is also the normal mode for Facebook Messenger, which like WhatsApp is owned by Meta Platforms.</p>
<p><strong>What about Telegram? </strong></p>
<p>Telegram is an app that can be used for one-on-one discussions, group chats and broadcast “channels.” But Telegram does not use end-to-end encryption normally. Users have to turn on end-to-end encryption. And Telegram's end-to-end encryption does not work with group chats.</p>
<p>Cybersecurity experts have warned people against using Telegram for private communications.</p>
<p><strong>Making calls </strong></p>
<p>Instead of using your phone to make calls through a wireless cellular network, you can make voice calls with Signal and WhatsApp. Both apps encrypt calls with the same technology that they use to encrypt messages.</p>
<p>There are other choices. If you have an iPhone, you can use Facetime for calls, while Android owners can use the Google Fi service. Both are end-to-end encrypted.</p>
<p>However, with all these choices, the person on the other end will also have to have the app.</p>
<p>WhatsApp and Signal users can choose the privacy setting they want in the settings. Such choices include hiding an IP address during calls to prevent your general location from being guessed.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Kelvin Chan reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>encryption</strong><em> – n.</em> changing something (such as data) into a code</p>
<p><strong>hack </strong><em>– v.</em> to gain illegal access to a computer network, computer system, phone, etc.</p>
<p><strong>extent</strong> <em>– n.</em> a degree, point, or limit to which something goes to</p>
<p><strong>key</strong><em> –n.</em> information that permits a computer application to un-encrypt a message permitting the receiver to read it</p>
<p><strong>metadata</strong> <em>-- n.</em> data that gives information about other data</p>
<p><strong>recipient</strong> <em>– n.</em> someone who receives something</p>
<p><strong>text (message)</strong> <em>–n.</em> a short message sent through a computer program from one person to another which can contain a written message, links or pictures</p>
<p><strong>app (application)<em> </em></strong><em>–n.</em> a computer program that is designed to do one task or several linked tasks</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Winter Work for the Gardeners  (2024/12/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/winter-work-for-the-gardeners.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>For people in parts of the world with seasons — especially cold ones — winter might seem like a time to rest and to take a break from <strong>garden</strong> work.</p>
<p>But it is not, says Associated Press gardening expert Jessica Damiano.</p>
<p>Autumn and winter are the best times to attend to your garden's needs and prepare for the next growing season. There is much to do for both outdoor and indoor plants.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This Dec. 5, 2024, image provided by Jessica Damiano shows a thick layer of fallen leaves serving as mulch to protect spring bulbs planted in a Long Island, New York, garden bed. (Jessica Damiano via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/0043f07c-2958-42c0-b929-da9acf869f82_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This Dec. 5, 2024, image provided by Jessica Damiano shows a thick layer of fallen leaves serving as mulch to protect spring bulbs planted in a Long Island, New York, garden bed. (Jessica Damiano via AP)</span></div>
<p><strong>Outdoor care</strong></p>
<p>For people who want flowers like tulips in the early spring plant the <strong>bulbs</strong> that produce them if your soil is not frozen. If you can still dig, plant tulips, daffodils and other bulbs.</p>
<p>Cover them with about eight centimeters of <strong>mulch</strong>, leaves or dried grass. This will prevent freezing and melting temperatures from forcing them out of the ground over the winter.</p>
<p>During winter months, even in more temperate areas, some plants need protection from the cold. These include some fruit trees, like citrus, dahlias and many plants that <strong>bloom</strong> in the spring. In winter conditions, a cloth cover called burlap can help limit the damaging effects of wind.</p>
<p>If snow builds up on the branches of evergreen trees and shrubs, remove it. The heavy weight can damage branches.</p>
<p>Keep a record of plants you mean to move from one place to another in your garden. The notes will guide you in early spring: a time that is best to move plants that bloom early in the season.</p>
<p>if you have extra seeds, consider trading them with gardening friends or at a gardening event. Store and organize seeds for the future in glass containers in cool places without light. Make sure to write down what they are and when they were collected.</p>
<p>If insects or diseases were a problem during the growing season, use winter months to read about <strong>companion</strong> plants that can ease the problem in the coming year.</p>
<p><strong>Indoor care</strong></p>
<p>The cold winter months also affect houseplants. Bring houseplants near a south-facing or west-facing window to get the most sunlight possible. Turn the houseplants about one fourth of a turn each time you water them. This will support more even growth.</p>
<p>If you are buying poinsettias for the holidays, be sure to examine them for whiteflies before bringing them home. If you do not, you could bring home insects.</p>
<p>If you plant Amaryllis bulbs indoors now, they will bloom during the coldest months of the winter. Plant them with their pointed ends reaching out of the potting soil and place them in a warm, sunny spot, watering them well.</p>
<p>After they bloom, keep them in a cooler place to extend the life of their flowers but keep them away from children and pets. Amaryllis bulbs are poisonous to eat.</p>
<p><strong>Remember the birds</strong></p>
<p>Damiano also advises to remember that non-migrating birds need food because most of their food sources are gone during the winter months. High quality birdseed and water can help.</p>
<p>These same birds will repay the effort by feeding on thousands of insects that threaten your garden during the warm growing season.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Jessica Damiano reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>garden</strong><strong> </strong>–n. an area where trees and plants grow in a way designed by a gardener to produce flowers and small crops for food</p>
<p><strong>bulb</strong> <em>–n. </em>a round piece of plant tissue that becomes a flowing plant when grown in the ground</p>
<p><strong>bloom</strong> <em>–n. </em>the flowering state</p>
<p><strong>mulch</strong> <em>–n.</em> broken down plant material such as leaves and bark that is put on the ground to enrich the soil and protect existing plants</p>
<p><strong>delicate</strong><strong> </strong>–adj. very fine and sensitive to difficult conditions</p>
<p><strong>companion</strong><strong> </strong>–n. someone or something that goes well with another</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Youth Church Orchestra Aims to Help Musicians of Color  (2024/12/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/youth-church-orchestra-aims-to-help-musicians-of-color.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>For more than two years, Ebonie Vazquez searched to find a music teacher of color for her son, Giovanni. He is 11 years old and loves to play the violin. Now, she has found that teacher at New Hope Presbyterian Church, a Christian religious center, near Los Angeles, California.</p>
<p>Chineta Goodjoin, a Black <strong>pastor, </strong>leads New Hope. She started a string orchestra at the church in April to help children of color have a better chance to learn classical music.</p>
<p>Goodjoin and the orchestra's leaders think it is important for the music teachers to look like their students and share similar life experiences. That is why the orchestra's director, Charles Dickerson and all its music teachers are people of color.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Giovanni Vazquez plays the violin during a string orchestra rehearsal at New Hope Presbyterian Church on Wednesday, Oct. 16, 2024, in Anaheim, California. (AP Photo/William Liang)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/dcb9f483-89e9-4534-b7ba-c39840f9051d_cx13_cy0_cw83_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Giovanni Vazquez plays the violin during a string orchestra rehearsal at New Hope Presbyterian Church on Wednesday, Oct. 16, 2024, in Anaheim, California. (AP Photo/William Liang)</span></div>
<p>Dickerson is also the director of the Inner City Youth Orchestra of Los Angeles, which he founded in 2009. After Goodjoin's daughter Nyla began playing in that orchestra, Goodjoin decided to build a similar group at her church.</p>
<p>The church's orchestra now has about 18 members, aged nine to 20. They play the violin, viola, bass and cello. The orchestra accepts all students who want to join.</p>
<p>Ebonie Vazquez says having teachers of color has helped the orchestra members feel like they fit in well.</p>
<p>“It's important they don't feel like <strong>outsiders</strong>, but are supported and feel like they belong,” she said. “It has definitely helped my son connect more to the music and the <strong>craft</strong>.”</p>
<p>Her son Giovanni said that in the church orchestra, he could play classical music or popular modern music. He values being part of the church orchestra because “it's a piece of our community.”</p>
<p>“They <strong>encourage</strong> young musicians of color and everyone gets a chance to play and maybe use it as <strong>a stepping stone</strong> to get better or even turn this into a career,” he said.</p>
<p>Elizabeth Moulthrop is executive director of El Sistema, an international network of music education programs that was founded in Venezuela.</p>
<p>She said programs like the church orchestra can help students go to life-changing summer music camps, receive college scholarships, and find connections to jobs.</p>
<p>Goodjoin said she and her husband, Reggie Goodjoin, see a future for the orchestra where “African American kids play classical music and play it well.” Reggie Goodjoin is a jazz musician and the church's music director.</p>
<p>The group plays a mix of both classical and popular music. “I like to say they play everything from Bach to Beyonce,” added Goodjoin. They also learn music by famous African American jazz composers such as Count Basie and Duke Ellington.</p>
<p>Goodjoin said she believes the church is a great place to start talking about fairness<strong> </strong>in music. “Music is freedom,” Goodjoin added.</p>
<p>The pastor is already getting praise from parents. One boy who plays the upright bass was about to quit playing because no one in his school orchestra looked like him.</p>
<p>“His mom said that when he came here, the pressure to play and compete was taken off and that it's a <strong>delight</strong> to now watch her son light up feeling a sense of worthiness,” she said.</p>
<p>Dickerson said he started the Los Angeles orchestra when a group of students told him they wanted to play closer to where they live.</p>
<p>“They would have to drive long distances to be in these orchestras where they didn't know the other kids,” he said. “The young kids from our communities were always put in the back row and the back row was right next to the door.”</p>
<p>“It's easy to walk out that door,” he added, “when you don't really feel accepted and when you know you're probably not as skilled as the others.” He added that those other students usually had more music lessons and started playing at a younger age.</p>
<p>Dickerson said the Black Church has at times been the only place the African American community could organize services they needed, such as banks and newspapers.</p>
<p>“If we can come together in the church and create a symphonic orchestra, all I can say is all praise to God,” he added.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith. And I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Deepa Bharath wrote this story for The Associated Press. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>_________________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>pastor </strong><em>-n. </em>a leader of a church</p>
<p><strong>outsider </strong><em>-n. </em>a person who does not belong to a particular group</p>
<p><strong>craft </strong><em>-n. </em>an activity that involves doing something skillfully</p>
<p><strong>encourage</strong><em> -v. </em>to help people want to do things</p>
<p><strong>a stepping stone </strong><em>-noun phrase -- </em>an experience that can help you make progress, especially in your career</p>
<p><strong>delight </strong><em>-n. </em>something that brings happiness</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Geothermal Development Faces Barriers in Southeast Asia  (2024/12/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/geothermal-development-faces-barriers-in-southeast-asia.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Indonesia and the Philippines aim to increase their use of geothermal energy to move away from highly polluting fossil fuels.</p>
<p>However, money issues, governmental rules, and community protests have slowed the growth of geothermal energy production.</p>
<p>Geothermal energy uses heat from underground <strong>reservoirs</strong> of hot water to produce electricity. Environmental experts see geothermal as a good source of clean energy because it can provide power 24 hours a day. Geothermal power plants also require little <strong>maintenance</strong> and can last for many years.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Cars drive on a road as steam rises from a geothermal power plant in Dieng, Central Java, Indonesia, Nov. 15, 2024. (AP Photo/Beawiharta)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/86617547-029e-4e25-ac87-d4342ea88fa7_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Cars drive on a road as steam rises from a geothermal power plant in Dieng, Central Java, Indonesia, Nov. 15, 2024. (AP Photo/Beawiharta)
</span></div>
<p>Countries with high geothermal possibilities — such as the United States, Indonesia and the Philippines — have areas where volcanic activity naturally carries hot water or steam to the Earth's surface. The hot water or steam can also be reached by <strong>drilling</strong> into the ground.</p>
<p>Marit Brommer is head of the International Geothermal Association based in Germany. She told The Associated Press, “We're essentially standing on our own sun, which we can get clean, reliable energy from.”</p>
<p><strong>Geothermal energy in Southeast Asia</strong></p>
<p>In Southeast Asia, geothermal energy production is expected to increase ten times greater from 2020 to 2050, reaching 276 million megawatt-hours, the International Energy Agency says.</p>
<p>After the U.S., Indonesia and the Philippines are the second and third-largest users of geothermal energy in the world.</p>
<p>Still, Indonesia uses less than one-tenth of its large reserves of geothermal energy. Six percent of the country's power supply comes from geothermal sources.</p>
<p>And the Philippines has only developed about eight percent of its geothermal resources. It makes up 14.6 percent of the country's energy use.</p>
<p>Both countries plan to expand their production of geothermal energy. Indonesia aims to increase geothermal production by at least 8 percent by 2030. The Philippine government is targeting several projects to increase geothermal <strong>capacity</strong> by nearly 1.5 gigawatts, nearly doubling its current use.</p>
<p><strong>Facing difficulties</strong></p>
<p>However, developing new geothermal projects is costly and sometimes risky for companies when they test and drill to look for reservoirs. That makes it hard to get money for development, said Shigeru Yamamura. He is an energy specialist at the Asia Development Bank.</p>
<p>“That's the most difficult part of developers, because (in terms of money) they cannot take 100 percent of the exploration risk themselves,” Yamamura said.</p>
<p>The Philippine government has announced plans to <strong>auction</strong> for developing geothermal projects. The government is also preparing a “smart green <strong>grid</strong> plan” that centers on renewable energy. The plans may make it more likely that banks will give loans to private companies seeking to develop geothermal projects.</p>
<p>The Indonesian Ministry of Energy and Mineral Resources says it is working to shorten the wait time to get permits for new geothermal projects. It is also considering ways to increase the amount of money companies could make from the projects.</p>
<p>The World Bank is providing a $150 million loan to increase Indonesian investments in geothermal energy. And the Green Climate Fund and the Clean Technology Fund are providing $127.5 million.</p>
<p>Still, community pushback can slow development even when there is enough money.</p>
<p>In Indonesia, villagers have protested geothermal projects. They say the projects are not safe and can harm the environment. Several geothermal projects in Indonesia have had deadly gas leaks in the past five years.</p>
<p>In the Philippines, protests have led at least one company to pay money to <strong>Indigenous</strong> groups for the use of their lands.</p>
<p>Brommer, of the International Geothermal Association, thinks governments and businesses should work with nearby communities.</p>
<p>“We need to show that this development benefits all people, not just a company,” she said. “It's not about being a good neighbor; it's about being the best neighbor and really working with communities to respect their concerns.”</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith. </p>
<p>And I'm Jill Robbins. </p>
<p><em>Vitoria Milko wrote this story for The Associated Press. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>reservoir </strong><em>-n. </em>a large natural or manmade lake used as a source of water supply</p>
<p><strong>maintenance </strong><em>-n. </em>the act of keeping property or equipment in good condition by making repairs</p>
<p><strong>drill </strong><em>-v. </em>to make a hole in the ground or some other surface</p>
<p><strong>capacity </strong><em>-n. </em>the largest amount or number something can hold</p>
<p><strong>auction </strong><em>-v. </em>to make a public sale where something is sold to the person or group that offers the highest price</p>
<p><strong>grid </strong><em>-n. </em>the physical system that delivers electricity in a country</p>
<p><strong>Indigenous </strong><em>-adj. </em>native to an area; groups of people who are descended from the first people to ever live in an area or country</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Spanish Scrabble Winner Does Not Speak Spanish  (2024/12/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/spanish-scrabble-winner-does-not-speak-spanish.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A New Zealand man recently won an international Spanish Scrabble competition although he does not speak Spanish.</p>
<p>Scrabble is a board game in which players form words from letters to gain points.</p>
<p>Nigel Richards is a professional Scrabble player. He holds five English-language world championships in the board game. But in November, he won the Spanish world Scrabble championship in Granada, Spain. In the competition, he lost one game out of 24.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - National SCRABBLE Champion Nigel Richards spells F-O-V-E-A-E (a part of the eye) in the final game of the competition at the Royal Pacific Resort in Orlando, Florida, on July 29, 2008. (Joe Kaleita/AP Images/SCRABBLE)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/cdd950c3-f6b2-49ed-946f-c4f62faa8003_cx1_cy3_cw93_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - National SCRABBLE Champion Nigel Richards spells F-O-V-E-A-E (a part of the eye) in the final game of the competition at the Royal Pacific Resort in Orlando, Florida, on July 29, 2008. (Joe Kaleita/AP Images/SCRABBLE)</span></div>
<p>Many people are wondering how Richards could win without speaking Spanish.</p>
<p>Liz Fagerlund is a New Zealand Scrabble official and a friend of Richards. She recently told the Associated Press that Richards started memorizing the Spanish language Scrabble word list one year ago.</p>
<p>She said, “He can't understand why other people can't just do the same thing.” Fagerlund added, “He can look at a <strong>block</strong> of words together, and once they go into his brain as a picture he can just <strong>recall</strong> that very easily.”</p>
<p>In second place was defending champion Benjamín Olaizola of Argentina. He won 18 of his games.</p>
<p>Nothing like the New Zealander's win had ever happened in Spanish Scrabble, said Alejandro Terenzani, an organizer of the competition.</p>
<p>“It was impossible to react <strong>negatively</strong>, you can only be <strong>amazed</strong>,” Terenzani said. “We certainly expected that he would perform well, but it is perhaps true that he <strong>surpassed </strong>our expectations.”</p>
<p>However, the recent Scrabble competition is not the first that Richards has won in a language that he does not speak.</p>
<p>In 2015, he became the French language Scrabble world champion although he does not speak French. He studied the French language word list for nine weeks. He won the French championship again in 2018.</p>
<p>Richards is known in the world of international Scrabble as the greatest player of all time. He has been playing in competitions for about 30 years. But other players have said his Spanish language victory was notable even by his <strong>standards</strong>.</p>
<p>Playing Spanish Scrabble required some different methods to win. The wooden pieces, or tiles, used in the word game have different values in English and Spanish Scrabble. Richards also had to consider thousands of additional seven-, eight- and nine-letter words in the Spanish language.</p>
<p>In 2008, Richards was the first player ever to hold the world, U.S., and British titles at the same time. He had to “forget” 40,000 English words that do not appear in the American Scrabble word list to win in the U.S.</p>
<p>His victories are famous in the Scrabble community. Tens of thousands of people have watched and <strong>analyzed</strong> his games in YouTube videos.</p>
<p>Scrabble does not require players to know the definitions of words. Players only need to know what combinations of letters can be used in a country's version of the game.</p>
<p>Native speakers have “a huge <strong>leg up</strong>,” American Scrabble player Will Anderson said in a video explaining Richards' Spanish win.</p>
<p>In 2010, Richards' mother, Adrienne Fischer, told a New Zealand newspaper that he was not a great English student in school. He never attended university. And he took a mathematical approach to the game rather than a <strong>linguistic</strong> one.</p>
<p>“I don't think he's ever read a book,” she said, “apart from the dictionary.”</p>
<p>Fagerlund said Richards <strong>impressed</strong> her when he arrived at his first Scrabble club meeting at age 28. Two years later, in 1997, he rode a bicycle 350 kilometers from Christchurch to the city of Dunedin where he won the New Zealand championship on his first try. Then he rode the bicycle home again.</p>
<p>At the Spanish event, he was <strong>shy</strong> and <strong>modest</strong>, organizer Terenzani said. But he happily had his picture taken and spoke with fans who sought him out.</p>
<p>“Although he did so in English, of course,” Terenzani joked.</p>
<p>Richards now lives in Malaysia. He never speaks to reporters. What drives him is a mystery.</p>
<p>“I get lots of requests from journalists wanting to interview him, and he's not interested,” Fagerlund said.</p>
<p>She added that he does not understand what all the <strong>fuss</strong> is about.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Charlotte Graham-Mclay reported this story for the Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>________________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>block</strong> <em>–n.</em> a group or a set of something</p>
<p><strong>recall </strong><em>–v.</em> to remember</p>
<p><strong>negatively </strong><em>–adv.</em> in a bad, unhelpful or unhappy way</p>
<p><strong>amazed </strong><em>–adj.</em> to be filled with wonder or admiration</p>
<p><strong>surpass </strong><em>–v.</em> to go beyond something</p>
<p><strong>standards </strong><em>–n. (pl.)</em> a level of expectations involving several qualities or conditions</p>
<p><strong>linguistic</strong> <em>–adj.</em> related to languages</p>
<p><strong>leg up </strong><em>–idiom</em> something that helps a person do better at something than other people</p>
<p><strong>impressed</strong> <em>–adj.</em> causing a person to remember something about you</p>
<p><strong>shy </strong><em>–adj.</em> unwilling or afraid to talk to other people for some reason</p>
<p><strong>modest </strong><em>–adj.</em> unwilling to bring attention to oneself or to show excessive concern for one's appearance</p>
<p><strong>fuss </strong><em>–n. </em>a show of too much praise or interest that might not seem real or honest</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>In Uganda, Cost of Attending School Keeps Children Home  (2024/12/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/in-uganda-cost-of-attending-school-keeps-children-home.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The World Bank said last year that 54 percent of adults in Africa south of the Sahara Desert ranked the issue of paying school costs higher than medical or other costs.</p>
<p>The aid organization said school fees were the biggest financial worry for 40 percent of people in Uganda. In that country, a top government-supported school reportedly costs $700 for a three-month term. That is a lot of money in a country where yearly economic activity per person was $864 in 2023.</p>
<p>World Bank information shows that African countries in the area also have the highest rates of children out of school in the world. Parents in Uganda report unpredictable increases in the cost of attending school, or tuition, as a cause of tension. Some critics are calling for laws to protect parents from exploitation.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A teacher gives a lesson to his students at Wampewo Ntakke Secondary School in Kawempe tula village, Kampala, Uganda on Nov. 4, 2024. (AP Photo/Hajarah Nalwadda)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/cce01551-1243-4617-aa6c-dd120d6db408_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A teacher gives a lesson to his students at Wampewo Ntakke Secondary School in Kawempe tula village, Kampala, Uganda on Nov. 4, 2024. (AP Photo/Hajarah Nalwadda)</span></div>
<p>The Equal Opportunities Commission is a government agency that reports on the issues of inequality and discrimination. It released a report in September that called for punishment against government-supported schools that demand fees that are too high. It warned that <strong>arbitrarily</strong> raising fees can force children to drop out of school.</p>
<p>The Uganda Bureau of Statistics says that children's attendance in early grades is about 68 percent. But the percentage falls to 22 percent for secondary school. The main reason given is financial difficulty.</p>
<p>Uganda has a program of secondary education for all students. It was introduced in 2007. However, schools are not in good condition. The schools usually do not require <strong>tuition</strong>, but parents must pay for <strong>uniforms</strong>, textbooks and other costs.</p>
<p>Private schools are more popular but also more costly. Spokesperson for the Ministry of Education Dennis Mugimba said the government is not interested in making rules about prices. Mugimba said setting private school <strong>fees</strong> is “purely administrative and it is <strong>adjusted</strong> according to the business environment.” But he said costs linked to “capital development” should not be the responsibility of parents.</p>
<p>The number of private schools across Uganda has increased. The Associated Press (AP) reports that they are now a majority of the country's schools. But some people with ties to education say placing importance on the profitability of education as a business is worrying.</p>
<p>Fagil Mandy is a former inspector of schools. Mandy said there should be standardized rules to make school fees predictable for everyone.</p>
<p>It is normal for both private and government-supported schools to request money for many projects. These can include buying a bus or purchasing laboratory equipment.</p>
<p><strong>One student's story</strong></p>
<p>Shalom Mirembe is a student who spoke to the AP. Her mother takes care of four children. Her father recently died.</p>
<p>The school Mirembe attends near Kampala costs $300 per term. But her mother sends Mirembe to school without paying. She is depending on the <strong>mercy</strong> of officials.</p>
<p>But Joanita Seguya, a teacher at Wampewo Ntakke Secondary, said schools are taking measures to bar students from school if their parents do not pay. Seguya said of the school's 2100 students, 400 are from families that struggle to pay fees.</p>
<p>Twenty-year-old Mirembe is taking her final exams this year. At one point, school officials were going to bar her from school because her mother had failed to pay the fees. But when school administrators found out that her father had died recently, they permitted her to return. Some of her teachers attended the funeral.</p>
<p>But other families are not so fortunate.</p>
<p>Moses Serikomawa is jobless with seven children. He said paying $200 in school fees each term is too much when the family lacks food sometimes. But he added, “The children still want to go back to school.”</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Rodney Muhumuza reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>arbitrarily</strong><strong> </strong><em>–adj.</em> not based on a plan or for a specific or good reason</p>
<p><strong>tuition</strong> <em>–n. </em>the stated cost of attending a school or education program</p>
<p><strong>uniform</strong> <em>–n.</em> identical clothing that is worn by people in some professions or by students at certain schools</p>
<p><strong>fee</strong><strong> </strong><em>–n.</em> an amount that must be paid sometimes in addition to other costs</p>
<p><strong>adjust</strong><strong> </strong><em>–v.</em> to change a value or a piece of equipment so that it is correct or is enough</p>
<p><strong>mercy </strong><em>–n.</em> willingness to forgive or to do something because it appears to be kind or good</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>NASA’s James Webb Confirms Continued Expansion of the Universe  (2024/12/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/nasa-s-james-webb-confirms-continued-expansion-of-the-universe.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Data collected by the James Webb Space Telescope has confirmed earlier information suggesting the universe is expanding at a faster rate than scientists had expected.</p>
<p>The new finding is based on measurements collected by the Webb over the past two years. The telescope is operated by the American space agency NASA.</p>
<p>Researchers say the new readings show that our universe is growing faster today than it did in the period after it first formed billions of years ago. The data suggests the distances between nearby stars and galaxies are increasing. This confirms earlier studies based on data collected by other telescopes.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Spiral galaxy NGC 628, located 32 million light-years away from Earth, is seen in an undated image from the James Webb Space Telescope. (NASA, ESA, CSA, STScI, Janice Lee (STScI), Thomas Williams (Oxford), and the PHANGS team/Handout via REUTERS)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/aefe56cf-bed5-4209-94cc-7479821e730e_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Spiral galaxy NGC 628, located 32 million light-years away from Earth, is seen in an undated image from the James Webb Space Telescope. (NASA, ESA, CSA, STScI, Janice Lee (STScI), Thomas Williams (Oxford), and the PHANGS team/Handout via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>The finding that today's universe is expanding faster than expected was first made in the 1990s by data gathered by NASA's Hubble Space Telescope. In 1998, data examinations led a group of scientists to first conclude that our universe is expanding at an ever-increasing rate.</p>
<p>That finding was based on studies of huge explosive events called supernovas. NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://spaceplace.nasa.gov/supernova/en/#:~:text=A%20supernova%20is%20the%20biggest,that%20humans%20have%20ever%20seen.">describes</a> a supernova as an “extremely bright, super-powerful explosion of a star.” A supernova takes place at the end of a star's life.</p>
<p>The 1990s research on supernovas and the universe's continued expansion resulted in three scientists winning the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/physics/2011/press-release/">2011 Nobel Prize in Physics</a>. One of the winners – Adam Riess of Johns Hopkins University in Maryland – was the lead writer of a study on the new data collected by the Webb telescope.</p>
<p>The study notes the idea of the universe expanding at an unexpected rate – and the mysterious reasons behind the growth – has long been known as <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/missions/webb/nasas-webb-hubble-telescopes-affirm-universes-expansion-rate-puzzle-persists/">Hubble Tension</a>. The Nobel winners were awarded the prize in part for showing evidence that Hubble Tension may be caused by forces they describe as “dark energy.”</p>
<p>NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/universe/dark-matter-dark-energy/">says</a> astronomers believe dark energy makes up about 68 percent of the universe, while dark matter makes up around 27 percent. But beyond that, very little is known about these two “dark” elements.</p>
<p>Riess – a professor of physics and astronomy – wrote about the new data produced by the Webb telescope observations. He said in a statement, "The <strong>discrepancy</strong> between the observed expansion rate of the universe and the predictions of the standard model suggests that our understanding of the universe may be incomplete."</p>
<p>Riess noted that data from both the Webb and Hubble instruments had confirmed the earlier findings linked to the Hubble Tension problem. He said the ongoing mysteries of how dark energy might affect faster universe expansion presents a major “<strong>challenge</strong>” for scientists. However, the new data also provides new possibilities “to learn more about our universe.”</p>
<p>The researchers used three different methods to measure a specific value – the distances from Earth to galaxies where a kind of <strong>pulsating</strong> star called a Cepheid had been identified.</p>
<p>The universe's expansion rate is measured in kilometers per second as megaparsecs, a distance equal to 3.26 million light-years. A light-year is the distance light travels in a year, about 9.5 trillion kilometers.</p>
<p>The researchers said the Webb's observations appear to rule out the idea that the earlier Hubble data might have returned false information because of possible instrument errors. The team's findings recently appeared <a class="wsw__a" href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ad8c21">in a study</a> in the publication <em>The Astrophysical Journal</em>.</p>
<p>Siyang Li is a doctoral student in astronomy at Johns Hopkins who was a co-writer of the study. He told Reuters news agency the Webb results could mean “there may be a need to <strong>revise</strong> our model of the universe.” However, Li added that such a revision would be very difficult to make currently with existing data.</p>
<p>Li also noted a great improvement in the Webb data compared to the older Hubble information. "The Webb data is like looking at the universe in <strong>high-definition</strong> for the first time and really improves the signal-to-noise of the measurements,” he said.</p>
<p>The researchers suggested more work is needed to possibly unlock the Hubble Tension mystery. Riess said more data observations will be necessary to learn about what forces are continuing to drive expansion of the universe. And the team will next try to capture more detailed data on the rate of expansion, as well as seek to establish timelines for the growth.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from Reuters, NASA and Johns Hopkins University. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>discrepancy</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a difference between two things that should be the same</p>
<p><strong>challenge </strong><em>– n.</em> something difficult that tests one's ability or determination</p>
<p><strong>pulsate</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to beat or move with a strong, regular rhythm</p>
<p><strong>revise</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to change something so that it is more correct</p>
<p><strong>high-definition</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj.</em> a system for showing very clear pictures on a television or computer screen</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Highly Effective HIV Drug to Be Offered at Low Cost to Poor Countries  (2024/12/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/highly-effective-hiv-drug-to-be-offered-at-low-cost-to-poor-countries.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A yearly two-shot treatment shown to be highly effective in preventing HIV infections is to be offered at low cost to people in 120 poor nations.</p>
<p>Experts have called the treatment the closest the world has ever come to developing a vaccine against HIV. HIV stands for human immunodeficiency virus. It is an infection that destroys cells of a person's <strong>immune</strong> <strong>system</strong> and makes it difficult for them to fight off diseases.</p>
<p>The HIV virus can progress to the related disease AIDS. The World Health Organization (WHO) <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.who.int/news-room/questions-and-answers/item/hiv-aids">explains</a> that AIDS is a term used to describe “the most <strong>advanced</strong> stages of HIV infection.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file image, a pharmacist holds a vial of lenacapavir, the new HIV prevention injectable drug, at a health research center in Cape Town, South Africa, Tuesday, July 23, 2024. (AP Photo/Nardus Engelbrecht, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/0694c119-3073-45b3-ac6a-ac94300ef2dc_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this file image, a pharmacist holds a vial of lenacapavir, the new HIV prevention injectable drug, at a health research center in Cape Town, South Africa, Tuesday, July 23, 2024. (AP Photo/Nardus Engelbrecht, File)</span></div>
<p>American-based drugmaker Gilead is the developer of the medication, called lenacapavir. The drug is already sold under the name Sunlenca to treat HIV infections in the U.S., Canada, Europe and elsewhere. But Gilead plans to seek approval soon for the medication to be used to prevent HIV infection.</p>
<p>Studies have shown the twice-yearly injection was 100 percent effective in preventing HIV infections in a study of women. And another recent study found the drug worked nearly as well in men.</p>
<p>Winnie Byanyima is the executive director of UNAIDS. She told The Associated Press that the shots had worked so well, she sees them as an “<strong>unprecedented</strong>” treatment. Byanyima praised Gilead for developing the drug. But she noted that the world's ability to stop HIV/AIDS also depends on its use in at-risk countries.</p>
<p>Gilead has said it plans to offer low-cost, <strong>generic</strong> versions of lenacapavir for sale in numerous poor countries with high HIV rates. These are mostly in Africa, Southeast Asia and the Caribbean.</p>
<p>However, the company does not plan on launching the drug in most of Latin America. HIV infection rates are far lower in Latin America than Gilead's targeted countries. But critics of the drug company's deployment plans say HIV in these countries is increasing. So several groups have called on Gilead to reconsider its plans to include sales in Latin America.</p>
<p>In a recent report, the United Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS, UNAIDS, noted the number of AIDS death last year — an estimated 630,000 — was the lowest since 2004, when AIDS deaths were at their highest. The organization suggested the decreasing numbers mean the world is now at “a historic <strong>crossroads</strong>,” with a chance to end the epidemic.</p>
<p>There are other methods to protect against HIV infection. These include <strong>condoms</strong>, daily pills and bi-monthly shots. But experts say the Gilead twice-yearly shots would be especially useful for underrepresented groups. These could include people fearful of seeking care, including <strong>gay</strong> men, sex workers and young women.</p>
<p>Byanyima told the AP, the treatment “would be a <strong>miracle</strong> for these groups because it means they just have to show up twice a year at a <strong>clinic</strong> and then they're protected.”</p>
<p>A collection of 15 activist groups – in Peru, Argentina, Ecuador, Chile, Guatemala and Colombia – recently wrote to Gilead to voice their concerns. They are asking for the generic version to be made available in Latin America. They say there is “alarming” <strong>inequity</strong> there in providing new HIV prevention tools with infection rates rising.</p>
<p>Countries including Norway, France, Spain and the U.S. have been paying more than $40,000 per year for Sunlenca. But experts have said it could be produced for as little as $40 a treatment once generic production expands.</p>
<p>In a statement, Gilead said it has “an ongoing commitment to help enable <strong>access</strong> to HIV prevention and treatment <strong>options</strong> where the need is the greatest.” Among the 120 countries approved for the generic version are 18 mostly African nations that make up about 70 percent of the world's HIV cases.</p>
<p>The drugmaker said it is also working to establish “fast, <strong>efficient </strong>pathways to reach all people who need or want lenacapavir for HIV prevention.”</p>
<p>Dr. Chris Beyrer is the director of the Global Health Institute at Duke University in North Carolina. He said it will be greatly useful to have the Gilead shots available in the hardest-hit countries in Africa and Asia. But he added that rising HIV rates among groups including gay men and <strong>transgender</strong> populations represents “a public health emergency” in Latin America.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>immune system</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> the cells and tissues in the body that fight against infection</p>
<p><strong>advanced </strong><em>– adj.</em> having developed to a late stage</p>
<p><strong>crossroads</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a time when you have to make an important decision that will affect your future life</p>
<p><strong>condom </strong><em>– n. </em>a thin rubber covering worn by a man to stop a woman from becoming pregnant</p>
<p><strong>gay</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj.</em> being attracted to others of the same sex</p>
<p><strong>miracle</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> something that is very surprising or difficult to believe</p>
<p><strong>clinic </strong><em>– n. </em>a place where people go to see doctors or receive medical treatment</p>
<p><strong>inequity </strong><em>– n.</em> the state of being unfair, or something that is unfair</p>
<p><strong>access</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> the ability to get or use something</p>
<p><strong>option </strong><em>– n. </em>a choice among things</p>
<p><strong>efficient</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj.</em> working well and not wasting time or energy</p>
<p><strong>transgender</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj.</em> used to describe someone whose gender does not match the body they were born with</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Mayans Ask Mexican Court to Recognize Lakes as Legal Persons  (2024/12/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/mayans-ask-mexican-court-to-recognize-lakes-as-legal-persons.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In the Mexican state of Yucatan, hundreds of underground lakes form a semicircular shape in the northwestern part of Yucatan state. They are called the Ring of Cenotes. The lakes provide water for the area, but they are also part of a dispute between local people and pig farmers.</p>
<p>The cenotes are also important to local people who earn a living by leading foreign visitors into the <strong>caverns</strong> to swim and explore.</p>
<p>Maribel Ek lives in the community of Homun, near the cenote known as Santa Maria. To native Mayans like Ek, cenotes are holy. She calls the Sant Maria cenote her "neighbor."</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Maribel Ek, guardian of the cenotes, rests inside the Santa Maria cenote, in Homun, Mexico, Monday, March 4, 2024. (AP Photo/Rodrigo Abd)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1955184f-5b8a-4a58-ae00-4127608fccdc_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Maribel Ek, guardian of the cenotes, rests inside the Santa Maria cenote, in Homun, Mexico, Monday, March 4, 2024. (AP Photo/Rodrigo Abd)</span></div>
<p>That belief is behind a legal action, or lawsuit, that aims to have the Ring of Cenotes legally recognized as a person. Personhood would give the lakes the same rights and protections of law that human citizens have.</p>
<p>A Mayan organization called Guardians of the Cenotes has brought the lawsuit. It aims to keep large pig farms out of the area because they are affecting the water quality of the underground lakes.</p>
<p>If the group wins, the lakes will become the first <strong>ecosystem</strong> in Mexico to be considered a person. There have been other such cases worldwide, such as the Whanganui River in New Zealand or the Komi Memem River in the Brazilian Amazon.</p>
<p>Ek is a member of the Guardians group.</p>
<p><strong>Polluting the waters</strong></p>
<p>The threats to cenotes have been growing. Cities in Yucatan are growing and there are new <strong>breweries</strong> and soybean fields in the area. But what most worries the Guardians of the Cenotes are the pig farms.</p>
<p>Mexico's Ministry of the Environment reports that 507 pig farms are operating near the Ring of Cenotes. There is little to no control over what happens to the thousands of liters of water containing pig waste from the farms.</p>
<p>Yameli Aguilar is a biologist from the Autonomous University of Yucatan. He said the polluted water goes into the <strong>aquifer</strong>.</p>
<p>A study carried out last year by the Ministry of the Environment found E. coli bacteria in 20 cenotes near pig farms.</p>
<p>The state has named the land a natural protected area, and it is an important wetland. Lourdes Medina is a lawyer who represents the Guardians in the legal case. She said the government still has failed to prevent “serious <strong>contamination</strong>” from taking place.</p>
<p>Ek and others created the Guardians of the Cenotes group to lead the fight against one pig farm built near Homun in 2017. They organized protests and legal actions without any effect. A year later, six children from Homun brought a case demanding their right to water and a healthy environment. A judge ordered the farm closed.</p>
<p>In 2022, the group began its personhood legal action. If successful, it would affect 52 communities within the Ring of Cenotes. A Yucatan state judge has ordered officials not to give permission to any project that could affect the area until the lawsuit is settled.</p>
<p>That could happen at the beginning of next year.</p>
<p><strong>What do the pig farmers say?</strong></p>
<p>Pig farms and other large industries come to the area because of the availability of water. The farms use a lot of water to cool the animals and clean their waste.</p>
<p>The industry says it is not causing the contamination. Carlos Ramayo Navarrete is director of the Pig Farmers Association in Merida. It represents the largest pig farms in Yucatan. He said the problem comes from a lack of <strong>drainage</strong> systems in cities and small pig farmers. Navarrete said small pig farms are not as officially <strong>regulated</strong> as the big farms he represents.</p>
<p>He said around half the water the farms use is reused. In addition, he said all of the farms have treatment systems to reduce pollution in their wastewater. The remaining water is then used as fertilizer.</p>
<p>However, both the Ministry of the Environment and Aguilar, the biologist, have said that the measures taken by the industry are still not enough.</p>
<p><strong>What will the future bring?</strong></p>
<p>Back in Homun, Maribel Ek enjoys swimming in the waters of the cenote. She said that she has learned the cenote is "a blessing, a dark hole that becomes a friend," and she added "That's why we demand rights for our cenotes."</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Teresa de Miguel reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>cavern</strong> – <em>n</em>. a large cave</p>
<p><strong>ecosystem</strong> – <em>n</em>. everything that exists in a particular environment</p>
<p><strong>brewery</strong> – <em>n</em>. a company that makes beer</p>
<p><strong>aquifer </strong>- <em>n</em>. a layer of rock or sand that holds a lot of water</p>
<p><strong>contamination </strong>–n. when a substance, like pollution, gets into places where it is not supposed to be</p>
<p><strong>drainage </strong><em>–n. </em>related to systems that carry rain or wastewater away from streets and buildings</p>
<p><strong>regulate</strong> – <em>v.</em> to make rules or laws that control activities like business or travel</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Google Announces Solution to a Big Problem in Quantum Computing  (2024/12/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/google-announces-solution-to-a-big-problem-in-quantum-computing.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Google recently said that it had solved a major problem in supercomputing with a new generation of processor called Willow.</p>
<p>Along with other technology companies such as Microsoft and International Business Machines (IBM), Google, whose parent company is Alphabet, is working on <strong>quantum</strong> computing. The new development promises to increase computing speeds while limiting mistakes, or errors, which are a problem with quantum computing systems.</p>
<p>Scientists at the company's Santa Barbara, California quantum laboratory announced they had at least partly solved the error problem on December 9. On the same day, the scientific publication <em>Nature </em>published their paper on error correction.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A person shows Google Quantum AI's " by="" chip="" december="" handout="" in="" obtained="" on="" photo="" reuters="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/b9e503d9-3cc7-4766-8a3b-8507989df74c_w268_r1.jpg" this="" undated="" via="" willow=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A person shows Google Quantum AI's "Willow" chip, in this undated handout photo obtained by Reuters on December 6, 2024. (Handout via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>Google said that the Willow processor carried out a <strong>computation</strong> in under five minutes that would have taken a fast supercomputer longer than the current age of the universe to complete.</p>
<p>The work of the Google researchers, however, does not have any <strong>commercial</strong> uses yet. But Google hopes quantum computers will one day solve problems in medicine, battery chemistry and artificial intelligence (AI) that today's computers cannot solve.</p>
<p><strong>The Willow chip</strong></p>
<p>The Willow processor, or chip, runs on units of data called “quantum bits” or “qubits” for short. Qubits permit fast computing but can easily create errors. Google researchers have a theory that qubits might be affected by subatomic particles from events in space.</p>
<p>As more qubits are placed onto a chip, however, the errors can increase to make the chip no better than today's usual computer chips. As a result, scientists have been working on quantum error-correction since the 1990s.</p>
<p>Hartmut Neven, who leads Google's Quantum AI group, said that Willow has 105 qubits.</p>
<p>In the paper recently published in <em>Nature</em>, Google researchers said they have found a way to connect the Willow chip's qubits so that error rates go down as the number of qubits goes up. Neven also said Willow can correct errors in “real time.” That is an important step toward making quantum computers useful.</p>
<p>"We are past the break even point," Neven told Reuters. In a blog post, he said it was an unmistakable sign that “error correction is improving overall.”</p>
<p>In 2019, IBM challenged the claim that Google's quantum chip solved a problem that would take a normal computer 10,000 years to complete. IBM said the problem could be solved in two-and-a-half days using different <strong>assumptions</strong> about computer system design.</p>
<p>Google said in its blog post that it considered some of those concerns in its newest estimates. Even under the best conditions, Google said a computer of today would still take a billion years to get the same results as its latest chip.</p>
<p>Some of Google's competitors are producing chips with more qubits than Willow. But Anthony Megrant, who is also with Google Quantum AI, told Reuters that Google is trying to make the most dependable qubits possible.</p>
<p>Google produced its earlier chips in a shared building at the University of California, Santa Barbara. But for the Willow chips, Google built its own special laboratory. Megrant said that the new lab will speed up the process of making future chips.</p>
<p>One major problem is that quantum chips must be kept at low temperatures in machines that can produce extremely low temperatures called cryostats. The new laboratory permits the researchers to work more quickly.</p>
<p>"If we have a good idea, we want somebody on the team to be able to...get into that clean room and into one of these cryostats as fast as possible, so we can get lots of <strong>cycles</strong> of learning," Megrant said.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Stephen Nellis</em> <em>reported this story for Reuters news agency. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English with additional information from Google and Nature. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>quantum</strong> – <em>adj</em>. of, relating to, or using the principles of quantum theory</p>
<p><strong>computation </strong><em>–n</em>. an operation carried out by a computing device that is mathematical and digital in nature</p>
<p><strong>commercial </strong>–adj. related to business activity</p>
<p><strong>assumption </strong>–n. one of the basic conditions that is accepted in making a computation, but which might not exist in reality</p>
<p><strong>cycle </strong>– <em>n.</em> a repeating series of events or actions</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Europe Launches Mission to Create Simulated Solar Eclipse  (2024/12/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/europe-launches-mission-to-create-simulated-solar-eclipse.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Two European satellites were recently launched on a mission that will include a <strong>simulated</strong> total solar eclipse.</p>
<p>The European Space Agency (ESA) launched the satellites on December 5 from southern India aboard an Indian-built rocket.</p>
<p>ESA says its Proba-3 mission aims to demonstrate <strong>precision </strong>formation flying abilities as the two satellites travel together in a fixed position.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This artist illustration shows one of two satellites - part of the European Space Agency's Proba-3 mission - positioned for a simulated total solar eclipse.
(Image Credit: CREDIT - ESA-P. Carril, 2013)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a624d48f-1a3a-46c6-afe3-13cf2ebaee4f_cx0_cy11_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This artist illustration shows one of two satellites - part of the European Space Agency's Proba-3 mission - positioned for a simulated total solar eclipse.
(Image Credit: CREDIT - ESA-P. Carril, 2013)</span></div>
<p>The two satellites are set to separate and fly 150 meters apart in about a month when they reach their target area high above Earth.</p>
<p><strong>Creating simulated solar eclipse</strong></p>
<p>In one of the mission's major experiments, the two spacecraft will carry out a series of <strong>artificial</strong> total solar eclipses. A shadow created by one satellite will permit the other to observe sun activity while blocking out the sun itself.</p>
<p>The goal of this operation is to give scientists the chance to study the sun's outermost atmosphere, known as the corona. The corona is difficult to observe because of the brightness of the sun.</p>
<p>Scientists have repeatedly tried to study this part of the sun from observations on Earth during real total solar eclipses. But those eclipses do not happen often and usually only last up to five minutes. The Proba-3 team plans to carry out total eclipses at least twice a week, with each lasting up to six hours.</p>
<p>Scientists say repeated studies of the corona can help provide new information about how solar activity influences Earth. For example, the project could help scientists better understand why the corona is so much hotter than the sun itself, and how the sun's energy output changes over time.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p>Sometimes, intense solar activity can result in geomagnetic storms, which can cause difficulties for power and communication systems on Earth.</p>
<p>"For six hours at a time, it will be able to see the sun's <strong>faint </strong>atmosphere, the corona, in the hard-to-observe region between the sun's edge and 1.4 million kilometers from its surface," ESA said in a pre-launch statement.</p>
<p>Mission leaders say the eclipse experiments will require extreme precision – within just one millimeter – to effectively position the spacecraft. To keep their position, the satellites will depend on <strong>GPS</strong>, laser systems and radio links.</p>
<p>ESA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.esa.int/Enabling_Support/Space_Engineering_Technology/Proba-3/Proba-3_Flying_two_spacecraft_is_harder_than_one">said</a> in a statement, “Proba-3 is very different because our satellites will be flying just one-and-a-half football fields away from each other during active formation flying.”</p>
<p>Esther Bastida Pertegaz is a systems engineer on the Proba-3 mission. She said in a video, "The corona of the sun ... has been very poorly investigated. One of the things we really want to understand is ... how do coronal mass ejections or solar wind <strong>originate</strong> in this area."</p>
<p>The $210 million project is being supported by over 40 European companies, Reuters news agency reports. These include SENER Aerospace, Redwire Space, and Airbus Defence and Space.</p>
<p>ESA says Proba-3 will aim for at least 1,000 hours of “on demand” totality during its two-year operation. Once the mission is complete, both satellites will continually drop lower until they burn up in the atmosphere. Officials said that would likely happen within five years.</p>
<p>ESA has said other orbits of Proba-3 – besides the eclipse experiments – will be carried out to demonstrate a range of precise formation flying to help support future missions.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters and the European Space Agency. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>simulate</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to do or make something that behaves or looks like something real but is not</p>
<p><strong>precise </strong><em>– adj.</em> exact</p>
<p><strong>artificial</strong><strong> </strong><em>–</em> <em>adj. </em>something created by a machine and not a natural process</p>
<p><strong>faint</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj. </em>very light; hard to see</p>
<p><strong>GPS</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a system built to follow the movements of something with an electronically-powered piece of equipment</p>
<p><strong>originate</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> where something begins</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Oldest Pet Burial Ground in America Is Final Resting Place for Thousands  (2024/12/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/oldest-pet-burial-ground-in-america-is-final-resting-place-for-thousands.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>On most days, Mark Lindenberg either drives or walks over to visit with Boots, his beloved cat who died in 2020 at 17 years old. The New York man had the animal buried at the Hartsdale Pet Cemetery, a burial place on small grassy hills near the main road.</p>
<p>The words on Boots' <strong>tombstone</strong> read, “You taught me how to love and be loved.”</p>
<p>Other tombstones include <strong>phrases </strong>such as “A truer friend we never had” and “Our beloved queen.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="The pet cemetery was established in 1896, when veterinarian Samuel Johnson allowed a client to bury her dog in his apple orchard. (VOA)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/7f181b9a-2e80-41ef-b608-cb91367c2d76_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">The pet cemetery was established in 1896, when veterinarian Samuel Johnson allowed a client to bury her dog in his apple orchard. (VOA)</span></div>
<p>“Human cemeteries are sad,” Lindenberg said. “This is one of the most <strong>cheerful </strong>places.”</p>
<p>He added, “I can't think of a better place.”</p>
<p>Hartsdale is America's oldest pet cemetery in operation. It was added to the National Register of Historic Places in 2012. Lindenberg says he paid about $7,000 to bury Boots at Hartsdale. Those costs cover the individual site, burial, burial container, tombstone, and grounds<strong> </strong>care.</p>
<p>“What have I worked for if I'm not going to do the things that matter most, and this mattered most,” Lindenberg said. “I got <strong>instant</strong> closure the day I decided I was going to bury her here.”</p>
<p>Pet burials started in Hartsdale in 1896 when animal doctor Samuel Johnson let a woman bury her dog on his property of apple trees. The place is about 30 kilometers north of New York City.</p>
<p>Since that time, about 70,000 animals have been laid to rest in the two-hectare cemetery. Most of the pets buried at Hartsdale are cats and dogs, but several other kinds of animals are also there.</p>
<p>“There's reptiles that are buried here. Mice,” said Edward Martin III, vice president of the Hartsdale Pet Cemetery. “There's a lion <strong>cub</strong> that was buried here in 1912 by a Russian <strong>princess</strong>. There's the ashes of Ming, who's a Bengal tiger that was buried here a few years ago. There are some m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s.”</p>
<p>There is also Hudson the horse, some birds and singer Mariah Carey's cat, Clarence. The oldest headstone, dating to 1898, remembers the life of a dog named Blague.</p>
<p>Martin operates the place with his father Edward Martin Jr., who purchased the cemetery in 1974. The younger Martin is a lawyer and accountant who decided later in his career to help run the cemetery. He had worked there also as a teenager.</p>
<p>“I've seen what people go through, and they lose their pets, and I feel like I'm in a good position where I can help them,” he said. “And I have helped them, and it makes me want to continue helping them.”</p>
<p>Between 250 and 300 burials take place at Hartsdale each year. The cemetery never runs out of space because not all of the burial sites are permanent. People can make a one-time forever maintenance payment of $3,500 or a yearly payment of $105. If the yearly payments stop, that gravesite is offered for sale.</p>
<p>“The pet in the grave will be removed from that plot so someone else who wants it can pay the maintenance. And the pets are taken out, and they're <strong>cremated</strong>, and they don't leave the cemetery,” said Martin Jr., Hartsdale's president. “Their remains are scattered over the cemetery grass.”</p>
<p>A centerpiece at the cemetery is the war dog memorial at the top of a hill. Established in 1923, the memorial honored World War I service dogs. But these days, the memorial honors service dogs of all kinds.</p>
<p>Although Hartsdale is mostly a resting place for animals, the cremated remains of about 800 humans are buried here with their pets. There is a Martin family plot, where the elder Martin plans to be laid to rest when he dies.</p>
<p>“I have to be buried somewhere. And why would I go to any place other than this?” he said. “My mother and father, and my mother-in-law or father-in-law are buried here, and so, that's a good reason by itself to do it.”</p>
<p>Lindenberg also likes the idea. He has already prepared to be cremated and buried alongside Boots when the time comes.</p>
<p>“I'm single. I don't know if I'll ever get married, and I can't think of a better place,” he said. “I lived with my cat every day for almost 17 years. Why stop now?”</p>
<p>In the meantime, Lindenberg, who lives a 10-minute walk away, will continue to visit his old friend almost daily.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Dora Mekouar reported this story for VOA News. Caty Weaver adapted the story for Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"> </h2>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in this Story</h2>
<p><strong>tombstone </strong><em>– n.</em> a marker attached to an individual burial place</p>
<p><strong>cheerful </strong><em>– adj.</em> pleasantly bright</p>
<p><strong>instant </strong><em>– n</em>. produced or happening with, or as if with, extreme quickness and ease</p>
<p><strong>cub </strong><em>– n</em>. a kind of baby animal</p>
<p><strong>princess </strong><em>– n.</em> a daughter or granddaughter of a king or queen:<strong> </strong>a female member of a royal family</p>
<p><strong>cremate </strong><em>– v.</em> to burn (as a dead body) to ashes</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>For Words of the Year: Brat, Brain Rot, Polarization  (2024/12/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/for-words-of-the-year-brat-brain-rot-polarization.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/><span class="datetime">14 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From “brat” to “brain rot” and “polarization,” word experts agree that social media and politics have driven conversations that use these terms. Here are their <strong>selections</strong> for word of the year.</p>
<p><strong>Polarization</strong></p>
<p>The American dictionary publisher Merriam-Webster selected <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/wordplay/word-of-the-year">polarization</a> as its word of the year for 2024. The dictionary publisher defines <u>polarization</u> as “division into two sharply <strong>distinct</strong> opposites; especially, a state in which the opinions, beliefs, or interests of a group or society...become concentrated at opposing extremes.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This cover image released by Atlantic Records shows " ap="" brat="" by="" charli="" records="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/96a5ce05-f6b6-4cfe-81f7-76c6a8e8dbae_cx0_cy23_cw0_w268_r1.jpg" via="" xcx.=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This cover image released by Atlantic Records shows "brat" by Charli XCX. (Atlantic Records via AP)</span></div>
<p>As divided as Americans appear, Merriam-Webster says <u>polarization</u> “happens to be one idea that both sides of the political <strong>spectrum</strong> agree on.”</p>
<p>The word was widely used in news stories and broadcasts to describe the presidential election in the United States. Supporters of both candidates, president-elect Donald Trump and Vice President Kamala Harris, voiced the opinion that the opposing candidate was a threat to the nation.</p>
<p>The U.S. election also brought attention to two other words: <u>pander</u> and <u>weird</u>. Trump's supporters accused Harris of <u>pandering</u>, in other words, changing her policy positions to get votes. And Democratic vice-presidential candidate Tim Walz called his opponents <u>weird</u>, meaning strange or unusual.</p>
<p><strong>Brain rot</strong></p>
<p>The editors at Britain's Oxford University Press say usage of its word of the year selection, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://corp.oup.com/news/brain-rot-named-oxford-word-of-the-year-2024/">brain rot</a><u>,</u> increased by 230 percent from 2023 to 2024.</p>
<p>Oxford defines brain rot as “the supposed <strong>deterioration</strong> of a person's mental or intellectual state, especially viewed as the result of overconsumption of material (now particularly online content) considered to be trivial or unchallenging.”</p>
<p>The phrase likely first appeared in written form in Henry David Thoreau's 1854 book <em>Walden</em> about his experiences living a simple lifestyle. He wrote: “While England <strong>endeavors</strong> to cure the potato rot, will not any endeavor to cure the brain-rot – which prevails so much more widely and fatally?”</p>
<p>In 2024, the phrase has been used to describe concerns about the harm of overconsuming, or watching and reading too much, online material.</p>
<p>Casper Grathwohl, President of Oxford Languages, noted, “I find it fascinating that the term ‘brain rot' has been adopted by Gen Z and Gen Alpha, those communities largely responsible for the use and creation of the digital content the term refers to.”</p>
<p><strong>Brat</strong></p>
<p>Politics and social media come together in the Collins Dictionary's selection of <a class="wsw__a" href="https://blog.collinsdictionary.com/language-lovers/a-year-when-hedonism-and-anxiety-combine/">brat</a> as its word of the year.</p>
<p>The most recent usage of <u>brat</u> started as the title of an album by pop singer Charli XCX. Then it went <strong>viral</strong> as a campaign <strong>slogan</strong> “Kamala IS <u>Brat</u>” for the Democratic presidential candidate.</p>
<p>The word means different things to different people.</p>
<p>Traditionally, <u>brat</u> describes an immature person or an unruly child. But Collins says it is now used to describe a person with “confident, independent, and <strong>hedonistic attitude</strong>.”</p>
<p>Collins says the term <u>brat</u> “has clearly captured something of the spirit of the age.” And for a short time, the word <u>brat summer</u> even “established itself as an aesthetic and a way of life.”</p>
<p><strong>Demure</strong></p>
<p>The online Dictionary.com selected <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.dictionary.com/e/word-of-the-year-2024/">demure</a> as its word of the year for 2024. Between January and the end of August, Dictionary.com<em> </em>said the word “saw a nearly 1200 percent increase in usage in digital web media alone.”</p>
<p>The sharp rise is credited to several videos on TikTok by Jools Lebron. “You see how I do my makeup for work?” she asked. “Very <u>demure</u>, very mindful.”</p>
<p><u>Demure</u> is another example of how popular word usage changes over time. In the 14th century, <u>demure</u> was used to describe people who avoid bringing attention to themselves. Today, the word is used to describe someone who brings attention to themselves with “refined and <strong>sophisticated</strong> appearance or behavior.”</p>
<p>And those are the Words of the Year for 2024.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Hai Do wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>selection </strong><em>–n.</em> a choice that is made from several possibilities</p>
<p><strong>distinct </strong><em>–adj.</em> different in an observable way</p>
<p><strong>spectrum </strong><em>–n.</em> a complete set of small differences that can exist within one thing: for example, the spectrum of light or of popular opinion</p>
<p><strong>deterioration </strong><em>–n.</em> the condition of being broken down and becoming worse and less effective</p>
<p><strong>endeavor </strong><em>–v.</em> to try to do something with continuous effort</p>
<p><strong>viral </strong><em>–adj. (social media)</em> something that is seen many times and is considered popular</p>
<p><strong>slogan </strong><em>–n.</em> an easily remembered phrase that is meant to build support for something or someone</p>
<p><strong>hedonistic</strong> <em>–adj.</em> interested only in pleasure</p>
<p><strong>attitude </strong><em>–n. </em>a way of acting that shows the way one thinks</p>
<p><strong>sophisticated </strong><em>–adj.</em> knowledgeable in worldly matters; complex is a way that appeals to people with a certain kind of knowledge</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Chicken Little  (2024/12/14)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/american-stories-chicken-little.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/><span class="datetime">13 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now an American Children's Story from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Today's story probably had its start long before it was published in Europe long ago.</p>
<p>It might have first been known as “Henny Penny.” But the story has been told to American children at least since the mid-1800s under a title similar to “Chicken Little.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e9b8d234-737f-4e19-8c46-ee5932263831_w100_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>Generations have heard and thought about the lessons of the little chicken who causes big problems for a group of well-meaning but not-so-thoughtful birds.</p>
<p>Today's version is based on two examples of the story. One is called <em>Remarkable Story of Chicken Little</em>. John Green Chandler had it published in the city of Boston, Massachusetts in 1842. Katharine Pyle published her 1918 version in <em>Mother's Nursery Tales</em>.</p>
<p>The story has taken on its own American qualities and is a little like a parable, a story that teaches a moral lesson. Later retellings including a few movie versions have made changes to some of the characters or aimed to teach different ideas.</p>
<p>Here is the story <em>Chicken Little</em> in VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>One day, Chicken Little fell asleep under some flowers.</p>
<p>Cow wandered by, reached over the fence and bit off some flowers.</p>
<p>The noise wakened Chicken Little just as a flower <strong>petal</strong> fell on her tail.</p>
<p>"Squawk! Squawk!” cried Chicken Little, frightened by the petal's landing.</p>
<p>“The sky is falling,” she continued, her call rising louder with her terror. “Squawk! Squawk!”</p>
<p>And, she jumped up and began to run, moving as fast as her two legs would carry her. She did not stop running until she came to the barnyard. There, she found Henny Penny scratching in the dirt of the barnyard.</p>
<p>“Oh, Henny Penny, do not scratch—run!” cried Chicken Little. “The sky is falling.”</p>
<p>The scratching stopped. Then Hen called out: “How do you know that, Chicken Little?”</p>
<p>“I saw it with my eyes, I heard it with my ears, and part of it fell on my tail. Let us run, until we get some place.”</p>
<p>“Squawk! Squawk,” cried Hen in return, a look of shock on her face. Then, run she did, speeding away from the barnyard.</p>
<p>Chicken Little followed close behind.</p>
<p>They almost ran right past the little lake, just as Ducky Lucky was going in for a swim.</p>
<p>“Oh, Ducky Lucky! Ducky Lucky! Do not try to swim,” cried Henny Penny. “The sky is falling.”</p>
<p>“Seriously, Henny Penny? Why do you think that?” asked Ducky Lucky.</p>
<p>“Chicken Little told me.”</p>
<p>“How do you know the sky is falling, Chicken Little?”</p>
<p>“I saw it with my eyes, I heard it with my ears, and part of it fell on my tail. Oh, let us run until we get some place.”</p>
<p>Ducky Lucky was persuaded.</p>
<p>“Yes, we had better run,” he yelled.</p>
<p>And the three took off, Ducky Lucky <strong>waddling</strong> faster than he ever had before. The birds ran and ran until they came to a green <strong>meadow</strong>, and there was Goosey Loose eating the green grass.</p>
<p>“Oh, Goosey Lucy, Goosey Lucy, do not eat; run,” cried Ducky Lucky.</p>
<p>“Why should I run?” asked Goosey Lucy.</p>
<p>“Because the sky is falling.”</p>
<p>“How do you know that, Ducky Lucky?”</p>
<p>“Henny Penny told me.”</p>
<p>“How do you know that, Henny Penny?”</p>
<p>“Chicken Little told me.”</p>
<p>“How do you know that, Chicken Little?”</p>
<p>“Because I saw it with my eyes, and heard it with my ears, and part of it fell on my tail. Oh, let us run some place.”</p>
<p>“Yes, we had better run,” cried Goosey Lucy.</p>
<p>Away they all ran, Goosey Lucy in the lead, and they ran and ran until they came to the turkey <strong>yard</strong>, and there was Turkey Lurkey <strong>strutting</strong> and <strong>gobbling</strong>.</p>
<p>“Oh, Turkey Lurkey! Do not strut!” cried Goosey Lucy.</p>
<p>“Why should I not strut?” asked Turkey Lurkey.</p>
<p>“Because the sky is falling.”</p>
<p>“How do you know it is?”</p>
<p>“Ducky Lucky told me!”</p>
<p>“How do you know, Ducky Lucky?”</p>
<p>“Henny Penny told me!”</p>
<p>“How do you know, Henny Penny?”</p>
<p>“Chicken Little told me!”</p>
<p>“Chicken Little, how do you know this for a fact?”</p>
<p>“I could not help knowing! I saw it with my eyes, I heard it with my ears, and a part of it fell on my tail. Oh, let us run until we get some place.”</p>
<p>“Yes, it would be best to run,” said Turkey Lurkey, so away they all ran, first Turkey Lurkey, and then Goosey Lucy, and then Ducky Lucky, and then Henny Penny and then Chicken Little.</p>
<p>They ran and ran until they came to Foxy Loxy's house.</p>
<p>Foxy Loxy was resting, spread out across the doorway. She kept <strong>yawning</strong>, opening her mouth wide so that all her sharp teeth showed. But, her mouth snapped shut at the sudden arrival of the frightened birds, Turkey Lurkey and Goosey Lucy and Ducky Lucky and Henny Penny and Chicken Little.</p>
<p>Her eyes softened and her ears stood up. She was so very happy to see them all and smiled sweetly.</p>
<p>“Well, well,” the fox said, “what brings you all here?”</p>
<p>“Foxy Loxy, prevent yourself from yawning,” cried old Turkey Lurkey, “Indeed, the sky is falling.”</p>
<p>“How do you know that, Turkey Lurkey?” asked the fox.</p>
<p>“Goosey Lucy informed me.”</p>
<p>“How do you know that, Goosey Lucy?”</p>
<p>“Ducky Lucky told me.”</p>
<p>“How do you know that, Ducky Lucky?”</p>
<p>“Henny Penny told me.”</p>
<p>“How do you know that, Henny Penny?”</p>
<p>“Chicken Little.”</p>
<p>“How do you know that, Chicken Little?”</p>
<p>“I could not help knowing, for I saw it with my eyes, and I heard it with my ears, and part of it fell on my tail. Oh, where shall we run? We ought to go someplace.”</p>
<p>“Well,” said the Fox, “you come right into my house, and I will protect you and take such good care of you that, even if the sky falls, you will not know anything about it.”</p>
<p>So, in ran Turkey Lurkey and Goosey Lucy and Ducky Lucky and Henny Penny and — Chicken Little.</p>
<p>Foxy Loxy waited for a while and then shut the door firmly behind her. She would not let the falling sky threaten her guests, you see. She was going to take special care of them all.</p>
<p>And, maybe she did. But no one ever saw Chicken Little or her friends again.</p>
<p><em>Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted this story for VOA Learning English from stories in the public domain.</em></p><p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>petal</strong> <em>–n. </em>a flat, soft colorful part of a flower</p>
<p><strong>waddle</strong> <em>–v.</em> to walk with short steps while moving from side to side like a duck</p>
<p><strong>meadow </strong>–n. a wide flat area covered with grass that is often surrounded by forest</p>
<p><strong>strut </strong>–v. to walk in a confident or proud way</p>
<p><strong>yawn </strong>–v. to open the mouth wide and take a deep breath usually as a reaction to being tired or bored</p>
<p><strong>curl </strong>–v. to form into a rounded shape</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Using the Phonetic Alphabet  (2024/12/14)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/using-the-phonetic-alphabet.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">13 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Mouhammed in Egypt about using the phonetic alphabet.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/d81a33a8-a0ed-4bc3-8954-e67593f8e401_w268_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>I want to ask about the most important sources through which I can learn to improve the [pronunciation] of English letters, [for] trying to master the American accent.</p>
<p>Thank you,</p>
<p>Mouhammed</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Mouhammed.</p>
<p><strong>Understanding phonemes and the phonetic alphabet</strong></p>
<p>You can use the phonetic alphabet to help you know each sound of American English. Let's start by looking at what the phonetic alphabet is.</p>
<p>Each separate sound we make when we talk is called a phoneme. For example, the word “cat” has three phonemes: /k/, /<i></i>230;/, /t/ --“cat.”</p>
<p>For every phoneme we say, in any language, we can show that phoneme by using a special symbol, or sign. Those symbols are what make The International Phonetic Alphabet, or IPA. Notice that in the example with “cat,” only the phonetic symbol for the letter “t” looks the same as the English letter for that sound.</p>
<p>For many phonemes, the phonetic symbol does not look the same as the letters of the English alphabet that make the sound of the phonemes. Consider the word “need,” for example. It is spelled N-E-E-D but the phonetic symbol signifying the vowel looks like the English letter “i.”</p>
<p><strong>Using the phonetic alphabet</strong></p>
<p>How can you use the phonetic alphabet? Try to identify the phonemes that are difficult for you. For example, small differences between some vowel sounds in American English may be difficult for some non-native speakers to hear. Consider the following example:</p>
<p><em>bit bet</em></p>
<p>Did you clearly hear the difference between the two words? Hearing the sounds more clearly can help you pronounce them.</p>
<p>The <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.vocabulary.com/resources/ipa-pronunciation/">IPA Pronunciation Guide</a> on the website Vocabulary.com has an audio element so you can listen to the sound of each symbol. It also provides example words that contain the sound of each symbol. So, you can use the guide to practice hearing and saying any phoneme in American English.</p>
<p>The VOA Learning English video series <em>How to Pronounce </em>has many lessons that use IPA symbols to help learners practice the sounds of American English. The 21 lessons <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/7120228.html">“Games with Vowel Sounds”</a> and the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/7070516.html" target="_blank">"Listening Practice”</a> lessons are good places to start.</p>
<p>On the VOA Learning English website, you can play a short piece of audio and listen for phonemes you want to <strong>practice</strong>. You can hear words pronounced clearly and look at the way English spelling represents the phonemes you hear.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? We want to hear from you! Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please let us know where you are from, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Ancient Americans Depended Heavily on Mammoth for Food  (2024/12/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/study-ancient-americans-depended-heavily-on-mammoth-for-food.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A new study finds that the first humans to live in North America depended heavily on mammoths and other large animals for food.</p>
<p>The finding is based on examinations of the diet of a woman who lived about 13,000 years ago during the last Ice Age. She belonged to a culture called the Clovis. They were among the first Native Americans to arrive on the continent.</p>
<p>The woman was still breast-feeding her 18-month-old son when he died. The boy's remains were discovered back in 1968 in an ancient burial ground in the western U.S. state of Montana. Scientists examined his bones to learn more about his mother's diet.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Illustration of a group of Western Clovis people at a site in Montana. as seen in this handout image released on December 4, 2024. (Ben Potter of the University of Alaska Fairbanks and Jim Chatters of McMaster University/Handout via REUTERS)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/b33d06e9-8bd5-4a22-9d1a-92e6f16ed19b_cx0_cy11_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Illustration of a group of Western Clovis people at a site in Montana. as seen in this handout image released on December 4, 2024. (Ben Potter of the University of Alaska Fairbanks and Jim Chatters of McMaster University/Handout via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>They found that the woman ate mostly meat from mammoths and other very large animals. The finding supports scientific theories that Clovis people specialized in hunting large animals instead of seeking plants or small animals to eat.</p>
<p>At the time the Clovis people lived, large animals like mammoths lived in areas covering the Americas, as well as parts of northern Asia. The researchers noted that mammoths traveled very long distances during this period. This made them a target for migrating humans seeking protein-rich foods to eat.</p>
<p>The team examined isotope data collected from the boy's bones to estimate the Clovis woman's dietary intake. An isotope is a kind of atom that has a different atomic weight than similar atoms, but the same chemical structure. The isotope experiments centered on the elements carbon and nitrogen.</p>
<p>Mat Wooller is a professor and director of the Alaska Stable Isotope center at the University of Alaska Fairbanks. He was a co-writer of the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.adr3814">study</a> describing the research in the publication <em>Science Advances</em>.</p>
<p>Wooller told Reuters news agency isotope examinations can provide “a chemical fingerprint” of parts of an ancient human's diet. "We are all made of elements, like carbon and nitrogen, and so is our food," he said.</p>
<p>James Chatters is a professor of Earth, Environment and Society at Canada's McMaster University. He helped lead the research. Chatters <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.uaf.edu/news/study-reveals-mammoth-as-key-food-source-for-ancient-americans.php">said</a> in a statement that centering on mammoths “helps explain how Clovis people could spread throughout North America and into South America in just a few hundred years.”</p>
<p>The scientists estimated the woman mostly ate meat from a group of animals called megafauna, the largest creatures that existed at the time. The study showed megafauna made up about 96 percent of her diet, with mammoth accounting for about 40 percent of the total.</p>
<p>Chatters said one mammoth could support “a dependent community of children, care-giving women, and less <strong>mobile </strong>elders for days or even weeks while the hunters sought their next kill." Mammoths stood to about four meters tall at the shoulder and weighed as much as 11 tons.</p>
<p>Chatters said the Clovis people were known to be highly skilled hunters with a 10,000-year history of hunting megafauna over wide areas of territory. He added that the great dependence of the Clovis on megafauna likely led to the pressures that later caused the <strong>extinction</strong> of large ice age animals.</p>
<p>Chatters noted the latest finding supports past studies that provided "indirect evidence” that Clovis people mainly depended on mammoths and other large animals for food. This evidence included examinations of different <strong>artifacts</strong> – such as stone tools or the ancient remains of large animals, he said.</p>
<p>Ben Potter was also a co-writer of the study. He is an archeologist at the University of Alaska Fairbanks. Potter told Reuters, "These results also help us understand megafauna extinctions at the end of the last Ice Age.” He added the findings suggest that humans may have played a more important part in the extinctions than is sometimes thought.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Reuters reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English, with additional information from the University of Alaska Fairbanks and Science Advances. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>mobile </strong><em>– adj. <strong> </strong></em>capable of moving or being moved</p>
<p><strong>artifact </strong><em>– n.</em> an object showing human work and representing a culture or a stage in the development of a culture</p>
<p><strong>extinct</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj.</em> no longer in existence</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Peace Brings Big Changes to Kabul's Luxury Housing Market  (2024/12/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/peace-brings-big-changes-to-kabul-s-luxury-housing-market.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The capital city of Kabul, Afghanistan, has seen big changes in its high-end housing market. Peace, it seems, is driving up property prices.</p>
<p>Omidullah, a <strong>real estate</strong> agent, is selling a white-and-gold house with nine bedrooms and nine bathrooms in the Afghan capital. The house is on the market for $450,000, a surprising number in a country where more than half of the population depends on humanitarian aid to survive.</p>
<p>Most Afghans do not have bank accounts. And it is rare to borrow money from banks to buy property. Yet the offers are coming in.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A man waters flowers outside a luxury house in the city of Kabul, Afghanistan, Sept. 29, 2024. (AP Photo/Siddiqullah Alizai)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/bb75cc0c-9bea-4398-b7fc-ec5762f4c409_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A man waters flowers outside a luxury house in the city of Kabul, Afghanistan, Sept. 29, 2024. (AP Photo/Siddiqullah Alizai)</span></div>
<p>“It's a <strong>myth </strong>that Afghans don't have money,” Omidullah said. “We have very big businessmen who have big businesses abroad. There are houses here worth millions of dollars.”</p>
<p><strong>Afghans coming home </strong></p>
<p>People who spent years living and working abroad are returning home. They are drawn by the country's much-improved security and stability after years of war and destruction. Those returning include Afghans escaping <strong>deportation</strong> campaigns in Iran and Pakistan.</p>
<p>Banks rarely have enough money for lending. So, Afghans buy properties with their own money or employ what is called “geerawi.” It is when someone provides a fixed amount to a property owner in return for living in his place. And the person stays until the property owner returns the money.</p>
<p>Before the Taliban takeover, people were afraid to invest in Kabul, said another real estate agent, Ghulam Mohammed Haqdoost.</p>
<p>But the Taliban have created better conditions for the property market. The city is less violent since the Taliban changed from an insurgency to a government. Foreign forces left the country, although <strong>armored</strong> vehicles, checkpoints and military buildings remain common sights.</p>
<p>The Taliban have promised to end corruption and establish order. That means no more dealing with militia chiefs or paying officials for land purchases or building projects.</p>
<p>Haqdoost is happy with how easily and quickly things are getting done under the new administration.</p>
<p>“House prices have risen by almost 40 percent,” he said. “In the last three years, we have sold almost 400 properties. It wasn't like that before.”</p>
<p><strong>Good times for builders </strong></p>
<p>Business is good for Haqdoost. He employs 1200 workers, including women who only deal with female buyers.</p>
<p>Haqdoost said most purchasers bring their wives along because women often make decisions when it comes to real estate purchases — even in a nation that critics say oppresses women. “They decide whether to buy the house or not,” he said.</p>
<p>Afghans often host visiting friends or family in their homes. So wealthy buyers want houses with a garden, gym, swimming pool, rooms for visitors and at least one kitchen.</p>
<p>Since most of Haqdoost's buyers are from overseas, their tastes are influencing the homes. They want houses with central heating, <strong>double-pane</strong> windows and <strong>elevators</strong>, and things like dining tables and beds.</p>
<p>Kabul's population was around 500,000 in the year 2000. Now it is more than 5 million. To make Kabul more livable, city officials are busy building and repairing roads, putting in streetlights, planting trees and removing <strong>trash</strong>. They are also developing plans for less costly housing and increased home ownership.</p>
<p>Just outside of Kabul, Arash Asad is trying to sell his uncle's property, which sits on around 4,000 square meters of land. He wants to sell the property for $800,000.</p>
<p>“People think this country has no jobs and no economy,” Asad said. “But Afghans have made their money, illegally or legally, over the years. You wouldn't believe it.”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Riazat Butt reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>real estate </strong><em>-- n.</em> property (buildings and land)</p>
<p><strong>myth</strong> <em>– n.</em> a false idea or notion</p>
<p><strong>deport</strong> <em>– v.</em> to send (a person) out of the country</p>
<p><strong>armored</strong> <em>-- adj. </em>protected with a defensive covering </p>
<p><strong>double-pane </strong><em>-- adj. </em>describes a kind of window with two panes or layers of glass </p>
<p><strong>elevator</strong><em> -- n.</em> a platform or cage that moves people up and down </p>
<p><strong>trash </strong><em>-- n.</em> objects that are no longer wanted or needed and are thrown away </p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>European Climate Agency: 2024 Is Likely Hottest Year on Record  (2024/12/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/european-climate-agency-2024-is-likely-hottest-year-on-record.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A recent report by the European climate service Copernicus says that November was the second-warmest November for which the agency has records.</p>
<p>The finding means that Copernicus will likely declare 2024 the hottest year ever measured using its sets of data.</p>
<p>Copernicus called last year the hottest on record. But after this summer, scientists involved in the effort were expecting that 2024 would set a new record.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Women cool themselves with fans in the Rastro flea market during a heatwave in Madrid, Spain, Aug. 15, 2021. (AP Photo/Andrea Comas, file)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/207d73c9-1299-4303-9983-16fefb6af150_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Women cool themselves with fans in the Rastro flea market during a heatwave in Madrid, Spain, Aug. 15, 2021. (AP Photo/Andrea Comas, file)</span></div>
<p>In November, the global temperature average was 14.10 Celsius. Through November, this year's average global temperature is 0.14 Celsius above the same period last year.</p>
<p>Jennifer Francis is a climate scientist at the Woodwell Climate Research Center in the northeastern U.S. state of Massachusetts. Francis, who was not involved in the report, said the big story about November is that “like 2023, it beat out previous Novembers by a large <strong>margin</strong>.”</p>
<p>The report said 2024 will likely be the first year in which the average temperature was more than 1.5 degrees Celsius above pre-industrial times. In earlier publications, Copernicus calls pre-industrial times the period between 1850 and 1900.</p>
<p>The 2015 Paris Agreement says human-caused warming should be limited to 2 degrees Celsius.</p>
<p>In the years following 2015, the world's top climate scientist said it was important to limit the rise in temperature to 1.5 degrees Celsius to prevent the worst effects of climate change. The scientists said these effects could include increasingly destructive and <strong>frequent</strong> extreme weather events.</p>
<p>Copernicus Deputy Director Samantha Burgess said in a news release that “<strong>ambitious</strong> climate action is more urgent than ever.”</p>
<p>Many scientists say the main cause of climate change is the burning of fuels like coal, oil and natural gas.</p>
<p>Francis said the new records are “terrible news for people and ecosystems.”</p>
<p>Francis predicted bad effects from the quickly changing climate. These include the possibility of animals dying off and changes to the natural food webs that the animals are part of.</p>
<p>She added that coastal communities may face problems because of rising sea levels.</p>
<p>Experts said heat waves over the oceans and a loss of sea ice and snow cover probably played a part in the temperature increase this year. Copernicus, the European agency, said the area of Antarctic sea ice in November was 10 percent below average, a record.</p>
<p>The Associated Press reports that oceans absorb about 90 percent of the heat trapped by greenhouse gases. They then release heat and water vapor back into the atmosphere.</p>
<p>Last year's record heat was caused partly by an El Ni<i></i>241;o — a temporary natural warming of parts of the central Pacific that affects weather worldwide.</p>
<p>But that ended earlier this year and an effect that often follows, called La Ni<i></i>241;a, failed to take place. This left the scientific community “a little perplexed by what's going on here...why temperatures are staying high,” said Jonathan Overpeck.</p>
<p>Overpeck is a climate scientist at the University of Michigan.</p>
<p>One theory is that an El Ni<i></i>241;o releases more heat to the atmosphere because of warmer ocean waters. Overpeck said, “we're not getting the cooling effect that often in decades gone by helps bring the temperature back down.”</p>
<p>This year, he said, “is such a big jump following yet another jump...”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Tammy Webber reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>margin </strong><em>– n.</em> a measure or degree of difference</p>
<p><strong>frequent</strong> <em>– adj.</em> acting or returning regularly or often</p>
<p><strong>ambitious</strong> <em>– adj.</em> hoping to reach a particular goal</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>TikTok Asks Court to Block US Ban, Seeks US Supreme Court Hearing  (2024/12/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/tiktok-asks-court-to-block-us-ban-seeks-us-supreme-court-hearing.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">11 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>TikTok has asked a U.S. appeals court to temporarily block a law requiring its parent company, ByteDance, to <strong>divest</strong> itself of the popular video sharing service, or face a U.S. ban.</p>
<p>The legal request comes after the same federal appeals court last week upheld a law that forces ByteDance to sell TikTok by January 19 or face the ban. Lawyers for ByteDance and TikTok are seeking to temporarily block the law to give the U.S. Supreme Court a chance to rule on the case.</p>
<p>The companies said the Supreme Court had “an established historical record of protecting Americans' right to free speech.” They added their opinion that they expected the high court to “do just that on this important constitutional issue."</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file photo, a man carries a Free TikTok sign in front of the courthouse where a trial of Donald Trump was underway on April 15, 2024, in New York. (AP Photo/Ted Shaffrey, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/634230ad-7808-4e9f-b14c-d240f3e648aa_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">In this file photo, a man carries a Free TikTok sign in front of the courthouse where a trial of Donald Trump was underway on April 15, 2024, in New York. (AP Photo/Ted Shaffrey, File)</span></div>
<p>In the legal request, the companies warned that, without court intervention, the law would take effect next month leading to the closure of TikTok in the U.S. They called the service, or app, “one of the nation's most popular speech <strong>platforms</strong>,” noting it currently has more than 170 million monthly users in the U.S.</p>
<p>TikTok also warned that, if the law takes effect, it would affect “services for tens of millions of TikTok users outside the United States.”</p>
<p>The companies asked the appeals court to act on their request by December 16. They noted that President-elect Donald Trump has suggested he may try to prevent a U.S. ban on TikTok. Trump is set to take office on January 20.</p>
<p>A temporary block on the law could “give the incoming administration time to <strong>determine</strong> its position,” they said. The new administration's position, the companies argued, could make the Supreme Court hearing of the case unnecessary.</p>
<p>Unless the Supreme Court rules, a decision about whether to delay the TikTok ban would rest with President Joe Biden. He could approve a 90-day extension past January 19. However, experts have noted it is not clear whether ByteDance could meet a series of requirements needed to permit an extension.</p>
<p>In its ruling, the appeals court recognized that “170 million Americans use TikTok to create and view all sorts of free expression.”</p>
<p>Reuters news agency reports that it is not yet clear whether the Supreme Court will consider the case. But some legal experts have said the high court is likely to agree to hear it. The law is considered by some a test to see how far the U.S. government should be permitted to go in acting against technology companies using national security as a reason.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press, Reuters and Agence France-Presse reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>divest</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to sell something, especially a business or part of a business</p>
<p><strong>platform </strong><em>– n.</em> a kind of computer system, smartphone or social media service</p>
<p><strong>determine</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to decide something</p>
<p><strong>essential</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj.</em> necessary or needed</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Looking Back on Mispronounced Names and Words  (2024/12/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/looking-back-on-mispronounced-names-and-words.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Vice President Kamala Harris and pop singer Chappell Roan were among the year's most talked-about people. Their names were also among those people said incorrectly, or mispronounced.</p>
<p>In early December, the language-learning company Babbel and The Captioning Group released a list of words that people in the U.S. struggled with the most in 2024. The list also provides a look back at the year's most discussed subjects and people, from pop culture to politics.</p>
<p>Esteban Touma is a linguistic and cultural expert at Babbel. He said, "It's a nice way to kind of look back into the year and see everything that has happened."</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Los Angeles Dodgers' Shohei Ohtani brings his dog Decoy to deliver the ceremonial first pitch before a baseball game between the Dodgers and the Baltimore Orioles, Aug. 28, 2024, in Los Angeles, California. (AP Photo/Mark J. Terrill, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/cee80e45-a025-4b9f-8974-29ac985caa81_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Los Angeles Dodgers' Shohei Ohtani brings his dog Decoy to deliver the ceremonial first pitch before a baseball game between the Dodgers and the Baltimore Orioles, Aug. 28, 2024, in Los Angeles, California. (AP Photo/Mark J. Terrill, File)</span></div>
<p>Chappell Roan became famous this year and is <strong>nominated</strong> for six Grammy awards. But people still do not know how to say her name correctly. The list says her name is pronounced CHAP-uhl ROHN, not SHA-pel ROW-an.</p>
<p><strong>Help with pronouncing names</strong></p>
<p>During Harris' campaign for president this year, two of her young relatives spoke at the Democratic National Convention to teach the crowd how to say her first name, pronounced COM-a-la.</p>
<p>Also making the list was U.S. Transportation Secretary Pete Buttigieg, whose last name still causes some problems. During his 2020 presidential run, his campaign made shirts with the pronunciation "Boot-Edge-Edge" to help.</p>
<p>Other words on the list include:</p>
<p>— Dutch Kooikerhondje, pronounced COY-ker-HUND-che, is a breed of dog that became known this year. That is because Los Angeles Dodgers baseball player Shohei Ohtani has a Kooikerhondje called Decoy that appeared with him at an opening game.</p>
<p>— The name of the actress Zendaya is often mispronounced as zen-DIE-uh, but it should be zen-DAY-a.</p>
<p>— Online fast-<strong>fashion</strong> business Shein is SHE-in, not SHEEN.</p>
<p>— Newly discovered exoplanet Speculoos-3b is pronounced SPEK-yuh-lohss three bee.</p>
<p>— Phryge, the <strong>mascot</strong> of the Paris Olympics, is pronounced FREE-je.</p>
<p>— Semaglutide, the drug in weight-loss medications Ozempic and Wegovy, is pronounced sem-ah-GLOO-tide, not SEE-mah-gloo-tide.</p>
<p>— The last name of Irish actor Barry Keoghan, who starred in "Saltburn," is pronounced key-OH-gin.</p>
<p>Nancy Niedzielski is chair of the linguistics department at Rice University in Houston. She points out that most of the words on the list are not English, so it is not surprising that they would be mispronounced in the U.S. The key to pronouncing them correctly, she said, would probably just be hearing them spoken.</p>
<p>Touma, a native Spanish speaker, said if you cannot pronounce a word, it is important to just keep trying. "One of the problems we have is our mouths are not trained to do those sounds that come from different languages," he said.</p>
<p>Touma admitted even he struggles with some words, including Harris' first name. Even though he knows the correct pronunciation, he said, it is hard to get it right in a conversation.</p>
<p>As Roan's music gained popularity, it was an interesting cultural moment to watch as people learned to pronounce her first and last name, he said.</p>
<p>"The way we create understanding with each other is just trying to do these things," Touma said.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jamie Stengle </em><em>reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>nominate</strong> – <em>v.</em> to formally choose (someone) as a candidate for a job, position, office, or award</p>
<p><strong>fashion</strong> – <em>n</em>. a popular way of dressing during a particular time or among a particular group of people</p>
<p><strong>mascot</strong> - <em>n</em>. a person, animal, or object used as a symbol to represent a group (such as a sports team) and to bring good luck</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Saving Sea Turtles on Northeastern US Coast  (2024/12/11)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/saving-sea-turtles-on-northeastern-us-coast.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">10 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Over the last 20 years, the number of <strong>stranded </strong>sea turtles has increased in the waters off the northeastern coast of the United States. As a result, special animal hospitals in the New England area are now treating many sea turtles. Some kinds of these animals are highly endangered.</p>
<p>The turtles enter waters such as Cape Cod Bay when the weather is warm. But when temperatures drop, they cannot escape to head south, said Adam Kennedy. He is the director of rescue and <strong>rehabilitation</strong> at the New England <strong>Aquarium</strong>.</p>
<p>The aquarium operates a turtle hospital in Quincy, Massachusetts. On December 3, Kennedy said more than 200 young turtles needed to be treated there. The animals had been <strong>stunned</strong> by the cold.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Biologist Sammi Chaves, right, examines a Kemp's ridley sea turtle at a New England Aquarium marine animal rehabilitation facility, in Quincy, Mass., Tuesday, Dec. 3, 2024. (AP Photo/Steven Senne)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/72f1d803-3cad-4060-a8d2-6ae85ef97d13_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Biologist Sammi Chaves, right, examines a Kemp's ridley sea turtle at a New England Aquarium marine animal rehabilitation facility, in Quincy, Mass., Tuesday, Dec. 3, 2024. (AP Photo/Steven Senne)</span></div>
<p>The cold-stunned sea turtles wash up on the shores of Cape Cod every fall and winter. Kennedy said aquarium workers expect the number of turtles that they rescue to climb to at least 400. He said the average in 2010 was 40.</p>
<p>Kennedy said, “Climate change certainly is <strong>allowing</strong> those numbers of turtles to get in where normally the numbers weren't very high years ago.” He added that high winds and falling temperatures caused the recent strandings.</p>
<p>In the early 2010s, the five-year average of cold-stunned sea turtles in Massachusetts was around 200. In recent years, that number has grown to more than 700. These numbers come from the U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</p>
<p>All the turtles at the New England Aquarium's hospital are young. Most are<strong> </strong>the highly endangered Kemp's ridley turtles. The <strong>migration </strong>of these turtles often causes them to become stranded in the New England area. But some are green turtles or loggerheads which are not as endangered.</p>
<p>Kemp's ridley is the world's smallest sea turtle. The turtles mostly live in the Gulf of Mexico. But they travel into the northern Atlantic Ocean when young. A 2019 study in the scientific publication <em>PLoS One</em> said ocean warming increases the chance that turtles will become stunned by the cold in the waters of the Northwest Atlantic. The study said warmer water might push the turtles north in a way that makes stranding more likely.</p>
<p>Melissa Joblon is director of animal health at the New England Aquarium. She said most turtles that arrive at the center are sick: “The majority of the turtles arrive with serious <strong>ailments</strong> such as pneumonia, dehydration, traumatic injuries, or sepsis.”</p>
<p>The turtle hospital treats the animals so they can be returned to the wild. Kennedy said they are put in local waters or even taken south to warmer waters. He said about 80 percent survive.</p>
<p>“At the end of the day," Kennedy said, "getting these turtles back to the wild is what we are doing and what we want. We want them back in the ocean.”</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Patrick Whittle reported this story for the Associated Press from Portland, Maine. Anna Matteo adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>stranded </strong><em>–adj.</em> to be unable to leave a place</p>
<p><strong>rehabilitation </strong><em>–n.</em> the process of bringing a person or any living thing back to health after an accident or sickness</p>
<p><strong>aquarium </strong><em>–n</em>. a place that shows and takes care of fish and other sea life</p>
<p><strong>stun </strong><em>–v.</em> to make senseless, groggy, or dizzy by or as if by a blow</p>
<p><strong>allow </strong><em>–v.</em> to let something happen</p>
<p><strong>migration </strong><em>–n.</em> to regular movement of animals from one place to another to find food or better weather conditions</p>
<p><strong>ailment </strong><em>–n.</em> a sickness or condition that causes pain or poor health</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Power Outages Threaten Ice Cream Industry in Ecuadorean Town  (2024/12/11)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/power-outages-threaten-ice-cream-industry-in-ecuadorean-town.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">10 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In Ecuador, power outages threaten ice cream businesses in the small town of Salcedo in the country's central highlands.</p>
<p>Ice cream production in Salcedo began in the middle of the 1900s. Women working in a Roman Catholic religious center there would make a fruit drink with milk from the area's dairy farms. One of the female religious workers, called nuns, began collecting the unused drink mixture. She turned it into creamy popsicles, frozen <strong>treats</strong> that quickly became popular.</p>
<p>The nuns sold the popsicles in town to gather money for the poor. But the people of Salcedo saw a business opportunity and began trying new <strong>flavors</strong> and methods. Soon ice cream lovers came to support the industry in the town.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A worker packages popsicles at an artisanal factory in Salcedo, Ecuador, Thursday, Nov. 28, 2024, amid a wave of power outages, triggered by a prolonged dry spell. (AP Photo/Dolores Ochoa)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a5971131-f931-4e57-8289-fc1433bbb3bd_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A worker packages popsicles at an artisanal factory in Salcedo, Ecuador, Thursday, Nov. 28, 2024, amid a wave of power outages, triggered by a prolonged dry spell. (AP Photo/Dolores Ochoa)</span></div>
<p>However, a recent wave of power outages is threatening Salcedo's ice-cream industry. The daily loss of electrical power, began earlier this year. Each outage can last up to 14 hours. The problem is a long period without rain. Ecuador gets much of its power from hydroelectric centers which depend on lakes and rainwater.</p>
<p>Gabriel Pumasunta is part owner, with his two brothers, of the Polar Bear ice-cream factory. He said that if the power outages continue this month, they will have to shut down the factory. Pumasunta said that much of his product has melted because of power outages.</p>
<p>Before September, Polar Bear was producing 60,000 popsicles per month. Now, the small company makes 10,000 popsicles per month. The business has been forced to let go of eight of its 10 employees. Pumasunta is spending the company's savings and those of his family. He now works on the plant's machines himself. His parents are helping to run the factory.</p>
<p><strong>Severe business losses from power outages</strong></p>
<p>Ecuador's President Daniel Noboa has not been able to solve the electricity crisis. The chamber of commerce in Guayaquil, Ecuador's largest city, estimates that power outages are creating weekly losses of $700 million for Ecuadorian businesses.</p>
<p>Germán Soria is president of the association of <strong>artisanal</strong> ice-cream makers. He said that before the power crisis, Salcedo had 80 small- and medium-sized ice-cream makers and three large factories. Now, 30 of these smaller businesses have had to close. Even the large factories are slowing production.</p>
<p>Soria's own ice-cream business is no longer operating. He said he stopped production three weeks ago and had to sell some equipment, as well as some land to pay his debts.</p>
<p>He said that the outages happen at unexpected times. That means buyers, like small stores, are unwilling to purchase ice cream because they are unsure whether it will melt.</p>
<p>Local officials say the power crisis has cost 300 jobs in Salcedo. The town is known for its fruit-flavored ice-cream, including flavors such as blackberries and taxo, a kind of tropical fruit.</p>
<p><strong>New sources of power</strong></p>
<p>The Ecuadorian government has bought some large electric <strong>generators</strong> that run on oil or gas. But as Marco Acu<i></i>241;a, the president of Ecuador's national guild of engineers, said: "They do not have the <strong>capacity</strong> to make up for the current deficit."</p>
<p>In Salcedo, the collapse of the ice-cream industry has hurt the local economy. Dairy farms, fruit growers, transporters and small stores that sell popsicles all feel the effects.</p>
<p>"Before (the power cuts) we would buy up to 150 popsicles a day," said Maria Juliette López, who owns a small store on the Panamerican highway where <strong>tourists</strong> and truck drivers stop to buy <strong>snacks</strong>. "Now we can only take up to 40 popsicles a day, because any product that is left over will melt,” she said.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Gonzalo Solano reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>treat</strong> – <em>n</em>. something that tastes good and that is not eaten often</p>
<p><strong>flavor</strong> – <em>n.</em> the quality of something that you can taste</p>
<p><strong>artisanal</strong> – <em>adj</em>. made by a person who is skilled at making things by hand</p>
<p><strong>generator</strong> – <em>n</em>. a machine that makes electricity by burning gas or oil</p>
<p><strong>capacity</strong> – <em>n.</em> the ability to do something</p>
<p><strong>tourist</strong> – <em>n</em>. a person who travels to a place for pleasure</p>
<p><strong>snack</strong> – <em>n</em>. a small amount of food eaten between meals</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
