<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>VOA Special English</title>
        <link>https://www.51voa.com/VOA_Special_English/</link>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <itunes:category>ESL</itunes:category>
        <itunes:author>VOA</itunes:author>
        <description>美国之音（以下称VOA）的英语节目，按播音速度可分为两种：Standard English （标准英语）和 Special English（特别英语）。

Special English 又叫“慢速英语”，是VOA 专为全世界非英语国家初学英语的听众安排的一种简易、规范的英语广播节目。该节目创始于50年代末期，是VOA 的专家们研究如何与世界各地的英语学习者进行交际的产物。它正式开播于1959年10月。当时只面向欧洲和中东，但由于这个节目适合许多国家英语学习者的需要，所以它的广播对象不久就扩大到世界其他地区，并很快在全世界范围内产生了广泛的影响。现在这个节目对欧洲、非洲和拉丁美洲每晚广播一次，对加勒比地区每晚广播一次（星期天除外），对东南亚广播次数最多，每天上午两次，晚上三次。

30多年来，VOA 为了办好Special English节目，进行了大量的调查研究工作，对播音速度、内容及用词范围都作了具体规定，基本上达到了既能为英语学习者提供信息，又不损害英语本身风格的目的，使之成为VOA 独具特色，拥有最大量听众的节目。

美国著名词汇学家S. B. Flexmer 指明了Special English的三条标准，也就是它所“特别”的地方：

1、它是一种由美国人最常用的1500个基本单词为主体构成的美国英语；

2、它用简短、明晰的句子写作和广播；

3、它以每分钟90个单词的速度，即2/3的Standard English（标准英语）速度进行广播。

Special English的节目可分为两大类：一类是新闻节目；一类是专题节目。

1．新闻节目

VOA Special English 的新闻广播向听众提供世界范围内的政治、经济、军事、外交、国际关系、宗教、天气以及各种重大事件和珍闻奇事等各个方面的信息，每天向东南亚地区广播五次，早上两次，晚上三次，每逢半点播出。

Special English新闻节目每次长约十分钟，大都播出十条左右新闻，近一千个单词，每条新闻多为一分钟，但偶尔也有长达两分钟的要闻。除头条新闻外，每条新闻都由一个电头引导，这样显得结构分明，条理清晰，适宜初学英语的人收听。在节目结束之前，播音员常常用三四句话重播其中三条新闻的提要以加深听众对要闻的印象。

Special English新闻中70%左右的内容与同时整点播出的Standard English新闻相同，但相同新闻的先后次序有所变动。每次节目的开头和结尾大同小异，格式比较固定。

2．专题节目（一）

Special English的专题节目（Feature Programs）,从时间上看，可分为两大类：一是每五分钟一次的专题，二是每十五分钟一次的专题。本节先介绍每项五分钟一次的专题材节目。

Special English五分钟一次的专题材节目安排在Special English新闻节目之后和（或）每十五分钟一次的专题材节目之前播出，每星期播七次。根据内容，可分为三个小类，即：Science Report（科学报道），逢星期一、三、五播出，每天播六遍；Agriculture Report（农业报道），逢星期二、四播出，每天播六遍；Words And Their Stories（词语掌故），逢星期六和星期天播出，每天播五遍。这三个专题材各具特色，具有相对的独立性，听众每听完一个节目，都会获得一个完整的印象。

Science Report（科学报道）这一专题材节目每周向听众介绍三篇有关现代科学技术最新发展情况的报道，涉及物理、化学、天文至高无上理、生物、环卫、心理、教育、医学和计算机等方面。适宜理工科大学生和科技工作者收集信息，积累资料，学习科技英语。

Agriculture Report（农业报道） Agriculture Report是为农业科技工作者和生产者安排的一个专题。它专门报道世界各国，特别是美国现代农业生产的最新成文汇报总务科 学家对农业生产某一方面的研究进展，以及他们对影响农业生产的某一自然现象进行分析和研究的近况。此外，它还经常向听众介绍发展中国家家业生产的一些有益经验等内容。

Words And Their Stories（词语掌故）这一专题节目，旨在向学习英语的听众介绍美国英语中生动有趣的词语和惯用法，并从科学研究和通俗词源学的角度来解释它们的含意、产生的背景及其在使用过程中的演变情况等。它通过讲故事的形式讲解每一个词语。这是VOA Special English中的优秀节目之一，是学习美国英语的极好材料。通过收听这一节目，听众不仅能学到娓娓动听的掌故和地道的美国英语，而且能增加美国的社会文化背景知识，历史传统与现状的了解。

VOA 为了更好地办好这个节目，便于听众收听学习，于1978年编辑出版了一本名为Words And Their Stories的书，共收集一百篇故事，作者是Herbert Sutcliffe, Harold Bermen 及VOA 该节目的部分编辑人员。在每次的实际广播中，播音员都以此书为蓝本，再根据需要对原稿进行适当增删。按每周两个故事计算，此书的一百个故事还不能满足一年的播音需要。于是编辑们就是重播部分词语掌故的同时，不断增加许多新的词语掌故，及时将词源学家的最新研究成果和不断增加的新词汇介绍给听众。收听实践证明，初学者在收听过程中必然会遇到许多人名、地名和一些较难的句子，有时甚至在听完之后还很难理解所播词语的确切含义及其汉语意思，为此，听众可参看1983年由中国对外翻译出版公司出版的该书英汉对照本中的有关部分。

3．专题节目（二）

VOA Special English的专题节目，除上节谈的五分钟一次的以外，还有本节要介绍的每十五分钟一次的节目。这类节目共有七个不同的小专题，以星期为单位循环，每天分四次复播出一个专题，但星期日和星期六的两个专题材每晚只播三遍，每次节目约十分钟，继每次五分钟的专题节目之后播出。

这类专题节目的基本结构是，在特定的伴声中先报告当次节目的名称，并扼要介绍其主要内容，然后播送节目正文。最后，在伴乐声中报告节目主持人和撰稿人的姓名，以邀请听众在下周的这个时间继续收听该节目而结束。

People in America（美国人物志） 这是有关美国历史名人的一个专题节目，每逢星期天晚上播出。它向听众介绍在美国历史上产生过重大影响、起过重要作用、作出了突出贡献的科学、文学、政治、或其他各方面的历史人物。节目一般都对他们的生平事迹进行简要的叙述，对其贡献作出评介，类似人物小传。有的重要人物事迹很多，必须用两次或几次的节目时间进行联播。对这样的节目要坚持收听，才会获得完整的印象。

TThis is America（今日美国） This Is America向听众介绍美国人民的生活、学习、工作和娱乐情况，是英语学习者解美国社会的一条渠道。该专题大都一个节目一个整体，每逢星期一晚播出。

Science in the News（科学新闻） 这一专题材主要对新近的科学技术新闻进行综述或摘要广播。向听众介绍世界各国在自然、医学、疾病、原子能、航天等方面的科研动态、成果、突破性进展及存在的困难。涉及当今世界人们普遍关心的重大问题，如核事故、航天飞机爆炸、自然灾害、环境污染和爱滋病等等。每逢星期二播出，每次播一到五条新闻摘要。

Explorations（自然探索） 每逢星期三晚上，听众可以收听到Explorations这一专题节目。该专题既涉及人类遨游太空、探索原子、研究自身、改造自然的现代技术，也报道发展中国家开发新资源，利用新工艺改善人民生活等方面的成就，其侧重点在各种科技实验和简易实用技术方面。该节目一般安排一段时间播一个系列，每次播出一个主题，以便能将某项新技术的研究和应用的全过程介绍给听众，电台还乐意为感兴趣的听众提供所需的文字材料。

The Making of a Nation（建国史话） 这一专题节目向听众介绍美利坚合众国从十三个殖民地区域到现代工业国的孕育、诞生以及形成超级大国的历史过程，并以历史为线索，特定的历史时期为单位，以重大的历史事件为主题材来叙述各个党派、各届总统和政府的历史作用与贡献。这是每个英语学习者都应了解的基本知识。The Making of a Nation每逢星期四播出。这是个系列节目，坚持收听，则有助于系统了解美国的历史概况。

American Mosaic（美国万花筒） American Mosaic是一个radio magazine（广播杂志）节目。该节目题材广泛、内容丰，展示着美国社会文化生活中比较轻松愉快的生活画面；听众收听该节目就如同在阅读一本图文并茂的杂志。它每次有三到五个小节目，涉及音乐、图书、技术和教育等方面的内容。我们既可以从中欣赏到著名歌唱的优秀歌曲，对美国音乐有所了解，又可以获取一些生动有趣的现代美国社会生活知识，随着播音员那亲切悦耳的声音步入美国风景如画的大好河山；同时还能听到世界各地的听众提出的有关英语语方文学等方面的问题和电台的解答。

American Stories（美国故事） 这一专题材节目安排在每星期六晚上播出。这样能使听众在学习和工作之余，得以轻松一下头脑。我们可以通过这一美国文学的“窗口”，接触各种流派、各类名家的文学作品。了解美国英语的时代特色，欣赏、学习美国人民运用语方的技巧，并从那些佳作名篇中获得艺术享受。该节目对短篇故事采取一次播一篇的方式，对中、长篇小说则先进行简写加工，再分几次播出全文。在播出故事正文之前，播音员常常先介绍故事的主要情节。对需要分几次节目时间播出的中长篇，在播第二或以后各部分之前，主持人还先重述已播部分的故事梗概，以唤起听众的回忆，使故事听起来更加连贯。</description>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          <item>
            <title>Pigs in Yoga Class Put People at Ease  (2024/5/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/pigs-in-yoga-class-put-people-at-ease.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">28 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>In the northeastern American state of Massachusetts, people are combining a form of exercise for the body and spirit with pigs.</p>
<p>The yoga classes in Massachusetts are selling out within hours. People come from far away to exercise with Wilbur, Charlotte and Bluey, who are piglets, or young pigs.</p>
<p>The pigs come from a nearby farm to play among people in the yoga class at Ashley Bousquet's business Beyond Yoga &amp; Wellness in the town of Spencer. Bousquet tells people not to worry if piglets climb on top of them or want to <strong>cuddle</strong>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Piglets interact with yoga class participants, Friday, May 17, 2024, in Spencer, Mass. (AP Photo)
" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-f059-08dc7bf78bac_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Piglets interact with yoga class participants, Friday, May 17, 2024, in Spencer, Mass. (AP Photo)
</span></div>
<p><strong>Goat yoga</strong></p>
<p>Yoga classes with animals are not new. Goats might have been the first. Lainey Morse started yoga classes with goats in the state of Oregon in 2016. She found she felt happier and more at ease around goats. She talked with a friend who was a yoga teacher. They decided to offer classes with the goats. Their business was successful, and the idea soon spread to other places.</p>
<p>In Ashley Bousquet's class, the little pigs walk around humans who are moving into exercise positions called downward dog, crow and cobra. Among the other animals in the outdoor class are two rabbits and a goat named Munchie.</p>
<p>Stacey Delbridge and her daughter drove almost two hours to attend a class with the pigs. She said it was worth the drive.</p>
<p>"The best thing about the piglet yoga was, of course, the piglets and how <strong>cute</strong> they are," Delbridge said with a smile. "They were funny, you know. Just when you were getting to a point where you needed a break, you had a great visitor come see you, and you could quit without looking like a quitter. Yeah. They're <strong>adorable</strong>."</p>
<p>Bousquet said there is such demand that online registrations are usually full within hours.</p>
<p>The classes begin with Bousquet inviting her students not to worry about stopping their exercises to spend time with the piglets.</p>
<p>"During the class you have piglets causing <strong>mischief</strong> and running on you, on top of you or cuddling with you," Bousquet said. "It's super cute."</p>
<p>Amy Finkel brought her two daughters with her, smiling while taking photos of piglets as the girls held a rabbit.</p>
<p>"The highlight of the class, in my opinion, was just having them run around, and seeing them so joyful and happy," she said.</p>
<p>The only problem was that the time passed too quickly.</p>
<p><strong>Good results for humans and animals</strong></p>
<p>Doing yoga with animals produces good results.</p>
<p>Rebecca Purchase is a Volunteer Coordinator of the Massachusetts Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals-Angell. If animal yoga includes shelter, or unwanted, animals, it may even <strong>encourage</strong> people to give them a home, she said.</p>
<p>"Is yoga <strong>stressful</strong> to animals that join? It can be if it's not the right animal," Purchase said. "For animals that really thrive, being around people, and getting to socialize with them, it absolutely can be a <strong>benefit</strong>."</p>
<p>Finkel enjoys animal yoga — she said it helped keep her mind from moving on to other things.</p>
<p>"I just wanted to sit with them," Delbridge said.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Rodrique Ngowi reported on this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>yoga</strong> – <em>n</em>. a system of exercises for mental and physical health</p>
<p><strong>cuddle</strong> – <em>v.</em> to lie or sit close together</p>
<p><strong>cute </strong><em>–adj.</em> having a pleasing appearance</p>
<p><strong>adorable</strong> – <em>adj. </em>very appealing or attractive</p>
<p><strong>mischief </strong><em>–n</em>. trouble that is not serious</p>
<p><strong>encourage </strong><em>–v.</em> to urge or persuade a person to do something</p>
<p><strong>stressful</strong> – <em>adj</em>. full of or causing stress; making you feel worried or anxious</p>
<p><strong>thrive</strong> – <em>v.</em> to grow or develop successfully</p>
<p><strong>benefit</strong> – <em>n.</em> a good result</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>70 Years after Brown Decision, School Segregation Getting Worse  (2024/5/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/years-after-brown-decision-school-segregation-getting-worse.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Dan Novak</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">28 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>May 17 marked the 70th anniversary of one of the most notable cases in U.S. Supreme Court history – Brown versus Board of Education.</p>
<p>The 1954 decision declared <strong>segregated</strong> schools unconstitutional. It also struck down the principle of "separate but equal," which was used as the basis for U.S. government policies related to racial segregation. President Dwight Eisenhower famously sent federal troops to southern states to enforce the decision.</p>
<p>Today, American schools cannot legally restrict students based on race. But because of long-held economic divides and other issues, some schools have become segregated in a <strong>de facto </strong>way.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Third-grade students do school work during class at Hanby Elementary School, Feb. 15, 2011, in Mesquite, Texas. (AP Photo/LM Otero, File)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-3042-08dc7e862547_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Third-grade students do school work during class at Hanby Elementary School, Feb. 15, 2011, in Mesquite, Texas. (AP Photo/LM Otero, File)</span></div>
<p><strong>‘Moving backward'</strong></p>
<p>Some researchers say that despite the continuing ban, school segregation has gotten worse over the years, even as the U.S. overall has become more racially <strong>diverse</strong>.</p>
<p>A team from the University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA) recently released a report examining the ways segregation has changed in U.S. schools. The report is called "The Unfinished Battle for Integration in a Multiracial America – from Brown to Now." It was written by two UCLA professors – Gary Orfield and Ryan Pfleger.</p>
<p>The study found that schools have gotten less white, and more Latino, Asian and multiracial. But it also noted the number of schools considered "intensely segregated" tripled from 1988 to 2021. The study defined intensely segregated as schools with white student populations of less than 10 percent. About 20 percent of American schools are intensely segregated, up from 7 percent in 1988, the report found.</p>
<p>The study's writers state that "schools of the South are <strong>dramatically</strong> less segregated than the <strong>apartheid</strong> conditions that had always existed before Brown." However, Orfield and Pfleger add that the Supreme Court decision's historic aims "have not been <strong>attained</strong> and, as this report shows, we have been moving backward."</p>
<p>The researchers found that Black and Latino students were the most highly segregated populations. In 2021, schools overall were 45 percent mostly white. But on average, Black students attended schools that were about 76 percent non-white. For Latino students, the school average was about 75 percent non-white.</p>
<p>Education experts say segregation especially hurts Black and Latino schools. This is because they are often underfunded and have higher rates of teacher shortages. Non-white school districts receive $23 billion less funding than mostly white school districts, a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://edbuild.org/content/23-billion">2019 report</a> by the nonprofit group EdBuild found.</p>
<p>"The trends are toward increasing double segregation, by both race or ethnicity and poverty," the UCLA study said.</p>
<p>Researchers at another California university, Stanford, found that schools are getting more segregated even as neighborhoods have gotten more diverse and racial economic inequality has improved.</p>
<p>The "findings indicate that policy choices – not <strong>demographic</strong> changes – are driving the increase," <a class="wsw__a" href="https://ed.stanford.edu/news/70-years-after-brown-v-board-education-new-research-shows-rise-school-segregation">said</a> Sean Reardon. He is a professor at Stanford who specializes in how poverty and inequality affects education.</p>
<p><strong>Reintegrating Schools</strong></p>
<p>The UCLA study noted that desegregation policies following the Brown decision were generally aimed at improving <strong>access</strong> to schools for Black students.</p>
<p>But 70 years later, the issue of school segregation has gotten more complex. Latinos now make up the largest U.S. minority group and the Asian population has also grown. "Most Americans of all racial groups think <strong>integrated</strong> schools are better, but are divided about what, if anything, to actually do," the UCLA study states.</p>
<p>The researchers offered several suggestions for improving integration. One is for districts to increase efforts to register students from poorer areas and offer more diverse school programs.</p>
<p>A 2018 <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.edutopia.org/article/3-promising-models-school-integration/">article</a> by the nonprofit group Edutopia described how some school districts have been successful in improving integration. In Cambridge, Massachusetts, for example, every school must have a balance of wealthier and poorer families. In San Antonio, Texas, bilingual schools and other specialized programs have brought in students from many different backgrounds.</p>
<p>And in New York City, schools have made progress by removing standardized testing requirements. Others introduced admittance systems that take into account whether a student is poor, homeless or a non-native English speaker.</p>
<p>"American schools have been moving away from the goal of Brown and creating more ‘<strong>inherently</strong> unequal' schools for a third of a century," writers of the UCLA study wrote. "It will soon become understood once more that ... schools that serve all children together with equity are central to any good outcomes."</p>
<p>I'm Dan Novak.</p>
<p><em>Dan Novak wrote this story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><em>_______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>segregate </strong><em>— v. </em>to separate groups of people because of their particular race, religion, etc.</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>de facto </strong><em>— adj. </em>used to describe something that exists but that is not officially accepted or recognized</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>diverse </strong><em>— adj. </em>different from each other</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>dramatic </strong><em>— n. </em>sudden and extreme</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>apartheid </strong><em>— n. </em>a policy or system of segregation or discrimination on grounds of race.</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>attain </strong><em>— v. </em>to accomplish or achieve</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>demographic </strong><em>— n. </em>the qualities of a specific group of people</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>access </strong><em>— n. </em> a way of getting near, at, or to something or someone</p>
<p><strong>integrate </strong><em>— v. </em> to combine to form or create something</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>inherent </strong><em>— adj. </em>belonging to the basic nature of someone or something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Melinda French Gates to Donate $1 Billion for Women’s Rights  (2024/5/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/melinda-french-gates-to-donate-1-billion-for-women-s-rights.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Dan Friedell</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">28 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>Melinda French Gates announced this week that she plans to give $1 billion over the next two years to support women and families around the world.</p>
<p>French Gates is the former wife of Microsoft founder Bill Gates.</p>
<p>Earlier in May, French Gates said she would step down from her position with the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation. She said she wanted to center her work on helping push forward women's rights.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Co-chair of the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation Melinda French Gates speaks at the forum Empowering Women as Entrepreneurs and Leaders during the World Bank/IMF Spring Meetings in Washington, on April 13, 2023. (AP Photo/Jose Luis Magana, File)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/5e9a7bf2-abe7-49b1-86c1-982022bb7c41_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Co-chair of the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation Melinda French Gates speaks at the forum Empowering Women as Entrepreneurs and Leaders during the World Bank/IMF Spring Meetings in Washington, on April 13, 2023. (AP Photo/Jose Luis Magana, File)</span></div>
<p>French Gates received $12 billion from Bill Gates for her <strong>philanthropy</strong> efforts.</p>
<p>Writing in <em>The New York Times</em> on Tuesday, French Gates said she is not happy with people who say it is not the right time to talk about <strong>gender</strong> equality.</p>
<p>"<strong>Decades</strong> of research on economics, well-being and governance make it clear that investing in women and girls benefits everyone," she wrote.</p>
<p>In her statement, French Gates discussed the high death rates for Black and Native American women during childbirth in the United States.</p>
<p>She also criticized the reduced ability women have to end a pregnancy in some states, and the lack of national policy giving women time off from work after having a baby. She added that the number of teenage girls feeling hopeless and having thoughts of suicide<strong> </strong>is at its highest level in many years.</p>
<p>In the last few weeks, she said, she had already sent money to groups including the National Women's Law Center, the National Domestic Workers Alliance and the Center for Reproductive Rights. The donations came from her organization Pivotal Ventures, which is organized as a private company. There is not much public information about how it invests and spends its money. French Gates said recent gifts, or grants, to activist groups, are not meant for specific projects but are for operating support.</p>
<p>In the past, the organization has spent money on projects related to several causes. They include closing what is often called the <strong>wage gap</strong> between men and women, supported women running for office and, what the Associated Press calls, "<strong>compensating</strong> care work often done by women."</p>
<p>French Gates plans to introduce a $250 million plan in the fall that will center its energy on improving the mental and physical health of women and girls worldwide.</p>
<p>French Gates will be leaving the organization she founded with her ex-husband next week. The Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation supported public health projects worldwide.</p>
<p>The Associated Press reports that the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation will change its name to the Gates Foundation. It is one of the largest philanthropic organizations in the world with an estimated value of $75 billion.</p>
<p>I'm Dan Friedell.</p>
<p><em>Dan Friedell adapted this story for Learning English based on a report by the Associated Press</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>philanthropy </strong>–n. the activity of giving money to causes that are supposed to help people</p>
<p><strong>gender </strong>–n. the condition of being male or female</p>
<p><strong>decade </strong>–n. a period of 10 years</p>
<p><strong>wage </strong>–n. pay for work that is based on the amount of time that is worked</p>
<p><strong>gap </strong>–n. a difference between to values or things that are being compared</p>
<p><strong>compensate </strong>–v. to provide something of value in exchange for something that was lost or damage that was suffered</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Rescue Efforts in New Guinea Delayed by Dangerous Conditions  (2024/5/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/rescue-efforts-in-new-guinea-delayed-by-dangerous-conditions.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">28 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>Officials in Papua New Guinea (PNG) have ordered people in parts of Enga Province to leave their homes because of the continuing danger of landslides.</p>
<p>The government estimates that the collapse of a mountainside buried at least 2,000 people on Friday. Officials said the likelihood of finding survivors is small. That number is higher than an earlier estimate from the United Nations, which placed possible deaths at 670.</p>
<p>An estimated 150 structures were buried in the landslide.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Villagers move a rock as part of search efforts following a devastating landslide, in Yambali village, in the Highlands of Papua New Guinea, May 27, 2024. (Juho Valta/UNDP Papua New Guinea via AP)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-c9f6-08dc7f38e88b_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Villagers move a rock as part of search efforts following a devastating landslide, in Yambali village, in the Highlands of Papua New Guinea, May 27, 2024. (Juho Valta/UNDP Papua New Guinea via AP)</span></div>
<p>Rescue teams have been slow to arrive. Heavy rain and tribal unrest have delayed aid supplies and the heavy equipment needed to dig into the earth. The U.N. International Organization for Migration (IOM) said a bridge to the area had collapsed forcing aid vehicles to travel farther.</p>
<p>A military <strong>escort</strong> has guarded groups of rescue vehicles because of the unrest. A continuing deadly tribal conflict has made it more difficult for aid workers to get to the area.</p>
<p>Local people have used hand tools to search for survivors.</p>
<p>Sandis Tsaka is a provincial administrator and heads a disaster committee. He told Reuters that conditions remained dangerous. "The landslide area is very <strong>unstable</strong>," he said, "...there are still rocks and <strong>debris</strong> coming down."</p>
<p>Tsaka also said the military had set up security stops and is moving people to <strong>evacuation</strong> centers.</p>
<p>The U.N. said on Tuesday that six bodies had been recovered so far. The U.N. estimated the total number of those affected to be 7,849.</p>
<p>Nicholas Booth is a representative of the U.N. Development Program. He said the aid operation is very complex because the landslide area is increasing.</p>
<p>"It means that now, the area that's been affected by the landslide is greater than it was at the beginning. We don't know how it will develop, but that's the nature of the geology in PNG."</p>
<p>Booth also spoke about the tribal violence. He said eight people were killed and 30 houses burned in fighting on Saturday.</p>
<p>Itayi Viriri of the IOM spoke in Geneva. Viriri said aid teams need to be careful to prevent "another disaster," saying "all response efforts have to be done in a very careful manner."</p>
<p>On Tuesday, the U.N. said that immediate needs include clean water, food preparation tools, medicine, and psychological and social support.</p>
<p>A U.N. statement said provincial officials in New Guinea have asked the international community to send engineers to study geological dangers in the area.</p>
<p>Officials said the difference in the estimated number of dead is the result of the difficulty the country has in counting its population. The nation's last <strong>credible</strong> population count, or census, was in 2000. A 2022 list of registered voters for the area does not include people under the age of 18.</p>
<p>Booth said estimates should be treated with "great <strong>caution</strong>." He said, "It's just not possible at this stage to make a very scientific, verified estimate." Booth added, "But it's going to be a very high number of <strong>casualties</strong>. We have to be prepared for that."</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Lewis Jackson and Renju Jose reported this story for Reuters. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>escort</strong><strong> </strong><em>–n. </em>a group that accompanies and protects another group that is traveling</p>
<p><strong>unstable</strong> <em>–adj.</em> in a condition that is likely to change and that is not solid or steady</p>
<p><strong>debris </strong><em>–n.</em> what is left behind after something has been destroyed</p>
<p><strong>evacuation </strong><em>–n.</em> an effort to move people out of an area for their safety</p>
<p><strong>credible </strong><em>–adj</em>. believable</p>
<p><strong>caution </strong><em>–n.</em> care and concern about something</p>
<p><strong>casualties </strong><em>–n. (pl.)</em> the number of injuries and deaths in a disaster</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study Explores History of Cockroaches  (2024/5/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/study-explores-history-of-cockroaches.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">27 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>They are six-legged, hairy home invaders that will not die, no matter how hard you try.</p>
<p>Cockroaches are experts at surviving indoors. But they did not start out that way.</p>
<p>A recent study uses genetics to examine cockroaches' spread across the world, from beginnings in southeast Asia to Europe and beyond. The findings cover thousands of years of cockroach history and suggest the pests may have spread across the world by getting a ride with another <strong>species</strong>: people.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This photo provided by Qian Tang shows a German cockroach and an Asian cockroach, specimens from Harvard Museum of Comparative Zoology, Friday, May 17, 2024, in Cambridge, Mass. (Qian Tang via AP)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/09c449d9-366d-477f-9fc6-77362bb65b95_cx11_cy19_cw71_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This photo provided by Qian Tang shows a German cockroach and an Asian cockroach, specimens from Harvard Museum of Comparative Zoology, Friday, May 17, 2024, in Cambridge, Mass. (Qian Tang via AP)</span></div>
<p>"It's not just an insect story...It's an insect and humanity story," said Stephen Richards of Baylor College of Medicine. Richards was not involved with the study.</p>
<p>Researchers studied the genes of over 280 cockroaches from 17 countries and six continents. They confirmed that the German cockroach — a species found worldwide — has its beginnings in southeast Asia. The creature likely <strong>evolved</strong> from the Asian cockroach around 2,100 years ago. Scientists have long suspected the German cockroach's Asian beginnings since similar species still live there.</p>
<p>The research appeared recently in the publication Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences.</p>
<p>The cockroaches then spread around the world on two major paths. They traveled west to the Middle East about 1,200 years ago, perhaps living in soldiers' food storage containers. And they may have gotten on Dutch and British East India Company trade ships to get to Europe about 270 years ago, the scientists' findings suggest.</p>
<p>Once the creatures arrived in Europe, inventions like the steam engine and indoor <strong>plumbing</strong> likely helped the insects travel further and get used to living indoors, where they are most commonly found today.</p>
<p>Researchers said exploring how cockroaches conquered past environments may lead to better pest control.</p>
<p>Modern-day cockroaches are tough to keep away because they evolve quickly to resist <strong>pesticides</strong>, said the study's writer Qian Tang of Harvard University.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Adithi Ramakrishnan reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>species </strong><em>– n.</em> group of animals or plants that are similar</p>
<p><strong>evolve </strong><em>– v.</em> to develop by a process of evolution</p>
<p><strong>plumbing </strong><em>-- n. </em><strong> </strong>the system of pipes and fixtures that distribute and use water in a building</p>
<p><strong>pesticide </strong><em>-- n. </em>an agent used to destroy insects or pests</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Don’t Have Soil, Try Planting in Straw Bales  (2024/5/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/don-t-have-soil-try-planting-in-straw-bales.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Gregory Stachel</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">27 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>You do not need good soil – or even soil at all – to grow plants. Straw bales can work, too.</p>
<p>Straw is the dry stems of wheat and other grain plants. Straw bales are made of straw that has been tightly pressed together. They can be used to grow vegetables in a cost-effective and easy-to-care-for way.</p>
<p>If you are going to use straw bales for your gardening needs, it is important to know what to look for. Avoid bales made of hay. Hay bales contain seeds and are meant for horses.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This July 2023 image provided by Adrienne Reeves shows a variety of crops growing in staw bales in a garden in Livonia, Mich. (Adrienne Reeves via AP)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/2c16b056-65fb-4336-9ff2-823facb50a72_cx0_cy13_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This July 2023 image provided by Adrienne Reeves shows a variety of crops growing in staw bales in a garden in Livonia, Mich. (Adrienne Reeves via AP)</span></div>
<p>Straw is for gardening. Most of its seeds have been harvested. There should not be many (or any) remaining seeds in the bale.</p>
<p>Straw is less likely than hay to have been treated with chemicals that could slow your plants' growth or even prevent it. To be sure, it is a good idea to ask the seller if their bales have been treated with chemicals.</p>
<p><strong>Preparation </strong></p>
<p>It will take about two weeks to condition your straw bales. The process turns it into a fertile bed for plants.</p>
<p>Choose an area that offers the correct amount of sunlight for the plants you will be growing. You can place the bale on any flat surface. But keep in mind that after the bale is wet, it will be very heavy and difficult to move.</p>
<p>Set the bale with its cut end facing up, then begin the conditioning process.</p>
<p>During the first three days, <strong>apply</strong> water slowly and evenly until it begins to run out the bottom of the bale. You can use equipment like a hose set over the top to do this.</p>
<p>On days four through 10, spread 78 milliliters of <strong>herbicide</strong>-free grass fertilizer that contains at least 20 percent nitrogen. Spread it across the top of the bale. If you do not want to use chemicals, you can also spread a 50/50 mix of ground bone and blood.</p>
<p>Water the bale to spread the fertilizer. But do not overwater. That could wash out the nutrients.</p>
<p>Continue to water the bale daily.</p>
<p>The nitrogen will break the straw down and make the bale into a nutrient-rich environment for plants. As this happens, the center of the bale will heat up and then begin to cool. It will be safe to plant seeds or young plants when the temperature drops below 38 degrees Celsius.</p>
<p>Some <strong>mushroom</strong> growth at the beginning of the process is normal. They will die down on their own. But do not eat them.</p>
<p><strong>Planting and growing</strong></p>
<p>Finally, it is time for planting. Make holes or cut open the top of the bale and plant your seedlings. Fill each hole with soil. If you are planting seeds, make holes that follow the depth suggestion in the directions. Drop larger seeds in, and then fill each hole with soil.</p>
<p>If you are planting smaller seeds, spread some soil over the bale's surface, plant the seeds, and then spread more soil to meet the suggested depth.</p>
<p>Continue to water your seeds or plants daily to make sure the center of the bale and the area around each plant are kept <strong>moist</strong>. Depending on the weather, additional watering may be necessary. Do not let the bale dry out.</p>
<p>Add fertilizer and amendments throughout the growing season as you would with normal plants.</p>
<p>Many flowers and vegetables grow well in straw bales. But vegetables that have heavy tops and <strong>shallow</strong> roots should be avoided.</p>
<p>I'm Gena Bennett.</p>
<p><em>Jessica Damiano reported this story for The Associated Press. Gregory Stachel adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>apply </strong><em>– v. </em>to put or spread (something) on a surface or a part of the body</p>
<p><strong>herbicide </strong><em>– n. </em>a chemical used to destroy plants or stop plant growth</p>
<p><strong>mushroom </strong><em>– n. </em>a fungus that is shaped like an umbrella</p>
<p><strong>moist </strong><em>– adj. </em>slightly or barely wet: not completely dry</p>
<p><strong>shallow </strong><em>– adj. </em>having a small distance to the bottom from the surface or highest point</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>New Rocket Engine Could Cut Travel Time to Mars from Years to Months  (2024/5/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/new-rocket-engine-could-cut-travel-time-to-mars-from-years-to-months.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">26 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>A private company is working with the American space agency NASA to develop a new rocket that could greatly reduce space travel times.</p>
<p>The engine for such a rocket will be designed to sharply increase the amount of thrust to speed up space travel and improve rocket <strong>efficiency</strong>.</p>
<p>Thrust is the force that pushes a spacecraft through the air. It is produced by a <strong>propulsion</strong> system. Generally, a gas or liquid fuel is burned to produce thrust from the back of a spacecraft to propel it forward at high-speed.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="NASA's Curiosity Mars rover used its black-and-white navigation cameras to capture panoramas at two times of day on April 8, 2023. (Image Credit: NASA/JPL-Caltech)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-8886-08dc7b722878_w268_r1.png"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">NASA's Curiosity Mars rover used its black-and-white navigation cameras to capture panoramas at two times of day on April 8, 2023. (Image Credit: NASA/JPL-Caltech)</span></div>
<p>The new design, called Pulsed Plasma Rocket (PPR), is being developed by Arizona-based company <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.howeindustries.net/">Howe Industries</a>. The company is currently in the early stages of studying the technology before building working engine models.</p>
<p>In a recent statement, Howe Industries <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/directorates/stmd/niac/niac-studies/pulsed-plasma-rocket-ppr-shielded-fast-transits-for-humans-to-mars/">said</a> such rocket technology will be needed to support NASA's plans to return humans to the moon and after that, possibly Mars. The space agency has also set a goal to build a long-term base in space. But one barrier to all these plans is the long travel times necessary with current spacecraft systems.</p>
<p>NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2009/07/180561main_ETM.Distance.Moon_.pdf">estimates</a> the moon sits an average of about 382,500 kilometers from Earth. The exact distance changes because of the moon's orbit around Earth. The average distance from Earth to Mars is 225 million kilometers.</p>
<p>NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/planetary-science/programs/mars-exploration/mission-timeline/">says</a> a trip to Mars with existing spacecraft would take at least 200 days each way. Developers of the proposed Pulsed Plasma Rocket have said it could reduce travel time to the Red Planet to about two months each way.</p>
<p>Howe Industries said its new design gives the rocket the ability to reach extremely high speeds to complete "reasonable" space travel times. The development team estimates its PPR system could produce up to 100,000 N of thrust. The ‘N' at the end of the number stands for Newtons, a unit of measurement for thrust.</p>
<p>NASA has described its <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.51voa.com/a/nasa-pleased-with-orion-test-flight-as-spacecraft-heads-back-to-earth/6868275.html">Space Launch System</a> (SLS) as the most powerful ever built. The agency has <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/sls-introductory-pages.pdf">said</a> the SLS rocket system is expected to provide nearly 53 N of thrust during space travel.</p>
<p>Developers of PPR say that in addition to a huge increase in thrust, the new design also provides a "specific impulse" rate of 5,000. <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www1.grc.nasa.gov/beginners-guide-to-aeronautics/liquid-rocket-engine/">Specific impulse</a> is a method for measuring – in seconds –thrust and efficiency levels of rocket engines. The higher this rate is, the more efficient the rocket system is. By comparison, the SLS rocket has specific impulse rates below 500.</p>
<p>Officials at Howe have said the PPR is based on another <strong>plasma</strong>-based technology known as pulsed fission fusion. NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/general/pulsed-fission-fusion-puff-propulsion-concept/#:~:text=The%20pulsed%20fission%20fusion%20propulsion,energy%20for%20the%20next%20pulse.">says</a> this process involves quickly pressing plasmas into high pressures to produce thrust. But the developers say the PPR system is smaller, simpler and costs less to operate.</p>
<p>Howe's statement introducing the technology said the combination of extremely high thrust and higher specific impulse rate "holds the <strong>potential</strong> to revolutionize space exploration."</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p>The team said such a system should be able to propel much heavier spacecraft and support much longer trips to more distant areas of space. The planned system could also make it easier for spacecraft to be equipped with heavy shields to protect traveling astronauts from Galactic Cosmic Rays. These are highly energetic particles that move through space at nearly the speed of light. The rays can be harmful to humans in large amounts.</p>
<p>The PPR project is one in a series of NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.51voa.com/a/nasa-details-plans-for-railway-system-on-the-moon/7605113.html">development projects</a> that recently received additional financial assistance to keep running. The projects are part of a NASA program called Innovative Advanced Concepts (NIAC).</p>
<p>PPR is currently in <strong>Phase</strong> I of development. The team said if chosen by NASA to continue with Phase II, it will be centered on improving the performance of the proposed engine, as well as carrying out experiments on major engine systems. The last phase will involve completing a spaceship design for carrying humans to Mars.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from NASA and Howe Industries. </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________</strong><strong> </strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>efficient </strong><em>– adj. </em>working well and not wasting time or energy</p>
<p><strong>propulsion </strong><em>– n. </em>a force that pushes something forward</p>
<p><strong>plasma </strong><em>– n. </em>a collection of charged particles</p>
<p><strong>potential </strong><em>– n. </em>possible</p>
<p><strong>phase </strong><em>– n. </em>a specific period during which something happens</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How to Protect Your Car from Being Stolen  (2024/5/27) | 如何防止汽车被盗？</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/how-to-protect-your-car-from-being-stolen.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>Most recent cars have an electronic key that lets the owner get into and start the car.<br/>
大多数新款汽车都有一个电子钥匙，车主可以用它进入并启动汽车。</p>
<p>The electronic key is called a "fob" to those who know about the technology. The fob sends a short-range signal to the car. As the owner gets close, the fob unlocks the door.<br/>
对于那些了解这项技术的人来说，该电子钥匙被称为“遥控钥匙”。遥控钥匙向汽车发送近距离信号。当车主靠近时，遥控钥匙打开车门。</p>
<p>But the new technology also makes it easier for criminals to open the car without the key.<br/>
但这项新技术也使犯罪分子更容易在没有钥匙的情况下打开汽车。</p>
<p>When you lock your car and take the key with you inside your home, the fob does not stop sending its signal.<br/>
当你锁上车并把钥匙带到家里时，遥控钥匙不会停止发送信号。</p>
<p>Thieves, who have special equipment known as scanners, will pass by streets with a lot of cars. If the scanner shows that a fob is sending a signal, the thieves use a device that clones the signal and opens the car doors.<br/>
小偷拥有被称为扫描仪的特殊设备，他们会带着设备经过交通繁忙的街道。如果扫描仪显示有遥控钥匙正在发送信号，小偷就会使用一种设备来克隆该信号，然后打开车门。</p>
<p>Government officials around the world have asked carmakers to warn car buyers of the risks of the new technology. They also have asked them to make the fobs more secure.<br/>
世界各地的政府官员已要求汽车制造商向购车者警示这种新技术的风险。他们还要求汽车制造商提高遥控钥匙的安全性。</p>
<p>Until then, what can you do to prevent your car from being stolen?<br/>
在那之前，你能做些什么来防止你的车被偷？</p>
<p>Steve Launchbury has some suggestions he shared with the Associated Press. He is the head engineer of automotive security company Thatcham Research based in Britain.<br/>
Steve Launchbury与美联社分享了一些建议。他是英国汽车安全公司Thatcham Research的首席工程师。</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: bold;">Place your key in a protective bag<br/>
将钥匙放在保护袋中</span></p>
<p>"It's relatively easy for drivers to protect themselves," he said.<br/>
他说：“对司机来说，保护自己相对容易。”</p>
<p>The first tip is to put your key into a protective container or bag when you get home. One kind is called a Faraday bag. They are not very costly. The bag is made from a special metal material called mesh that blocks the signal from the fob. Just do not forget to put any extra keys you have into that bag, too.<br/>
第一个建议是回家后把钥匙放进一个保护性的容器或袋子里。有一种叫做法拉第袋。它们卖得不贵。这个袋子是由一种叫做网状物的特殊金属材料制成的，它可以阻挡来自遥控钥匙的信号。只是别忘了把备用钥匙也放进那个包里。</p>
<p>Some advice that is easy to find online says people should put their keys into the microwave or freezer to prevent their signal from being stolen. Launchbury said that does not work and it could harm your key.<br/>
网上常见的一些建议说，人们应该把钥匙放进微波炉或冰箱，以防止信号被盗。Launchbury说这不起作用，还可能会损坏你的钥匙。</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: bold;">Get a steering wheel lock<br/>
买把方向盘锁</span></p>
<p>You may have seen large locks that go across the steering wheel in television advertisements many years ago. It turns out they are still useful. They may be considered "old school," but the presence of big locks that are easy to see makes car thieves turn away. The only problem is that you must take extra time to unlock the device and put it away before you can drive away.<br/>
很多年前，你可能在电视广告中看到过方向盘上的大锁。事实证明它们仍然有用。它们可能被认为是“老派”，但显眼的大锁会让偷车贼望而却步。唯一的问题是，你开车驶离前必须额外花时间来打开方向盘锁并将其放好。</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: bold;">Change the settings<br/>
更改设置</span></p>
<p>Some car makers permit owners to deactivate the signal sent out by the fob. For Ford, Honda and Audi, owners can use their car's touchscreen system to find the correct way to turn off the signal. For Toyota, you can turn off the signal by pressing a combination of buttons on the fob.<br/>
一些汽车制造商允许车主停用遥控钥匙发出的信号。对于福特、本田和奥迪来说，车主可以使用汽车的触摸屏系统找到关闭信号的正确方法。对于丰田，您可以通过按下遥控钥匙上的组合按钮来关闭信号。</p>
<p>Read your car's owner's manual to be sure how to do this.<br/>
阅读车主手册以确定如何做到这一点。</p>
<p>Some car makers include motion sensors on their key fobs. If the fob has not been moved in a while, the fob turns off.<br/>
一些汽车制造商在他们的遥控钥匙上安装了运动传感器。如果遥控钥匙有一段时间没有移动，遥控钥匙将关闭。</p>
<p>If you buy a used car, some experts suggest that you get your keys reprogrammed in case the earlier owner still has a key.<br/>
如果你买了一辆二手车，一些专家建议你重新编程钥匙，以防前车主还有钥匙。</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: bold;">New theft techniques<br/>
新型盗窃技术</span></p>
<p>Launchbury said some cars have a new system called a controller area network, or CAN. The network permits different parts, or components of the car to communicate with each other. He said some thieves are trying to join the CAN through some physical electronic connection to unlock the car. They can do this by removing a headlight and plugging in a device that lets them in the car's network.<br/>
Launchbury说，一些汽车有一种称为控制器局域网（CAN）的新系统。该网络允许汽车的不同零部件相互通信。他说，一些小偷试图通过某种物理电子连接进入控制器局域网来解锁汽车。他们可以通过拆除前照灯，然后插入一个可以进入汽车网络的设备来实现这一点。</p>
<p>The device can send a signal, such as "unlock" or "start" to the central system.<br/>
该设备可以向中央系统发送信号，如“解锁”或“启动”。</p>
<p>Launchbury said this is where the physical lock can cause thieves to change their mind and force them to move on. Owners can also consider electronic immobilizers. These devices prevent a car from moving even if a thief gets into the internal system. However, immobilizers can be costly.<br/>
Launchbury说，这是物理锁可能导致小偷改变思路并迫使他们继续前行的地方。车主也可以考虑使用电子防盗器。即使小偷进入内部系统，这些装置也能防止汽车移动。然而，防盗器价格可能很贵。</p>
<p>I'm Dan Friedell.<br/>
我是丹·弗里德尔。(51VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Electric Spoons, Chopsticks May Help Cut Salt  (2024/5/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/electric-spoons-chopsticks-may-help-cut-salt.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">26 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>Researchers in Japan say they will begin selling new devices that will help people reduce how much sodium, or salt, they use to improve the taste of their food.</p>
<p>The developers are from Japan's Meiji University and drink company Kirin based in Tokyo.</p>
<p>One new device is an electric <strong>spoon</strong>. It uses a small computer worn on a person's arm to send electrical signals to activate sodium atoms. The developers say the signals increase the food's salty taste.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="An employee of Kirin Holdings demonstrates an electric spoon in Tokyo, May 20, 2024. (REUTERS/Tom Bateman)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-78fb-08dc7a57ca3f_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">An employee of Kirin Holdings demonstrates an electric spoon in Tokyo, May 20, 2024. (REUTERS/Tom Bateman)</span></div>
<p>The Electric Salt Spoon will sell in Japan for around $120 beginning in June. Meiji University professor Homei Miyashita developed the spoon and a similar device, electric <strong>chopsticks</strong>. The chopsticks will likely go on sale next year.</p>
<p>The recent announcement marks the first time the technology has been used in a product for sale to the public. Last year, the effort gained a different sort of attention. It won the 2023 Ig Nobel Prize in nutrition. Organizers describe the prize as recognizing research that makes "people LAUGH, then THINK."</p>
<p><strong>How the devices work</strong></p>
<p>The devices both use a weak electrical current to send the sodium <strong>ions</strong> from food, through the chopsticks or spoon, to the mouth where they create a sense of saltiness, said Miyashita.</p>
<p>"As a result, the salty taste <strong>enhances</strong> one and a half times," he said.</p>
<p>Miyashita and his laboratory have explored ways that technology can interact with and create human sensory experiences. He has also developed a <strong>lickable</strong> TV screen that can recreate the taste of food.</p>
<p>The beer producer Kirin is turning to healthcare products to expand its traditional business. A company spokesperson said the technology might be especially useful for Japanese people, whose traditional diet favors salty foods. The average adult in Japan consumes about 10 grams of salt per day. The World Health Organization recommends half that amount.</p>
<p>Eating foods with too much sodium can increase the chances of having high blood pressure, <strong>strokes</strong> and other health problems.</p>
<p>"To prevent these diseases, we need to reduce the amount of salt we take," said Kirin researcher Ai Sato.</p>
<p>Sato said it is hard to cut salt in the usual way because it would mean "eating <strong>bland</strong> food."</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Tom Bateman, Rikako Murayama and Akiko Okamoto reported on this story for Reuters. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>spoon</strong> – <em>n.</em> an eating or cooking tool that has a small shallow bowl attached to a handle</p>
<p><strong>chopsticks</strong> – <em>n. </em>either one of a pair of thin sticks that are used especially by people in Asia to pick up and eat food</p>
<p><strong>ion </strong>- <em>n.</em> an atom or group of atoms that has a positive or negative electric charge from losing or gaining one or more electrons</p>
<p><strong>enhance </strong>- <em>v.</em> to increase or improve something</p>
<p><strong>lickable</strong> – <em>adj.</em> able to be touched with the tongue</p>
<p><strong>stroke</strong> – <em>n.</em> (<em>medical)</em> a serious illness caused when a blood vessel in your brain suddenly breaks or is blocked</p>
<p><strong>bland</strong> <em>– adj.</em> lacking strong flavor</p>
<p><em>What do you think of the electric spoon and chopsticks? We want to hear from you. Write to us in the Comments Section. </em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers in Australia Develop a ‘Water Harvester’   (2024/5/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/researchers-in-australia-develop-a-water-harvester.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">25 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>Researchers in Australia recently announced the launch of a new device that, they say, <strong>absorbs </strong>water from air to produce drinkable water.</p>
<p>Researchers at the University of Newcastle call the device the Hydro Harvester. They said it can produce up to 1,000 liters of drinkable water a day, adding that it could be "lifesaving during <strong>drought</strong> or emergencies."</p>
<p>The Australian team said that unlike other atmospheric water <strong>generators</strong>, their invention works by heating air instead of cooling it.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A flock of sheep drink from a dam at the edge of the dried-up Lake George, about 250 kilometers southwest of Sydney, Australia, on Tuesday, March 3, 2015. (AP Photo/Rob Griffith)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/63ebba35-e9e7-49e5-9b7c-0752e774324d_cx0_cy16_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">FILE - A flock of sheep drink from a dam at the edge of the dried-up Lake George, about 250 kilometers southwest of Sydney, Australia, on Tuesday, March 3, 2015. (AP Photo/Rob Griffith)</span></div>
<p>The device absorbs water from the atmosphere. Solar energy or heat from other industrial processes can be used to produce hot, wet air. After heating, the air cools, producing water for drinking or watering crops.</p>
<p>Behdad Moghtaderi of the University of Newcastle's Centre for Innovative Energy Technologies told VOA how the technology operates.</p>
<p>"Hydro Harvester uses an absorbing material to absorb and <strong>dissolve</strong> moisture from air. So...we use renewable energy..." Moghtaderi said. He added, "When you <strong>condense</strong> water contained in that air you would have the drinking water at your <strong>disposal</strong>."</p>
<p>The researchers say the device can produce enough drinking water each day for a small rural town of up to 400 people. It could also help farmers keep livestock alive during droughts.</p>
<p>Moghtaderi said the technology could be used in parts of the world where water is limited.</p>
<p>Researchers thought their device would be useful because Australia's climate is dry.</p>
<p>"More than 2 billion people around the world, they are in a similar situation where they do not have access to...high-quality water and they deal with water <strong>scarcity</strong>," Moghtaderi said</p>
<p>Studies of the technology will be done in several Australian communities this year.</p>
<p>The World Economic Forum (WEF), a nonprofit group based in Switzerland, says water scarcity continues to be a problem worldwide.</p>
<p>The WEF said getting water from the atmosphere is a "promising emergency solution that can immediately generate drinkable water using <strong>moisture </strong>in the air."</p>
<p>However, the group warns that the technology is costly. It estimates that one mid-sized device could cost between $30,000 and $50,000.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Phil Mercer reported on this story for VOA News. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>absorb </strong><em>– v.</em> to take something in, such as a liquid</p>
<p><strong>drought </strong><em>– n.</em> a period of time with too little rain</p>
<p><strong>generator </strong><em>– n.</em> a machines whose processes produce energy or a material</p>
<p><strong>dissolve </strong><em>–v.</em> to become mixed into and part of a liquid</p>
<p><strong>condense </strong><em>– v.</em> to change from a gas to a liquid</p>
<p><strong>at (one's) disposal</strong> <em>–idiom</em> to be able to use</p>
<p><strong>scarcity</strong> <em>– n.</em> the condition of having very little of something</p>
<p><strong>moisture</strong> <em>–n. </em>wetness or water in small amounts</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study Reveals History, Travels of Baobab Tree  (2024/5/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/study-reveals-history-travels-of-baobab-tree.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Dan Novak</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">25 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>The baobab tree is a special thing to see. During the dry season, its leafless branches look like roots coming from a thick <strong>trunk</strong>. It appears as if someone took a tree from the ground, flipped it on its head and put it back into the earth.</p>
<p>That is why the tree is sometimes called the "upside down tree."</p>
<p>Baobab trees grow in Madagascar, mainland Africa and Australia. The <strong>origins</strong> and history of the baobab have been something of a mystery. But a new study that looked at all eight recognized species helps tell the baobab's story.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A motorcycle drives between baobab trees at baobab alley near the city of Morondava, Madagascar, August 30, 2019. (REUTERS/Baz Ratner/File Photo)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-e649-08dc78e88efb_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A motorcycle drives between baobab trees at baobab alley near the city of Morondava, Madagascar, August 30, 2019. (REUTERS/Baz Ratner/File Photo)</span></div>
<p>The baobab originated in Madagascar about 21 million years ago. It reached the African continent and Australia sometime in the past 12 million years, researchers found. Madagascar, an island off Africa's southeastern coast, has a large ecosystem. It is home to many kinds of plants.</p>
<p>Two baobab <strong>lineages</strong> went extinct in Madagascar. But the lineages established themselves elsewhere, one in mainland Africa and one in Australia, the study showed.</p>
<p>It appears that baobab seed <strong>pods</strong> floated from Madagascar to mainland Africa, located about 400 kilometers to the west. The seeds also traveled to Australia, nearly 7,000 kilometers to the east.</p>
<p>"The plants almost certainly got to Africa and Australia floating on or with vegetation <strong>rafts</strong>," said plant expert Tao Wan of the Wuhan Botanical Garden in China. He is one of the writers of the study, which appeared recently in the publication <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07447-4" target="_blank">Nature</a>.</p>
<p>Wan added that the seeds were able to travel to Australia because of the Indian Ocean gyre, an oceanic current.</p>
<p>Baobab trees provide food, shelter and nesting places for wildlife, including bees, birds and various mammals. Their fruits also provide important nutrients and medicines for people. Baobab leaves can be eaten, too.</p>
<p>The trees produce large, sweet-smelling flowers. Their sugary nectar appeals to nighttime <strong>pollinators</strong> like fruit bats and hawk moths. Their flowers also attract two kinds of <strong>primates</strong> -- lemurs in Madagascar and bush babies in Africa.</p>
<p>Ilia Leitch is a plant geneticist at the Royal Botanic Gardens Kew in London. He is also a study co-writer. He said baobabs can grow to be very large and live for thousands of years.</p>
<p>Their very large root systems "play an important ecological role, helping to slow down soil <strong>erosion</strong> and <strong>enabling</strong> nutrient recycling," he said.</p>
<p>Baobabs are a water source for local people during the dry season. But Africa's baobabs are at risk from elephant damage. The animals sometimes cut the tree trunks with their <strong>tusks</strong> to get water.</p>
<p>I'm Dan Novak.<em> </em></p>
<p><em>Dan Novak adapted this story for VOA Learning English based on reporting by Reuters. </em></p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><em>_________________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p class="CxSpFirst"><strong>trunk </strong><em>— n. </em>the thick main stem of a tree</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>origin </strong><em>— n. </em> the point or place where something begins or is created</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>lineage </strong><em>— n. </em>the people who were in someone's family in past times</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>pod </strong><em>— n. </em>a long, thin part of some plants that has seeds inside</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>raft </strong><em>— n. </em>a flat structure that is used for floating or sailing on water</p>
<p><strong>pollinator </strong><em>— n. </em>to give pollen from another plant of the same kind so that seeds will be produced</p>
<p><strong>erosion </strong><em>— n. </em>the gradual destruction of something by natural forces</p>
<p><strong>enable </strong><em>— v. </em>to make able to do or to be something</p>
<p><strong>tusk </strong><em>— n. </em> a very long, large tooth that sticks out of the mouth of an animal</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Community Colleges Offer Clean Energy Training  (2024/5/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/us-community-colleges-offer-clean-energy-training.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">25 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>Across the United States, students are now looking to community colleges for training in jobs related to climate change solutions. These include wind and solar energy, electrification, and protecting water and farmland.</p>
<p>For example, on the south side of Chicago, Illinois, students learn how to work on an electric vehicle (or EV) in a new technician program at Olive-Harvey College.</p>
<p>About 240 kilometers south, students at Danville Area Community College learn how to fix<strong> </strong>large <strong>wind turbines</strong>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Associate professor Vered Mirmovitch, front, leads students on a plant tour on the West Los Angeles College campus, March 12, 2024. As students consider jobs that play a role in solving the climate crisis, community colleges are responding. (AP Photo/Jae C. Hong" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-e634-08dc7aacb4f0_cx0_cy7_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Associate professor Vered Mirmovitch, front, leads students on a plant tour on the West Los Angeles College campus, March 12, 2024. As students consider jobs that play a role in solving the climate crisis, community colleges are responding. (AP Photo/Jae C. Hong</span></div>
<p>In Albuquerque, students learn how to work on <strong>solar panels</strong> at Central New Mexico Community College.</p>
<p>In Boston, Massachusetts, students at Roxbury Community College's Center for Smart Building Technology learn how to strengthen buildings against extreme temperatures. They also learn how to build structures that contribute less to climate change.</p>
<p>Kyle Johnson is a 34-year-old student at Olive-Harvey College in Illinois. Johnson has long enjoyed working on gasoline-fueled cars. But automobiles are increasingly electric.</p>
<p>"When it came to EVs, I knew that the times are changing, and I didn't want to get left behind," he said. "Climate change has a lot to do with my decision," he added.</p>
<p><strong>Changing job market</strong></p>
<p>The job market already has been changing. Businesses and jobs that address climate change are growing. And now legislation like the 2022 <em>Inflation Reduction Act </em>is adding more investment which will most likely mean more jobs.</p>
<p>Millions of clean energy workers are needed to meet targets set by governments and companies to reduce their <strong>greenhouse gas emissions</strong>. Many of these job opportunities are growing faster than overall employment in the U.S.</p>
<p>Brian Lovell of Roxbury Community College has seen that firsthand. "While the students are still in the program, they get employed because the demands of industry are so <strong>acute,"</strong> he said of the students in Roxbury, Massachusetts.</p>
<p>Traditionally, people going into these industries gained skills through local employers and labor organizations. But now community colleges can help. They listen to companies and state officials and create hands-on training for open jobs.</p>
<p>Kate Kinder is executive director of the National Council for Workforce Education. She said "over half of these jobs" require less than a four-year college degree and more than a high school education.</p>
<p>"That's <strong>prime </strong>community college space," she said of the two-year <strong>associate</strong> program.</p>
<p>These job openings draw in students like Tannar Pouilliard.</p>
<p>Pouilliard had thought he would become an automotive technician. However, after learning about openings in the wind power industry, he <strong>enrolled</strong> in Danville's wind energy technician classes. He said, "It really opens the door for people out here for jobs."</p>
<p><strong>College investment in new programs</strong></p>
<p>At the same time, community colleges have been losing students, not unlike the rest of higher education. Currently, more people are entering the workforce straight out of high school. And some community colleges have not recovered from the decrease in enrollment that happened during the pandemic.</p>
<p>Some schools say investing in these programs is a balancing act between staying up-to-date and risking a bet on developing technology.</p>
<p>"We feel the pressure," said Monica Brummer. She is director of the Pacific Northwest Center of Excellence for Clean Energy at Centralia College in Washington. "If we create <strong>curriculum</strong> today for, say, a hydrogen technician, it may not be the curriculum we need in two or three years, because the technology is changing so fast ..."</p>
<p>Some schools hope to make the change without new and costly investments.</p>
<p>For example, Minnesota's Inver Hills Community College launched a climate change program in 2022 using existing areas of study at the school. Now, administrators are considering expanding that program. As well, Cape Cod Community College recently changed from specialized workforce training to a wider sustainable energy study program.</p>
<p>Other community colleges help prepare students like Sarah Solis for a four-year degree program related to climate change.</p>
<p>Solis was enrolled at West Los Angeles College, a community college near the Inglewood Oil Field. The oil field is what led her to environmental studies. She later changed to the school's climate change degree, which was new at the time. Its climate change program has grown since then; it is now home to the California Center for Climate Change Education.</p>
<p>Then Solis went to the University of California, Davis, and earned a degree in environmental science and management. She teaches city farms how to deal with a warming future. And she credits her success to her community college experience.</p>
<p>Solis called her experience at the community college "life changing." She added, "I would not be an environmental scientist right now if I hadn't gone to West."</p>
<p>Many other students said the same thing.</p>
<p>I'm Dan Friedell. And I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Alexa St. John in Detroit and Melina Walling reported this story for the Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>wind turbine </strong><em>-n.</em><strong> </strong>an engine whose central driving shaft is fitted with a series of blades spun around by the pressure wind for generating electricity</p>
<p><strong>solar panel </strong><em>-n. </em>a battery of solar cells (as on a rooftop)</p>
<p><strong>greenhouse gas </strong><em>-n.</em> any of various gaseous compounds (such as carbon dioxide or methane) that absorb infrared radiation, trap heat in the atmosphere, and contribute to the greenhouse effect<em> </em></p>
<p><strong>acute </strong><em>-adj. </em>demanding urgent attention</p>
<p><strong>prime </strong><em>-adj. </em>first in rank or importance</p>
<p><strong>associate </strong><em>-adj. </em>a degree given especially by a junior college</p>
<p><strong>enroll </strong><em>-v. </em>to become a member</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Many Handy 'Hand' Expressions  (2024/5/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/many-handy-hand-expressions.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">25 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Every day, we do countless things with our hands. So, it's not surprising that we have many "hand" expressions that describe how we do something. These hand expressions could be called <u>handy</u> ... meaning they are useful.</p>
<p>When we do something with our<u> <strong>bare</strong> hands</u>, we do it on our own, usually with much effort. When we use this expression, we are expressing <strong>pride</strong> in something we have done.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Business team putting hands together on top of each other. (Prostock-studio via Adobe Stock)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-c969-08dc7a833d58_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpeg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Business team putting hands together on top of each other. (Prostock-studio via Adobe Stock)</span></div>
<p>For example, let's say I decided to build my own gardening shed -- a small outdoor building for gardening supplies. It was hard work and took me days to finish. But at the end of the project, I could proudly say that I built it with <u>my own bare hands</u>.</p>
<p>Feeling proud and finishing a big project <u>go hand in hand.</u> They go together!</p>
<p><strong>Firm hand = strict</strong></p>
<p>Let's say you are asked to lead a project. You want it to be successful. You want it to be on time and on budget. So, you lead with a <u>firm hand</u>. If you lead with a <u>firm hand</u>, you are <strong>strict</strong>. You follow all the rules closely. You don't let jokes or laziness affect your team's progress. Teachers can teach with a <u>firm hand</u>. And parents can parent with a <u>firm hand</u>, too. Having a <u>firm hand</u> and being strict <u>go hand in hand.</u></p>
<p><strong>Heavy hand = oppressive</strong></p>
<p>A <u>firm hand</u> is not the same as a <u>heavy hand</u>. If a person or organization has a <u>heavy hand</u>, they use a lot of force or power to control people and events. A <u>heavy hand</u> is often considered a bad thing. When you deal with a situation with a <u>heavy hand</u>, you could be seen as <strong>oppressive</strong>. Someone who is <u>heavy-handed</u> is severe or <strong>harsh</strong> when dealing with others or when dealing with a situation.</p>
<p>Sometimes we call this an <u>iron hand</u> or even an <u>iron fist</u>. A fist is a closed hand that is used for hitting.</p>
<p><strong>High-handed = arrogant &amp; condescending</strong></p>
<p>Now, what kind of person has a <u>high hand</u>? Someone who has a <u>high hand</u> is <strong>domineering</strong>. They like to be in control. They are bossy.</p>
<p>Sometimes we use the adjective <u>high-handed.</u></p>
<p><u>High-handed</u> people do not consider the rights, concerns, thoughts, or feelings of others. They look down on people. In other words, they are <strong>arrogant</strong> and <strong>condescending</strong>.</p>
<p>Hand expressions can also describe our involvement in a situation. Let's look at a couple examples.</p>
<p>A friend of yours asks you to find a manager for her company. But you don't know anyone who fits the job description. So, you don't suggest anyone. You don't <u>have a hand in</u> the selection. If you have <u>a hand in something</u>, you have helped to make it happen.</p>
<p>Your friend was able to find someone for the job through another person – someone you know. Let's call him Bob. You know Bob, and you don't trust Bob. So, you warn your friend. But they don't take the warning seriously. In the end, Bob is a terrible choice. He steals a lot of money from your friend's company. Your friend is <strong>furious!</strong> And you feel bad.</p>
<p><strong>Clean hands = innocent</strong></p>
<p>But in this matter, your <u>hands are clean</u>. You did nothing wrong. In fact, you tried to warn your friend. We use this expression to state innocence in a bad situation.</p>
<p>Here's another example. Let's say you are babysitting some children. They want to make a cake. And they make a total mess in the kitchen. Flour, sugar, and broken eggs are everywhere. When their parents come home and see the <strong>mess</strong>, you can say you did not <u>have a hand</u> in it. The kids did it all. All you did was turn on the oven.</p>
<p>Maybe these kids do this every time you watch them. You are tired of it – even though they do make tasty cake. So, you <u>throw your hands up</u>! When you <u>throw your hands up</u>, you are tired of fighting something. It is a sign that you give up.</p>
<p>A good word that describes this feeling is <strong>exasperation. </strong>People who are exasperated are tired of something, and they often throw their hands in the air.</p>
<p>And that's the end of this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>. Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>bare</strong> <em>-adj. </em>lacking clothing</p>
<p><strong>pride</strong> <em>-n. </em>reasonable self-esteem <strong>: </strong>confidence and satisfaction in oneself</p>
<p><strong>strict </strong><em>-adj. </em>severe in discipline</p>
<p><strong>oppressive</strong> <em>-adj. </em>cruel or harsh without just cause</p>
<p><strong>harsh</strong> <em>-adj.</em> making many or difficult demands</p>
<p><strong>domineering</strong> <em>-adj. </em>inclined to exercise arbitrary and overbearing control over others</p>
<p><strong>arrogant</strong> <em>-adj. </em>showing an offensive attitude of superiority</p>
<p><strong>condescending </strong><em>-adj. </em>showing or characterized by a patronizing or superior attitude toward others</p>
<p><strong>furious </strong><em>-adj. </em>exhibiting anger</p>
<p><strong>mess </strong><em>-n. </em>a disordered, untidy, offensive, or unpleasant state or condition</p>
<p><strong>exasperated </strong><em>-v. </em>having or showing strong feelings of irritation or annoyance : <strong>exasperation </strong><em>-n</em></p>
<p><em>We want to hear from you. Do you have similar expressions in your language? Our comment policy is </em><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.51voa.com/p/5378.html">here</a><em>.</em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>New Food Flavors Coming to Stores  (2024/5/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/new-food-flavors-coming-to-stores.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Gregory Stachel</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">24 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>In New York, Van Leeuwen Ice Cream brings people in with classic <strong>flavors</strong> like vanilla and pistachio. But, sometimes, the ice cream maker adds what it calls a "<strong>shock</strong> flavor," like Hidden Valley Ranch or pizza, to the treat.</p>
<p>Recently, chocolate maker Hershey added pink lemonade, a summer drink flavor, to its candy Kit Kats. And Frito-Lay introduced potato chips that taste like strawberries with a little bit of bacon.</p>
<p>Not to be outdone, Britain's food company Little Moons produced fish-and-chip mochi ice cream flavor while Walkers celebrated the holidays with a potato chip flavor of Brussels sprouts.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Ben Van Leeuwen scoops Kraft Mac &amp; Cheese flavored ice cream Wednesday, May 15, 2024, in the Brooklyn borough of New York. (AP Photo/Frank Franklin II)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/f195ee67-0812-4794-9267-9e6810f9c67f_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Ben Van Leeuwen scoops Kraft Mac &amp; Cheese flavored ice cream Wednesday, May 15, 2024, in the Brooklyn borough of New York. (AP Photo/Frank Franklin II)</span></div>
<p>Usually, these flavor combinations are introduced for a limited time. But sometimes the flavors are so popular that they become permanent additions. That is what happened with Frito-Lay's Flamin' Hot Dill Pickle chips in 2019.</p>
<p>While it would be easy to say the new and surprising flavors are produced to get attention on social media, experts say there is more to the story.</p>
<p>They say food companies are reacting to people's changing and expanding tastes while also trying to stay current and win over space in stores.</p>
<p>Kristen Braun works for Chicago-based food and drink company Mondelez International. She says people now want more than just one flavor and "companies are finding the freedom to explore a little bit more and get more creative."</p>
<p>Mondelez plans to release Sour Patch Kids Oreos – a kind of sweet vanilla cream-filled cookies combined with sour candies. The flavor is one of more than ten different Oreo flavors being sold this year for a limited time of nine weeks.</p>
<p>Mark Lang teaches food marketing at the University of Tampa in Florida. He said that manufacturers and their suppliers have increased their ability to create such products. That has made it easier for them to experiment and put out limited <strong>editions</strong> more often.</p>
<p>Kyle Shadix is a research <strong>chef</strong> for the drink company PepsiCo. He said members of Generation Z, born between 1997 and 2012, are also fueling new ideas.</p>
<p>Shadix is currently experimenting with Mexican, Korean and Japanese flavors. "Gen Z is going to drive us faster. We're going to start to see even more exploration quicker than in the past because they're just so open to it."</p>
<p>Experimenting with new flavors can increase sales in several ways. Sometimes they bring in new buyers to a product. And sometimes they also influence buyers to pick up more of the <strong>original</strong> flavor.</p>
<p>Russell Zwanka is director of the food marketing program at Western Michigan University. He said, "Sour Patch Oreos sound interesting, but nobody wants to risk buying Oreos that don't taste good, so people buy both."</p>
<p>When companies combine products, they are trying to build a link in people's minds. For example, Lang said when Pepsi combined its drink with Peeps candy flavor, it sent a message that Pepsi is current and fun.</p>
<p>But new flavor combinations do not always work.</p>
<p>Ben Van Leeuwen, the founder of the ice cream company bearing his name, said he could not eat more than a few bites of his company's Hidden Valley Ranch ice cream. It contained onion and garlic powders. And the "shock flavor" did not become a permanent part of his company's offerings because of their lower "eat-ability," he said.</p>
<p>But Lang thinks the more time people spend in restaurants or trying out new foods, the more they seek out unusual flavors.</p>
<p>He said as humans, "We like to experiment."</p>
<p>I'm Gregory Stachel.</p>
<p><em>Dee-Ann Durbin reported this story for The Associated Press. Gregory Stachel adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>shock </strong><em>– adj. </em>used to describe something that surprises and usually upsets people</p>
<p><strong>flavor </strong><em>– n. </em>the quality of something that you can taste</p>
<p><strong>edition </strong><em>– n. </em>a particular version of a product</p>
<p><strong>chef </strong><em>– n. </em>a professional cook who usually is in charge of a kitchen in a restaurant</p>
<p><strong>original </strong><em>– adj. </em>happening or existing first or at the beginning</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Conflict Hurts Mali's Tourism Industry  (2024/5/25) | 战乱损害马里的旅游业</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/conflict-hurts-mali-s-tourism-industry.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>Kola Bah used to earn money as a guide in Mali's historic city of Djenné, once a center of Islamic learning.<br/>
科拉·巴赫曾在马里历史名城杰内当导游赚钱，杰内曾是伊斯兰学术中心。</p>
<p>The city is known for its large Grand Mosque of Djenné. The religious center has been on the UNESCO World Heritage in Danger list since 2016.<br/>
这座城市以其巨大的杰内大清真寺而闻名。自2016年以来，该宗教中心一直被联合国教科文组织列入世界濒危遗产名录。</p>
<p>The world's largest mud-brick building used to draw tens of thousands of visitors to central Mali every year. Now, the structure is threatened by conflict between rebels, government forces and other groups.<br/>
这座世界上最大的砖土建筑过去每年吸引数以万计的游客来到马里中部。现在，该建筑受到叛军、政府军和其他组织之间冲突的威胁。</p>
<p>Bah says the money he used to earn was enough to support his family, which now includes nine children, and to pay for a small group of cattle.<br/>
巴赫说，他以前赚的钱足以养活他的家庭（现在这个家庭有九个孩子），还可以养一小群牛。</p>
<p>But now, few visitors come to the city. Bah has been largely out of work. When he needs money, he sells some of his cattle.<br/>
但现在，很少有游客来这座城市。巴赫基本上处于失业状态。当他需要钱时，他会卖掉一些牛。</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: bold;">Grand Mosque<br/>
大清真寺</span></p>
<p>Djenné is one of the oldest towns in sub-Saharan Africa. It has served as a market center and an important link in the trans-Saharan gold trade. Almost 2,000 of its traditional houses still survive in the old town.<br/>
杰内是撒哈拉以南非洲最古老的城镇之一。它一直是跨撒哈拉黄金贸易的市场中心和重要纽带。近2000栋传统房屋仍保留在老城区。</p>
<p>The Grand Mosque, built in 1907 on the area of an older mosque dating back to the 13th century, is worked on every year by local people. The work is a ritual that brings together the entire city. The large, earth-colored structure requires a new layer of mud before the rainy season starts.<br/>
建于1907年的大清真寺坐落在一座可追溯到13世纪的古老清真寺的原址上，当地人每年都在修建。这项工作是一种将整个城市聚集在一起的仪式。这个巨大的土色建筑在雨季开始前需要覆盖一层新泥。</p>
<p>Women are responsible for carrying water from the nearby river to mix with clay and rice hulls. This mixture is the mud used to cover the wall of the structure. Adding a new layer of mud is a job for men. The joyful ritual is a source of pride for a city that has fallen on hard times, uniting people of all ages.<br/>
妇女负责从附近的河里运水，将粘土和稻壳混合。这种混合物就是用来覆盖建筑物墙壁的泥浆。覆盖一层新泥是男人的工作。对于一座经历了艰难时期的城市来说，这种欢乐的仪式是一种骄傲，它将各个年龄段的人们团结在一起。</p>
<p>Bamouyi Trao Traoré is one of Djenné's lead builders. He said they worked as a team from the very start. This year's wall covering took place earlier in the month.<br/>
巴莫阿依·特拉奥·特拉奥雷是杰内大清真寺的主要建设者之一。他说他们从一开始就是一个团队。今年的墙面覆盖工作在本月早些时候进行。</p>
<p>"Each one of us goes to a certain spot to supervise," he said. "This is how we do it until the whole thing is done. We organize ourselves, we supervise the younger ones."<br/>
他说：“我们每个人都会去某个地方监督。我们就是这样做的，直到全部完工。我们自我组织起来，我们监督年轻人。”</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: bold;">Conflict and the future<br/>
冲突与未来</span></p>
<p>Mali's conflict broke out following a coup in 2012. Militant groups took control of important northern cities. A French-led military operation pushed them out of the city centers the following year, but the success was short-lived.<br/>
马里的冲突在2012年政变后爆发。激进组织控制了北方重要城市。第二年，一场由法国领导的军事行动将他们赶出了市中心，但这场胜利维持没多久。</p>
<p>The militants regrouped and launched attacks on the Malian military, as well as the United Nations, French and other forces in the country. The militants publicly stated their connection to al-Qaida and the Islamic State group.<br/>
武装分子重新集结，对马里军方以及该国境内的联合国、法国等部队发动袭击。武装分子公开表示他们与基地组织以及伊斯兰国组织有联系。</p>
<p>Sidi Keita is the director of Mali's national tourism agency in the capital of Bamako. Keita said the drop in tourism was sharp following the violence.<br/>
西迪·凯塔是马里首都巴马科国家旅游局局长。凯塔表示，暴力事件发生后，旅游业急剧下降。</p>
<p>"It was really a popular destination," he said, describing tens of thousands of visitors a year and adding that today, tourists are rare in Mali.<br/>
“这里曾是一个颇受欢迎的旅游目的地，”他描述每年有数以万计的游客，并补充说，如今马里的游客很少。</p>
<p>Despite being one of Africa's top gold producers, Mali ranks among the least developed nations in the world, with almost half of its 22 million people living below the national poverty line. Without tourism, few means are left for Malians to make a living.<br/>
尽管马里是非洲最大的黄金生产国之一，但它是世界上最不发达国家之一，其2200万人口中有近一半生活在国家贫困线以下。没有旅游业，马里人几乎没有谋生手段。</p>
<p>Anger over what many Malians call "the crisis" is rising. The country also saw two more coups since 2020, during a wave of political instability in West and Central Africa.<br/>
对许多马里人称之为“危机”的愤怒情绪正在上升。在西非和中非的政治不稳定浪潮中，该国自2020年以来又发生了两次政变。</p>
<p>Moussa Moriba Diakité is head of Djenne's cultural office, which works to save the city's heritage. Diakité said there are other difficulties beyond security — including illegal digs and waste disposal in the city.<br/>
穆萨·莫里巴·迪亚基特是杰内文化办公室的负责人，该办公室致力于保护这座城市的遗产。迪亚基特说，除了安全之外，还有其他困难，包括城内的非法挖掘和废物处理。</p>
<p>He said the office is trying to send a message that security is not as bad as it seems. The office also hopes to get more young people involved in the mud-covering ritual, to help the new generation recognize its importance.<br/>
他说，该办公室正试图传递一个信息，即安全并不像看上去那么糟糕。该办公室还希望让更多的年轻人参与到覆泥仪式中来，帮助新一代认识到它的重要性。</p>
<p>"It's not easy to get people to understand the benefits of preserving cultural heritage right away," he said.<br/>
他说：“要让人们立即了解保护文化遗产的好处并不容易。”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.<br/>
我是约翰·拉塞尔。(51VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Improve Your Vocabulary: Part 2  (2024/5/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/improve-your-vocabulary-part-2.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Yaroslav Khrokalo</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">24 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher,</em> we continue our answer about the best way to expand your <strong>vocabulary</strong>.</p>
<p>Last week, we said the best way to improve vocabulary is to really "know a word." We talked about the form of a word -- or how it sounds, is written, and what its parts are.</p>
<p>Today let's talk about the meaning of words.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Improve Your Vocabulary: Part 2" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-444f-08dc78d9e595_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Improve Your Vocabulary: Part 2</span></div>
<p>Knowing the meaning of a word seems easy: translate it into your native language or look up the definition in a dictionary. But, to fully know the meaning of a word in English, one definition is often not enough.</p>
<p>English words are famous for having more than one definition. For example, look at the word "run" in these sentences.</p>
<p><em>I'm going to <u>run</u> to the shop.</em></p>
<p><em>She <u>runs</u> the local bakery.</em></p>
<p><em>Water <u>was running</u> down the table.</em></p>
<p><em>All the papers <u>are running</u> the story.</em></p>
<p>The first <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/run">definition in Merriam-Webster's dictionary</a> for "run" is to go faster than a walk. That is certainly the meaning of run in the first sentence but not in the others.</p>
<p>When we say, "<em>she <u>runs</u> the local bakery"</em>, we mean she is the person who <em><u>operates, manages</u></em> or <em><u>owns</u></em> the shop.</p>
<p>We could say "<em>Water <u>was running</u> down the table</em>" or "<em>Water <u>was flowing</u> down the table."</em></p>
<p>And when "<em>all the papers <u>are running</u> the story", they <u>publish</u></em> it.</p>
<p>We also have to know the ideas or feelings that a word suggests to fully understand the meaning of a word.</p>
<p>Let's look at the first example with the word "run."</p>
<p><em>I'm going to <u>run</u> to the shop.</em></p>
<p>This is different than saying:</p>
<p><em>I'm going to <u>go</u> to the shop</em>.</p>
<p>The second example simply states that we are going to the shop. But the word "run" tells that the trip will be fast.</p>
<p>When we look at the meaning of English words in this way, we can see that our vocabulary expands by fully understanding a word's meaning.</p>
<p>However, we cannot just exchange one word for another without changing the overall meaning of the sentence. So, next week we will take a look at synonyms - or words that have the same or nearly the same meaning.</p>
<p>Do you have a question about American English? Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="mailto:learningenglish@voanews.com">learningenglish@voanews.com</a>.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask </em><em>a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Gena Bennett.</p>
<p><em>Yaroslav Khrokalo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>vocabulary</strong>–<em>n</em>. all the words a person knows</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Microsoft Announces New PCs with Built-in AI  (2024/5/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/microsoft-announces-new-pcs-with-built-in-ai.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">23 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>American software maker Microsoft says it will release new computer models with built-in artificial intelligence (AI) tools.</p>
<p>The new computers will be equipped with a new version of Microsoft's existing AI tool, called Copilot. Copilot can operate across a series of Microsoft business products.</p>
<p>The Copilot service is based on OpenAI's ChatGPT tool, which launched in late 2022. ChatGPT is an AI tool designed to <strong>interact</strong> smoothly with humans and perform high-level writing and creative work. Such tools are also known as chatbots or generative AI.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Brett Ostrum, Microsoft corporate vice president of Surface, holds up the new Surface Laptop and Surface Pro with built-in AI at an event of the company's AI assistant, Copilot, Monday, May 20, 2024, in Redmond, Wash. (AP Photo/Lindsey Wasson)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-7b32-08dc79dfc264_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Brett Ostrum, Microsoft corporate vice president of Surface, holds up the new Surface Laptop and Surface Pro with built-in AI at an event of the company's AI assistant, Copilot, Monday, May 20, 2024, in Redmond, Wash. (AP Photo/Lindsey Wasson)</span></div>
<p>Microsoft is a major investor in OpenAI. It is providing computing power and support for ChatGPT's operations.</p>
<p>Microsoft recently introduced the new tools at an event at its headquarters in Seattle, Washington. Chief executive Satya Nadella announced that the new computers will come loaded with the new Copilot+ system. The company <a class="wsw__a" href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2024/05/20/introducing-copilot-pcs/">said</a> these new Windows-based PCs – which it calls "AI-ready" – will be "the fastest, most intelligent" ever built.</p>
<p>The event came one day before Microsoft's yearly developer conference. That is where Microsoft introduces its latest new products and services to developers and the public.</p>
<p>The announcement is Microsoft's latest move to deploy OpenAI's technology through Copilot to many product offerings. The system is already available for the company's Teams, Outlook, Bing search engine and Windows operating system.</p>
<p>Microsoft said its AI-based PCs will start being released on June 18 on the company's own Surface models. It will also be on PCs produced by partners. These include Lenovo, Dell, Acer and HP.</p>
<p>"These improvements provide the most <strong>compelling</strong> reason to <strong>upgrade</strong> your PC in a long time," said Microsoft Vice President Yusuf Mehdi.</p>
<p>Microsoft said the AI operations on the new PCs will take place on the device itself rather than a cloud server. This means users will not have to wait for information to be sent to and from the company's data centers or pay extra money for this service.</p>
<p>Microsoft has also promised that any <strong>tracking</strong> activity will only be done and saved on the device, not on company servers. Users will also be able to choose not to be tracked, the company added.</p>
<p>The Copilot+ AI offerings include live language <strong>translation </strong>and image creation. It also offers the ability to interact with the PCs through voice commands instead of clicking to perform certain jobs.</p>
<p>The new offerings also include a tool called Windows Recall. This gives the Copilot+ assistant what Microsoft describes as a "photographic memory" of a person's computer activity. The tool is designed to remember the things a user does on the PC in an effort to predict what the user might want to do next.</p>
<p>It's a step toward machines that "instantly see us, hear, reason about our <strong>intent</strong> and our surroundings," Microsoft's Nadella said. He added: "We're entering this new era where computers not only understand us, but can actually <strong>anticipate</strong> what we want and our intent."</p>
<p>Nadella's announcement on AI comes shortly after some other major technology players announced new releases of their latest AI assistance systems.</p>
<p>Last week, Google introduced an improved search engine that shows brief AI-produced results before direct website links. The company also showed off an AI assistant called Astra, which is still in development. Astra is designed to be able to "see" and talk about things shown through a smartphone's camera.</p>
<p>OpenAI introduced its latest chatbot version, ChatGPT-4o last week. Company officials demonstrated the new tool, which showed improved human <strong>characteristics</strong> that can give opinions about things. The new version also comes with tools that aim to judge a person's emotions.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press, Reuters and Agence France-Presse reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong><strong> </strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>compelling </strong><em>– adj. </em>very exciting or interesting and making you want to watch, listen, etc.</p>
<p><strong>upgrade </strong><em>– v. </em>to improve something so that it is of a higher quality or a newer model</p>
<p><strong>track </strong><em>– v. </em>to follow the online activities of a user</p>
<p><strong>translate </strong><em>– v. </em>to change written or spoken words from one language to another</p>
<p><strong>intent </strong><em>– n. </em>what a person wants and plans to do</p>
<p><strong>anticipate </strong><em>– v. </em>to expect something or to prepare for something before it happens</p>
<p><strong>characteristic </strong><em>– n. </em>a typical quality that makes one person or thing different from others</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Businesses Aim to Get More Africans Using Smartphones  (2024/5/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/businesses-aim-to-get-more-africans-using-smartphones.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Dan Friedell</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">23 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>Modern smart phones are still seen as a <strong>curiosity</strong> in some parts of sub-Saharan Africa.</p>
<p>Experts believe mobile internet service is an important tool for economic growth in places such as Ghana. However, only about 25 percent of adults in the area south of the Sahara Desert have a tool that provides internet service.</p>
<p>Anita Akpeere is one person who uses an internet-connected smart mobile phone in her food business in Ghana's capital, Accra. She makes rice and dumplings, a kind of local food. Her phone alerts her when a new order comes in.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Anita Akpeere, who uses her mobile phone to run her business, stands inside her restaurant in Accra, Ghana, Tuesday, April 23, 2024. (AP Photo/ Misper Apawu)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/3c6d0d9f-c3c3-4d43-b93f-d152862ef7ed_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Anita Akpeere, who uses her mobile phone to run her business, stands inside her restaurant in Accra, Ghana, Tuesday, April 23, 2024. (AP Photo/ Misper Apawu)</span></div>
<p>Claire Sibthorpe is head of digital <strong>inclusion</strong> at the Britain-based mobile-phone manufacturers group GSMA. She said the cost of new phones is the main barrier to more Africans getting internet service. The lowest-priced smart phones still cost about 95 percent of monthly pay for the poorest 20 percent of the population.</p>
<p>Jenny Aker is a professor at Tufts University near Boston, Massachusetts. She said mobile technology is more important in Africa than in more developed parts of the world. She said the small programs that run on smart phones, called apps, are able to overcome a lack of <strong>infrastructure</strong>. That is why more people in Africa need phones that connect to the internet. She said people without bank accounts use their phones to send and receive mobile money. Other people can use apps that help with farming. Still others use apps that help them learn languages.</p>
<p>Uniti Networks has a "super app" that permits smart phone users in poor places to use lots of other apps. The business also has a payment plan that permits people in Ghana who do not have much money to get smart phones. Cyril Fianyo is a farmer who uses the plan. He is a 64-year-old farmer in the country's eastern Volta area. He paid about $25 to get his phone and will pay the remaining $66 in regular payments. The phone has an app called Cocoa Link that helps him learn planting methods for his cocoa crop.</p>
<p>In the past, Fianyo used his <strong>intuition</strong> to decide when to plant. However, now he thinks Cocoa Link will look at the upcoming weather and tell him the right time to plant. He hopes it will lead to a bigger crop.</p>
<p>Kami Dar is chief of Uniti Networks. He said mobile phones could also improve Africa's health care system. So far, he said, Uniti has 650 <strong>participants</strong> in its program that permits regular payments over time. The goal is to have 100,000 people taking part within five years.</p>
<p>Uniti, however, will only reach its <strong>customer</strong> goal if more people in Ghana learn how to use smart phones. But there is both a language barrier and a technology barrier. Although many people in Ghana speak English, some cannot read the language. In addition, many people do not know how to operate a smart phone. They will have to learn to read English and learn how to use the phone.</p>
<p>The barriers mean many people decide a smart phone is not worth the cost.</p>
<p>Alain Capo-Chichi is trying to fix that problem. He is the head of CERCO Group, a company that developed a smart phone that works with only voice commands. "If you buy a car, it's because you can drive it." The voice control, he said, will permit more people to "drive" their smart phone. His system supports 50 African languages, including Swahili, Yoruba and Wolof.</p>
<p>Aker, the professor near Boston, said it is unclear at this time how many apps will be able to improve life in Africa. She has looked at health and farming apps. She said the health apps mostly tell people when to take medicine or advise them of the need to be vaccinated. The farming apps, she noted, do not clearly show evidence of producing more productive crops.</p>
<p>Capo-Chichi said one reason people are unsure about investing in smart phones is the lack of useful apps.</p>
<p>Dar from Uniti Networks said app makers are trying to do better. He gave the example of an app that helps cocoa farmers save money for retirement. At first, the app was hard to use, so many farmers needed help or decided it was not worth their time. But the company that provided the savings service fixed some of the problems.</p>
<p>Over time, the apps improve. One example is a health app that helps women follow their reproductive, or menstrual, cycle to avoid pregnancy. Another app helps people find medicinal plants.</p>
<p>Aker said more investment in public services is needed for Africa. But she also worried about a dependence on smart phones and said some people could lose personal data to criminals or <strong>hackers</strong>.</p>
<p>The expert noted that companies that make apps can only do well if they have more users. Companies that are creating payment plans for Africans can only make money if they get more customers.</p>
<p>In addition, Aker noted the phones can still make a difference for some. She noted that the United Nations says over 700 million people around the world are illiterate, meaning they cannot read or write any language. Aker said smart phones can help people learn to read and write.</p>
<p>However, curiosity may still be the biggest driver of smart phone sales, especially if the cost is not so high.</p>
<p>Back in Fianyo's fields, his new smartphone has <strong>attracted</strong> interest. "This is something I would like to be part of," said neighboring farmer Godsway Kwamigah.</p>
<p>I'm Dan Friedell. And I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Dan Friedell adapted this story for Learning English based on a report by The Associated Press.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>curiosity </strong><em>–n.</em> the state of mind of being interested in something and wanting to learn more about it</p>
<p><strong>inclusion </strong><em>–n.</em> the act of making a group out of many different things</p>
<p><strong>infrastructure </strong><em>–n.</em> things like roads, bridges, electricity lines and other structures that are associated with civilization</p>
<p><strong>intuition </strong><em>–n.</em> a sense of knowing something without proof or evidence</p>
<p><strong>participant </strong><em>–n.</em> a person who takes part in an activity with a group</p>
<p><strong>hacker </strong><em>–n.</em> a person who gets inside a computer system to take information or to cause damage</p>
<p><strong>attract </strong><em>–v.</em> to cause someone to become interested in something</p>
<p><em>We want to hear from you. Do you have a smart phone? How does it help you?</em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Business, Political Leaders Agree to Safely Develop, Deploy AI  (2024/5/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/business-political-leaders-agree-to-safely-develop-deploy-ai.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">22 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>Major AI developers and top government officials have agreed on measures that aim to ensure that artificial intelligence (AI) systems are safely built and deployed.</p>
<p>The announcement came at the end of a two-day meeting in Seoul, South Korea. The gathering continues discussions from a similar event held last November in Britain. The goal of both meetings was to bring AI developers together with government representatives to establish goals and guidelines related to safe AI development.</p>
<p>Many governments and international organizations across the world are seeking to create rules for AI technology development. Officials and activists have raised concerns that AI systems could present risks. The concerns include AI possibly attacking online systems controlling infrastructure. Another concern is that AI systems might help spread misinformation or create "<a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.51voa.com/a/deepfake-of-biden-s-voice-called-early-example-of-us-election-disinformation/7455392.html">deepfakes</a>" to mislead voters in elections.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Han Duck-soo, South Korean Prime Minister, gives a speech during the opening ceremony of the AI Global Forum in Seoul, South Korea, May 22, 2024. (REUTERS/Kim Soo-hyeon)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-0a06-08dc7a8cf5ce_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Han Duck-soo, South Korean Prime Minister, gives a speech during the opening ceremony of the AI Global Forum in Seoul, South Korea, May 22, 2024. (REUTERS/Kim Soo-hyeon)</span></div>
<p>Legislative attempts to create rules for AI development, especially in the United States, have not been successful. Last October, President Joe Biden <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.51voa.com/a/biden-signs-order-requiring-artificial-intelligence-safeguards/7333444.html">issued an executive order</a> calling on companies working on AI projects to develop guidelines for protecting users of the technology.</p>
<p>At the latest meeting, officials from 16 different technology companies signed a voluntary agreement on Tuesday. In it, they promised to develop AI technology in ways that limit possible harm to the public. Among the companies were American-based Google, IBM, Amazon, Microsoft and OpenAI. Others included China's Alibaba and Tencent, as well as South Korea's Samsung Electronics and G42 from the United Arab Emirates.</p>
<p>The British government co-led the summit with South Korea. It said in a statement that the leaders in attendance sought to establish "a common understanding of AI safety and <strong>align</strong> their AI research."</p>
<p>One of the main parts of the latest agreement calls for creating a network of publicly supported safety <strong>institutes</strong> designed to guide research and testing of AI technologies. Some of these institutes have already been set up by Britain, the U.S. and Singapore.</p>
<p>United Nations Secretary-General Antonio Guterres told the meeting through a video link that AI technology has continued to quickly develop since the group's last meeting in Britain. Such development had led to "life-changing technological <strong>advances</strong>." But Guterres added that the progress had also created "life-threatening new risks."</p>
<p>"We cannot sleepwalk into a <strong>dystopian</strong> future," he added. "Where the power of AI is controlled by a few people — or worse, by <strong>algorithms</strong> beyond human understanding," he said.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, the U.N. General Assembly approved its first resolution on AI. The measure received support from all 193 U.N. member states. It called for international efforts to ensure that new technologies help all nations, respect human rights, and stay "safe, secure and trustworthy."</p>
<p>Attendees agreed on the need for AI companies to exchange ideas on their progress and development methods. The group also agreed to provide information on safety.</p>
<p>South Korea's science and information minister, Lee Jong-Ho, spoke to the gathering before it ended on Wednesday. He said worldwide AI development had reached a point where "cooperation is not an <strong>option</strong>; it is a necessity."</p>
<p>AI experts welcomed the steps to start creating rules, or regulations, to keep the technology safe. But some noted that such rules need to be enforced to be effective.</p>
<p>Francine Bennett is director of the AI-centered Ada Lovelace Institute in Britain. She told Reuters news agency, "We need to move past voluntary...the people affected should be setting the rules <strong>via</strong> governments."</p>
<p>AI companies should be able to prove their products meet established regulations before they even reach the market, said Max Tegmark. He is president of the Future of Life Institute, a nonprofit bringing attention to the risks of AI. Tegmark said companies should equate safety with profit and attempt to limit possible harms during the development of systems.</p>
<p>South Korean minister Lee said a big problem is that any laws aimed at making AI systems safer are far behind continuous development and public releases. He told Reuters, "But for safe use by the public, there needs to be <strong>flexible</strong> laws and regulations in place."</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters and Agence France-Presse.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>align </strong><em>– v. </em>to support the opinions of a political group, country, etc.</p>
<p><strong>institute </strong><em>– n. </em>an organization where people do a particular kind of scientific, educational or social work</p>
<p><strong>advancement </strong><em>– n. </em>progress</p>
<p><strong>dystopian </strong><em>– adj. </em>relating to a very bad or unfair society in which there is a lot of suffering</p>
<p><strong>algorithm </strong><em>– n. </em>a set of steps that are followed to complete a computing process or problem</p>
<p><strong>option </strong><em>– n. </em>a thing that is chosen from a set of possibilities</p>
<p><strong>via </strong><em>–prep. </em>through</p>
<p><strong>flexible </strong><em>– adj. </em>able to change or be changed easily according to a particular situation</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>When Does Air Turbulence Become Dangerous?  (2024/5/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/when-does-air-turbulence-become-dangerous.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">22 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>If you have flown on an airplane before, you might have experienced turbulence. Turbulence is a sudden movement of air. It can move the plane around and force sudden changes in height.</p>
<p>Flying through mild turbulence feels like driving a car over big bumps or holes in the road.</p>
<p>But passengers on a Singapore Airlines flight on Tuesday experienced severe turbulence. Several people were injured and one person, a 73-year-old British man, died. The exact cause of the man's death is still unclear.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="The Boeing 777-300ER aircraft of Singapore Airlines is parked at Suvarnabhumi International Airport, near Bangkok, Thailand, May 22, 2024. The plane dropped around 1,800 meters in about three minutes after hitting severe turbulence over the Indian Ocean. (AP Photo/Sakchai Lalit)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-1178-08dc7a6c8cce_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">The Boeing 777-300ER aircraft of Singapore Airlines is parked at Suvarnabhumi International Airport, near Bangkok, Thailand, May 22, 2024. The plane dropped around 1,800 meters in about three minutes after hitting severe turbulence over the Indian Ocean. (AP Photo/Sakchai Lalit)</span></div>
<p>While turbulence-related deaths are rare, injuries have increased over the years. Some weather and <strong>aviation</strong> experts have noted increasing reports of turbulence. They say climate change may be behind the increase.</p>
<p><strong>What is turbulence?</strong></p>
<p>Turbulence is <strong>unstable</strong> air that moves unpredictably. Most people link it with heavy storms. But the most dangerous kind is clear-air turbulence. This often happens with no warning signs in the sky ahead.</p>
<p>Clear-air turbulence happens most often in or near rivers of air called jet streams. The cause is something called wind shear. That is when two huge air masses near each other move at different speeds. If the difference in speed is big enough, it breaks into circular movements.</p>
<p>Thomas Guinn is an aviation science expert at the Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University in Daytona Beach, Florida. He said, "When you get strong wind shear near the jet stream, it can cause the air to overflow. And that creates these <strong>chaotic</strong> motions in the air."</p>
<p><strong>How common are turbulent-related injuries?</strong></p>
<p>The U.S. National Transportation Safety Board (NTSB) <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.ntsb.gov/safety/safety-studies/Documents/SS2101.pdf">reported</a> that more than one-third of all airline incidents in the U.S. from 2009 to 2018 were related to turbulence. Most of them resulted in one or more serious injuries to passengers, but no damage to the plane.</p>
<p>Between 2009 and 2022, the NTSB said 163 people were injured seriously enough during turbulence events to require hospital treatment for at least two days. Most of those injured were flight attendants. They are especially at risk because they are more likely to be out of their seats during a flight.</p>
<p>Singapore Airlines said its plane dropped about 1,800 meters in about three minutes last Tuesday, after hitting severe turbulence over the Indian Ocean. In addition to the one death, six or seven passengers were severely injured. Several others suffered less serious injuries.</p>
<p>Larry Cornman is a scientist at the U.S. National Center for Atmospheric Research. He has studied turbulence for many years. He said, "It's not uncommon to have turbulence <strong>encounters</strong> that cause minor injuries up to, say, a broken bone,... But <strong>fatalities</strong> are very, very rare — especially for large transport aircraft."</p>
<p>Stuart Fox is with the International Air Transport Association. He said, until Tuesday, it had been 27 years since a passenger died following clear-air turbulence on a major airline.</p>
<p><strong>Can pilots avoid turbulence?</strong></p>
<p>Pilots use several methods to avoid turbulence, including using weather radar<strong> </strong>images. Sometimes they can simply see and fly around the storms.</p>
<p>But clear-air turbulence can happen unexpectedly.</p>
<p>Doug Moss is a former airline pilot and safety expert. He said air traffic controllers will warn pilots after another plane runs into clear-air turbulence. Many pilots also look at the upper-level jet streams along their flight path for signs of wind shear. They can plan to move above, below, or around those areas, he added.</p>
<p><strong>Does climate change lead to more turbulence?</strong></p>
<p>Some scientists note that reports of turbulence encounters are on the rise. There are several possible explanations for that. But several researchers have pointed to climate change.</p>
<p>Guinn, of Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University, explained that some experts predict climate change could change the jet stream and increase the wind shear. This would drive up turbulence in the air.</p>
<p>Paul Williams is a professor of atmospheric science at Britain's University of Reading. In a statement Tuesday, he said there was "strong evidence that turbulence is increasing because of climate change."</p>
<p>Williams said his research team recently discovered that severe clear-air turbulence in the North Atlantic has increased by 55 percent since 1979. The team estimated that severe turbulence in the jet streams could double or <strong>triple</strong> in the coming years under current conditions.</p>
<p>Other experts note that an increase in air travel could be the reason for the increase in turbulence encounters.</p>
<p><strong>How can travelers stay safe?</strong></p>
<p>Turbulence can be hard to predict. But experts note that the first line of defense in the air is keeping seat belts <strong>fastened</strong> whenever possible.</p>
<p>"Wear your seat belt," Guinn said. "That's just a really quick fix to prevent injury."</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p>And I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>Wyatte Grantham-Philips reported this story for The Associated Press. Hai Do adapted the story for Learning English.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>aviation</strong> - n. the business and practice of flying airplanes, helicopters...</p>
<p><strong>unstable</strong> - adj. having a physical state that can change easily</p>
<p><strong>chaotic</strong> - adj. in a state of complete confusion or disorder</p>
<p><strong>encounter</strong> - n. an occasion when you deal with or experience something</p>
<p><strong>fatality</strong> - n. a death that results from a disaster, accident</p>
<p><strong>triple</strong> - v. to cause something to become three times as many</p>
<p><strong>fasten</strong> - v. to close and attch something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Locals Report Monkey Deaths During Heat Wave in Mexico  (2024/5/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/locals-report-monkey-deaths-during-heat-wave-in-mexico.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Dan Novak</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">22 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>An environmental group is warning that the hot weather in Mexico is among the causes of many deaths of howler m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s.</p>
<p>Howler m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s are big <strong>primates</strong> known for the loud sound they make.</p>
<p>The Associated Press (AP) reported that the group Biodiversity Conservation of The Usumacinta said that at least 138 howler m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s have been found dead. The deaths have taken place in the state of Tabasco on the Gulf of Mexico. Local people rescued others, including five that were rushed to a local <strong>veterinarian</strong> who tried to save them.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A veterinarian feeds a young howler m&lt;I&gt;&lt;I&gt;onkey&lt;/I&gt;&lt;/I&gt; rescued amid extremely high temperatures in Tecolutilla, Tabasco state, Mexico, Tuesday, May 21, 2024. (AP Photo/Luis Sanchez)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-766a-08dc7a710886_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A veterinarian feeds a young howler m<i><i>onkey</i></i> rescued amid extremely high temperatures in Tecolutilla, Tabasco state, Mexico, Tuesday, May 21, 2024. (AP Photo/Luis Sanchez)</span></div>
<p>"They arrived in <strong>critical</strong> condition, with <strong>dehydration</strong> and fever," said Sergio Valenzuela. "It was a heatstroke."</p>
<p>Mexico's severe heat wave has been connected to the deaths of at least 26 people since March. Veterinarians and rescuers said it has killed tens or even hundreds of howler m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s. The AP said that one third of the country reported high temperatures of 45 degrees Celsius on Tuesday.</p>
<p>In the town of Tecolutilla, Tabasco, dead m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s started appearing in recent weeks. A local volunteer fire and rescue team recently brought in five of the creatures. Valenzuela told the AP that the volunteers "asked for help, they asked if I could examine some of the animals they had in their truck."</p>
<p>The veterinarian put ice on their <strong>limp</strong> hands and feet. They were given fluid with<strong> </strong>nutrients. The m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s appeared to be recovering. "They're recovering. They're aggressive...they're biting again," he said, noting that is a healthy sign.</p>
<p>Most are not so lucky. Wildlife biologist Gilberto Pozo counted about 138 of the animals dead or dying on the ground under trees. The deaths started in early May.</p>
<p>"They were in a state of severe dehydration, and they died within a matter of minutes," Pozo said. Already weakened, the falls from <strong>dozens</strong> of meters high cause more damage that often finishes the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s off.</p>
<p>Pozo said there were several causes for the deaths, including high heat, <strong>drought</strong>, forest fires and logging. All of that leads to less water, shade, and fruit for the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s to eat. Pozo noted that it is also possible a disease is causing the deaths.</p>
<p>Pozo said the local people have tried to help the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s, especially babies. They see the young animals around their farms. But he said that can be dangerous.</p>
<p>The "babies are very <strong>delicate</strong>, they can't be in a house where there are dogs or cats" because they have diseases that can be deadly for howler m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s, he said. After the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s recover, they must be released into the wild, Pozo added.</p>
<p>Pozo's group has set up special recovery stations for m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s. It currently holds five m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s, but birds and reptiles have also been affected. He is also trying to organize a team of specialized veterinarians to give the primates the care they need.</p>
<p>Below-average rainfall across the country so far this year has caused lakes and water supplies to dry up. Officials have had to provide water for hospitals and fire fighters. Low water levels at hydroelectric dams have led to electricity outages, or blackouts, in some parts of the country.</p>
<p>Pozo said the death of the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s says a lot about the state of the whole ecosystem.</p>
<p>He told the AP: "It is telling us something about what is happening with climate change."</p>
<p>I'm Dan Novak.</p>
<p><em>Dan Novak adapted this story for VOA Learning English based on reporting by The Associated Press. </em></p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><em>______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>primate </strong><em>–n.</em> an order of mammals that includes m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s and humans</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>veterinarian </strong><em>— n. </em>a doctor who treats animals</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>critical </strong><em>–adj.</em> very serious</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>dehydration </strong><em>— n. </em>the state of not having enough water</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>dozens</strong> <em>— n. (pl.) </em>groups of 12</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>limp </strong><em>— adj. </em>weak and unable to stand or move normally</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>drought </strong><em>— n. </em>when there is not enough rain in an area for an extended period</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>delicate </strong><em>— adj. </em>weak and unfirm</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scarlett Johansson Says ChatGPT Voice ‘Similar’ to Hers  (2024/5/22) | 斯嘉丽称chatgpt的语音像极了她的声音</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/scarlett-johansson-says-chatgpt-voice-similar-to-hers.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>The American artificial intelligence company OpenAI has removed one of its ChatGPT voices. The move came after actor Scarlett Johansson said the voice sounded "eerily similar" to her voice in the movie Her.<br/>
美国人工智能公司OpenAI已经删除了其ChatGPT的一种语音。此前，演员斯嘉丽·约翰逊表示，该语音与她在电影《她》中的声音听上去“惊人地相似”。</p>
<p>In a post Monday on the social media service X, OpenAI said it is "working to pause" Sky. That is the name of one of five voices that ChatGPT users can choose to speak with in its artificial intelligence (AI) chatbot.<br/>
周一，OpenAI在社交媒体服务X上发帖称，它正在“努力暂停”Sky语音。这是ChatGPT用户可以在其人工智能聊天机器人中选择与之对话的五种语音之一的名称。</p>
<p>In a statement, Johansson said that OpenAI CEO Sam Altman had asked her last September if she would lend her voice to the ChatGPT system. Johansson said she declined the offer.<br/>
约翰逊在一份声明中表示，OpenAI首席执行官萨姆·奥特曼去年9月曾问她是否愿意为ChatGPT系统提供语音。约翰逊说她拒绝了这个邀约。</p>
<p>Johansson said, "When I heard the released demo, I was shocked, angered and in disbelief that Mr. Altman would pursue a voice that sounded so eerily similar to mine." She added that her close friends and even the news media "could not tell the difference" between her voice and the voice of Sky.<br/>
约翰逊说：“当我听到发布会的演示时，我感到震惊、愤怒和难以置信，奥特曼先生会追求一种听起来与我如此相似的声音。她补充说，她的密友，甚至新闻媒体都“无法区分”她的声音和Sky的声音。</p>
<p>Johansson said OpenAI agreed to take down the Sky voice after her lawyers asked about the process by which the company came up with the voice.<br/>
约翰逊表示，在她的律师询问该公司创造该语音的过程后，OpenAI同意删除Sky语音。</p>
<p>OpenAI said in an online post that the voice of Sky belongs to a "different professional actress." But it added that it could not share the name of that actress for privacy reasons.<br/>
OpenAI在一篇网贴中表示，Sky语音来自于“另一位专业女演员”。但它补充说，出于隐私原因，它不能公开这位女演员的名字。</p>
<p>In an email sent to The Associated Press following Johansson's statement Monday, Altman said that OpenAI selected the voice actor behind Sky "before any outreach" to Johansson. "The voice of Sky is not Scarlett Johansson's, and it was never intended to resemble hers," Altman added.<br/>
在约翰逊周一发表声明后，奥特曼在发给美联社的一封电子邮件中表示，OpenAI“在与约翰逊接触之前”就选定了Sky语音背后的配音演员。奥特曼补充道：“Sky语音不是斯嘉丽·约翰逊的声音，也从来没有打算和她的声音相似。”</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: bold;">Voice Mode<br/>
语音模式</span></p>
<p>OpenAI added voice capabilities to ChatGPT last September. The feature is called "Voice Mode." It permits users to have a conversation with the AI assistant. In November, OpenAI announced that the feature would become free for all users with the mobile app.<br/>
去年9月，OpenAI为ChatGPT添加了语音功能。该功能被称为“语音模式”。它允许用户与人工智能助手进行对话。11月，OpenAI宣布该功能将免费提供给所有使用该移动应用程序的用户。</p>
<p>Last week, OpenAI showed off its latest AI model, called ChatGPT-4o. The program lets users speak to the chatbot and get real-time answers. The chatbot now has emotion in its voice and even tries to understand a person's emotional state by looking at a selfie video of their face.<br/>
上周，OpenAI展示了其最新的人工智能模型，名为ChatGPT-4o。该程序允许用户与聊天机器人对话并获得实时答案。该聊天机器人现在的声音富有情感，它甚至试图通过观察用户的面部自拍视频来了解他们的情绪状态。</p>
<p>The capabilities have brought comparisons to the 2013 movie Her. The film follows a man who falls in love with an AI assistant, which is voiced by Johansson.<br/>
这些能力被拿来与2013年的电影《她》相比较。这部电影讲述了一个男人爱上了由约翰逊配音的人工智能助理的故事。</p>
<p>Altman appeared to make the same comparison. He wrote the word "her" on the social media service X on the day of GPT-4o's release.<br/>
奥特曼似乎也做了同样的比较。GPT-4o发布当天，他在社交媒体服务X上写下了“她”一词。</p>
<p>I'm Ashley Thompson.<br/>
我是阿什利·汤普森。(51VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Tree Rings Show Summer of 2023 Was Very Hot  (2024/5/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/study-tree-rings-show-summer-of-2023-was-very-hot.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">21 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>A recent study found that the summer of 2023 was the hottest in the Northern Hemisphere in more than 2,000 years.</p>
<p>When the temperatures increased last year, many weather agencies said it was the hottest month, summer and year on record. But those records only go back to 1850 because they are based on thermometers - devices used for measuring temperature.</p>
<p>Now, however, scientists can look back to year one of the modern western <strong>calendar</strong>. And researchers have found no hotter northern summer than that of last year.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A woman watches the sun sets on a hot day, Aug. 20, 2023, in Kansas City, Mo. A new study on May 14, 2024, finds that the summer of 2023 was the hottest in the Northern Hemisphere in more than 2,000 years. (AP Photo/Charlie Riedel, File)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-1a5c-08dc75d9c6aa_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A woman watches the sun sets on a hot day, Aug. 20, 2023, in Kansas City, Mo. A new study on May 14, 2024, finds that the summer of 2023 was the hottest in the Northern Hemisphere in more than 2,000 years. (AP Photo/Charlie Riedel, File)</span></div>
<p>A study in the scientific publication Nature uses a well-established method and record of more than 10,000 tree rings to <strong>calculate</strong> summertime temperatures for each year since the year 1. No year came even close to last summer's high heat, said the study's lead writer Jan Esper of the Gutenberg Research College in Germany.</p>
<p>Before modern times, the hottest summer was in the year 246, Esper said.</p>
<p>Esper's paper showed that in the Northern Hemisphere, the summer of 2023 was as much as 1.2 degrees Celsius warmer than the summer of 246. In fact, 25 of the last 28 years have been hotter than that early medieval summer, said study co-writer Max Torbenson.</p>
<p>"That gives us a good idea of how extreme 2023 is," Esper told The Associated Press.</p>
<p>The team used thousands of trees in 15 different places in the Northern Hemisphere where there was enough data to get a good measure going back to year 1, Esper said. There was not quite enough tree data in the Southern Hemisphere to publish, but even the limited data showed something similar, he said.</p>
<p>Scientists looked at the rings of yearly tree growth to then give yearly dates to every ring, Torbenson suggested.</p>
<p>But outside experts had questions about the study. University of Pennsylvania climate scientist Michael Mann, who was not part of the study, wondered why researchers stopped their look back at year 1. Mann suggested other temperature estimates go back more than 20,000 years. He said just using tree rings is "considerably less <strong>reliable</strong>" than looking at all sorts of other data, including ice cores, <strong>corals</strong> and more.</p>
<p>Esper said his new study only uses tree data because it is exact enough to give summer-by-summer temperature estimates, which cannot be done with corals, ice<strong> cores </strong>and other data sources. Tree rings are higher resolution, he said.</p>
<p>The worldwide temperature records set last summer were so high "that it's not surprising they would ...clearly be the warmest in the past 2,000 years," said Berkeley Earth climate scientist Zeke Hausfather. Hausfather was not part of the study.</p>
<p>"It's likely the warmest summer in 120,000 years, though we cannot be absolutely sure," he added, because data exact to a year does not go back that far.</p>
<p>Because high-resolution yearly data does not go back that far, Esper said it is wrong for scientists and the media to call it the hottest in 120,000 years. Two thousand years is enough, he said.</p>
<p>Esper also said the period of 1850 to 1900 that scientists — especially the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change — use for the base period before warming may be a bit cooler than the instrumental records show.</p>
<p>The instruments back then were more often in the hot sun instead of sheltered from it, as they are now. And tree rings continue to show that it was about 0.2 degrees Celsius cooler than thermometers show.</p>
<p>That means there has been a bit more warming from human-caused climate change than most scientists calculate, an issue being examined by researchers over the last few years.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Seth Borenstein reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted if for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>calendar </strong>– n. an arrangement of time into days, weeks, months, and years</p>
<p><strong>calculate </strong>– v. to determine by mathematical processes</p>
<p><strong>reliable </strong>– adj. giving the same result on many trials; dependable</p>
<p><strong>coral </strong>– n. a kind of animal (a polyp) that forms reefs</p>
<p><strong>core </strong>– n. a part (such as a thin cylinder of material) removed from the interior of a mass especially to determine composition</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>For Children of Gaza, War Means No School  (2024/5/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/for-children-of-gaza-war-means-no-school.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Dan Novak</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">21 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>Atef Al-Buhaisi is a 6-year-old from the Palestinian territory of Gaza. He once dreamed of a career building houses. Now, all he wants is to return to school.</p>
<p>In Israel's war with Hamas, Atef's home has been bombed, his teacher killed and his school in Nuseirat made into a refuge for displaced people. He lives in a crowded tent with his family in Deir al-Balah in central Gaza.</p>
<p>The war started last October. It was Israel's answer to the Hamas attack on October 7. The terrorists killed some 1,200 people and took 250 hostages from southern Israel.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Children attend an activity at a makeshift class in Deir al Balah, on Sunday, April 21, 2024. (AP Photo/Abdel Kareen Hana)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-7ff9-08dc790582c9_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Children attend an activity at a makeshift class in Deir al Balah, on Sunday, April 21, 2024. (AP Photo/Abdel Kareen Hana)</span></div>
<p>Since the start of the war, all of Gaza's schools have closed, leaving hundreds of thousands of students like Atef without <strong>formal</strong> schooling or a safe place to spend their days. Aid groups are working to keep children off the streets and their minds centered on something other than the war.</p>
<p>"What we've lost most is the future of our children and their education," said Irada Ismael, Atef's grandmother. "Houses and walls are rebuilt, money can be earned again...but how do I <strong>compensate</strong> for (his) education?"</p>
<p><strong>Gaza faces a humanitarian crisis</strong></p>
<p>Aid groups say about 80 percent of Gaza's population has been driven from their homes. Much of Gaza is damaged or destroyed, including nearly 90 percent of school buildings.</p>
<p>The Gaza Health Ministry, which is controlled by Hamas, says more than 35,000 Palestinians, including civilians and fighters, have been killed in the war.</p>
<p>And the head of the U.N. World Food Program said a "full-blown <strong>famine</strong>" is already underway in the north.</p>
<p>Children are among the most severely affected. The U.N. estimates some 19,000 children have been <strong>orphaned</strong> and nearly a third under the age of two face <strong>malnutrition</strong>.</p>
<p>In emergencies, education is less important than safety, health and sanitation, education experts say. But the effects are lasting.</p>
<p>Before the war, Gaza was home to more than 625,000 students and some 20,000 teachers, the U.N. says. In other conflicts, aid groups can create safe spaces for children in neighboring countries. Poland has been used for shelter and schooling for Ukrainians during the war there, for example.</p>
<p>That is not possible in Gaza, a highly populated area locked between the sea, Israel and Egypt. Since October 7, Palestinians from Gaza have not been permitted to cross into Israel. Egypt has let a small number of Palestinians leave.</p>
<p>Tess Ingram is with the children and education organization UNICEF. She told the Associated Press, "It's very hard to provide them with certain services, such as mental health and psychosocial support or consistent education and learning."</p>
<p><strong>Aid groups try to help</strong></p>
<p>Aid groups hope classes will start by September. But even if a cease-fire deal is reached, much of Gaza must be cleared of mines. And rebuilding schools could take years.</p>
<p>In the meantime, aid groups are providing activities like games, drawing, and art. The activities are not a formal education but provide children with a sense of normalcy. Even then, supporters say, their attention often turns to the war. Atef's grandmother sees him draw pictures only of tents, planes and missiles.</p>
<p>Finding free space is among the biggest difficulties. Some volunteers use the outdoors, do their best inside tents where people live, or find a room in homes still standing.</p>
<p>This month, UNICEF had planned to build at least 50 tents for some 6,000 children from preschool to grade 12 to provide some informal schooling. But UNICEF says those plans could be disrupted by Israel's operation there.</p>
<p>Lack of schooling can cause psychological impacts. It disrupts daily life and, combined with conflict, makes children more likely to experience <strong>anxiety</strong>, said Jesus Miguel Perez Cazorla. He is a mental health expert with the International Committee of the Red Cross.</p>
<p>Children in conflicts are also at increased risk of forced labor, sexual violence, <strong>trafficking</strong> and <strong>recruitment</strong> by criminal and armed groups, experts warn.</p>
<p>Samantha Nutt is with War Child USA, a group that supports children and families in war zones. She said the children are in danger of being recruited by Hamas and other militant groups. The constant violence makes children believe that they "want to take action against the groups they consider responsible," she said.</p>
<p>Palestinian parents say they have seen more children on the streets trying to earn money for their families. Some try to find small ways to teach their children. But many say the kids are too distracted, with the world around them at war.</p>
<p>Sabreen al-Khatib is a mother whose family was displaced to Deir al-Balah from Gaza City. She said it is especially hard for the many who have seen relatives die.</p>
<p>"When you speak in front of children," al-Khatib said, "what do you think he is thinking? Will he think about education? Or about himself, how will he die?"</p>
<p>I'm Dan Novak.</p>
<p>And I'm Gena Bennett.</p>
<p><em>Dan Novak adapted this story for VOA Learning English based on reporting by The Associated Press. </em></p>
<p><em>________________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p class="CxSpFirst"><strong>formal </strong><em>— adj. </em> requiring or using serious and proper clothes and manners</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>compensate </strong><em>— v. </em>to provide something good as a balance against something bad or undesirable</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>famine </strong><em>— n. </em>a situation in which many people do not have enough food to eat</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>orphan </strong><em>— n. </em>a child whose parents are dead</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>malnutrition </strong><em>— n. </em>the unhealthy condition that results from not eating enough food or not eating enough healthy food</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>anxiety </strong><em>— n. </em>fear or nervousness about what might happen</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>traffic </strong><em>— v. </em>to buy or sell something especially illegally</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>recruit </strong><em>— v. </em>to find suitable people and get them to join a company, an organization, the armed forces, etc.</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Blue Origin Sends Oldest Person into Space  (2024/5/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/blue-origin-sends-oldest-person-into-space.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">20 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>The American space travel company Blue Origin announced that it sent 90-year-old Ed Dwight into space, making him the oldest space traveler.</p>
<p>The company said Dwight was the first Black astronaut candidate and was picked personally by President John F. Kennedy in 1961. But it said Dwight was not chosen to be among the next group of astronauts.</p>
<p>Dwight spent a few minutes of weightlessness with five other passengers on the Blue Origin spacecraft. It reached the edge of space for about 10 minutes. Dwight called the flight "a life changing experience."</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Former NASA astronaut Ed Dwight poses for a portrait to promote the National Geographic documentary film The Space Race during the Winter Television Critics Association Press Tour, Feb. 8, 2024. (AP Photo/Chris Pizzello, File)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-27ec-08dc78eaaa34_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Former NASA astronaut Ed Dwight poses for a portrait to promote the National Geographic documentary film "The Space Race" during the Winter Television Critics Association Press Tour, Feb. 8, 2024. (AP Photo/Chris Pizzello, File)</span></div>
<p>With the flight, Dwight passed <em>Star Trek </em>actor William Shatner as the oldest person to reach space. Shatner's flight took place in 2021.</p>
<p>Dwight joined four businessmen from the U.S. and France. The cost of the trip for each was not released. Blue Origin said Dwight's flight was paid for by Space for Humanity, a nonprofit group based in Denver, Colorado. The group aims to send people of many different backgrounds into space as "citizen astronauts."</p>
<p>Dwight was in a test pilot program at Edwards Air Force Base in California. The program called "The Right Stuff" was the training ground for early astronauts. After being passed over, he retired from the military in 1966.</p>
<p>He later became a sculptor who made statues of Civil Rights leaders including Martin Luther King, Jr., Frederick Douglass, Harriet Tubman and others.</p>
<p>The U.S. space agency NASA announced Guion Bluford as the first Black astronaut in 1978, Bluford first reached space in 1983. The former Soviet Union placed the first person with African and Cuban ancestry, Arnaldo Tamayo Mendez, into orbit in 1980.</p>
<p>The stories of Dwight and Bluford are among those told in the documentary movie from National Geographic called <em>The Space Race</em>. It is about Black astronauts.</p>
<p>Dwight's flight on May 19 was the first launch with a crew for Blue Origin in nearly two years. All flights were <strong>grounded</strong> after an accident in 2022. Flights without a crew restarted last December. Sunday's flight was the seventh to carry space <strong>tourists</strong>.</p>
<p>Businessman and founder of Amazon Jeff Bezos also started started Blue Origin, a company that seeks to make space tourism popular.</p>
<p>After completing his flight on Blue Origin's spacecraft, Dwight said, "I thought I really didn't need this in my life," but added, "But now, I need it in my life...I am <strong>ecstatic</strong>."</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English with additional sources of information. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>grounded</strong><strong> </strong><em>–adj.</em><em> </em>not permitted to fly</p>
<p><strong>tourist</strong> <em>–n.</em> a person who travels for enjoyment and not for business reasons</p>
<p><strong>ecstatic </strong>–adj. extremely happy and excited</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Gene May Cause Alzheimer’s in Some Cases  (2024/5/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/study-gene-may-cause-alzheimer-s-in-some-cases.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Gregory Stachel</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">20 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>For the first time, researchers have identified a genetic form of late-in-life Alzheimer's disease.</p>
<p>Alzheimer's is a disease of the brain that causes people to lose their memory and mental abilities as they grow old.</p>
<p>Scientists have long known a gene called APOE4 is one of the many things that can increase a person's risk for Alzheimer's.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A section of a human brain with Alzheimer's disease is displayed at the Museum of Neuroanatomy at the University at Buffalo, in Buffalo, N.Y., Oct. 7, 2003. (AP Photo/David Duprey, File)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/75a1a624-8dba-4645-98ba-b5c92d2701b5_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A section of a human brain with Alzheimer's disease is displayed at the Museum of Neuroanatomy at the University at Buffalo, in Buffalo, N.Y., Oct. 7, 2003. (AP Photo/David Duprey, File)</span></div>
<p>One risk includes simply getting old; most Alzheimer's cases appear after age 65. But new research suggests that a cause of the disease is carrying two copies of the APOE4 gene. People with two copies of APOE4 inherited the gene from both parents.</p>
<p>Those patients may experience signs of Alzheimer's seven to 10 years sooner than other adults who develop Alzheimer's, the research found.</p>
<p>Dr. Juan Fortea led the study. He is with the Sant Pau Reasearch Institute in Barcelona, Spain. He said the findings mark a difference with "<strong>profound implications</strong>."</p>
<p>An estimated 15 percent of Alzheimer's patients carry two copies of APOE4. Those cases "can be <strong>tracked</strong> back to a cause and the cause is in the genes," Fortea said.</p>
<p>Until now, genetic forms of Alzheimer's were thought to be only kinds that appear at much younger ages. They were also thought to make up less than one percent of all cases.</p>
<p>Scientists say the new research shows the importance of developing treatments that target the APOE4 genes.</p>
<p>Dr. Reisa Sperling is with Harvard's Brigham and Women's Hospital in Boston. She helped write the study, which appeared recently in the publication <em>Nature Medicine</em>.</p>
<p>She said some doctors will not offer the only drug that has been shown to slow the disease, Leqembi, to people with the gene pair. She said that they are not offered the drug because those patients are at an especially high risk of developing a dangerous side effect.</p>
<p>Sperling studies ways to prevent or at least delay Alzheimer's. She said, "This data for me says wow, what an important group to be able to go after before they become symptomatic."</p>
<p>But the news does not mean people should race for a gene test. She told The Associated Press, "It's important not to scare everyone who has a family history" of Alzheimer's. She said the gene pair is not the cause of most cases of the disease.</p>
<p><strong>How do genetics affect Alzheimer's?</strong></p>
<p>More than 6 million Americans, and millions more worldwide, have Alzheimer's. Some genes are known to cause rare "early-onset forms." This is where changes in the genes are passed through families that can cause <strong>symptoms</strong> to appear by age 50.</p>
<p>But Alzheimer's most commonly appears after 65. Most cases begin after the age of 70. The APOE gene was known to play some part.</p>
<p>Most people carry the APOE3 gene that appears to neither increase nor decrease Alzheimer's risk. Some carry APOE2, which provides some protection against Alzheimer's.</p>
<p>APOE4 has long been called the biggest genetic risk <strong>factor</strong> for late-in-life Alzheimer's, with two copies riskier than one. About two percent of the world's population is estimated to have a copy of the gene from both parents.</p>
<p><strong>Research points to a cause for a kind of Alzheimer's</strong></p>
<p>Fortea's team used data from over 3,000 brains donated for research and from more than 10,000 people in U.S. and European Alzheimer's studies. The team's aim was to better understand genes' role in Alzheimer's. They examined symptoms and early signs of Alzheimer's such as sticky <strong>amyloid</strong> in the brain.</p>
<p>Amyloid is a protein that can exist in different body parts, including the brain, with certain diseases.</p>
<p>The researchers found that people with two APOE4 copies were gaining more amyloid at age 55 than those with just one copy of APOE4. They were also gaining more amyloid than people who had the "neutral" APOE3 gene.</p>
<p>By age 65, brain imaging showed large amounts of harmful amyloid buildup in nearly 75 percent of individuals with two copies of APOE4. Those individuals were also more likely to have beginning Alzheimer's symptoms by that age rather than later in life.</p>
<p>Sperling noted that not everyone with two APOE4 genes develops Alzheimer's symptoms. Researchers hope to learn why.</p>
<p><strong>How the new findings may affect Alzheimer's research and treatment</strong></p>
<p>The drug Leqembi works by clearing away some amyloid in patients' brains. But Sperling said it is not clear if carriers of two APOE4 genes gain from taking the drug. That is because they have such a high risk of brain <strong>swelling</strong> and bleeding.</p>
<p>One research question is whether patients with two APOE4 genes should start such drugs sooner than other people.</p>
<p>Dr. Eliezer Masliah of the National Institute on Aging said other research aims to develop gene <strong>therapy</strong> or drugs that target APOE4. He said it is important to understand APOE4's effects in different populations. So far, studies related to APOE4 have mostly involved white people of European ancestry.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo. And I'm Gregory Stachel.</p>
<p><em>Lauran Neergaard reported this story for The Associated Press. Gregory Stachel adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>profound </strong><em>– adj.</em> very great</p>
<p><strong>implications </strong><em>– n. </em>a possible future effect or result</p>
<p><strong>symptoms </strong><em>– n.</em> a change in the body or mind which indicates that a disease is present</p>
<p><strong>track </strong><em>– v. </em>to follow and find (someone or something) especially by looking at evidence</p>
<p><strong>factor </strong><em>– n.</em> something that helps produce or influence a result</p>
<p><strong>swelling </strong><em>– adj.</em> something that helps produce or influence a result</p>
<p><strong>therapy </strong><em>– n.</em> the treatment of physical or mental illnesses</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Coin Collection to be Sold 100 Years after Owner’s Death  (2024/5/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/coin-collection-to-be-sold-100-years-after-owner-s-death.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">20 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>A Danish businessman's large <strong>coin </strong>collection is set to go on sale one hundred years after his death. The collection could be worth up to $72 million.</p>
<p>Lars Emil Bruun directed lawyers what to do with the coin collection after his death in a legal document called a will. In it, Bruun required that his collection of about 20,000 coins be kept safe for 100 years before being sold. Deeply moved by the destruction of World War I and fearing another war, Bruun wanted the collection to be a <strong>reserve</strong> for Denmark.</p>
<p>Now, over a hundred years since Bruun's death at the age of 71 in 1923, the collection will begin to be sold.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Coins from L. E. Bruun's collection on display on a wooden tray, in Zealand, Denmark, May 7, 2024. The large collection could get up to $72 million. (AP Photo/James Brooks)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/6b180b57-7318-412f-979f-4d1848e08a57_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Coins from L. E. Bruun's collection on display on a wooden tray, in Zealand, Denmark, May 7, 2024. The large collection could get up to $72 million. (AP Photo/James Brooks)</span></div>
<p>New York-based Stack's Bowers, a rare coin <strong>auction</strong> house, will begin selling the collection this fall. Several sales are planned. On its website, the auction house calls it the "most valuable collection of world coins to ever come to market." The collection's existence has not been widely known, and the public has never seen it before.</p>
<p>"When I first heard about the collection, I was in disbelief," said Vicken Yegparian of Stack's Bowers Galleries.</p>
<p>"We've had collections that have been off the market for 100 years plus," he said. "But they're extremely well known internationally. This one has been the best open secret ever."</p>
<p>Born in 1852, Bruun began to collect coins as a boy in the 1850s and 1860s. Years later, he grew very rich selling the milk product, butter.</p>
<p>His wealth permitted him to continue his <strong>hobby</strong>. Bruun went to auctions, and he built a large collection that came to include 20,000 coins, medals, tokens and banknotes from Denmark, Norway and Sweden.</p>
<p>Following World War I, Bruun left exact instructions in his will for the collection.</p>
<p>"For a period of 100 years after my death, the collection shall serve as a reserve for the Royal Coin and Medal Collection," the will said.</p>
<p>It added, "Should the next century pass with the national collection <strong>intact</strong>, it shall be sold at public auction and the proceeds shall <strong>accrue</strong> to the persons who are my direct descendants."</p>
<p>Some descendants tried to break the will and get money early. But they were not successful. "I think the will and <strong>testament </strong>were pretty <strong>ironclad</strong>. There was no <strong>loophole</strong>," Yegparian said.</p>
<p>Yegparian estimated some pieces may sell for just $50, but others could be sold for over $1 million. He said possible buyers were requesting a list of the objects before the auction was announced.</p>
<p>The collection first remained at the former Danish royal residence of Frederiksborg Castle. Later, it was stored at Denmark's National Bank.</p>
<p>Denmark's National Museum had the right to purchase some of the coins before the public. The National Museum purchased seven rare coins from Bruun's collection. Six of the coins were gold and one was silver. They all were made between the 15th and 17th centuries by Danish or Norwegian rulers. A supporting group paid the cost of over $1.1 million.</p>
<p>Helle Horsnaes, a coin expert at the national museum, used the term unique – meaning one of a kind – to talk about those coins. She said, "We chose coins that were unique. They are described...as the only existing <strong>specimen </strong>of this kind."</p>
<p>Horsnaes expressed wonder about the collection: "The pure fact that this collection has been closed for a hundred years makes it a legend."</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>James Brooks reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"> </h2>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>coin</strong> <em>–n.</em> metal money that is round in shape</p>
<p><strong>reserve</strong> <em>– n.</em> something set aside for a particular purpose, use, or reason</p>
<p><strong>auction</strong> <em>– n</em>. a sale of something to the highest bidder</p>
<p><strong>hobby </strong><em>– n.</em> an activity done for fun or relaxation</p>
<p><strong>intact</strong> <em>– adj. </em>untouched or unharmed</p>
<p><strong>accrue</strong> <em>– v. </em>to come into existence as a legally enforceable claim; to come as a direct result of something</p>
<p><strong>testament</strong> <em>– n.</em> an act by which a person outlines the uses of his or her property after death</p>
<p><strong>ironclad</strong> <em>– adj.</em> very firm or secure</p>
<p><strong>loophole</strong> <em>– n.</em> an unclear or doubtful item in a text through which the intent of a contract or obligation may be evaded</p>
<p><strong>specimen</strong> <em>– n.</em> an individual or item considered typical of a group</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Iran's President, Foreign Minister Killed in Helicopter Crash  (2024/5/21) | 伊朗总统、外长在直升机事故中遇难</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/iran-s-president-foreign-minister-killed-in-helicopter-crash.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>Iranian state media reported Monday that Iranian President Ebrahim Raisi and other top officials died in a helicopter crash in the country's northwest.<br/>
伊朗官方媒体星期一报道说，伊朗总统易卜拉欣·莱希和其他高级官员在该国西北部的一次直升机坠毁事故中遇难。</p>
<p>The helicopter crashed on Sunday in bad weather in Iran's East Azerbaijan province. Search crews found the wreckage Monday. Iranian Foreign Minister Hossein Amirabdollahian was also among those killed.<br/>
这架直升机周日在恶劣天气下坠毁在伊朗东阿塞拜疆省。搜救人员星期一发现了残骸。伊朗外交部长侯赛因·阿米尔·阿卜杜拉希扬也在遇难者之列。</p>
<p>The Iranian officials were returning to Iran after attending the opening of a joint dam project at the Iran-Azerbaijan border.<br/>
伊朗官员在参加完伊朗与阿塞拜疆边境一处联合大坝项目的落成仪式后返回伊朗。</p>
<p>Iran's Supreme Leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei announced five days of mourning. He appointed Vice President Mohammad Mokhber as acting president. Mokhber then named Deputy Foreign Minister Ali Bagheri Kani as foreign minister caretaker, a Cabinet official said.<br/>
伊朗最高领袖哈梅内伊宣布全国哀悼五天。他任命穆罕默德·莫赫贝尔副总统为代理总统。一名内阁官员表示，莫赫贝尔随后任命外交部副部长阿里·巴盖里·卡尼为代理外交部长。</p>
<p>An election for a new president is set to take place in the next 50 days.<br/>
新总统的选举将在未来50天内举行。</p>
<p>Raisi was 63 years old. He was elected president in 2021. Most of his main opponents were barred from running in the election, which had record low turnout among voters. Raisi, an ultraconservative, had strong support from Khamenei.<br/>
莱希今年63岁。他于2021年当选总统。他的大多数主要对手都被禁止参加选举，这场选举的投票率创下了历史新低。极端保守派莱希得到了哈梅内伊的大力支持。</p>
<p>On Sunday, Iranian state television showed video of government supporters gathering in different parts of the country to pray for Raisi's safe return.<br/>
周日，伊朗国家电视台播放了政府支持者聚集在该国不同地区祈祷莱希平安返回的视频。</p>
<p>Images published on social media Sunday showed opponents of Iran's Islamist rulers setting off fireworks in several places to celebrate the possibility of Raisi's death.<br/>
周日在社交媒体上发布的图片显示，伊朗伊斯兰统治者的反对者在多个地方燃放烟花，庆祝莱希的死亡。</p>
<p>VOA's Persian Service examined the images and said they are credible, or real. But it could not independently confirm the reason for the fireworks. VOA is barred from reporting inside Iran.<br/>
美国之音波斯语服务台检查了这些图片，并表示它们是可信的，或者是真实的。但它无法独立证实燃放烟花的原因。美国之音被禁止在伊朗境内进行报道。</p>
<p>In one video, a woman identifies the location of fireworks as southern Tehran. In another video, a man reacts to what he says are fireworks in the city of Saqqez in northwestern Iran's Kurdistan province.<br/>
在一段视频中，一名妇女确认燃放烟花的位置在德黑兰南部。在另一段视频中，在伊朗西北部库尔德斯坦省的塞盖兹市，一名男子对他所说的烟花做出回应。</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: bold;">Reactions from world leaders<br/>
世界领导人的反应</span></p>
<p>Governments around the world reacted to the news of Raisi's death. Pakistan, Lebanon, Iraq and other nations announced a period of mourning.<br/>
世界各国政府对莱希去世的消息作出了反应。巴基斯坦、黎巴嫩、伊拉克等国宣布进入哀悼期。</p>
<p>Azerbaijan's President Ilham Aliyev said Monday that he was "deeply shocked by the heavy loss."<br/>
阿塞拜疆总统伊利哈姆·阿利耶夫周一表示，他“对这一重大损失深感震惊”。</p>
<p>Russian President Vladimir Putin praised Raisi as an "outstanding politician." He called him a "true friend of Russia."<br/>
俄罗斯总统弗拉基米尔·普京称赞莱西是“杰出的政治家”。他称他是“俄罗斯真正的朋友”。</p>
<p>Egyptian President Abdel Fattah El-Sissi expressed Egypt's solidarity with "the leadership and people of Iran in this great loss."<br/>
埃及总统阿卜杜勒·法塔赫·塞西表达了埃及对“遭遇这一巨大损失的伊朗领导人和人民”的声援。</p>
<p>Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi said he was shocked by the development. He added that "India stands with Iran in this time of sorrow."<br/>
印度总理纳伦德拉·莫迪表示，他对事态发展感到震惊。他补充说，“在这个悲痛的时刻，印度与伊朗站在一起。”</p>
<p>European Council President Charles Michel said the European Union "expresses its sincere condolences."<br/>
欧洲理事会主席查尔斯·米歇尔表示，欧盟“表示诚挚的哀悼”。</p>
<p>"Our thoughts go to the families," Michel said.<br/>
米歇尔说：“我们向遇难家庭表示慰问。”</p>
<p>I'm Ashley Thompson.<br/>
我是阿什利·汤普森。(51VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Severe Solar Storm Hits Earth, Causing Colorful Light Shows  (2024/5/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/severe-solar-storm-hits-earth-causing-colorful-light-shows.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">19 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>Earth was recently hit by the most powerful solar storm in more than 20 years.</p>
<p>The storm caused some colorful light shows in some parts of the world, but no major damage was reported. Solar storms can hurt the operation of some equipment on Earth that uses radio waves. This includes GPS services, electrical systems and satellites.</p>
<p>The U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) issued warnings about the storm before it reached Earth on May 10. In a statement, NOAA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.noaa.gov/stories/strong-geomagnetic-storm-reaches-earth-continues-through-weekend">said</a> it had observed heavy solar storm activity in the days before. Based on the activity, the agency issued a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.swpc.noaa.gov/news/g4-conditions-observed">Geomagnetic Storm Warning</a>.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="The northern lights flare in the sky over a farmhouse, late Friday, May 10, 2024, in Brunswick, Maine. (AP Photo/Robert F. Bukaty)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-a03e-08dc761d7eee_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">The northern lights flare in the sky over a farmhouse, late Friday, May 10, 2024, in Brunswick, Maine. (AP Photo/Robert F. Bukaty)</span></div>
<p>Solar storms can involve two different processes. One is called a solar flare, while the other is a coronal mass ejection (CME). Both involve huge releases from the sun of magnetic field energy and a substance called plasma. The American space agency NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://svs.gsfc.nasa.gov/14299/">explains</a> that plasma is a form of matter made up of ionized particles. This means the particles have taken in so much energy that it causes electrons to separate from their atoms.</p>
<p>Solar flares travel at the speed of light in all directions. They can reach Earth in about eight minutes. But CMEs travel much slower. They reach Earth in one to three days. NOAA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.swpc.noaa.gov/news/region-3664-not-done-yet-produces-x87-flarelargest-solar-cycle">said</a> a strong "solar flare event" had led to the latest CMEs hitting Earth.</p>
<p>NASA says its observatories see solar flares as flashes of light on the sun, while CMEs are seen as large explosions spreading out into space. The agency examines data from its Parker Solar Probe on plasma flowing out of the sun's corona.</p>
<p>Because the latest CME explosions were directed at Earth, they caused geomagnetic storms. NOAA's Space Weather Prediction Center issued a warning, calling the storm activity "an unusual and <strong>potentially</strong> historic event."</p>
<p>NOAA noted that such storms can cause problems for some communication systems. The agency informed major power operators and NASA officials about the storm activity. The electric power <strong>grid</strong> can also be affected, or disrupted, along with radio, satellite and spacecraft operations.</p>
<p>NOAA noted that severe geomagnetic storms can also produce intense, colorful light shows, or displays, in the sky. Such shows are also known as auroras.</p>
<p>Colorful displays could be seen overnight in different parts of the world. Reuters news agency reported on several areas in Latin America experiencing auroras after the solar storm activity. In Mexico's desert city of Mexicali, pink and purple light could be seen lighting up the night sky last Friday and Saturday.</p>
<p>In Chile, Reuters reported local media and social media users shared photos of the sky in the city of Punta Arenas, where the lights took on red and purple <strong>tones</strong>. Local media in Argentina also reported similar displays in the Patagonian city of Ushuaia.</p>
<p>The French news agency AFP reported social media services were filled up with people publishing images of auroras from areas including northern Europe and Australasia.</p>
<p>Iain Mansfield lives in Hertford, Britain. He told AFP, "We've just woken the kids to go watch the Northern Lights in the back <strong>garden</strong>! Clearly visible with <strong>the</strong> <strong>naked eye</strong>."</p>
<p>Other people also compared the intense color shows to the Northern Lights. Sometimes also called aurora borealis, the Northern Lights are natural, colored light displays that sometimes appear in the night sky in the most northern parts of the world.</p>
<p>From Australia's island state of Tasmania, photographer Sean O' Riordan published a message on X explaining what he saw. "Absolutely biblical skies in Tasmania at 4am this morning. I'm leaving today and knew I could not pass up this <strong>opportunity</strong>."</p>
<p>People in the United States were also able to see colorful auroras, including parts of the West Coast and as far south as Alabama.</p>
<p>The most intense solar storm in recorded history happened in 1859. It mainly produced auroras in Central America. A severe geomagnetic storm in 2003 cut power in Sweden and damaged power transformers in South Africa.</p>
<p>Storm activity coming from the sun generally intensifies as it reaches the height of a repeating, 11-year solar cycle. The activity increases as the sun experiences magnetic field changes that affect its polar areas.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters, Agence France-Presse, NASA and NOAA. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>potential </strong><em>– adj. </em>possible when the necessary conditions exist<em> </em></p>
<p><strong>grid </strong><em>– n. </em>a system of wires through which electricity is connected to different power stations across a particular area</p>
<p><strong>tone </strong><em>– n. </em>a form or degree of color</p>
<p><strong>garden </strong><em>– n. </em>a piece of land, usually in a yard next to a house, where things are grown</p>
<p><strong>the naked eye </strong><em>– n. </em>something that can be seen with just the eyes, without the need for devices or special equipment</p>
<p><strong>opportunity </strong><em>– n. </em>the chance to do something</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>UN Authorizes Second Shot to Fight Dengue in Americas  (2024/5/20) | 联合国批准第二种登革热疫苗</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/un-authorizes-second-shot-to-fight-dengue-in-americas.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>The World Health Organization recently authorized a second dengue vaccine. The move could provide protection for millions of people worldwide against the mosquito-borne disease.<br/>
世界卫生组织最近批准了第二种登革热疫苗。此举可以保护全世界数百万人免受这种蚊子传播的疾病的侵害。</p>
<p>This year, several dengue outbreaks have happened in places across the Americas.<br/>
今年，美洲各地发生了几起登革热疫情。</p>
<p>In a statement on May 15, the U.N. health agency said it approved the dengue vaccine made by the Japanese drugmaker Takeda.<br/>
这家联合国卫生机构在5月15日发布一份声明中表示，它批准了日本制药商武田制药生产的登革热疫苗。</p>
<p>Takeda's dengue vaccine is known as Qdenga. It was previously approved by the European Medicines Agency in 2022. The two-dose vaccine is given three months apart. It protects against the four kinds of dengue. The WHO recommends its use in children between the ages of 6 and 16 who live in areas with high rates of dengue.<br/>
武田制药的登革热疫苗名为Qdenga。此前，该药物已于2022年获得欧洲药品管理局的批准。这种两针剂的疫苗接种间隔为三个月。它可以预防四种登革热。世卫组织建议将其用于登革热高发地区6至16岁的儿童。</p>
<p>Approval by the WHO now means that donors and other U.N. agencies can purchase the vaccine for poorer countries.<br/>
世界卫生组织的批准现在意味着捐助者和其它合国机构可以采购这种疫苗用于贫穷国家。</p>
<p>Studies have shown Takeda's vaccine is about 84 percent effective in preventing people from being hospitalized and about 61 percent effective in stopping symptoms.<br/>
研究表明，武田制药的疫苗在预防人们住院方面的有效性约为84%，在阻止症状方面的有效率约为61%。</p>
<p>WHO's Rogerio Gaspar is director for the agency's approvals of medicines and vaccines. He said it was "an important step in the expansion of global access to dengue vaccines."<br/>
世卫组织的罗杰里奥·加斯帕是该机构药品和疫苗审批主任。他说，这是“扩大全球登革热疫苗获取途径的重要一步”。</p>
<p>The first dengue vaccine that the WHO approved was made by the drugmaker Sanofi Pasteur. The vaccine was later found to increase the risk of severe dengue in people who had not been infected with the disease before.<br/>
世界卫生组织批准的第一种登革热疫苗由制药商赛诺菲巴斯德生产。后来发现，这种疫苗会增加以前没有感染过登革热的人士罹患重症的风险。</p>
<p>There is no exact treatment for dengue. It is a leading cause of serious illness and death in about 120 Latin American and Asian countries. About 80 percent of infections are mild. But severe cases of dengue can lead to internal bleeding, organ failure, and death.<br/>
登革热没有确切的治疗方法。它是约120个拉丁美洲和亚洲国家严重疾病和死亡的主要原因。大约80%的感染是轻微的。但登革热的严重病例会导致内出血、器官衰竭和死亡。</p>
<p>Last week, the WHO reported there were 6.7 million suspected cases of dengue in the Americas. That is an increase of 206 percent compared with the same period last year. In March of this year, officials in Rio de Janeiro declared a public health emergency over its dengue epidemic. Brazilian health officials began giving out the Takeda vaccine with the goal of protecting at least 3 million people.<br/>
上周，世界卫生组织报告美洲有670万例登革热疑似病例。这与去年同期相比，增长了206%。今年3月，里约热内卢官员宣布由于其登革热疫情进入公共卫生紧急状态。巴西卫生官员开始分发武田制药疫苗，目标是保护至少300万人。</p>
<p>Infectious disease experts say climate change and the increased range of mosquitoes that carry dengue are partly to blame for the spread of the disease.<br/>
传染病专家表示，气候变化和携带登革热的蚊子数量增加是该疾病传播的部分原因。</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.<br/>
我是安娜·马泰奥。(51VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Young South Koreans Drawn to Buddhism via Social Media  (2024/5/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/young-south-koreans-drawn-to-buddhism-via-social-media.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Gregory Stachel</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">19 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>Religious beliefs in South Korea have been decreasing for years. In 2021, just 22 percent of South Koreans between the ages of 20 and 29 identified as religious. In 2004, that number was 45 percent. Those numbers are from the Washington, D.C.-based data organization Gallup.</p>
<p>But that might be changing. Social media is fueling an increased interest in Buddhism among young people.</p>
<p>Music creator Youn Sung Ho is one reason for this increase. Youn said he has received support from younger generations for his Buddhist <strong>monk</strong> <strong>character. </strong>He calls the character NewJeansNim.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="NewJeansNim, a comedian and a DJ, whose real name is Youn Sung Ho, performs at an annual lantern-lighting festival dressed up as a monk, in Seoul, South Korea on May 12, 2024. (AP Photo/Juwon Park)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/6caa6e5c-39c1-4f11-869c-c061ab8a7d47_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">NewJeansNim, a comedian and a DJ, whose real name is Youn Sung Ho, performs at an annual lantern-lighting festival dressed up as a monk, in Seoul, South Korea on May 12, 2024. (AP Photo/Juwon Park)</span></div>
<p>Youn said he created the character last year when he was performing at a ceremony to celebrate Buddha's birthday.</p>
<p>He wore a hanbok, the traditional Korean clothing that looks like monk's <strong>robe</strong>. He said a video of the performance got millions of views on social media. "That's when I thought, ‘Oh, I need to make a character quickly,'" he said.</p>
<p>He carefully built his character while seeking support from Buddhist leaders in South Korea. His goal was to balance popular culture with Buddhist teachings.</p>
<p>NewJeansNim is a combination of Sunim, a Korean title for Buddhist monks, and NewJean, a name that a senior monk gave to Youn.</p>
<p>Youn's music-creating character has appealed to many young South Korean adults. And the character has increased young Koreans' interest in Buddhism.</p>
<p>Kwon Dohyun is a university student. He attended the ceremony and said he was happy to see NewJeansNim perform. Kwon told The Associated Press "Isn't the hairstyle really <strong>hip</strong>?" He added that his interest in Buddhism also came from the inclusivity and openness of the religion.</p>
<p>Youn said he believes his attempts to break traditional attitudes towards Buddhism has gained support among South Koreans. He said that when most people think of Buddhism, they think of things like sitting still, quiet <strong>temples </strong>in the mountains and the sound of wind <strong>chimes.</strong></p>
<p>"People think these are Buddhism, but what I am doing now is the opposite," he said.</p>
<p>Venerable Beomjeong is another Buddhist who has been gaining young followers on social media. He is also known as Kkotsnim, which means "flower monk" in Korean. He is active on Instagram, where he communicates with both Buddhists and non-believers.</p>
<p>Beomjeon often shares photos of himself with descriptions including Buddhist teachings and his thoughts.</p>
<p>"People think monks are supposed to be <strong>noble</strong>, they are supposed to be in the mountains, they are supposed to be purer than anyone else," he said. He added that he hopes to change the ideas around monks and Buddhism in South Korea through social media.</p>
<p>He said he receives many messages asking him simple questions about Buddhism. They include: Are monks not supposed to eat meat? Are monks able to get married? He has also been asked: "Will you marry me?"</p>
<p>Beomjeong said he aims for his answers to be clear but carefully worded. He said, "I tell it like it is."</p>
<p>Beomjeong and NewJeansNim both say their efforts to bring in younger generations to Buddhism have left them open to criticism.</p>
<p>Beomjeong said Korean Buddhist monks had the opinion that a monk should not be sharing images of himself and using Instagram.</p>
<p>But Youn said such criticisms come from people who resist change. And he added that the younger generations "who want and like new things are so welcoming and love it."</p>
<p>Beomjeong said he is happy to be considered an influencer if it means sharing messages about Buddhism with the public.</p>
<p>Beomjeong said, "I don't know what it means to be an influencer, but if I can get many people to see and hear what I say, I want to be an influencer."</p>
<p>I'm Gregory Stachel.</p>
<p><em>Juwon Park reported this story for The Associated Press. Gregory Stachel adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>monk </strong><em>– n. </em>a member of a religious community of men who usually promise to remain poor, unmarried, and separated from the rest of society</p>
<p><strong>character </strong><em>– n. </em>a person who appears in a story, book, play, movie, or television show</p>
<p><strong>robe </strong><em>– n. </em>a long, loose piece of clothing that is worn on top of other clothes to show that someone has a high rank or an important job</p>
<p><strong>hip </strong><em>– adj. </em>very popular or fashionable</p>
<p><strong>temple </strong><em>– n. </em>a building for worship</p>
<p><strong>chimes </strong><em>– n. </em>a device that produces a sound like the sound made by a set of bells</p>
<p><strong>noble </strong><em>– </em>adj. having, showing, or coming from personal qualities that people admire (such as honesty, generosity, or courage)</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists in Thailand Free Endangered Sea Turtles into the Wild  (2024/5/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/scientists-in-thailand-free-endangered-sea-turtles-into-the-wild.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">18 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists in Thailand have released a group of endangered sea turtles in an effort to save the wild population.</p>
<p>A total of 11 baby leatherback sea turtles were recently released into the Indian Ocean from Thailand's vacation island of Phuket. The researchers are hoping the one-year-old turtles will get strong in the wild and return in 20 years to reproduce.</p>
<p>The release follows an intense <strong>conservation</strong> effort in recent years that centered on improving longtime survival rates for the sea creatures. In 2018, scientists discovered that leatherback sea turtles had returned to lay eggs in southern Thailand.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="One-month-old baby leatherback turtles swim inside a pond at Phuket Marine Biological Center, in Phuket province, Thailand, April 7, 2024. (REUTERS/Napat Wesshasartar)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-19e0-08dc75f2a962_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">One-month-old baby leatherback turtles swim inside a pond at Phuket Marine Biological Center, in Phuket province, Thailand, April 7, 2024. (REUTERS/Napat Wesshasartar)</span></div>
<p>Some stronger members of that group successfully entered the ocean, but others died after <strong>hatching</strong>.<strong> </strong>So, a program was launched to help the weak baby leatherbacks grow, said Pinsak Suraswadi. He is the Director-General of Thailand's Department of Marine and Coastal Resources.</p>
<p>Thailand is one of five countries – including Sri Lanka and Canada – that has been able to keep leatherback turtles in good health through their first year. Usually, a leatherback will lay eggs after 20 to 25 years.</p>
<p>The baby sea turtles, released last month, have satellite devices attached to them to follow their progress. The release was part of an international effort by the nonprofit conservation organization Upwell Turtles.</p>
<p>Pinsak told Reuters news agency that it is necessary for researchers to study the animals' travel path in order "to understand where they are going." This helps the group know which measures to launch to protect the turtles' hatching process.</p>
<p>Leatherback sea turtles are believed to have developed more than 150 million years ago. But the animals are now extremely endangered in the Pacific area. The World Wildlife Fund estimates the current population in the Pacific to be fewer than 2,300 adult females.</p>
<p>While in the ocean, the turtles face dangers from fishing equipment, eating plastic waste and coming in contact with poisonous substances.</p>
<p>"I'm happy to know whether our effort in <strong>nurturing</strong> the leatherback sea turtles for a year proves <strong>fruitful</strong> or not," said Hirun Kanghae. He is with Thailand's Phuket Marine Biological Center.</p>
<p>"If they survive it answers everything about the conservation and population restoration of the leatherback sea turtles in the best way possible," Hirun added.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn</p>
<p><em>Reuters reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>conservation </strong><em>– n. </em>an organized effort that aims to protect animals and natural resources</p>
<p><strong>hatch </strong><em>– v. </em>the process of an egg opening to give birth to a particular animal</p>
<p><strong>nurture </strong><em>– v. </em>to take efforts to look after, feed and protect young children, animals or plants</p>
<p><strong>fruitful </strong><em>– adj. </em>producing good or useful results</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Campus Protests Face Summer Break  (2024/5/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/us-campus-protests-face-summer-break.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Gregory Stachel</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">18 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>How long student protests over the war in Gaza can continue is in question with the removal of encampments, graduations and summer break.</p>
<p>The student protests came after the Israeli offensive in the Palestinian territory of Gaza. The offensive was to answer the Hamas attack on October 7 that killed some 1,200 people in southern Israel. The resulting war in Gaza has killed more than 35,000 people, including civilians and fighters. Those numbers come from Gaza's Health Ministry and are not independently confirmed.</p>
<p>The protesters say they will continue until college officials meet their demands. They include a permanent ceasefire in Gaza and ending university investment in companies profiting from the war. They also include the removal of punishments for students and school employees for protesting.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Student protest organizer, Steph W. raises her right fist as she poses for a portrait at an encampment in support of Palestinians in Gaza at the Auraria Campus in Denver, Colorado, U.S., May 10, 2024. (REUTERS/Kevin Mohatt)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/b56b1355-453a-4fd5-8620-c1d25e7da4ed_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Student protest organizer, Steph W. raises her right fist as she poses for a portrait at an encampment in support of Palestinians in Gaza at the Auraria Campus in Denver, Colorado, U.S., May 10, 2024. (REUTERS/Kevin Mohatt)</span></div>
<p>Experts who study protest movements say it is difficult to continue the protests' energy if most of the students are gone. But they also point out that student demonstrations are just one way to protest in the wider pro-Palestinian movement that has existed for many years. They say this summer will provide more chances for the energy that started at universities to move to the streets.</p>
<p><strong>Evolve or disappear</strong></p>
<p>Dana Fisher is a professor at American University in Washington, D.C. She has written several books on social movements and has seen some of her students among protesters at the university.</p>
<p>She noted the <strong>campus</strong> protests spread across the country as a <strong>response</strong> to police activity at Columbia University on April 18. More than 100 people were arrested then. Since those first arrests, the Associated Press estimated that nearly 2,900 people have been arrested at 57 colleges and universities around the U.S.</p>
<p>Fisher told Reuters news agency that she does not see enough organizational structure for the young people to continue protesting when they are not at school. She said the movement will have to <strong>evolve</strong> "or it can't continue."</p>
<p>In Denver, Colorado, police on April 26 arrested 45 people at an encampment protest at the Auraria campus used by the University of Colorado-Denver, Metropolitan State University, and the Community College of Denver.</p>
<p>On May 8, the students returned for a sit-in inside the Aerospace and Engineering Sciences building. The building was developed in part with a $1 million gift from arms manufacturer Lockheed Martin.</p>
<p>Steph, who chose to not give her last name due to fear of punishment, is a 21-year-old student on the Auraria campus. She said, "We're keeping our protests up and our encampment going until our demands are met, however long that takes." She added, "We'll be here through summer break and into next fall if needed."</p>
<p>Fisher said the police response to protests has helped create a sense of activism in a new generation of students. She thinks the current campus demonstrations are the beginning of a "long, hot summer of protest" about many issues.</p>
<p>And she thinks the Republican National Convention in July and the Democratic National Convention in August will become targets for large protests.</p>
<p>Fisher said the current police response has been "much more aggressive and repressive" than the time of student-led protests against the Vietnam War in the 1960s. "And then... in the middle of all that the presidential election," she added.</p>
<p><strong>After graduation, a ghost town</strong></p>
<p>Michael Heaney teaches politics at the University of Glasgow in Britain. His research and books have dealt with U.S. protest movements.</p>
<p>Heaney said the campus protests are just one method in the wider movement to support Palestinians, an ongoing effort that goes back many years. He pointed to the U.S. civil rights protests that went back 200 years, saying just because one moment of protest ends does not mean the end of a movement.</p>
<p>He said pro-Palestinian protests in American cities this summer could grow if Israel's offensive in Gaza continues. And he added that such demonstrations would have been supported by the widespread university activism.</p>
<p>Jacob, 22, is one of the student protest organizers on Denver's Auraria campus. He said, "After graduation, it may be a <strong>ghost town</strong> on this campus - but we'll still be here." He added, "We're not going anywhere."</p>
<p>I'm Gregory Stachel. And I'm Gena Bennett.</p>
<p><em>Brad Brooks reported this story for Reuters. Gregory Stachel adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>campus </strong><em>– n. </em>the area and buildings around a university, college, or school</p>
<p><strong>response </strong><em>– n. </em>something that is done as a reaction to something else</p>
<p><strong>evolve </strong><em>– v. </em>to change or develop slowly often into a better, more complex, or more advanced state</p>
<p><strong>ghost town </strong><em>– n. </em>a town that no longer has any people living in it</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Ways to 'Divide and Conquer'  (2024/5/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/ways-to-divide-and-conquer.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">18 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>On today's show, we talk about a strategy for winning or for completing a big task. That strategy is called <u>dividing and <strong>conquering</strong></u>.</p>
<p>With this strategy, you gain an <strong>advantage</strong> by creating divisions within a group. You might try to turn your enemies against each other. You try to keep control over a group of people by creating problems among them. You could also make a group of people disagree and fight with one another. When you do this, they will likely be too busy fighting each other to think about fighting you.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Dividing and conquering is a useful strategy in many situations.
(Adobe Stock Photo/Miha Creative)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-1638-08dc7673ff59_w268_r1.jpeg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Dividing and conquering is a useful strategy in many situations.
(Adobe Stock Photo/Miha Creative)</span></div>
<p>For example, the police detectives tried <u>to divide and conquer</u> warring drug dealers. The drug dealers were so busy fighting each other, they made mistakes and got arrested by police.</p>
<p>However, you must be careful when trying to<strong> </strong><u>divide and conquer</u>. The people you are trying to divide may <strong>band together</strong>. This means they form an alliance<strong>.</strong> They overcome their differences, work together, and turn against you.</p>
<p>Now, this expression is not just used when talking about defeating people. We can also <u>divide and conquer</u> when trying to complete a difficult task.</p>
<p>If you want to complete a complex task, it is helpful to have several people working on it at the same time. You would divide the tasks and <strong>delegate</strong> them to others. That way, you can conquer - or complete - the task.</p>
<p>Here's an example. Let's say you are working on a big project with some co-workers. The project is complex and has many moving parts. So, instead of everyone working on the same things at once, you decide to <u>divide and conquer</u>. You assign each person a different task. In the end, the project gets done smoothly and on time.</p>
<p>Now, let's hear some friends use this expression this way. They are preparing for a surprise birthday party and have lots to do.</p>
<p><em>A: Okay, change of plans. Samantha just texted. She canceled her work meeting and will be here in two hours, not four.</em></p>
<p><em>B: Two hours?! That's not enough time! We'll never be ready for her surprise party. You need to <strong>stall</strong> her. But don't make her suspicious.</em></p>
<p><em>A: If I try to keep her away, she'll know <strong>something's up</strong>. She knows us too well. </em></p>
<p><em>B: You're right. What are we going to do??</em></p>
<p><em>A: First, calm down. What still needs to be done?</em></p>
<p><em>B: The food needs to be cooked, the cake and drinks need to be picked up, the living room needs to be decorated, and the gift needs to be wrapped. We'll never finish in time!</em></p>
<p><em>A: We will! We just need to <u>divide and conquer!</u> You keep cooking. I'll text Claudia and ask her to pick up the cake on the way over. Then I'll text Gwen. She can pick up the drinks. When Steve gets here, he can wrap the gift and decorate. He's good at those things.</em></p>
<p><em>B: Ok, sounds like a plan! Wait a minute. What will you be doing?</em></p>
<p><em>A: I'm busy! <u>Dividing and conquering</u> doesn't happen by itself. </em></p>
<p>And that's the end of this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>.</p>
<p>If you have a big goal, maybe it's time you <u>divide and conquer</u> it. Break it down into small tasks and get them done.</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"> </h2>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>conquer </strong><em>–v.</em><strong> </strong>to get or gain by force of arms<strong> </strong>: to defeat by force of arms<strong> </strong>: to be victorious</p>
<p><strong>advantage </strong><em>–n.</em><strong> </strong>the fact of being in a better position or condition : something that helps the one it belongs to</p>
<p><strong>band together </strong><em>–phrasal verb </em>to form a group in order to do or achieve something</p>
<p><strong>delegate </strong><em>–v. </em>to assign a task or responsibility : to entrust to another</p>
<p><strong>stall </strong><em>–v. </em>to distract attention or make excuses to gain time</p>
<p><strong>something's up </strong><em>–set phrase</em><strong> </strong>indicates that a situation is or seems suspicious, peculiar, or out of the ordinary</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Air Force Shows Fighter Plane Piloted by AI  (2024/5/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/us-air-force-shows-fighter-plane-piloted-by-ai.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Dan Friedell</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">18 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>Two American Air Force fighter airplanes recently flew into the sky above California.</p>
<p>The military planes were taking part in training, practicing a wartime maneuver called a dogfight.</p>
<p>One of the planes had a human pilot inside. The other did not. It was operated by artificial intelligence, or AI, software.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Air Force Secretary Frank Kendall in the cockpit of an X-62A VISTA at Edwards Air Force Base, Calif., on May 2, 2024. The AI-controlled plane flew Kendall in maneuvers that put 5Gs of pressure on his body at speeds exceeding 550 miles an hour. (AP Photo/Damian Dovarganes)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/10ac7e21-169d-4e0b-8db5-ffe72a7c8a84_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Air Force Secretary Frank Kendall in the cockpit of an X-62A VISTA at Edwards Air Force Base, Calif., on May 2, 2024. The AI-controlled plane flew Kendall in maneuvers that put 5Gs of pressure on his body at speeds exceeding 550 miles an hour. (AP Photo/Damian Dovarganes)</span></div>
<p>A human was in the airplane's other seat.</p>
<p>The Air Force was demonstrating how far its AI piloting technology has come.</p>
<p>The United States is competing to stay ahead of China on AI and its use in weapon systems. The <strong>focus</strong> on AI has led to public concern. People worry that future wars will be fought by machines that choose and strike targets without direct human intervention. The U.S. has said it would never send a pilotless fighter plane into war because of concerns that civilians could be harmed mistakenly. But it is unclear if other countries have the same policy.</p>
<p>So the U.S. is working on AI piloting technology, just in case.</p>
<p>Admiral Christopher Grady is vice chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, the top U.S. military leadership group. When speaking about the use of AI in war, he said: "China's working on it as hard as we are."</p>
<p>Here is a look at the U.S. history of machine learning and AI in the military.</p>
<p>The military started putting computers in control of some systems in the 1960s and 1970s. The Aegis missile defense system was programmed by humans. They gave the system a set of "if/then" commands because the computer could <strong>detect</strong> incoming missiles faster than humans. The system could not learn, it could only carry out the rules. So it was not AI as we understand it today, said Christopher Berardi, an Air Force Lt. Colonel who is working with the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) on AI development.</p>
<p>AI took a step forward in 2012 when faster computer processors started to analyze information and write rules. Computer experts call that period "the <strong>big bang</strong>" for AI. The new data created by a computer is considered artificial intelligence.</p>
<p>Air Force Secretary Frank Kendall was the human on board the F-16 fighter jet called Vista. The Vista jet is the most visible AI project, but the U.S. Department of Defense has hundreds in place.</p>
<p>One project going on at MIT includes recordings of Air Force pilots speaking with people in air operations centers on the ground. Service members are training the AI systems to detect the most important conversations and separate them from <strong>mundane</strong> <strong>chatter</strong>. The plan is to use AI to <strong>alert</strong> pilots to critical messages.</p>
<p>The Air Force is also working on an AI-powered navigation system that does not depend on satellites. The concern is that satellites could be targeted in war.</p>
<p>So instead of using satellite navigation, the Air Force is working on a navigation system that uses the magnetic fields of the Earth. The idea is not new, but before AI, experts worried that navigation systems would not work due to the electromagnetic signal created by most aircraft. But programmers are training an AI system to ignore the signal created by the airplane and instead pay attention to the Earth's magnetic emissions.</p>
<p>Col. Garry Floyd is head of the Air Force-MIT Artificial Intelligence Accelerator Program. He said magnetometers are so sensitive they would pick up the signal from flashing lights on a C-17 airplane. Floyd called the work so far, "very, very <strong>impressive</strong>."</p>
<p>"We think we may have added an <strong>arrow to the quiver</strong> in the things we can do, should we end up operating in a GPS-denied environment. Which we will," Floyd said.</p>
<p>The system has only been tested on the C-17 so far.</p>
<p>There are some limits to what AI can do. So there is always a human safety pilot on board. For example, AI cannot learn in mid-flight. It can only learn from the data it collects each time the plane is in the air. When the plane is back on the ground, the new information is loaded into a <strong>simulator</strong> and the AI system learns and creates more flight rules.</p>
<p>But unlike in the past, AI now learns fast. Today's computers have more power than ever before and sometimes the AI system learns new ways to fly the planes. Sometimes it can beat human pilots in tests.</p>
<p>But there are still "guardrails." AI may learn a new way to fly a plane, but a human observer will prevent the computer from <strong>transferring </strong>the<strong> </strong>details on how to do an unsafe maneuver in the air. The Air Force said it hopes the system it is working on today can be used to create a fleet of 1,000 unpiloted airplanes.</p>
<p>I'm Dan Friedell.</p>
<p><em>Dan Friedell adapted this story for Learning English based on a report by The Associated Press.</em></p>
<p>____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>focus </strong><em>–n.</em> attention or concern</p>
<p><strong>detect </strong><em>–v. </em>to study information in order to come up with a conclusion</p>
<p><strong>big bang </strong><em>–n.</em> a time of fast discovery or change</p>
<p><strong>mundane </strong><em>–adj.</em> usual, routine or unimportant</p>
<p><strong>chatter </strong><em>–n.</em> words spoken quickly</p>
<p><strong>alert </strong><em>–v.</em> to direct someone's attention to something important</p>
<p><strong>impressive </strong><em>–adj.</em> causing great appreciation or interest</p>
<p><strong>arrow to the quiver </strong><em>–expression.</em> another kind of weapon added to a group of weapons</p>
<p><strong>simulator </strong><em>–n.</em> a machine or computer system that permits a user to experience an activity such as flying without getting into an airplane</p>
<p><strong>transfer </strong><em>–v.</em> to move information from one place to another</p>
<p><em>We want to hear from you. What would you think if a war was conducted without humans flying airplanes?</em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Taco Stand in Mexico City Gets Michelin Star  (2024/5/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/taco-stand-in-mexico-city-gets-michelin-star.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">17 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>Mexico City's Tacos El Califa de León recently became the first Mexican taco stand to get a Michelin star – an award presented by the famous French restaurant guide.</p>
<p><strong>Chef</strong> Arturo Rivera Martínez recently stood over a very hot <strong>grill</strong> when Michelin representatives came to present him with one of the company's heavy white chef's coats. But Rivera Martinez did not put the jacket on.</p>
<p>In this very small, 3-meter by 3-meter business space, the heat makes the meat. And the heat is strong.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="An overhead view of the Tacos El Califa de León taco stand, in Mexico City, Wednesday, May 15, 2024. Tacos El Califa de León is the first ever taco stand to receive a Michelin star from the French dining guide. (AP Photo/Fernando Llano)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-36d1-08dc7672ecb4_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">An overhead view of the Tacos El Califa de León taco stand, in Mexico City, Wednesday, May 15, 2024. Tacos El Califa de León is the first ever taco stand to receive a Michelin star from the French dining guide. (AP Photo/Fernando Llano)</span></div>
<p>At El Califa de León there are only four things on the menu -- all of them tacos. The food business has been doing the same four things since opening in 1968.</p>
<p>"The secret is the <strong>simplicity</strong> of our taco. It has only a <strong>tortilla</strong>, red or green <strong>sauce</strong>, and that's it. That, and the quality of the meat," said Rivera Martínez. He is also probably the only Michelin-starred chef who, when asked what drink should go with his food, answers "I like a Coke."</p>
<p>Other than perhaps one street food stand in Bangkok, Thailand, El Califa de León is probably the smallest restaurant ever to get a Michelin star. And half of the small space is taken up by a solid steel plate grill that is hotter than the salsa.</p>
<p>Thousands of times a day, Rivera Martínez gets a fresh, thinly sliced piece of beef and puts it on the hot steel grill.</p>
<p>The heat is one of the few secrets Rivera Martínez would share. The steel grill has to be heated to 360 Celsius.</p>
<p>Asked how it felt to get a Michelin star, he said in classic Mexico City <strong>slang</strong>, "it's neat, it's cool."</p>
<p>The prices at his stand are quite high by Mexican standards. A single taco costs nearly $5. But many customers are sure it is the best in the city.</p>
<p>"It's the quality of the meat," said Alberto Munoz, who has been coming to the place for about eight years. "I have never been disappointed. And now I'll <strong>recommend</strong> it with even more reason, now that it has a star."</p>
<p>His son, Alan, who was waiting for a beef taco alongside his father, noted "this is a historic day for Mexican <strong>cuisine</strong>, and we're witnesses to it."</p>
<p>It really is about not changing anything — the freshness of the tortillas, the menu, the design of the restaurant. Owner Mario Hernández Alonso will not even tell where he buys the stand's meat.</p>
<p>By law, following the coronavirus pandemic, Mexico City restaurants have been permitted to open up street-side seating areas. But El Califa de León does not even have a sidewalk where customers could eat because of all the street <strong>vendors.</strong></p>
<p>Asked if he would like them to make room for a street-side seating area, Hernández Alonso said pointing to the street vendors, "As the saying goes, why fix or change something that's alright? You shouldn't fix anything... It's the way God ordered things, and you have to deal with it."</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Mark Stevenson reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>________________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>grill </strong><em>– n.</em> a metal object or frame that is used to cook food over hot coals or a fire</p>
<p><strong>tortilla </strong><em>– n. a</em> round, thin Mexican bread</p>
<p><strong>slang </strong><em>– n. an </em>informal word or expression used in everyday situations</p>
<p><strong>cuisine </strong><em>– n. </em>a kind of cooking</p>
<p><strong>vendor </strong><em>– n. </em>a person who sells something (often on the street)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Brazilian State Lawmakers Declare a Dance ‘Cultural Heritage’  (2024/5/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/brazilian-state-lawmakers-declare-a-dance-cultural-heritage.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Dan Novak</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">17 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>A dance that started in some of Brazil's poorest neighborhoods is being honored by Rio de Janeiro state lawmakers.</p>
<p>The passinho started with leg movements, strong steps backwards and forwards, while moving to a Brazilian form of funk music. It took moves from dance <strong>styles</strong> like break dancing, samba, capoeira and frevo.</p>
<p>Young people in Rio de Janeiro's poor neighborhoods known as favelas started the dance style. Rio de Janeiro state lawmakers declared the dance a piece of "cultural <strong>heritage</strong>" in March. The declaration honors a cultural expression from the favelas.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Youth perform a street dance style known as passinho for their social media accounts, in the Rocinha favela of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, Wednesday, April 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Silvia Izquierdo) " src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-5013-08dc75ef63b4_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Youth perform a street dance style known as passinho for their social media accounts, in the Rocinha favela of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, Wednesday, April 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Silvia Izquierdo) </span></div>
<p>The creators of the passinho were young people and children. They started trying out new moves at home and then showing them off at funk parties in their communities. The dances became more popular after people started sharing them on the internet.</p>
<p>In the early days of social media, people shared videos of their dance moves on Orkut and YouTube. The style started spreading to other favelas and competitions started. The young people copied and learned from the top dancers, leading them to invent new moves.</p>
<p>"Passinho in my life is the basis of everything I have," dancer and <strong>choreographer</strong> Walcir de Oliveira told the Associated Press. "It's where I manage to earn my livelihood, and I can show people my joy and <strong>blow off steam</strong>," he said. "It's where I feel happy, good."</p>
<p>Brazilian producer Julio Ludemir helped discover new dancers by organizing "passinho battles" in the early 2010s. At these events, youths <strong>took turns showing off</strong> their steps before a jury that chose the winners.</p>
<p>A music and dance event in New York City held a competition in 2014. It showed Americans the dance style. Dancers started appearing on popular TV shows and performed at the opening ceremony of the Rio de Janeiro 2016 Olympic Games.</p>
<p>Ludemir describes the style as an expression of Brazilian culture, called "<strong>cannibalism</strong>." That is the idea of taking elements from other cultures to produce something new. He said the passinho is a dance that takes elements "from all dances. It's a crossing of the cultural influences <strong>absorbed</strong> by kids...as they were connecting with the world through social media in internet cafes."</p>
<p>Supporters say dancing also became a way for young people from the favelas to avoid becoming criminals. Rio state legislator Veronica Lima proposed the law honoring the passinho. In a statement, Lima said it was important to help "decriminalize funk and artistic expressions of youths" from the favelas.</p>
<p>Ludemir said the declaration honors the first generation of passinho dancers as examples for favela youths.</p>
<p>Among them is Pablo Henrique Goncalves. He won a passinho battle back in 2014 and created a boy group called OZCrias. The group has four dancers from Rocinha, Rio de Janeiro's largest favela. The group earns money performing.</p>
<p>Another dance group is Passinho Carioca in the Penha favelas on the other side of the city. One of its leaders, Nayara Costa, said she came from a family where everyone was involved in selling drugs. She said Passinho saved her from that life. Now she uses dance to help young people and teach anyone interested in learning.</p>
<p>"Today I give classes to people who are in their sixties; passinho is for everyone," said Costa, who is 23. "Passinho, in the same way that it changed my life, is still going to change the lives of others."</p>
<p>I'm Dan Novak.<em> </em></p>
<p><em>Dan Novak adapted this story for VOA Learning English based on reporting by The Associated Press. </em></p>
<p><em>_________________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>style </strong><em>–n.</em> a particular way of doing an activity or wearing clothes</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>heritage </strong><em>— n. </em>the traditions, beliefs and accomplishments that are part of the history of a group of people</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>choreographer </strong><em>— n. </em>a person who directs and teaches dance</p>
<p class="CxSpMiddle"><strong>blow off steam </strong><em>— v. (idiom) </em>to release energy to avoid getting angry or unhappy</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Improve Your Vocabulary: Part 1  (2024/5/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/improve-your-vocabulary-part-1.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Yaroslav Khrokalo</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">17 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we talk about how you can improve your <strong>vocabulary</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Many VOA Learning English fans write to us with this question: What is the best way to improve my vocabulary?</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Improve Your Vocabulary: Part 1" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-321b-08dc74f02b0c_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Improve Your Vocabulary: Part 1</span></div>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>This is a good question, VOA fans.</p>
<p>Many learners think the best way to improve their vocabulary is to learn the definition of many words. But this is not necessarily the best way to improve. The best way is to fully know a word.</p>
<p>To know a word, we must know its form, meaning, and usage. Today let's talk about the form of a word. In the coming weeks, we will talk about meaning and usage.</p>
<p>The form of a word can relate to how it sounds, is written and what its parts are. Knowing the sounds of a word includes recognizing it when it is spoken and being able to say it correctly. This includes the individual sounds and also how the sounds may change when people are saying the word quickly. For example,</p>
<p><em>It's nice to meet you</em>.</p>
<p>When some people say this sentence at a natural speed, they might make a /ch/ sound at the end of the word "meet" and the beginning of the word "you" although the words' spellings do not suggest this.</p>
<p>This sound change does not affect the meaning of the words. But it might cause you trouble when you are trying to understand the sentence.</p>
<p>In English, <strong>stress</strong> is important to the sound of a word, and it can even decide whether a word is a noun or a verb.</p>
<p>For example, the word spelled <em>r-e-c-o-r-d</em> can be thought of as two words. When we stress the first part of the word, <em>RE-cord</em>, it is a noun. When we stress the second part of the word, <em>re-CORD</em>, it is a verb. What appears to be one word is really two parts of speech. This is part of knowing what form a word takes.</p>
<p>The form of a word also involves its parts. It is important to recognize the root word in addition to <strong>prefixes</strong> or <strong>suffixes</strong>. These are added beginnings or endings, which change the meaning of the word's root.</p>
<p>For example, knowing that the word "addition" includes recognizing the verb "to add" plus the suffix –t-i-o-n, which suggests a state or an action. Knowing the word "untrue" includes recognizing the base word "true" and the prefix -un, which means "not."</p>
<p>When we look at English words in this way, we can see that our vocabulary expands by understanding a word's form.</p>
<p>As we saw in the word "<em>record,</em>" the same word can work as two parts of speech.</p>
<p>VOA fans, the best way to improve your vocabulary is to really "know a word," its form, meaning, and usage, not just a definition.</p>
<p>Do you have a question about American English? Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="mailto:learningenglish@voanews.com">learningenglish@voanews.com</a>.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher.</em></p>
<p>I'm Gena Bennett.<em> </em></p>
<p><em>Yaroslav Khrokalo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>__________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>vocabulary </strong><em>–n.</em> all the words a particular person knows</p>
<p><strong>stress </strong>–<em>n</em>. giving attention to one part of a word when speaking it</p>
<p><strong>prefix </strong>–n. <strong> </strong>a group of letters appearing at the beginning of a word that changes the word's meaning</p>
<p><strong>suffix </strong>–<em>n</em>. a group of letters appearing at the end of a word that changes the word's meaning</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>AI Helps Woman Regain Voice after Brain Surgery  (2024/5/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/ai-helps-woman-regain-voice-after-brain-surgery.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Dan Friedell</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">16 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>Lots of people are concerned about the ability that artificial intelligence (AI) has to copy their voices. When AI is used to make false recordings of things that a person never said, it is called a "deepfake."</p>
<p>However, more and more stories are coming out about how AI is helping people who can no longer speak, regain a version of their voice.</p>
<p>For example, country music singer Randy Travis recently released his first new song in over 10 years with the help of AI technology. Travis suffered a <strong>stroke</strong> and can no longer sing.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Alexis Bogan, whose speech was impaired by a brain tumor, uses an AI-powered smartphone app to create an audible drink order at a Starbucks drive-thru on Monday, April 29, 2024, in Lincoln, R.I. (AP Photo/Steven Senne)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/da658f9a-092b-4bc2-8939-527701567d1f_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Alexis Bogan, whose speech was impaired by a brain tumor, uses an AI-powered smartphone app to create an audible drink order at a Starbucks drive-thru on Monday, April 29, 2024, in Lincoln, R.I. (AP Photo/Steven Senne)</span></div>
<p>The technology is also able to help people like 21-year-old Alexis "Lexi" Bogan from the eastern state of Rhode Island.</p>
<p>Bogan used to love singing along with songs by her favorite musicians like Taylor Swift and Zach Bryan. She was a singer in her school music group as a teenager. If she was spending time with friends, she would be the loudest during a discussion about politics over a large fire in the back yard.</p>
<p>But a surprise <strong>diagnosis</strong> changed all that. Last August, doctors removed a <strong>tumor</strong> from the back of her brain. The surgery was a success. But after doctors removed a tube used to help her breathe during the operation, Bogan had trouble speaking.</p>
<p>Bogan is working with <strong>therapists</strong> and has regained some ability to speak, but there is no sign that she will ever be able to speak like she used to.</p>
<p>Last month, Bogan got her voice back in a way. Experts created a tool for her using AI. She uses a text-to-voice <strong>app</strong> on her phone so she can now do things like order her favorite coffee at Starbucks. She uses it by writing words in her phone and holding it up at the coffee shop so servers can hear her.</p>
<p>The app uses OpenAI's voice tool. Programmers trained the app using a 15-second sound recording from a cooking video Bogan made as a teenager. Most of the video had cooking sounds, so that is all they could use. But it was enough.</p>
<p>Bogan's doctors say Lexi's case shows why AI can be helpful.</p>
<p>Dr. Rohaid Ali is training in neuroscience at Brown University's medical school. He called Bogan "a <strong>trailblazer</strong>." He said the technology can help millions of people with brain injuries, throat cancer or other diseases that prevent a person from speaking.</p>
<p>Fatima Mirza is another doctor working on the project. She said there is a risk that AI technology can be used by bad people, "but we can't forget about the patient and the social good." She said the technology permits Bogan to have something close to her true voice.</p>
<p>The doctors had already worked with OpenAI on an earlier project. When they found out the company wanted to test their voice <strong>generator</strong> to help patients, they thought of Bogan.</p>
<p>Bogan said "it's almost like a part of my identity was taken when I lost my voice."</p>
<p>She said she was starting to forget what her real voice sounded like before she started using the app.</p>
<p>The app makes mistakes, but people who know Bogan do not seem worried. They are just happy to hear Lexi's voice.</p>
<p>"I get so emotional every time I hear her voice," said her mother, Pamela, with tears in her eyes.</p>
<p>Bogan said it helped "<strong>boost</strong> my <strong>confidence</strong> to somewhat where it was before all this happened." She said she uses the app about 40 times per day.</p>
<p>The doctors are working with other patients to gather voice samples and they hope to bring the app to other hospitals around the world. But right now, the app, called Voice Engine, is not publicly available. Other AI companies, however, are making their voice-<strong>cloning</strong> services available to entertainment companies or other organizations.</p>
<p>Jeff Harris is OpenAI's project leader for Voice Engine. He said the company is "very limited in who we're giving the technology to" because they want to be sure everyone whose voice is being used has given permission.</p>
<p>Bogan believes the technology will progress over time so that when she is older, she does not have to depend on the voice she had as a teenager. She is excited that she is contributing to a change that will help people who are currently using robotic-sounding voices.</p>
<p>For now, "even though I don't have my voice fully back, I have something that helps me find my voice again," she said.</p>
<p>I'm Dan Friedell.</p>
<p><em>Dan Friedell adapted this story for Learning English based on a report by The Associated Press.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>stroke </strong><em>—n.</em> a serious medical problem in which a blood vessel gets blocked</p>
<p><strong>diagnosis </strong><em>–n.</em> a medical opinion that explains the cause of an illness or disease</p>
<p><strong>tumor </strong><em>–n.</em> an abnormal growth of tissue</p>
<p><strong>therapist </strong><em>–n.</em> a person who helps a patient with a medical or physical problem with treatments that do not usually use medicine</p>
<p><strong>app </strong><em>–n.</em> a computer program that has one main purpose</p>
<p><strong>trailblazer </strong><em>–n.</em> a person who is among the first to do something</p>
<p><strong>generator </strong><em>–n.</em> something that creates things automatically like numbers, or electrical current</p>
<p><strong>boost </strong><em>–v.</em> to lift or raise up</p>
<p><strong>confidence </strong><em>–n.</em> a feeling of being sure of and believing in oneself</p>
<p><strong>cloning </strong><em>–n. (technology)</em> using software and computer commands to create copies of digital things</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>New Study Examines How Elephants Say ‘Hello’  (2024/5/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/new-study-examines-how-elephants-say-hello.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">16 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>People <strong>greet</strong> each other in many ways. They might say "hello" in different languages. They might physically do something like shaking hands, giving hugs, or exchanging kisses.</p>
<p>Elephants seem to have many greetings too. A recent study gives new information about these greetings, including how greetings differ depending on the animals' sex and whether they are looking at each other.</p>
<p>The study was based on observations of African savannah elephants in the Jafuta Reserve in Zimbabwe.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - The male savannah elephant Doma and the female savannah elephant Kariba engage in greeting behavior at Jafuta Reserve in Zimbabwe in this undated handout picture. (Vesta Eleuteri/Handout via REUTERS)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/e3a6ea94-33e0-446e-b2be-40694509cdaf_cx0_cy11_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - The male savannah elephant Doma and the female savannah elephant Kariba engage in greeting behavior at Jafuta Reserve in Zimbabwe in this undated handout picture. (Vesta Eleuteri/Handout via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>Vesta Eleuteri of the University of Vienna in Austria was the lead writer of the study that appeared recently in Communications Biology.</p>
<p>"Elephants live in a so-called '<strong>fission-fusion</strong>' society, where they often separate and reunite, meeting after hours, days or months apart," Eleuteri said.</p>
<p>Elephants are Earth's largest land animals. They are highly intelligent, with strong memories and problem-solving skills, and complex communication.</p>
<p>Female elephants of different family groups might have strong social bonds with each other, forming "bond groups." Earlier studies in the wild have reported that when these groups meet, the elephants perform special greeting ceremonies to announce and strengthen their social bonds, Eleuteri said.</p>
<p>Male elephants have different social bonds from females. Male greetings may serve to ease possible hostility. Male elephants greet mainly by smelling each other, reaching with their trunks, Eleuteri added.</p>
<p>The recent study gives details on around 20 movements tied to greetings. It showed that elephants mix these movements in exact ways with sounds. The different sounds are described as rumbles, roars and trumpets.</p>
<p>The study also showed how smell plays an important part in greetings. Elephant greetings include behaviors unusual for humans, including releasing body waste. Elephants can also release <strong>secretions</strong> from a special <strong>gland</strong>.</p>
<p>Elephants may greet each other by making <strong>gestures</strong> meant to be seen, like spreading their ears or showing their behinds. The creatures also use movements producing special sounds, or they may use movements that involve touching other elephants. Movements involving touching are known as tactile gestures.</p>
<p>Eleuteri suggested that elephants appeared to know what other elephants can see. "They preferred using visual gestures when their partner was looking at them, while tactile ones when they were not," Eleuteri explained.</p>
<p>Greeting behavior has been studied in a number of animals.</p>
<p>"Many other <strong>species</strong> greet, including different primates, hyenas and dogs," Eleuteri said.</p>
<p>These animal greetings help guide social situations by reducing tension or confirming social bonds, Eleuteri added.</p>
<p>The new research builds on earlier studies of elephant greeting behavior. The nine observed elephants - four females and five males - were "semi-captive." That means they freely moved around their natural environment during daytime and stayed in structures at night.</p>
<p>Greetings used by the female elephants closely matched the behavior of wild elephants. The greeting behavior of the male elephants appeared to be different from wild male elephants.</p>
<p>Wild male elephants are often alone, forming loose connections with other elephants.</p>
<p>The temporal gland is midway between the eye and the ear. That gland plays a part in elephant greeting by releasing a substance called temporin. Temporin contains chemical information about an elephant's condition. Elephants often use their trunks to touch the temporal glands of others.</p>
<p>Eleuteri said elephant body wastes "contain chemical information important for elephants, like the identity of the individual, their reproductive state or even their emotional state."</p>
<p>"Maybe they don't need to tell each other how they're doing, as they can smell it," Eleuteri added.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Will Dunham reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>greet</strong> <em>–v.</em> to perform actions or say words on meeting someone</p>
<p><strong>fission</strong> <em>– n.</em> a breaking up into parts of a thing</p>
<p><strong>fusion</strong> <em>– n.</em> a union or merging of more than one thing</p>
<p><strong>secretion</strong> <em>– n.</em> a substance release by the body as the result of a process</p>
<p><strong>gland </strong>–<em> n</em>. a specialized organ that releases a substance used by the body</p>
<p><strong>gesture </strong><em>–n. </em>a movement that can be repeated and means something to someone who sees it</p>
<p><strong>species</strong><em> – n</em>. a class of plants or animals having common attributes</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Agency Permits Qualified Health Claim for Yogurt  (2024/5/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/us-agency-permits-qualified-health-claim-for-yogurt.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">16 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle </em>report.</p>
<p>The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) recently permitted yogurt producers to make a health claim on containers of their products.</p>
<p>Yogurt is a food made from milk and special bacteria.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Dannon yogurt sits on display in a market in Pittsburgh, Wednesday, Aug. 8, 2018. (AP Photo/Gene J. Puskar)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-8af9-08dc741eade8_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Dannon yogurt sits on display in a market in Pittsburgh, Wednesday, Aug. 8, 2018. (AP Photo/Gene J. Puskar)</span></div>
<p>The claim is that eating yogurt might reduce the risk of type 2 diabetes, a health problem linked to how the body uses sugar for fuel. Type 2 diabetes is believed to affect about 38 million Americans.</p>
<p>Danone North America is the U.S. division of a French food company that makes several popular yogurt products. In 2018, the company asked the FDA for permission to make what is known as a "<strong>qualified</strong> health claim" about yogurt.</p>
<p>In March, the FDA said it would not object to such a claim. The food agency said that there is some evidence to support the claim that eating at least 900 grams of yogurt per week might reduce the risk of developing type 2 diabetes.</p>
<p>However, the agency said there is not "significant scientific agreement" about the claim.</p>
<p><strong>What is a ‘qualified health claim'?</strong></p>
<p>A "qualified health claim" means that the health effects have not been supported by wide scientific agreement.</p>
<p>Food producers are permitted to make some claims about the healthfulness of their products, but they also must include additional information to prevent misleading the public.</p>
<p>The FDA has permitted "qualified health claims" on <strong>dietary supplements</strong> since 2000 and on foods since 2002. The policy formed after the FDA faced legal action in the 1990s because it did not permit food companies to put any health claims on products that the agency did not approve. Lawyers successfully argued that such bans violated free speech rights guaranteed by the First Amendment of the U.S. Constitution.</p>
<p>Rather than fight in court, the FDA created a new<strong> </strong>term, separate from "<strong>authorized</strong> health claims." These claims, the agency says, are supported by scientific agreement.</p>
<p>Examples of "qualified health claims" include claims that eating some kinds of cocoa might reduce heart disease. Another example is that cranberry juice might cut the risk of repeated urinary tract infections in women.</p>
<p><strong>Yogurt and type 2 diabetes</strong></p>
<p>In the case of yogurt, Danone submitted information from studies that observed people over time. The yogurt company found a link between eating yogurt and fewer signs of diabetes. The FDA agreed that there is "some <strong>credible</strong> evidence" that eating yogurt as a whole food has good health effects but not because of any one nutrient that it contains. In other words, there is no direct evidence that yogurt can prevent diabetes. There is only indirect evidence that eating yogurt may be connected to reducing signs connected to an increased risk of the disease.</p>
<p>The FDA says that it will not object to a qualified health claim rather than authorizing it.</p>
<p>Critics questioned the use of such a claim. They say it is not based on research that proves yogurt reduces Type 2 diabetes risk.</p>
<p>The Center for Science in the Public Interest is a nonprofit <strong>advocacy</strong> group based in Washington, D.C. It is critical of the qualified health claim related to yogurt. It said no single food can reduce the risk of a disease that is tied to overall diet.</p>
<p>It even warned that the claim might raise the risk of diabetes. The center said people might eat more yogurt products that include added sugars including cookies and pretzels—even if they do not have the claim on their containers.</p>
<p>Marion Nestle is a food policy expert at New York University. She said qualified health claims based on limited evidence are "<strong>ridiculous</strong> <strong>on their face</strong>."</p>
<p>And that's the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report. I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Jonel Aleccia reported this story for the Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em><i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;___________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>qualified </strong><em>–adj.</em> provided with a condition or an exception</p>
<p><strong>dietary supplement </strong><em>–n.</em> a class of products whose sales are based on the belief that they are good for a person's health</p>
<p><strong>authorized</strong><em>–adj.</em> officially approved by a qualified agency</p>
<p><strong>urinary tract</strong> <em>–n.</em> the path from the bladder that urine takes to go out of the body</p>
<p><strong>credible </strong><em>–adj.</em> something that can reasonably be believed</p>
<p><strong>advocacy </strong><em>–n.</em> the activity of supporting a cause or a group of people through several means</p>
<p><strong>ridiculous </strong><em>–adj.</em> not serious</p>
<p><strong>on their face </strong><em>–</em><em>idiom<strong> </strong></em>from only what is known at first</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Reviewing Prefixes in Protest Stories  (2024/5/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/reviewing-prefixes-in-protest-stories.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">16 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>In last week's <em>Everyday Grammar</em>, we looked at prefixes in reports of student protests against the war between Israel and Hamas.</p>
<p>Then, we asked our readers to use prefixes from that story to write about their experiences with protests in their own countries.</p>
<p>Our reader Kaori from Japan wrote to us about her father's experiences with student protests. She begins:</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-340e-08dc75677d23_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption"></span></div>
<p><em>"My father experienced anti-war demonstration against Japanese military re-establishment after World War Ⅱ when he was a university student."</em></p>
<p><strong>Use an article before a singular noun</strong></p>
<p>First, let us consider some small grammatical corrections. The <strong>phrase</strong>, <em>"anti-war demonstration," </em>needs an indefinite <strong>article</strong> as in <em>"an anti-war demonstration,"</em> or it needs to be plural, as in <em>"anti-war demonstrations."</em> This is because it is the first time the demonstrations are being described. Remember this rule:</p>
<p>Definite or indefinite article + Singular noun</p>
<p>(Definite article) + Plural noun</p>
<p>Using the definite article can be <strong>optional</strong> in some cases.</p>
<p>Another correction is to the phrase, <em>"Japanese military."</em> This is a singular noun phrase, and it should have a definite article before it, as in <em>"the Japanese military."</em></p>
<p>The phrase, <em>"the Japanese military re-establishment"</em> might be unclear to a reader who does not know a lot about the history of Japan.</p>
<p>We can change this statement to make it a little easier to understand. Rather than <em>"the Japanese military re-establishment,"</em> we suggest using a prepositional phrase, <em>"the re-establishment of the Japanese military."</em> This kind of possessive structure can help clarify that the process of <em>"establishing the military again"</em> is being described.</p>
<p>Among the prefixes Kaori uses in the statement, we find "anti-," which means "against" and "re-," which means "do again."</p>
<p>Kaori might re-write her statement:</p>
<p><em>"My father experienced an anti-war demonstration against the re-establishment of the Japanese military after World War II when he was a university student."</em></p>
<p><strong>Looking back from age 80</strong></p>
<p>Kaori continued, <em>"Now, he is over 80 years old and says that it was some stupid memory because he didn't have any anti-war policy and reforming <strong>unstable</strong> society after war."</em> Here we have the prefix "un-," which means "the opposite of."</p>
<p>A formal way to say how your father sees this experience is <em>"he looks back on it with some <strong>embarrassment</strong>."</em> You say, <em>"He didn't have any anti-war policy"</em> but usually we talk about a government or organization having a policy.</p>
<p>Speaking of an individual, Kaori may re-write this statement:</p>
<p><em>"He looks back on the protests with some embarrassment because he did not hold strong anti-war opinions."</em></p>
<p>The next phrase, <em>"reforming unstable society after war,"</em> is a little unclear. It might mean that Kaori's father did not understand the need to reform Japan's society, which was unstable after the war. A clearer way to say this uses the noun form, "instability," where the prefix "un" changes to "in-."</p>
<p>Then we can use the <strong>conjunction</strong> "nor" to connect two <strong>negative</strong> statements:</p>
<p><em>"He looks back on the protests with some embarrassment because he did not hold strong anti-war opinions, nor did he understand the instability of Japan's society after the war."</em></p>
<p><strong>Youthful energy</strong></p>
<p>Kaori's next statement is, <em>"Young power and enthusiastic mood at that time let him to march with his friends near U.S. navy camp in Yokosuka."</em></p>
<p>Let us correct one word choice first. The verb "let" does not fit well in this statement because it means to <em>permit</em> someone to do something. "Led" works better because it means to <em>cause</em> someone to do something. Note that we can express <em>"young power and enthusiastic mood"</em> with the shorter phrase, "youthful energy." And remember our rule about the definite article. We need "the" before "U.S."</p>
<p>To describe a large group of military structures, we usually use "base" rather than "camp." We should use the adjective form, "naval" instead of the verb form, "navy." Putting these changes together, we can say, "His youthful energy led him to march with his friends near the U.S. naval base in Yokosuka."</p>
<p>Thank you for writing to us, Kaori. It was good for you to talk with your father about his youthful experience with anti-war protests. And we are grateful to you for sharing it with us.</p>
<p>And that's Everyday Grammar!</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jill Robbins wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>phrase</strong> – <em>n.</em> a group of two or more words that express a single idea but do not usually form a complete sentence</p>
<p><strong>mention</strong> – <em>n. </em>an act of saying something about a topic</p>
<p><strong>optional</strong><em> – adj.</em> available as a choice but not required</p>
<p><strong>stable</strong> – <em>adj.</em> in a good state or condition that is not easily changed or likely to change</p>
<p><strong>embarrassment</strong> – <em>n.</em> the state of feeling foolish in front of others</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers: Smarter Vehicles Could Greatly Change Traffic Signals  (2024/5/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/researchers-smarter-vehicles-could-greatly-change-traffic-signals.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">15 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>Researchers say the rise of more smart and connected vehicles on American roads could lead to big changes for traffic signals.</p>
<p>The current U.S. traffic signal system has been in existence for more than 100 years. But experts are now studying ways to link technology-equipped vehicles to signal systems in an attempt to improve safety and traffic flows.</p>
<p>One research effort is led by a team at North Carolina State University. Engineering professor Ali Hajbabaie is the leader of that research. He told The Associated Press one major change that signal systems could see is different colored lights.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This University of Michigan College photo shows vehicles as they drive through an intersection in Birmingham, Michigan. (Jeremy Little/University of Michigan College of Engineering via AP)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-771e-08dc74fb2b32_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This University of Michigan College photo shows vehicles as they drive through an intersection in Birmingham, Michigan. (Jeremy Little/University of Michigan College of Engineering via AP)</span></div>
<p>Most U.S. traffic signals currently include three lights to direct drivers at <strong>intersections</strong>: red, yellow and green. But Hajbabaie said it might make sense to add a fourth color, possibly white.</p>
<p>This color could inform motorists when there is a large collection of self-driving vehicles in a particular area. When many self-driving vehicles are present, the additional light would signal other drivers to follow the lead of those vehicles.</p>
<p>"When we get to the intersection, we stop if it's red and we go if it's green," said Hajbabaie. "But if the white light is active, you just follow the vehicle in front of you."</p>
<p>The North Carolina State team estimated that such changes are likely years away. Hajbabaie said one reason for this is because this kind of system would require between 40 to 50 percent of all vehicles on the road to be self-driving.</p>
<p>Sandy Karp is a spokesperson for Waymo. Waymo is a self-driving vehicle company owned by Google's parent, Alphabet. She told the AP that Waymo had already launched ride-sharing services that use full self-driving vehicles in Los Angeles, California and Austin, Texas. Those services do not use a fourth traffic light.</p>
<p>In an email to the AP, Karp said she thought it was good that researchers are currently "thinking creatively" about ways to change traffic light signals to improve safety and traffic flows. However, she said that officials and companies should think very carefully before deciding on, and moving forward with, major <strong>infrastructure </strong>changes.</p>
<p>Researchers at the University of Michigan are also testing different methods. They have carried out a test program in an area outside the city of Detroit. Their research collects data on the speed and <strong>location</strong> of General Motors (GM) vehicles in the area. The data has been used to change the timing of city traffic lights in an effort to improve traffic flows.</p>
<p>Henry Liu is a civil engineering professor at the University of Michigan. He helped lead the research. He said the launch of a new U.S. traffic system could be a lot closer than people might think.</p>
<p>Liu said that even with as few as 6 percent of vehicles connected to the GM system, there is still enough data to change the timing of the traffic lights enough to smooth traffic flows.</p>
<p>The area near Detroit where the testing is taking place has 34 traffic signals. It was chosen because lights in the area are set to change at the same times each day. This is the case for more than half of traffic signals nationwide. These signals are not connected to cameras or sensors to watch traffic flows in real time.</p>
<p>Liu noted that higher-tech solutions will require cities to make complex and costly investments.</p>
<p>"The beauty of this is you don't have to do anything to the infrastructure," Liu said. "The data is not coming from the infrastructure. It's coming from the car companies."</p>
<p>Danielle Deneau is the director of traffic safety at the Road Commission in Oakland County, Michigan. She said results of the University of Michigan research changed the timing of green lights only by a few seconds. However, Deneau added, even that was enough to improve traffic flows.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong><strong> </strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>intersection </strong><em>– n. </em> the place where two or more streets meet or cross each other</p>
<p><strong>infrastructure </strong><em>– n. </em>the system of public works of a country, state, or region; also : the resources (such as buildings or equipment) required for an activity</p>
<p><strong>location </strong><em>– n. </em>the place or position where something happens</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Teen Started College at 10, Earns Doctorate at 17  (2024/5/16) | 美国天才10岁上大学18岁博士毕业</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/us-teen-started-college-at-10-earns-doctorate-at-17.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>Dorothy Jean Tillman II of Chicago, Illinois took her first college class at age 10. This month, she became the youngest person to earn a doctorate in integrated behavioral health at Arizona State University.<br/>
来自伊利诺伊州芝加哥市的多萝西·吉恩·蒂尔曼二世在10岁时首次就读大学课程。本月，她成为亚利桑那州立大学获得综合行为健康博士学位最年轻的学生。</p>
<p>When she completed her study program, she was 17.<br/>
当她完成学业时年仅17岁。</p>
<p>Arizona State professor Leslie Manson told the television program Good Morning America, "It's a wonderful celebration, and we hope ... that Dorothy Jean inspires more students." And she added, "But this is still something so rare and unique."<br/>
亚利桑那州立大学教授莱斯利·曼森在电视节目《早安美国》中表示，“这是一个美妙的庆典，我们希望多萝西·吉恩能激励更多的学生。”她补充道，“但这仍然是一件非常罕见和独特的事情。”</p>
<p>Her friends and family, though, call Tillman by another name, "Dorothy Jeanius." A "genius" is a very smart person.<br/>
然而，她的朋友和家人都叫蒂尔曼另一个名字，“多萝西·吉恩天才”。“天才”是指一个非常聪明的人。</p>
<p>When most students her age were still in middle school, Tillman took classes through the College of Lake County in northern Illinois. She studied psychology and completed her associate's degree in 2016.<br/>
当大多数和她同龄的学生还在上中学时，蒂尔曼在伊利诺伊州北部的莱克县学院上课。她学习了心理学，并于2016年修完了副学士学位。</p>
<p>She earned a bachelor's in humanities from New York's Excelsior College in 2018. About two years later, she finished her master of science degree from Unity College in Maine. In 2021, she started work on her doctoral degree at Arizona State.<br/>
她于2018年获得纽约伊克塞尔希尔学院人文学科的学士学位。大约两年后，她在缅因州的联合学院完成了理学硕士学位。2021年，她开始在亚利桑那州立大学攻读博士学位。</p>
<p>Most of her work has been done online while living at home.<br/>
她的大部分学业都是在家里上网完成的。</p>
<p>Tillman told the Associated Press that she credits her mother and grandmother for her educational success.<br/>
蒂尔曼告诉美联社，她把自己在教育上的成功归功于母亲和祖母。</p>
<p>"Everything that we were doing didn't seem abnormal to me or out of the ordinary until it started getting all of the attention," said Tillman.<br/>
蒂尔曼说：“在我看来，我们所做的一切都稀松平常，直到它开始引起所有人的注意。”</p>
<p>But she did not get to do all the normal things for young people. "I didn't have the everyday school things like (school) dances or spirit weeks or just school pictures and things like that ..." she said.<br/>
但她并没有机会去做那些对年轻人来说很平常的事情。她说：“我没有参加过日常学校活动，比如学校舞会或精神周，也没有校内照片之类的……”</p>
<p>She did find time for a dance program and started an organization called the Dorothyjeanius STEAM Leadership Institute. STEAM stands for "science, technology, engineering, arts and math." The program helps young people interested in those subjects during school breaks.<br/>
她确实抽出时间参加了一个舞蹈项目，并创办了一个名为Dorothyjeanius STEAM领导力研究所的组织。STEAM代表“科学、技术、工程、艺术和数学”。该项目帮助在课余时间对这些科目感兴趣的年轻人。</p>
<p>Now that she has finished her studies, Tillman who is now 18, plans to work on raising money to expand her organization. She hopes to bring it to other places beyond Chicago.<br/>
现在18岁的蒂尔曼已经完成了学业，她计划筹集资金来扩大她的组织。她希望把它带到芝加哥以外的其他地方。</p>
<p>Manson, the Arizona State professor, said Tillman is creative and energetic, and that she is "a true leader."<br/>
亚利桑那州立大学教授曼森说，蒂尔曼富有创造力和活力，她是“一个真正的领导者”。</p>
<p>Her mother Jimalita Tillman said she is proud of her daughter's ability to deal with success while making good choices between taking part in social activities and her studies.<br/>
她的母亲表示，她为女儿能够在参加社交活动和学习之间做出良好选择的同时应对成功而感到骄傲。</p>
<p>I'm Dan Friedell.<br/>
我是丹·弗里德尔。(51VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Miniature Poodle Wins Westminster Dog Show  (2024/5/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/miniature-poodle-wins-westminster-dog-show.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">15 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>A miniature poodle named Sage won the top prize Tuesday night at the 148th Westminster Kennel Club dog show.</p>
<p>That is the 11th victory for poodles at the famous dog competition in New York City – only wire fox terriers have won more times.</p>
<p>Kaz Hosaka is the <strong>handler</strong> for Sage. "No words," he said about Sage's win and added, "So happy — <strong>exciting</strong>." He also was the handler of Spice, when that miniature poodle won the 2002 Westminster.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Sage, a miniature poodle, poses for photos after winning best in show at the 148th Westminster Kennel Club dog show Tuesday, May 14, 2024, at the USTA Billie Jean King National Tennis Center in New York. (AP Photo/Julia Nikhinson)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-be85-08dc750203f8_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Sage, a miniature poodle, poses for photos after winning best in show at the 148th Westminster Kennel Club dog show Tuesday, May 14, 2024, at the USTA Billie Jean King National Tennis Center in New York. (AP Photo/Julia Nikhinson)</span></div>
<p>But Hosaka said this latest victory would be his final competition after 45 years.</p>
<p>Hosaka said Sage "gave a great performance for me." The black poodle won over six other dogs to take the "best in show." Second place went to Mercedes, a German shepherd.</p>
<p>Others in the final round included Comet, a shih tzu, Monty, a giant schnauzer, Louis, an Afghan hound, Micah, a black cocker spaniel, and Frankie, a colored bull terrier.</p>
<p>While Sage was going around the competition <strong>ring</strong>, a protester interfered in the event. The protester carried a sign urging people to "boycott <strong>breeders</strong>" and tried to enter the ring. Security guards seized the activist. Police and the animal rights group, PETA, said three demonstrators were arrested.</p>
<p>Rosalind Kramer, a judge at the event, called the final lineup "excellent, <strong>glorious</strong>." Monty's handler and co-owner, Katie Bernardin added, "just to be in the ring with everyone else is an honor."</p>
<p>Dogs first compete against others of their breed. Then the winner of each breed goes up against others in its "group." The seven group winners meet in the final round.</p>
<p>The "best in show" winner gets a trophy and a place in dog-world history, but the prize does not include money.</p>
<p>Besides the winners, other dogs were also popular with the crowd. A lagotto Romagnolo named Harry made people laugh by sitting up and begging for a treat from his handler; and a vizsla named Fletcher appealed to the crowd by jumping up on its handler after finishing a turn around the ring.</p>
<p>There were also some very big dogs at the event. One was Ralphie, a great Dane weighing 80 kilograms. His much smaller handler, Shane Jichetti, said it takes a lot of experience to show an animal so big. But she added, "If you have a <strong>bond</strong> with your dog, and you just go with it, it works out."</p>
<p>The Westminster show dates to 1877 and centers on the traditional purebred judging that leads to the "best in show" prize. But over the last few years, the club has added <strong>agility</strong> and obedience events open to mixed-breed dogs.</p>
<p>This year, a border collie-papillon mix named Nimble became the first non-purebred winner of the agility competition.</p>
<p>Kramer, the best in show judge, made a point of thanking "every dog, whether it's a house dog or a show dog."</p>
<p>"Because," she said, "you make our lives whole."</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Jennifer Peltz reported this story for The Associated Press. Hai Do adapted the story for Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>handler</strong> - n. a person who guides and controls a dog in public</p>
<p><strong>exciting</strong> - adj. causing feelings of interest and enthusiasm</p>
<p><strong>ring</strong> - n. an area that is used for shows or contests</p>
<p><strong>breeder</strong> - n. people who raise particular kinds of dog</p>
<p><strong>glorious</strong> - adj. deserving fame and honor</p>
<p><strong>bond</strong> - n. something that is shared</p>
<p><strong>agility</strong> - n. quick, easy and smooth movement</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Migration Group Says 76 Million Displaced in 2023  (2024/5/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/migration-group-says-76-million-displaced-in-2023.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Gregory Stachel</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">15 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>Conflicts and natural disasters caused nearly 76 million people to be displaced within their countries a migration research group says.</p>
<p>The Internal Displacement Monitoring Center (IDMC) said violence in Sudan, Congo and the Middle East is driving two-thirds of new displacement.</p>
<p>The Geneva-based IDMC released its report on May 14. It found that the number of internally displaced people has increased 50 percent over the past five years. The number does not cover refugees: displaced people who flee to another country.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="South Sudanese shelter in a transit center in Renk, South Sudan Wednesday, May 17, 2023. (AP Photo/Sam Mednick)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/6f7f2726-473b-4635-81e1-066773f4cff7_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">South Sudanese shelter in a transit center in Renk, South Sudan Wednesday, May 17, 2023. (AP Photo/Sam Mednick)</span></div>
<p>The report deals with two major sets of information. It counted 46.9 million physical movements of people in 2023. Sometimes the people moved more than once. In most of those cases, the displaced people are expected to return. They are forced from their homes because of natural disasters like floods.</p>
<p>The group also follows the number of people who were living away from their homes in 2023. Those include people still displaced from earlier years. That total is 75.9 million people at the end of last year. Half of those people were in countries south of the Sahara Desert in Africa.</p>
<p>Jan Egeland is secretary-general of the Norwegian Refugee Council, which runs the research organization. He said the findings of the latest report are that the world is in a deep crisis. He said, "We have never, ever recorded worse <strong>figures</strong> for internal displacement by violence, by conflict, by <strong>persecution</strong>."</p>
<p>Almost 90 percent of the total displacement was linked to conflict. About 10 percent was tied to the effects of natural disasters.</p>
<p>The displacement of more than 9 million people in Sudan at the end of 2023 was a record for a single country since the center started collecting information 16 years ago. Sudan's conflict began in April 2023 as increasing tensions between the military and the Rapid Support Forces broke out into open fighting.</p>
<p>The group also reported on movements in Gaza. It said there were a total of 3.4 million movements in Gaza in the last three months of 2023. The activity followed the Israeli military reaction to the October 7 attacks on Israel by Gaza's Hamas rulers. Many people moved more than once within the territory, and all of the movements were counted. There are about 2.2 million people in Gaza. At the end of the year, 1.7 million people were displaced in Gaza.</p>
<p>Director Alexandra Bilak said the millions of people forced to flee in 2023 was the "<strong>tip of the iceberg</strong>." She said there are tens of millions of displaced people from other conflicts, violence and disasters.</p>
<p>Supporters say the report's figures show the effects of conflict, climate change and other <strong>factors </strong>on human movements. The United Nations refugee agency follows data on displacement across borders but not within countries. And the U.N. migration agency follows all movements of people, including for economic or lifestyle reasons.</p>
<p>I'm Gregory Stachel.</p>
<p><em>Jamey Keaten reported this story for The Associated Press. Gregory Stachel adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>figures </strong><em>– n. (pl.)</em> numbers</p>
<p><strong>persecution </strong><em>– v. </em>to treat (someone) cruelly or unfairly especially because of race or religious or political beliefs</p>
<p><strong>tip of the iceberg </strong><em>– idiom </em>evidence of a problem that seems small but hides a much larger problem that is not known and is a big threat</p>
<p><strong>factor </strong><em>– n. </em>something that helps produce or influence a result: one of the things that cause something to happen</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Two Win World Food Prize for Securing Agricultural Seeds  (2024/5/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.51voa.cn/202405/two-win-world-food-prize-for-securing-agricultural-seeds.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">14 May 2024</span><br/>
<p>About 20 years ago, Cary Fowler and Geoffrey Hawtin wanted to prevent hunger and protect the world's food supply. The two men imagined a so-called "<strong>doomsday</strong> vault" for plant seeds. (A vault is a secure storage structure.)</p>
<p>Fowler and Hawtin's goal was to keep a supply of seeds safe if existing seed banks were threatened by war, climate change, or other crises. They decided to build their storage building into the side of a mountain north of the Arctic Circle.</p>
<p>"To a lot of people today, it sounds like a perfectly reasonable thing to do," Fowler said from Saudi Arabia in an interview with the Associated Press. Seeds, he added, are a valuable natural resource that needs protection.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Snow blows off the Svalbard Global Seed Vault on Feb. 26, 2008. . (AP Photo/John McConnico)" src="https://img.51voa.cn/1/01000000-0aff-0242-eb15-08dc73a0e15c_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Snow blows off the Svalbard Global Seed Vault on Feb. 26, 2008. . (AP Photo/John McConnico)</span></div>
<p>But Fowler said: "Fifteen years ago, shipping a lot of seeds to the closest place to the North Pole that you can fly into (and) putting them inside a mountain..." did not sound reasonable. In his words, it was "...the craziest idea anybody ever had."</p>
<p><strong>The World Food Prize</strong></p>
<p>Their idea became the Svalbard Global Seed Vault on the Norwegian island of Svalbard. The vault opened in 2008 and now holds 1.25 million seed <strong>samples</strong> from nearly every country in the world. The structure was built into the side of a mountain. It protects the seeds of over 6,000 kinds of agriculturally important plants. <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.croptrust.org/work/svalbard-global-seed-vault/">The Crop Trust website</a> says: "Its purpose is to backup genebank collections to secure the foundation of our future food supply."</p>
<p>Last week, Fowler and Hawtin were named the 2024 World Food Prize winners for their work. Fowler is now the U.S. special diplomat for global food security. Hawtin is an agricultural scientist from Britain.</p>
<p>They were named the winners of the yearly prize at the U.S. Department of State in Washington. Secretary of State Antony Blinken praised the men at the announcement for their "<strong>critical</strong> role in <strong>preserving</strong> crop <strong>diversity</strong>."</p>
<p><strong>Fear of climate change</strong></p>
<p>For many years, countries have created seed banks to store seeds for future use. But Fowler said he was concerned that climate change would cause disorder in agriculture. This would make the seed supply even more important.</p>
<p>Hawtin is an executive board member at the Global Crop Diversity Trust, an international nonprofit group. He said there were a lot of threats to crops in the past, such as insects, disease, land <strong>degradation,</strong> and political unrest. He said that climate change has made these problems worse. So, he and Fowler saw a need for additional secure seed storage.</p>
<p>Hawtin explained that climate change is changing <strong>pests</strong> and diseases. He added, "Climate change is putting a whole lot of extra problems on what has always been <strong>significant</strong> ones."</p>
<p>Fowler and Hawtin said they hope winning the World Food Prize will help them raise more money for seed banks around the world. Operating them is not too costly. However, the financial support needs to continue forever.</p>
<p>"This is really a chance to get that message out and say, look, this relatively small amount of money is our <strong>insurance policy -- </strong>our insurance policy that we're going to be able to feed the world in 50 years," Hawtin said.</p>
<p>Norman Borlaug established the World Food Prize. He received the Nobel Peace Prize in 1970 for his part in what is called the "Green Revolution." That was a big effort to make crops more productive so the world's growing population would not go hungry.</p>
<p>This fall, Fowler and Hawtin will accept the prize in Des Moines, Iowa, the city where the food prize foundation is based. They will also split the $500,000 award. This year's prize will be presented at the yearly Norman E. Borlaug International Dialogue. The conference will be held in Des Moines from October 29 to the 31.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Scott McFetridge reported this story for the Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em><i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;______________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>doomsday </strong><em>–n.</em> the end of the world or judgement day</p>
<p><strong>sample </strong><em>–n.</em> a small amount of something taken for scientific study</p>
<p><strong>critical </strong><em>–adj.</em> very important</p>
<p><strong>diversity </strong><em>–n.</em> having many different kinds of things</p>
<p><strong>degradation </strong><em>–n. </em>the condition of breaking down and decreasing in quality <strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>significant </strong><em>–adj.</em> notable or worth discussing</p>
<p><strong>insurance policy </strong><em>–n.</em> a contract with an insurance company that promises to pay the holder or people named by the holder a certain amount if there is a loss of the covered property by the contract</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
