<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>VOA Special English</title>
        <link>https://www.21voa.com/special_english/</link>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <itunes:category>ESL</itunes:category>
        <itunes:author>VOA</itunes:author>
        <description>美国之音（以下称VOA）的英语节目，按播音速度可分为两种：Standard English （标准英语）和 Special English（特别英语）。

Special English 又叫“慢速英语”，是VOA 专为全世界非英语国家初学英语的听众安排的一种简易、规范的英语广播节目。该节目创始于50年代末期，是VOA 的专家们研究如何与世界各地的英语学习者进行交际的产物。它正式开播于1959年10月。当时只面向欧洲和中东，但由于这个节目适合许多国家英语学习者的需要，所以它的广播对象不久就扩大到世界其他地区，并很快在全世界范围内产生了广泛的影响。现在这个节目对欧洲、非洲和拉丁美洲每晚广播一次，对加勒比地区每晚广播一次（星期天除外），对东南亚广播次数最多，每天上午两次，晚上三次。

30多年来，VOA 为了办好Special English节目，进行了大量的调查研究工作，对播音速度、内容及用词范围都作了具体规定，基本上达到了既能为英语学习者提供信息，又不损害英语本身风格的目的，使之成为VOA 独具特色，拥有最大量听众的节目。

美国著名词汇学家S. B. Flexmer 指明了Special English的三条标准，也就是它所“特别”的地方：

1、它是一种由美国人最常用的1500个基本单词为主体构成的美国英语；

2、它用简短、明晰的句子写作和广播；

3、它以每分钟90个单词的速度，即2/3的Standard English（标准英语）速度进行广播。

Special English的节目可分为两大类：一类是新闻节目；一类是专题节目。

1．新闻节目

VOA Special English 的新闻广播向听众提供世界范围内的政治、经济、军事、外交、国际关系、宗教、天气以及各种重大事件和珍闻奇事等各个方面的信息，每天向东南亚地区广播五次，早上两次，晚上三次，每逢半点播出。

Special English新闻节目每次长约十分钟，大都播出十条左右新闻，近一千个单词，每条新闻多为一分钟，但偶尔也有长达两分钟的要闻。除头条新闻外，每条新闻都由一个电头引导，这样显得结构分明，条理清晰，适宜初学英语的人收听。在节目结束之前，播音员常常用三四句话重播其中三条新闻的提要以加深听众对要闻的印象。

Special English新闻中70%左右的内容与同时整点播出的Standard English新闻相同，但相同新闻的先后次序有所变动。每次节目的开头和结尾大同小异，格式比较固定。

2．专题节目（一）

Special English的专题节目（Feature Programs）,从时间上看，可分为两大类：一是每五分钟一次的专题，二是每十五分钟一次的专题。本节先介绍每项五分钟一次的专题材节目。

Special English五分钟一次的专题材节目安排在Special English新闻节目之后和（或）每十五分钟一次的专题材节目之前播出，每星期播七次。根据内容，可分为三个小类，即：Science Report（科学报道），逢星期一、三、五播出，每天播六遍；Agriculture Report（农业报道），逢星期二、四播出，每天播六遍；Words And Their Stories（词语掌故），逢星期六和星期天播出，每天播五遍。这三个专题材各具特色，具有相对的独立性，听众每听完一个节目，都会获得一个完整的印象。

Science Report（科学报道）这一专题材节目每周向听众介绍三篇有关现代科学技术最新发展情况的报道，涉及物理、化学、天文至高无上理、生物、环卫、心理、教育、医学和计算机等方面。适宜理工科大学生和科技工作者收集信息，积累资料，学习科技英语。

Agriculture Report（农业报道） Agriculture Report是为农业科技工作者和生产者安排的一个专题。它专门报道世界各国，特别是美国现代农业生产的最新成文汇报总务科 学家对农业生产某一方面的研究进展，以及他们对影响农业生产的某一自然现象进行分析和研究的近况。此外，它还经常向听众介绍发展中国家家业生产的一些有益经验等内容。

Words And Their Stories（词语掌故）这一专题节目，旨在向学习英语的听众介绍美国英语中生动有趣的词语和惯用法，并从科学研究和通俗词源学的角度来解释它们的含意、产生的背景及其在使用过程中的演变情况等。它通过讲故事的形式讲解每一个词语。这是VOA Special English中的优秀节目之一，是学习美国英语的极好材料。通过收听这一节目，听众不仅能学到娓娓动听的掌故和地道的美国英语，而且能增加美国的社会文化背景知识，历史传统与现状的了解。

VOA 为了更好地办好这个节目，便于听众收听学习，于1978年编辑出版了一本名为Words And Their Stories的书，共收集一百篇故事，作者是Herbert Sutcliffe, Harold Bermen 及VOA 该节目的部分编辑人员。在每次的实际广播中，播音员都以此书为蓝本，再根据需要对原稿进行适当增删。按每周两个故事计算，此书的一百个故事还不能满足一年的播音需要。于是编辑们就是重播部分词语掌故的同时，不断增加许多新的词语掌故，及时将词源学家的最新研究成果和不断增加的新词汇介绍给听众。收听实践证明，初学者在收听过程中必然会遇到许多人名、地名和一些较难的句子，有时甚至在听完之后还很难理解所播词语的确切含义及其汉语意思，为此，听众可参看1983年由中国对外翻译出版公司出版的该书英汉对照本中的有关部分。

3．专题节目（二）

VOA Special English的专题节目，除上节谈的五分钟一次的以外，还有本节要介绍的每十五分钟一次的节目。这类节目共有七个不同的小专题，以星期为单位循环，每天分四次复播出一个专题，但星期日和星期六的两个专题材每晚只播三遍，每次节目约十分钟，继每次五分钟的专题节目之后播出。

这类专题节目的基本结构是，在特定的伴声中先报告当次节目的名称，并扼要介绍其主要内容，然后播送节目正文。最后，在伴乐声中报告节目主持人和撰稿人的姓名，以邀请听众在下周的这个时间继续收听该节目而结束。

People in America（美国人物志） 这是有关美国历史名人的一个专题节目，每逢星期天晚上播出。它向听众介绍在美国历史上产生过重大影响、起过重要作用、作出了突出贡献的科学、文学、政治、或其他各方面的历史人物。节目一般都对他们的生平事迹进行简要的叙述，对其贡献作出评介，类似人物小传。有的重要人物事迹很多，必须用两次或几次的节目时间进行联播。对这样的节目要坚持收听，才会获得完整的印象。

TThis is America（今日美国） This Is America向听众介绍美国人民的生活、学习、工作和娱乐情况，是英语学习者解美国社会的一条渠道。该专题大都一个节目一个整体，每逢星期一晚播出。

Science in the News（科学新闻） 这一专题材主要对新近的科学技术新闻进行综述或摘要广播。向听众介绍世界各国在自然、医学、疾病、原子能、航天等方面的科研动态、成果、突破性进展及存在的困难。涉及当今世界人们普遍关心的重大问题，如核事故、航天飞机爆炸、自然灾害、环境污染和爱滋病等等。每逢星期二播出，每次播一到五条新闻摘要。

Explorations（自然探索） 每逢星期三晚上，听众可以收听到Explorations这一专题节目。该专题既涉及人类遨游太空、探索原子、研究自身、改造自然的现代技术，也报道发展中国家开发新资源，利用新工艺改善人民生活等方面的成就，其侧重点在各种科技实验和简易实用技术方面。该节目一般安排一段时间播一个系列，每次播出一个主题，以便能将某项新技术的研究和应用的全过程介绍给听众，电台还乐意为感兴趣的听众提供所需的文字材料。

The Making of a Nation（建国史话） 这一专题节目向听众介绍美利坚合众国从十三个殖民地区域到现代工业国的孕育、诞生以及形成超级大国的历史过程，并以历史为线索，特定的历史时期为单位，以重大的历史事件为主题材来叙述各个党派、各届总统和政府的历史作用与贡献。这是每个英语学习者都应了解的基本知识。The Making of a Nation每逢星期四播出。这是个系列节目，坚持收听，则有助于系统了解美国的历史概况。

American Mosaic（美国万花筒） American Mosaic是一个radio magazine（广播杂志）节目。该节目题材广泛、内容丰，展示着美国社会文化生活中比较轻松愉快的生活画面；听众收听该节目就如同在阅读一本图文并茂的杂志。它每次有三到五个小节目，涉及音乐、图书、技术和教育等方面的内容。我们既可以从中欣赏到著名歌唱的优秀歌曲，对美国音乐有所了解，又可以获取一些生动有趣的现代美国社会生活知识，随着播音员那亲切悦耳的声音步入美国风景如画的大好河山；同时还能听到世界各地的听众提出的有关英语语方文学等方面的问题和电台的解答。

American Stories（美国故事） 这一专题材节目安排在每星期六晚上播出。这样能使听众在学习和工作之余，得以轻松一下头脑。我们可以通过这一美国文学的“窗口”，接触各种流派、各类名家的文学作品。了解美国英语的时代特色，欣赏、学习美国人民运用语方的技巧，并从那些佳作名篇中获得艺术享受。该节目对短篇故事采取一次播一篇的方式，对中、长篇小说则先进行简写加工，再分几次播出全文。在播出故事正文之前，播音员常常先介绍故事的主要情节。对需要分几次节目时间播出的中长篇，在播第二或以后各部分之前，主持人还先重述已播部分的故事梗概，以唤起听众的回忆，使故事听起来更加连贯。</description>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          <item>
            <title>Severe Drought Returns to the Amazon Earlier Than Expected (2024/8/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/severe-drought-returns-to-the-amazon-earlier-than-expected.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The Amazon <strong>Basin</strong> is facing one of the most severe <strong>droughts</strong> in recent years, the Amazon Cooperation Treaty Organization (or ACTO) said.</p>
<p>As the dry season begins in August, many of its rivers are already at very low levels. And several South American countries are preparing to deal with increasing forest fires, water shortages and higher food prices.</p>
<p>In several rivers in the southwestern Amazon, water levels are the lowest on record for this time of year. August and September are usually the driest months. That is also when most fires happen. The ACTO says the most affected countries so far this year are Bolivia, Peru and Brazil.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Boats sit on the bank of the Acre River, the main water source for the city of Rio Branco, which is facing water shortages amid a drought in Acre state, Brazil, Friday, Aug. 2, 2024. (AP Photo/Marcos Vicentti)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-52de-08dcb56c1f96_cx1_cy11_cw98_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Boats sit on the bank of the Acre River, the main water source for the city of Rio Branco, which is facing water shortages amid a drought in Acre state, Brazil, Friday, Aug. 2, 2024. (AP Photo/Marcos Vicentti)</span></div>
<p>Recently, Brazil's federal water agency declared a water shortage in two major basins, Madeira and Purus. Together, they cover an area nearly the size of Mexico. And in Brazil's Acre state, the drought has already caused water shortages in the city of Rio Branco. In June, neighboring Amazonas state declared a water shortage in 20 of its communities.</p>
<p>The declared shortages came more than two months earlier than last year when most of the Amazon Basin suffered its worst drought on record.</p>
<p>The 2023 drought <strong>isolated</strong> people who depend on water for transportation. Smoke from forest fires made the air in cities unhealthy to breathe. And high water temperatures killed more than 100 river dolphins.</p>
<p>The Madeira River is one of the largest rivers in the Basin. It is also an important waterway for soybeans and fuel. The river's level dropped below three meters near Porto Velho on July 20. In 2023, that happened nearly a month later on August 15.</p>
<p>The low water level means fewer boats could travel the river at night. And two of Brazil's largest hydroelectric plants may halt production, as happened last year.</p>
<p>In the Amazonas town of Envira, nearby rivers have become too <strong>shallow</strong> to travel by boat. Local officials have asked old people and pregnant women to move from communities by the river to the city center. This is because medical help may not be able to reach them.</p>
<p>The low water is also affecting food prices. Farmers who produce cassava flour cannot get it to market. As a result, this important Amazon food has more than doubled in price, local government says.</p>
<p>Another worry is fire. There were around 25,000 fires from January until late July — the highest number for this period in almost twenty years. In the Amazon, fires are mostly human-made. People use the fires to manage fields and clear areas where trees have been cut down.</p>
<p>Drought is not the only weather event affecting areas in Brazil's Acre state. Severe flooding hit 19 of the state's 22 communities last year.</p>
<p>“It's been two years <strong>in a row</strong> of extreme events,” said Julie Messias, Acre's secretary of environment. She added, “The result is that we are facing a threat of food shortage. First, the crops were flooded, and now the planting period is very dry.”</p>
<p>The Amazon is the world's largest river system, carrying 20 percent of the world's river water into the oceans each year.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Fabiano Maisonnave wrote this story for The Associated Press. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>basin </strong><em>-n. </em>the land around a river and the area from which water flows into it</p>
<p><strong>drought </strong><em>-n. </em>an extended period of very dry weather</p>
<p><strong>isolate </strong><em>-v. </em>to keep physically separated and away from other people or things</p>
<p><strong>shallow </strong><em>-adj. </em>not deep</p>
<p><strong>in a row </strong><em>-prep. phrase</em> consecutively</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Algae Blamed for Sickening California Sea Lions (2024/8/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/algae-blamed-for-sickening-california-sea-lions.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A California wildlife organization says it has been rescuing sick sea lions in recent weeks showing signs of <strong>algae</strong> poisoning.</p>
<p>On August 1, the Santa Barbara-based Channel Islands Marine &amp; Wildlife Institute said teams had rescued at least 23 animals. The U.S. Vandenberg Space Force Base recently <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.facebook.com/SLD30/">released photos</a> on social media of sea lions being taken from one of its beaches.</p>
<p>The institute said that since July 26, it had received numerous reports daily of sick lions along a 250-kilometer stretch of coastline in Santa Barbara and Ventura counties.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This photo provided by the Channel Islands Marine &amp; Wildlife Institute (CIMWI) shows a sick sea lion on San Buenaventura State Beach in Ventura, California on July 29, 2024. (Channel Islands Marine &amp; Wildlife Institute via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-54b5-08dcb62de4ca_cx0_cy37_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This photo provided by the Channel Islands Marine &amp; Wildlife Institute (CIMWI) shows a sick sea lion on San Buenaventura State Beach in Ventura, California on July 29, 2024. (Channel Islands Marine &amp; Wildlife Institute via AP)</span></div>
<p>The group said in a statement the sea creatures were found to be suffering from the effects of domoic acid, a poison that can harm the brain and heart. The release of the acid in a large ocean event is known as an algae <strong>bloom</strong>.</p>
<p>The poison is produced by microscopic algae eaten by shellfish or small fish. Those shellfish or fish are often then eaten by sea lions, dolphins or birds. The algae can also sicken humans.</p>
<p>Among the signs of sickness experienced by affected sea lions are unusual head movements, <strong>disorientation</strong>, foaming at the mouth and seizures.</p>
<p>In a message <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.facebook.com/CIMWI">published</a> on Facebook August 4, the institute said the poisoning event was “heating up,” with new cases of sick sea lions still appearing at multiple beaches. It explained that rescue teams first try to get the animals in a net so they can be transported for treatment and then returned to the sea.</p>
<p>The U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) says poisoning events linked to domoic acid are common along the California coast. Experts said the latest poisoning event seems to mostly be affecting adult female sea lions.</p>
<p>Last year, an especially severe poisoning event killed hundreds of sea lions and a number of dolphins during the first weeks of June.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>algae </strong><em>- n.</em> a plant with no stem or leaves that grows in or near water</p>
<p><strong>bloom </strong><em>– v.</em> to become densely populated with microorganisms such as algae</p>
<p><strong>disorient </strong><em>– v. </em>to make someone confused or unsure</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How a Small College Became a Top High-tech University (2024/8/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/how-a-small-college-became-a-top-high-tech-university.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A measure begun 40 years ago by South Dakota lawmakers and state higher education leaders has turned a small rural college into one of the top high-tech universities in the United States.</p>
<p>It began at a time when the future of Dakota State College itself was in question.</p>
<p>In 1984, the South Dakota Board of Regents, which oversees the school, was under pressure to cut its budget. It closed one college and turned it into a prison.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="MadLabs research facility of Dakota State University is a hub for cyber research. (Bart Pfankuch / South Dakota News Watch)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-2ebd-08dcb2212e2d_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">MadLabs research facility of Dakota State University is a hub for cyber research. (Bart Pfankuch / South Dakota News Watch)</span></div>
<p>Soon after, a new law went into effect. The measure put technology at the center of all Dakota State's study programs.</p>
<p>The decision to reinvent a teacher's college founded in 1881 in a rural city of 6,000 people seemed risky. But, at around the same time, Citibank, a major financial services company, decided to headquarter its credit card business in Sioux Falls, a city near the college.</p>
<p>José-Marie Griffiths is the current president of Dakota State University (DSU). The school changed its name from college to university in 1989.</p>
<p>Griffiths said Citibank was looking for computer programmers, and “somebody came up with the idea that, well, we could turn this college that's <strong>fumbling</strong> a little bit into a computer school with software development and engineering.”</p>
<p>Griffiths told <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.sdnewswatch.org/dakota-state-university-madison-cybsersecurity-program-growth/">South Dakota News Watch</a>, “That way, we could supply the needed programmers to the Sioux Falls workforce for Citibank and <strong>ultimately</strong> for others....”</p>
<p><strong>Change was not fully supported at first</strong></p>
<p>Lynette Molstad Gorder was teaching at DSU 40 years ago when the change to a high-tech campus began. She said, at first, some members of the college community were unsure about the change, and its effect on people and programs.</p>
<p>“Later on we looked upon it as a welcome opportunity,” she said. “It was kind of hazy (at first) and then all of a sudden, it just clicked.”</p>
<p>Suddenly, computers replaced pens, pencils and typewriters in classrooms. And later, the move into computer science and then cyber security, she said.</p>
<p>The jump into technology at DSU started with a bachelor's degree in computer science using teaching materials from IBM. The teaching of computer science and software development along with industry partnership laid the groundwork for what was to come, Griffiths said.</p>
<p>With a mix of private and public money, the university expanded the school and its offerings.</p>
<p>In 2004, the National Security Agency named DSU a Center of Academic Excellence in computer security, one of the first in the nation.</p>
<p>The number of students has also risen steadily, from 867 in 1985 to 3,509 in 2023. The university said DSU now offers 44 degrees, including seven master's degrees and four doctoral programs.</p>
<p>In 2017, DSU started Madison Cyber Labs with money from the state and local businesses. It expanded research at the university to include cyber security, machine learning, and artificial intelligence, among others.</p>
<p>The school is now planning an expansion into Sioux Falls itself. The plan includes partnerships with another research center and a cyber academy program for high school students.</p>
<p>DSU is also pushing the state for more money to start a new center for quantum computing.</p>
<p><strong>Opportunities for DSU graduates</strong></p>
<p>Jen Easterly is director of the federal Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency. She was the lead speaker at a DSU cybersecurity event last March.</p>
<p>Easterly said that before she visited Madison, she had been hearing increasing discussion on the national level about the growth and<strong> innovation</strong> taking place at DSU.</p>
<p>She said, “The ideas generated at forums like this are just further proof that it doesn't matter the size of the university. ...”</p>
<p>Alexis Kulm graduated from DSU in December of 2022. She studied cyber operations there.</p>
<p>The 23-year-old said she liked the small-town feel of the college. She took classes in web and network design, computer programming and malware analysis. All of them, she said, helped prepare her for the cyber workplace.</p>
<p>“You get a strong real-world education in your classes,” Kulm said.</p>
<p>Kulm also said she had several job offers after graduating. She chose Sanford Health, a company in Sioux Falls. It has a partnership with the university to increase employment opportunities for DSU graduates.</p>
<p>Kulm is not the only DSU graduate to stay in South Dakota. Jon Waldman and Chad Knutson were in the class of 2006. Soon after graduating, they set up a business together right in Madison. Their 90-employee company SBS CyberSecurity serves the banking industry in 49 states.</p>
<p>Waldman said DSU has “a commitment to innovation” that makes it easy for students to remain on top of the always-changing cyber technology and security industry.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p>And I'm Mario Ritter Jr. </p>
<p><em>Bart Pfankuch reported this story for </em><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.sdnewswatch.org/" target="_blank"><em>South Dakota News Watch</em></a><em> and distributed it through a partnership with The Associated Press. Hai Do adapted the story for VOA Learning English</em><em>.</em></p>
<p><em>______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>fumble</strong> - v. to handle something clumsily or awkwardly</p>
<p><strong>ultimately</strong> - adv. at the end of the process</p>
<p><strong>innovation</strong> - n. new idea, method</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Ancient Egyptian Woman’s Suffering Frozen in Final Scream (2024/8/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/ancient-egyptian-woman-s-suffering-frozen-in-final-scream.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists now have an explanation for the mysterious remains of an ancient Egyptian woman who has her mouth open in what appears to be a <strong>scream</strong>.</p>
<p>Scientists used a special computer aided X-ray, or CT scan, of the woman's body. What they found suggested that the so-called "Screaming Woman" <strong>mummy</strong> may have died in pain and experienced a form of muscular hardening known as a cadaveric <strong>spasm</strong>. This rare kind of spasm happens at the moment of death.</p>
<p>The examination found that the woman was about 48 years old when she died. Cairo University's Sahar Saleem said she had lived with mild <strong>arthritis</strong> of the spine and had lost some teeth.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="The face of the " at="" august="" cairo="" egypt="" egyptian="" handout="" in="" is="" january="" mummy="" museum="" on="" photograph="" released="" reuters="" saleem="" screaming="" seen="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/cb26197c-2c9a-434c-bca9-88d379eca2ed_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg" the="" this="" via="" woman=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">The face of the "Screaming Woman" mummy is seen at the Egyptian Museum in Cairo, Egypt, January 18, 2023 in this handout photograph released on August 2, 2024. (Sahar Saleem/Handout via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>Saleem led the study that appeared recently in the publication Frontiers in Medicine.</p>
<p>The woman's body was well-<strong>preserved</strong> although it had been <strong>embalmed</strong> 3,500 years ago. Embalmers used costly imported materials such as juniper oil and frankincense resin, Saleem added.</p>
<p>The ancient Egyptians considered preservation of the body after death important for securing a good existence in the afterlife. It was a custom to remove the internal organs during the mummification process. But the organ removals had not taken place with this woman.</p>
<p>Saleem said, "In ancient Egypt, the embalmers took care of the dead body, so it would look beautiful for the afterlife.”</p>
<p>She explained that embalmers were interested in closing the mouth of the dead. Embalmers kept the <strong>jaw</strong> in place by tying the jaw to the head. This prevented the normal jaw drop that occurs after death.</p>
<p>But the embalmers were likely not careless with the so-called “Screaming Woman.” They used high quality materials and gave her costly jewelry and a wig, Saleem said.</p>
<p>She added that this evidence "opened the way to other explanations of the widely opened mouth.”</p>
<p>The woman may have died screaming from pain. And the muscles of the face may have become tense to preserve this appearance “at the time of death due to cadaveric spasm," Saleem explained.</p>
<p>She said that the full history of the woman's death is unknown, adding the cause of her facial appearance cannot be known “with certainty."</p>
<p>Cadaveric spasm is a poorly understood condition. It is thought to happen after severe physical or emotional suffering. The <strong>contracted</strong> facial muscles become tense and unmoving immediately following death.</p>
<p>Saleem explained that unlike the stiffening of muscles and joints that happens after death - "cadaveric spasm affects only one group of muscles, not the entire body."</p>
<p>Asked whether the woman may have been embalmed while alive, Saleem added, "I don't believe that this is possible."</p>
<p>Saleem was unable to find out how the woman died.</p>
<p>The "Screaming Woman" was found in the ancient city of Thebes during a scientific search of the burial of a high-ranking official named Senmut in 1935.</p>
<p>The mummy was inside a wooden <strong>coffin</strong> in a room beneath Senmut's family burial area. Her identity is unknown, but her costly jewelry shows her important position.</p>
<p>"She was likely a close family member to be buried and share the family's<strong> eternal </strong>resting place," Saleem said.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Will Dunham reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>scream</strong> <em>–n.</em> to shout in a high voice or high pitch</p>
<p><strong>mummy </strong><em>– n.</em> a body embalmed or treated for burial with preservatives in the manner of the ancient Egyptians</p>
<p><strong>spasm</strong> <em>– n.</em> an involuntary and abnormal muscular contraction</p>
<p><strong>arthritis</strong> <em>– n.</em> inflammation of joints</p>
<p><strong>preserve</strong> <em>– v.</em> to keep free from decay or decomposition</p>
<p><strong>embalm</strong> –<em> v.</em> to treat (a dead body) so as to protect from decay</p>
<p><strong>jaw </strong><em>–n.</em> the bones that form the lower part of the mouth and which hold the lower teeth</p>
<p><strong>contract</strong> <em>–v. </em>to increase in tension and become shorter or smaller</p>
<p><strong>coffin</strong> <em>– n.</em> a box for burying a body</p>
<p><strong>eternal</strong> <em>–adj. </em>lasting forever</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Twice-yearly Injections Cut HIV Infections by 100 Percent (2024/8/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/study-twice-yearly-injections-cut-hiv-infections-by-100-percent.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>A new study has found that the twice-yearly injections of a treatment for AIDS were 100 percent effective in preventing new HIV infections in women.</p>
<p>The U.S. drugmaker Gilead sells the drug treatment under the name Sunlenca. The drug is approved in the United States, Canada, Europe and in other places, but only as a treatment for HIV.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A pharmacist holds a vial of lenacapavir, the new HIV prevention injectable drug, at the Desmond Tutu Health Foundation's Masiphumelele Research Site, in Cape Town, South Africa, July 23, 2024. (AP Photo/Nardus Engelbrecht)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-88d2-08dcb0038d29_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A pharmacist holds a vial of lenacapavir, the new HIV prevention injectable drug, at the Desmond Tutu Health Foundation's Masiphumelele Research Site, in Cape Town, South Africa, July 23, 2024. (AP Photo/Nardus Engelbrecht)</span></div>
<p>The researchers ended the study early because of the surprisingly good results. All the people in the study were then offered the injection, or shot, also known as lenacapavir.</p>
<p>Thandeka Nkosi helped run the Gilead research at the Desmond Tutu Health Foundation in Masiphumelele, South Africa. She said the idea of a twice-a-year shot is “quite revolutionary news.”</p>
<p>About 5,300 young women and girls in South Africa and Uganda took part in the study. Researchers reported that none of the women injected with the treatment became infected with HIV. Among those given daily prevention pills, about two percent became infected with HIV from infected sex partners.</p>
<p>Gilead said it is waiting for results of testing in men before seeking permission<strong> </strong>to use it as protection against HIV.</p>
<p>The <em>New England Journal of Medicine</em> published the results on July 24. Experts also discussed the study at an AIDS conference in Munich, Germany. Gilead paid for the study and some of the researchers are company employees.</p>
<p>There are other ways to prevent HIV infection. These include devices like condoms or drugs taken daily by mouth. However, regular use has been a problem in Africa. In the new study, only about 30 percent of people given Gilead's Truvada or Descovy HIV prevention pills actually took them. That percentage also dropped over time.</p>
<p>Nkosi said the twice-yearly injections give people a choice. She added that injections took away the “<strong>stigma</strong> around taking pills” to prevent HIV.</p>
<p><strong>High cost of the drug</strong></p>
<p>As an HIV treatment, the drug costs more than $40,000 a year in the U.S. Health insurance companies pay part of the cost and patients pay the balance.</p>
<p>People working to stop the spread of AIDS are interested in the Sunlenca shots. But they are concerned that Gilead has not agreed on a lower price for those who need the shots the most.</p>
<p>“Gilead has a tool that could change the <strong>trajectory</strong> of the HIV <strong>epidemic</strong>,” said Winnie Byanyima. She is executive director of the Geneva-based UNAIDS.</p>
<p>She said the U.N. AIDS agency urged Gilead to share Sunlenca's <strong>patent </strong>with a U.N. program. The program's goal is to let <strong>generic </strong>drugmakers manufacture low-cost versions of drugs for poor countries.</p>
<p>Dr. Helen Bygrave of Doctors Without Borders said in a statement that the injections could “reverse the epidemic if it is made available in the countries with the highest rate of new infections.” She urged Gilead to publish a lower price for Sunlenca that all countries could pay.</p>
<p>In other research presented at the AIDS conference, Andrew Hill of the University of Liverpool and others said the drug's price would go down. They estimated that once production of Sunlenca is expanded to treat 10 million people, the price would fall to about $40 per treatment.</p>
<p>He said it was important for health officials to get Sunlenca as soon as possible. “This is about as close as you can get to an HIV vaccine,” Hill said.</p>
<p>Gilead said it would seek a “voluntary <strong>licensing</strong> program.” It said a small number of generic producers would be permitted to make the drug.</p>
<p>In a statement last month, Gilead said it was too early to say how much Sunlenca would cost in poorer countries. Dr. Jared Baeten is a product development official with Gilead. He said the company was already talking to generic drugmakers and understood how “deeply important it is that we move at speed.”</p>
<p>Byanyima said many groups need long-lasting protection from HIV infection. They include women and girls who are victims of violence and <strong>homosexual</strong> men in countries where homosexuality is criminalized.</p>
<p>UNAIDS says that in 2022 46 percent of new HIV infections in the world were in women and girls. In Africa, females are three times more likely to get HIV than males, the U.N. group said.</p>
<p>Recently, UNAIDS released a report on the state of the HIV epidemic. It said that fewer people were infected with HIV in 2023 than at any time since the late 1980s.</p>
<p>The U.N. says HIV infects about 1.3 million people every year and kills more than 600,000, mainly in Africa. While much progress has been made in Africa, HIV infections are rising in Eastern Europe, Latin America, and the Middle East.</p>
<p>And that's the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo. And I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Maria Cheng and Gerald Imray reported this story for The Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;</em></p>
<p><em>_____________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>stigma</strong> –n. something that people feel ashamed about</p>
<p><strong>trajectory </strong>–n. the direction that something is going</p>
<p><strong>epidemic</strong> –n. when an infectious disease spreads over a population in a wide area</p>
<p><strong>patent </strong>–n. protection for the legal owner of a process or product against having intellectual property copies or stolen</p>
<p><strong>generic </strong>–adj. not sold under a brand name; a manufactured product that is not protected by a patent</p>
<p><strong>licensing </strong>–n. the legal process of permitting the production of a product protected by patent law by a company that does not own the patent</p>
<p><strong>homosexual </strong>–adj. the state of being sexually interested in the same sex</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>NASA Rover Captures Rock Showing Possible Signs of Microbial Life (2024/8/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/nasa-rover-captures-rock-showing-possible-signs-of-microbial-life.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A Mars explorer operated by the American space agency NASA has captured a rock that scientists say shows possible signs of ancient microbial life.</p>
<p>NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.jpl.nasa.gov/news/nasas-perseverance-rover-scientists-find-intriguing-mars-rock">said</a> in a recent statement that the Perseverance explorer, or rover, collected the rock on July 21. Scientists working on the Perseverance team <strong>nicknamed</strong> the rock “Cheyava Falls,” after the tallest waterfall in the Grand Canyon.</p>
<p>The rover's exploration area is believed to include a former river valley measuring about 400 meters wide. The valley is thought to have formed by water rushing into Jezero <strong>Crater</strong> billions of years ago. Scientists believe the area around Jezero Crater contained large bodies of water in the distant past.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="NASA's Perseverance rover made several new discoveries the space agency says support existing evidence that ancient microbial life may have lived on Mars when the planet had running water. (Credit: NASA/JPL-Caltech/MSSS Full Image Details)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-f15b-08dcb2614ede_cx2_cy3_cw93_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">NASA's Perseverance rover made several new discoveries the space agency says support existing evidence that ancient microbial life may have lived on Mars when the planet had running water. (Credit: NASA/JPL-Caltech/MSSS Full Image Details)</span></div>
<p>NASA's statement says the rock shows signs of “chemical <strong>signatures</strong> and structures that could possibly have been formed by life billions of years ago...”</p>
<p>NASA team members based their findings on examinations of the rock with imaging equipment and multiple scientific instruments. But they noted that additional research is needed to confirm a history of microbial life.</p>
<p>The examinations did suggest the rock contains “organic compounds,” NASA said. But the statement added, “While such carbon-based molecules are considered the building blocks of life, they also can be formed by non-biological processes.”</p>
<p>Perseverance uses its robotic arm and <strong>drilling</strong> equipment to capture rock and soil <strong>samples</strong> from the Martian surface. So far, it has collected 22 samples. The rover has secured the samples in special containers and they are to be picked up and returned to Earth during a future mission.</p>
<p>Ken Farley is a project scientist with the Perseverance team at Caltech in Pasadena, California. He said, “Cheyava Falls is the most <strong>puzzling</strong>, complex, and potentially important rock yet investigated by Perseverance.”</p>
<p>Farley said unusual color spots and other structural elements in the samples suggest “chemical reactions” that might have given energy to ancient microbial life. But he noted that so far, scientists have not been able to identify exactly how the rock formed.</p>
<p>The team described the rock as containing white <strong>veins</strong> that may have been created by the substance calcium sulfate. Between the veins, examiners found lines of material with a reddish color. These lines suggest the presence of hematite, a common substance found in many rocks on Earth.</p>
<p>David Flannery is an astrobiologist and member of the Perseverance science team from the Queensland University of Technology in Australia. He said that on Earth, these kinds of rock elements are often linked “with the <strong>fossilized</strong> record of microbes living in the subsurface."</p>
<p>The scientists said the new findings strengthen existing evidence that such rocks may have been created or were changed by flowing water on Mars billions of years ago.</p>
<p>Caltech's Farley said the rock sample had already been imaged and examined with lasers, X-ray equipment and other instruments as much as possible in recent weeks. He noted that Perseverance has done as much as it can to examine the newly discovered samples.</p>
<p>Farley added, “To fully understand what really happened in that Martian river valley at Jezero Crater billions of years ago, we'd want to bring the Cheyava Falls sample back to Earth.” That way, he said, “it can be studied with the powerful instruments available in laboratories.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from NASA and Agence-France Presse.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>nickname - </strong><em>n.</em><strong> </strong>a name used informally instead of an official name</p>
<p><strong>crater</strong><em> - n.</em> a hole left in the ground by an object that hits it with a huge force</p>
<p><strong>signature </strong><em>– n.</em> a feature in the appearance or qualities of a natural object</p>
<p><strong>drill </strong><em>– v. </em>to make a hole in a hard substance using a special tool</p>
<p><strong>puzzling </strong><em>– adj.</em> difficult to understand or figure out</p>
<p><strong>vein </strong><em>– n.</em> one of the thin lines found on an object</p>
<p><strong>fossil </strong><em>– n. </em>part of a plant or animal from many years ago that has been preserved in rock</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>African Health Officials Warn of Mpox Spread (2024/8/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/african-health-officials-warn-of-mpox-spread.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">04 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>African health officials say mpox infections on the continent have risen by 160 percent in 2024. They expect the spread to continue, they say, as Africa lacks effective treatments or vaccines for the viral disease.</p>
<p>The Africa Centers for Disease Control and Prevention reports that mpox, also known as m<i><i>onkey</i></i>pox, has been identified in 10 African countries this year.</p>
<p>Burundi and Rwanda both reported the virus for the first time recently.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Vials of single doses of the Jynneos vaccine for m&lt;I&gt;&lt;I&gt;onkey&lt;/I&gt;&lt;/I&gt;pox are seen from a cooler at a vaccinations site on Aug. 29, 2022, in the Brooklyn borough of New York. (AP Photo/Jeenah Moon, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-f50a-08dcb24a7fea_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Vials of single doses of the Jynneos vaccine for m<i><i>onkey</i></i>pox are seen from a cooler at a vaccinations site on Aug. 29, 2022, in the Brooklyn borough of New York. (AP Photo/Jeenah Moon, File)</span></div>
<p>New outbreaks were also declared this week in Kenya and Central African Republic.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, Kenya's Health Ministry said it found mpox in a passenger traveling from Uganda to Rwanda at a border crossing in southern Kenya. In a statement, the ministry said that a single mpox case was enough to require an outbreak declaration.</p>
<p>The Africa CDC has reported more than 14,000 cases of the disease. More than 96 percent of cases and deaths are in the Democratic Republic of the Congo. Earlier this year, scientists reported the appearance of a new form of mpox in a Congolese mining town. They fear it might spread more easily among people. Mpox spreads through close contact with infected people, including sex.</p>
<p>The Africa CDC said the mpox death rate is three percent. It said the rate “has been much higher on the African continent compared to the rest of the world.” During the global mpox emergency in 2022, less than one percent of people infected with the virus died.</p>
<p>The version of mpox in the Democratic Republic of the Congo could kill up to 10 percent of people infected, experts reported. The center noted that both of the mpox cases in Rwanda had been in Congo before testing positive.</p>
<p>A study of patients hospitalized from October to January in eastern Congo suggested that recent genetic changes in the virus were the result of ongoing spread in people.</p>
<p>In earlier mpox outbreaks, patients suffered <strong>lesions</strong> mainly on the chest, hands and feet. The new form of mpox causes less severe <strong>symptoms</strong> and lesions mainly appear on the genitals.</p>
<p>The Africa CDC said nearly 70 percent of cases in Congo are in children younger than 15. That group also represents 85 percent of deaths from the disease. The agency said the number of deaths across the continent has jumped by 19 percent since last year.</p>
<p>The medical aid group Doctors Without Borders called the expanding mpox outbreak “worrying.” It also said the disease has been found in camps for displaced people in Congo's North Kivu area, which shares a border with Rwanda.</p>
<p>Dr. Louis Massing is medical director for Congo at Doctors Without Borders. Massing said, “There is a real risk of explosion, given the huge population movements in and out.”</p>
<p>Mpox outbreaks in the West have been uncommon because of vaccines and treatments. But few treatments have been available in African countries including the Congo.</p>
<p>In May, the WHO said no donors had provided money to fight the spread of mpox.</p>
<p>The Coalition for Epidemic Preparedness Innovations is an aid organization based in Norway. It recently announced the start of an mpox vaccine study in Congo and other African countries. It aims to learn if vaccine treatment given just after infection could prevent severity of the disease.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Jean Fernand Koena and Maria Cheng reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>ravaging </strong><em>–adj.</em> damaging or harming badly</p>
<p><strong>lesions </strong><em>–n. (medical)</em> an area of infected skin that is usually swollen, red, bleeding or releasing fluid</p>
<p><strong>symptoms </strong><em>–n.</em> signs that an infection is present</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Singapore Approves Insects as Food (2024/8/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/singapore-approves-insects-as-food.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Singapore's House of Seafood restaurant is the country's first eatery to offer insects to <strong>customers</strong>.</p>
<p>The change comes after the city state's food <strong>authority</strong> recently approved 16 kinds of insects for humans to eat, including grasshoppers, grubs and mealworms.</p>
<p>Crickets and other insects have long been eaten as street food in Southeast Asia. But the wealthy financial center places heavy safety and cleanliness restrictions on food imports.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Restaurant owner Francis Ng prepares house crickets to add to his insect-based dishes at the House of Seafood restaurant in Singapore on July 16, 2024. (REUTERS/Edgar Su)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/682656eb-ce07-4736-9c9b-aebf5be77f04_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Restaurant owner Francis Ng prepares house crickets to add to his insect-based dishes at the House of Seafood restaurant in Singapore on July 16, 2024. (REUTERS/Edgar Su)</span></div>
<p>Francis Ng is the chief of House of Seafood. He said customers love it when the <strong>dishes</strong> bring attention to the insects. For example, the restaurant offers a tofu dish made to look like bugs are crawling out of it and a dish of rice balls <strong>decorated </strong>with silkworms.</p>
<p>"It looks scarier so customers can film (it) for their Tiktok," said Ng. He added that customers had been calling him regularly to plan a tasting of the dishes.</p>
<p>The restaurant has created a menu with 30 dishes that <strong>feature</strong> insects, which they can sell to the public once their importers are approved by the food authority. For now, Ng is offering free <strong>samples</strong>.</p>
<p>In 2019, Singapore declared it was aiming to produce 30 percent of its nutritional needs by 2030. Currently, around 90 percent of food is imported.</p>
<p>Food security expert Paul Teng said insects could certainly help move towards this goal - if people got over "the <strong>yuck </strong>factor.”</p>
<p>"Most insects are almost all protein," said Teng. Teng added that there needs to be local production to make this new way to get protein less costly.</p>
<p>"Getting people to accept insects in their diet is a <strong>challenge</strong>. But really, it's a normal food <strong>item</strong>. Let's do something about it to prepare the consumer for it," he said. "Me personally, I have no problem eating insects."</p>
<p>The United Nations has said bugs can be a <strong>sustainable</strong> way to get protein to feed the world. The U.N. estimates the global population will reach 9.7 billion by 2050. Extreme weather and conflicts have also increased the interest in insects as high-quality, low-cost nutrition.</p>
<p>In Singapore, all insects approved for human food must be farmed in a controlled environment. The insects cannot be taken from the wild. And they cannot be fed materials like human or animal waste or <strong>rotten</strong> food, the food agency says.</p>
<p>There has been local interest in importing insects, but cost remains an issue for now: Ng said insects make up 10 percent of his costs at the House of Seafood, and they are all imported.</p>
<p>"The price is definitely higher than eggs," he said.</p>
<p>It is too early to tell if insects will become an important part of the Singapore diet or whether demand will decrease as it has for <strong>fake</strong> meat products.</p>
<p>But for now, some diners say they are happy to develop a taste for bugs.</p>
<p>"If they have a higher source of protein, why not? I'll add it to my daily meal and daily food intake," said Bregria Sim, a 23-year-old logistics executive. She added that she would be willing to pay about $30 for the unusual dishes.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Xinghui Kok reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>customer</strong><em> –n.</em> a person or group who buys goods or services</p>
<p><strong>authority</strong> <em>–n. </em>an agency or office that oversees a public service or activity and has the power to make and enforce rules governing it</p>
<p><strong>dish</strong><em> –n.</em> a particular kind of food</p>
<p><strong>decorated</strong> <em>–adj.</em> made to look in a pleasing way</p>
<p><strong>feature</strong> <em>– v. </em> to bring attention to some element of a product or object</p>
<p><strong>sample </strong>–<em> n.</em> a small amount of something that is tested, or tasted, to see if it is good</p>
<p><strong>yuck</strong><em> – interjection</em> used to express strong dislike or displeasure</p>
<p><strong>challenge </strong><em>– n. </em>a task or problem</p>
<p><strong>item</strong><em> –n.</em> one of a group of similar things</p>
<p><strong>sustainable</strong><em> – adj.</em> relating to a method of using a resource so that it is not permanently damaged or used up</p>
<p><strong>rotten</strong> <em>–adj.</em> breaking down, decaying or impossible to eat</p>
<p><strong>fake</strong><em> –adj.</em> having the appearance of the real thing, but not real</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>When Is Two Too Many? When It's a 'Double Whammy'! (2024/8/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/when-is-two-too-many-when-it-s-a-double-whammy.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>On this program, we explore words and expressions in the English language. We give definitions, examples and notes on usage.</p>
<p>Today we talk about a word with an unusual history – <u>whammy</u>. A <u>whammy</u> can be a magical <strong>spell</strong> that brings bad luck. It can also be an attack or a damaging, destructive blow. A blow is an incident or event that hits you hard.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - An art installation dubbed " artist="" at="" by="" china="" double="" ducks="" dutch="" florentijn="" harbour="" hofman="" hong="" in="" is="" june="" kong="" seen="" siu="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1a7f6686-b59c-4b86-953e-7f923c29c73a_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg" tyrone="" victoria=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - An art installation dubbed "Double Ducks" by Dutch artist Florentijn Hofman, is seen at Victoria Harbour, in Hong Kong, China June 9, 2023. (REUTERS/Tyrone Siu)</span></div>
<p>So, one <u>whammy</u> is bad. But what happens when you have two?</p>
<p>That is called a <u>double whammy</u>.</p>
<p>People traditionally say they have been hit with a <u>double whammy</u>!”</p>
<p>The online dictionary Merriam-Webster defines a <u>double whammy</u> as a combination of two usually unfavorable forces, <strong>circumstances</strong>, or effects. Two bad things happen at the same time to make something really unpleasant or difficult.</p>
<p>It can also mean that two bad things happen <strong>consecutively</strong>, or one after the other.</p>
<p>The <strong>origin</strong> of the expression is unclear. Some guess it comes from taking the word “wham” which describes a hard <strong>punch</strong> or blow and adding a -y ending which makes it sound funny.</p>
<p>Others say the <strong>cartoonist</strong> Al Capp popularized the word <u>whammy</u> in his 1950s <strong>comic strip</strong> Li'l Abner. A <strong>character</strong> named Evil-Eye Fleegle could stop someone by simply looking at them. The single <u>whammy</u> was a look with one eye, and the feared <u>double whammy</u> used both eyes.</p>
<p>Now, let's listen to the expression used in a sentence.</p>
<p><em>Today, my friend Jonah lost his job. And then, on the way home, he fell and broke his leg. Talk about a <u>double whammy</u>! It has NOT been his best day. </em></p>
<p>Here is another example of the expression <u>double whammy</u>.</p>
<p><em>On their 3-hour hiking trip, the friends were hit with a<u> double whammy</u>. The first was a bad rainstorm. They were forced to take shelter in a cave. Then they realized the second bad thing. They left all their food and water in the car.</em></p>
<p>There is another English expression that has a similar meaning – <u>a one-two punch</u>. The first punch is a difficult blow to take, but then the second one aims to finish the job. The expression comes from boxing where one punch is quickly followed by another from the other fist, or closed hand.</p>
<p>A boxer using a <u>one-two punch</u> is trying to <strong>knock out</strong> their opponent or to score points.</p>
<p>Both <u>double whammy</u> and <u>one-two punch</u> are informal expressions. <u>One-two punch</u> might be less popular than it once was. But <u>double whammy</u> appears in some surprising places in both American and British English.</p>
<p>And that's Words and Their Stories. Until next time ... I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>Do you have a similar expression in your language? Let us know in the comments. Or send us an email at LearningEnglish@21voa.com.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>spell </strong>–n. magic that used on a person, often to create a bad or damaging effect</p>
<p><strong>circumstance </strong>–n. a situation <strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>consecutively </strong>–adv. taking place one after another in a series</p>
<p><strong>origin </strong>–n. the beginning point of something</p>
<p><strong>punch </strong>–n. the act of striking with a closed hand, or fist</p>
<p><strong>cartoonist </strong>–n. a person who draws simple pictures that tell stories</p>
<p><strong>comic strip </strong>–n. a series of pictures telling, often funny, stories that appears in newspapers or books as a series that continues for a time</p>
<p><strong>character </strong>–n. a person who appears in stories, plays, movies or TV who is not real</p>
<p><strong>knock out </strong>–v. to strike a person so that they lose consciousness or cannot continue</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>In Puerto Rico, Well-known Rapper also Works as a Doctor (2024/8/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/in-puerto-rico-well-known-rapper-also-works-as-a-doctor.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">02 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A popular rapper in Puerto Rico has kept his job as a doctor to help deal with a shortage of medical workers in the United States territory.</p>
<p>Many Puerto Ricans know Dr. Pedro Juan Vázquez by his performing name, PJ Sin Suela. But others are now getting to see his medical skills as he often goes <strong>door-to-door</strong> to serve patients.</p>
<p>The 34-year-old Vázquez recently told The Associated Press (AP) he is still living out his love of music. He also believes he is helping those in need and bringing attention to a health crisis in Puerto Rico.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="Dr. Pedro Juan Vázquez, better known by his stage name PJ Sin Suela, attends to a patient in Loiza, Puerto Rico, Saturday, May 25, 2024. (AP Photo/Alejandro Granadillo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-768e-08dcacb0edef_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">Dr. Pedro Juan Vázquez, better known by his stage name PJ Sin Suela, attends to a patient in Loiza, Puerto Rico, Saturday, May 25, 2024. (AP Photo/Alejandro Granadillo)</span></div>
<p>The U.S. territory is currently facing power outages as well as a shortage of medical professionals. Many doctors and other workers have gone to the U.S. mainland seeking better pay.</p>
<p>A 2023 report by Puerto Rican policy group Center for a New Economy found the territory had lost more than 8,600 doctors out of nearly 18,800 in just over 10 years. The problem is expected to get worse in the coming years.</p>
<p>“We have a huge <strong>exodus</strong> of young people,” Vázquez told the AP. He added, “In Puerto Rico, we have a crisis much bigger than people think.”</p>
<p>Vázquez said he travels from the capital, San Juan, to rural areas of the island at least once a week. During these trips, he seeks to treat communities struggling from the combined effects of hurricanes, earthquakes and a weak economy.</p>
<p>When not working as a doctor, Vázquez produces and performs music that brings attention to issues including social inequality, poverty and gun violence.</p>
<p>In one song, he brings up the territory's problems with violence. “A bullet is flying, lost like a child,” he raps, “the wind <strong>caresses</strong> it, seeks to make news, falling into a skull, without any kind of justice.” The rap song, in English, is called <em>Bullets Cry</em>.</p>
<p>In another song, called <em>We are More</em>, Vázquez comments on the territory's economic problems. He raps, “The debt has been placed before the worker, the one who goes outside under the rain and the sun, public servers, teachers and nurses."</p>
<p>Vázquez has left and returned to the island several times. This is common for many Puerto Ricans, who hold U.S. passports. He does not criticize those who have left Puerto Rico for the U.S. mainland. “You can't judge anybody, everybody has their story,” he said. “I'm <strong>blessed</strong> to have two <strong>careers</strong> that I can do and live off of.”</p>
<p>Vázquez was born in the Bronx area of New York City. But he moved with his family to the town of Ponce, Puerto Rico. Later, he went to Pennsylvania, before returning to Bayamón, Puerto Rico. It was there that Vázquez studied medicine. He became a doctor in 2015.</p>
<p>He became a household name as a rapper for a younger generation in Latin America in 2018. The single that made Vázquez a star was called <em>What Is Your Plan?</em> He worked with Puerto Rican musician Bad Bunny and reggaeton singer Nejo on the song.</p>
<p>When the COVID-19 pandemic hit in 2020, he decided to start working in medicine again. Vázquez worked full-time at a hospital in Ponce for a year. Then, as a general doctor, he treated patients of all ages.</p>
<p>Vázquez noted that some doctors questioned his medical abilities at first, since he had spent years performing as a rapper. But after a short time, he said, “Everybody knew that this wasn't a joke for me, and that I'm really good at what I do.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>door-to-door </strong><em>–idiom</em> to go from house to house in a neighborhood</p>
<p><strong>exodus</strong><em> - n.</em> when a large number of people all leave a place together</p>
<p><strong>caress </strong><em>– v.</em> to touch or stroke lightly or lovingly</p>
<p><strong>blessed </strong>-<strong> </strong><em>adj. </em>of or enjoying happiness</p>
<p><strong>career </strong>–n. the path of a person's work live involving different but usually related jobs or professions</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Spoiled Food and Drink (2024/8/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/spoiled-food-and-drink.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Noura about how to describe food that is no longer safe to eat.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-e47f-08dcb00fd98c_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>Would you please tell us the words we use to describe spoiled food? Now I use only one or two words for all of food types, such as " rotten" or "spoiled." However, in my native language we use different words for different categories like spoiled vegetables, bread, beverages, [and] meat-dishes. I wonder if it is the same in English too.</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>Thank you for writing to us, Noura. I'm happy to answer this question.</p>
<p>Let's begin with the two words you mention, “rotten,” and “spoiled”. We can use both words to talk about food in general. So, we can say either of the following:</p>
<p><em>That food is rotten.</em></p>
<p><em>That food is spoiled.</em></p>
<p>But for some foods, we use “rotten” much more than we use “spoiled.” For example, we can say rotten eggs, rotten tomatoes, rotten apples, rotten vegetables, rotten fruit, and so on. The most common usage of “rotten” is with eggs.</p>
<p>We use “spoiled” mostly when talking about meat or milk.</p>
<p>Another general term for spoiled food or drink is the expression “gone bad”.</p>
<p>Now let's look at some other terms we use with certain foods and drinks.</p>
<p>“Rancid” describes foods that contain fats that have started to go bad. These typically include nuts, seeds, and oils. Fish, meat, and poultry can also become rancid.</p>
<p>We use the word “stale” to describe bread that has become hard and difficult to eat. And “wilted” describes lettuce or other greens that are no longer fresh.</p>
<p>Mold is a kind of very small fungus. It makes food go bad and can be found on fruit, bread and cheese. The adjective we use for mold is “moldy.”</p>
<p>We use the adjective “sour” or the expression “to go sour” to describe milk or cream that has started to spoil. Note that there is also a food called sour cream, which is safe to eat – and quite tasty!</p>
<p>As you can see, a meal with rancid, stale, sour, wilted, moldy, rotten and spoiled food is one to avoid!</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, do you have a question about American English? Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: ‘Super Jupiter’ Planet Takes 100 Years to Orbit Star (2024/8/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/study-super-jupiter-planet-takes-100-years-to-orbit-star.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Astronomers say they have observed a new <strong>exoplanet</strong> that orbits far away from its star although it is a large and massive planet.</p>
<p>An international group of researchers said they learned new things about the planet after examining data from the James Webb Space Telescope. The telescope is operated by the American space agency NASA.</p>
<p>The gas giant, which has been named Epsilon Indi A b, was first <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/exoplanet-catalog/epsilon-indi-a-b/">discovered</a> in 2019. It is also known as a “super Jupiter,” meaning it is similar to Jupiter in our own solar system, but more massive.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This illustration provided by the Max Planck Institute for Astronomy in July 2024 depicts a cold gas giant orbiting a red dwarf. (T. M&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;252;ller (MPIA/HdA) via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-c0ba-08dcafdbe324_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This illustration provided by the Max Planck Institute for Astronomy in July 2024 depicts a cold gas giant orbiting a red dwarf. (T. M<i>&amp;#</i>252;ller (MPIA/HdA) via AP)</span></div>
<p>Scientists estimate the exoplanet's <strong>diameter</strong> is about the same as Jupiter's, but it is about six times more massive. The team said the planet has an atmosphere rich in hydrogen like Jupiter's.</p>
<p>Epsilon Indi A b is estimated to be about 12 light-years away from Earth. A light year is the distance light travels in a year – about 9.5 trillion kilometers.</p>
<p>International researchers led by Germany's Max Planck Institute examined new telescope images of Epsilon Indi A b. They said they learned the massive exoplanet orbits the star Epsilon Indi A, which is part of a three-star system.</p>
<p>The scientists said one surprising discovery was that the exoplanet seems to take at least 100 years to orbit its star and possibly as many as 250 years. The research shows Epsilon Indi A b orbits its star at a distance equal to 15 times the distance from the Earth to our own sun.</p>
<p>The researchers said they were able to “directly” observe the gas giant by using a tool on the James Webb to block the light of the planet's main star. The team was then able to identify the exoplanet as a bright spot of infrared light.</p>
<p>The new findings recently appeared <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07837-8">in a study</a> in the publication <em>Nature</em>.</p>
<p>Scientists estimate the planet and star are about 3.5 billion years old. That is 1 billion years younger than our own solar system.</p>
<p>Elisabeth Matthews is an astrophysicist at the Max Planck Institute for Astronomy. Matthews led the research. She told The Associated Press in an email the exoplanet appears to be older and brighter than had been thought.</p>
<p>The team noted the planet's star is so bright that it can be seen with the unaided eye from the Southern Hemisphere.</p>
<p>But Matthews noted that nothing in the newly collected data suggests that Epsilon Indi A b has the right conditions to support life. “This is a gas giant with no hard surface or liquid water oceans," she said.</p>
<p>Matthews said studying worlds similar to Jupiter can help scientists understand “how these planets <strong>evolve</strong>” over many, many years.</p>
<p>The first exoplanets outside our solar system were confirmed in the early 1990s. NASA's total count today stands at about 5,690. The majority of these exoplanets were identified through the so-called “<strong>transit</strong>” method. This involves repeatedly observing drops in starlight that might happen when a planet partly blocks light from its star.</p>
<p>Land- and spaced-based telescopes also search for new data on exoplanets, especially ones that might be similar to Earth.</p>
<p>NASA launched the James Webb Space Telescope in 2021. It is currently the largest and most powerful astronomical observatory ever placed in space.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>exoplanet </strong><em>- n.</em> a planet of a star that sits outside the solar system</p>
<p><strong>diameter </strong><em>– n.</em> the length of a straight line through the center of an object or space</p>
<p><strong>evolve </strong><em>– v. </em>to develop gradually over time</p>
<p><strong>transit </strong><em>– v. </em>to pass through or across a place, area of country, on the way to someplace else</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Some Plants Grow for a Long Time to Flower Only Once (2024/8/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/some-plants-grow-for-a-long-time-to-flower-only-once.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Some plants, known as flowering annuals, <strong>bloom</strong> without stop before dying at the end of the year or season.</p>
<p>Other flowering plants, known as perennials, return every year. They can bloom all season, with a lot of <strong>blossoms</strong> at first followed by additional flowers from time to time. Sometimes it is a limited show that can last as little as two weeks.</p>
<p>Biennials flower only in their second year before dying.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This May 19, 2018 image provided by the Lady Bird Johnson Wildflower Center shows American columbo (Frasera caroliniensis) flowers in bloom in Hayesville, North Carolina. (Stephanie Brundage/Lady Bird Johnson Wildflower Center via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/94af6fa6-deb3-4b31-9ade-72a96c54b4c5_cx0_cy7_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This May 19, 2018 image provided by the Lady Bird Johnson Wildflower Center shows American columbo (Frasera caroliniensis) flowers in bloom in Hayesville, North Carolina. (Stephanie Brundage/Lady Bird Johnson Wildflower Center via AP)</span></div>
<p><strong>Monocarpic plants</strong></p>
<p>But there is another group of plants called monocarpics. Their name comes from the Greek words for “single,” mono, and “fruit,” carpos. Monocarpics spend their whole lives growing in size only to produce a single bloom before dying.</p>
<p>Some monocarpic plants have a following among a small group of <strong>gardeners</strong>. These gardeners enjoy what can be years of waiting. They often throw parties to show their plant's once-in-a-lifetime bloom to others.</p>
<p>Other growers, however, can be surprised to discover their 30-year-old plant unexpectedly blooming, only to watch it die immediately afterward.</p>
<p>Flowers have a purpose: to ensure the continuation of their species. After their bloom ends, plants produce seeds that grow into new plants.</p>
<p>Monocarpic plants have just one chance at this. So, as you might imagine, the effort is often<strong> spectacular</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Examples of monocarpics</strong></p>
<p>Take the century plant. Rather than living for 100 years, as its name suggests, it has an average lifespan of just 10 to 30 years. It is a desert plant native to Mexico and Texas.</p>
<p>During its life, it grows to 1.8 meters tall before sending up a giant flower stalk that can reach nine meters, often surprising its owners.</p>
<p>A 19-year-old American columbo plant growing at the North Carolina Botanical Garden in Chapel Hill bloomed this spring. The plants are native to the eastern and central United States. They grow quickly for many years before pushing forth flowers that are up to two meters long.</p>
<p>The monocarpic plant group also includes the fishtail palm. It can grow over 15 meters in height. The trees produce flowers with yellow centers when they are between 10 and 20 years old.</p>
<p>The good news is the show of flowers can last up to 5 years, after which only the blooming <strong>trunk </strong>will die, leaving secondary trunks, if present, to take over. However, fishtail palms grown as houseplants are not likely to bloom.</p>
<p>Bamboo is also a monocarpic plant. But it can take more than 100 years for some bamboo <strong>species</strong> to flower, and even then, sometimes their roots push up new plants.</p>
<p>Bananas, too, are monocarpic, but they reproduce by sending up suckers, or small, new plants, from their roots. After their one-and-only fruit crop is harvested, the main plant is cut to ground level, leaving the suckers to take over.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Jessica Damiano reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>bloom </strong><em>– v.</em> to produce or yield flowers <em>—n.</em> a flower</p>
<p><strong>blossom</strong> <em>—n.</em> a flower <em>—v.</em> to produce flowers</p>
<p><strong>gardener</strong> <em>–n.</em> a person who raises and keeps plants for flowers and for food</p>
<p><strong>spectacular </strong>–<em> adj.</em> describes the quality of being unusual, notable, or entertaining</p>
<p><strong>trunk</strong><em> -- n.</em> the main part of a tree apart from limbs and roots</p>
<p><strong>species</strong><em> – n.</em> a category of biological classification ranking immediately below the genus or subgenus</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers: New Blood Tests Help Doctors Identify Alzheimer’s Disease (2024/8/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/researchers-new-blood-tests-help-doctors-identify-alzheimer-s-disease.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>New blood tests could help to identify, or <strong>diagnose</strong>, Alzheimer's disease faster and with more <strong>accuracy</strong>, researchers reported recently. However, some of the tests for the brain-wasting disease appear to work better than others.</p>
<p><strong>New tests, new drugs </strong></p>
<p>Doctors can confirm Alzheimer's in a patient if they find one of the disease's main signs: the development, or buildup, of a sticky protein called beta-amyloid. Currently, doctors use brain imaging or a special test known as a spinal tap to look for beta-amyloid buildup. Brain imaging is hard to get and spinal taps are painful.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A doctor points to PET scan results that are part of a study on Alzheimer's disease at Georgetown University Hospital, on Tuesday, May 19, 2015, in Washington. (AP Photo/Evan Vucci, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a199d0f1-3a06-4cff-81e0-ee533dd240c7_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A doctor points to PET scan results that are part of a study on Alzheimer's disease at Georgetown University Hospital, on Tuesday, May 19, 2015, in Washington. (AP Photo/Evan Vucci, File)</span></div>
<p>Instead, many patients are diagnosed based on their behavior and <strong>cognitive</strong> exams.</p>
<p>Now, labs have begun offering blood tests that can show some signs of Alzheimer's. Scientists are excited about the possibilities that the tests offer.</p>
<p>But the tests are not widely used yet because there is little data to guide doctors about which kind to order and when. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has not officially approved any of them, and few patients have insurance coverage for such tests.</p>
<p>“What tests can we trust?” asked Dr. Suzanne Schindler of Washington University in St. Louis. Schindler is part of a research project examining the tests. While some tests are very accurate, Schindler said, “other tests are not much better than a flip of a coin.”</p>
<p>More than 6 million people in the United States and millions more around the world have Alzheimer's, the most common form of dementia. Its usual signs, or “biomarkers,” are amyloid plaques and abnormal tau protein that leads to tangles that damage <strong>neurons</strong>.</p>
<p>New drugs such as Leqembi and Kisunla can slow the disease a little. The medicines remove amyloid from the brain. But these drugs only work in the early part, or stage, of Alzheimer's progression. Few patients get the costly brain scans and invasive spinal taps that could show early stage Alzheimer's.</p>
<p>Even specialists struggle to tell if Alzheimer's or something else is to blame for a patient's problems.</p>
<p>Schindler said she sometimes has patients “who I am convinced have Alzheimer's disease and I do testing and it's negative.”</p>
<p>A limited number of doctors have carried out blood tests for Alzheimer's in carefully controlled research settings. However, a new study of about 1,200 patients in Sweden shows they also can work in doctors' offices.</p>
<p>The findings suggest the blood tests may be more helpful for general care doctors. They see many more cases of people with memory problems than specialists do. However, general care doctors have fewer diagnostic tools.</p>
<p>In the study, patients who visited either a general care doctor or a specialist for memory problems got an early diagnosis using traditional exams. They gave blood for testing and got confirmatory spinal taps or brain scans.</p>
<p>Blood testing is far more accurate, Lund University researchers reported recently at the Alzheimer's Association International Conference in Philadelphia. They said that the primary care doctors' first diagnosis was 61 percent accurate and the specialists' first diagnosis 73 percent. However, the blood test was 91 percent accurate, their study showed. The Journal of the American Medical Association published the study.</p>
<p><strong>Different biomarkers</strong></p>
<p>Dr. John Hsiao of the National Institute on Aging said the new tests measure different biomarkers in different ways.</p>
<p>Doctors and researchers should only use blood tests proven to have a greater than 90 percent accuracy rate, said Alzheimer's Association chief science officer Maria Carrillo.</p>
<p>Carrillo and Hsiao agreed that the blood tests most likely to provide that accuracy measure what is called p-tau217. Schindler helped lead an unusual direct comparison of several kinds of blood tests that came to the same finding. The Foundation for the National Institutes of Health financed the work.</p>
<p>That kind of test measures a form of tau that <strong>correlates</strong> with how much plaque buildup someone has, Schindler explained. A high level signals a strong likelihood the person has Alzheimer's. A low level strongly suggests Alzheimer's is not the cause of a patient's thinking problems.</p>
<p>Several companies are developing p-tau217 tests.</p>
<p><strong>Who should use blood tests for Alzheimer's? </strong></p>
<p>In the United States, only doctors can order the blood tests from labs. The Alzheimer's Association is working on policy suggestions and several companies plan to seek FDA approval, which would clarify correct use.</p>
<p>For now, Carrillo said doctors should use blood testing only in people with memory problems, after checking the accuracy of the kind they order.</p>
<p>Especially for primary care physicians, “it really has great potential to help them in sorting out who to give a reassuring message and who to send on to memory specialists,” said Dr. Sebastian Palmqvist of Lund University. Palmqvist led the Swedish study with Lund's Dr. Oskar Hansson.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p>And I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Lauran Neergaard reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>diagnose </strong><em>– v.</em> to identify a disease from its signs and symptoms</p>
<p><strong>diagnosis</strong><em> – n.</em> the act of identifying a disease from its signs and symptoms</p>
<p><strong>accuracy</strong> <em>– n.</em> the quality of being precise or correct</p>
<p><strong>cognitive</strong> <em>– adj.</em> of or relating to thinking, reasoning, or remembering</p>
<p><strong>neuron</strong> <em>– n.</em> a cell that is the fundamental functional unit of nervous tissue transmitting and receiving nerve impulses</p>
<p><strong>correlate</strong> <em>– v.</em> to bear mutual relations</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>First Online Child Safety Bill Passes US Senate (2024/8/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/first-online-child-safety-bill-passes-us-senate.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">31 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The U.S. Senate has approved the nation's first major legislation aimed at protecting children from internet harms.</p>
<p>Two bills passed the Senate by a vote of 91-3 on Tuesday. But the measures will also need to be passed by the U.S. House of Representatives to become law. It is currently unclear whether the House will approve the bills in the future.</p>
<p>One bill is known as the Kids Online Safety Act, or KOSA. The other is called the Children's Online Privacy Protection Act (COPPA 2.0).</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE — Isabella Cimato, 17, from left, Arianna Schaden, 14, and Sofia Harrison, 15, check their phones at Roosevelt Field shopping mall in Garden City, N.Y., on July 27, 2015. (AP Photo/Seth Wenig, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-697c-08dcb163b3e2_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE — Isabella Cimato, 17, from left, Arianna Schaden, 14, and Sofia Harrison, 15, check their phones at Roosevelt Field shopping mall in Garden City, N.Y., on July 27, 2015. (AP Photo/Seth Wenig, File)</span></div>
<p><strong>What do the measures do?</strong></p>
<p>The KOSA bill requires technology companies to take steps to provide a “duty of care” to protect young users. This legal term covers a range of steps businesses need to take in an effort to “prevent and <strong>mitigate</strong>” harm to children. Such harms include <strong>bullying</strong> and violence, as well as online information related to suicide, eating disorders and substance and sexual abuse.</p>
<p>The bill known as COPPA 2.0 is designed to increase privacy rules related to children. The bill bans some targeted advertising to kids online. It also bars data collection on children without their knowledge or approval. And it gives parents and young users the ability to remove personal information from social media services.</p>
<p>In addition, the bills would require companies to permit minors to <strong>opt out</strong> of product tools that use activity history to predict and suggest additional content to keep users online for long periods.</p>
<p><strong>How will they be enforced?</strong></p>
<p>The bill empowers state attorney general representatives to enforce most parts of the laws. However, the “duty of care” part cannot be enforced by state attorneys general. That change was made after concerns were raised that some states may seek to block information related to <strong>LGBTQ</strong> issues or reproductive rights.</p>
<p>Wider enforcement will be dealt with by the Federal Trade Commission (FTC), which will help decide what kinds of content is “harmful” to children.</p>
<p><strong>Who supports the measures?</strong></p>
<p>KOSA and COPPA 2.0 are being supported by a wide range of nonprofits, technology <strong>accountability</strong> organizations and parental rights groups. In addition, the bills have been supported by major groups representing American doctors and teachers.</p>
<p>Some well-known technology companies – including Microsoft, X and Snap – have also expressed support. Meta, which owns Facebook, Instagram and WhatsApp, has not publicly expressed strong support or opposition to the measures. Meta has said in the past it is not completely against some government <strong>regulation </strong>of social media.</p>
<p><strong>Who opposes the legislation?</strong></p>
<p>Some technology industry groups and the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) have criticized the measures. They have suggested that differing definitions of what is considered harmful to children could result in minors being blocked from important information. Such information could include LGBTQ issues, reproductive rights or vaccines.</p>
<p>Some changes were made earlier to the legislation in an effort to overcome these concerns, but some critics said those did not go far enough. "They made improvements, but not enough," said Democratic Senator Ron Wyden of Oregon. He was one of three senators who voted against the bills. He recently told reporters, "I still think it is going to harm a lot of LGBTQ kids because of the way it's going to make it difficult for them to get information.”</p>
<p><strong>Can the legislation pass the House?</strong></p>
<p>Josh Golin is executive director of Fairplay, a nonprofit group working to protect children from online marketing and other possible harms. He told The Associated Press before the Senate vote that he is “very hopeful” the bills will eventually be passed by both houses of Congress.</p>
<p>“The reason it has not come to a vote yet is that passing legislation is really hard, particularly when you're trying to regulate one of the, if not the most powerful industry in the world,” Golin said.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters, Agence France-Presse and the European Commission.</em></p>
<p><strong>_________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>mitigate</strong><em> - v.</em> to reduce the harmful effects of something</p>
<p><strong>bully </strong><em>– v.</em> to purposefully frighten someone who is smaller or weaker than you</p>
<p><strong>opt out </strong><em>– v. </em>to choose not to be part of an activity or to stop being part of it</p>
<p><strong>LGBTQ </strong><em>– n. </em>lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, and queer/questioning one's sexual or gender identity</p>
<p><strong>accountable </strong>– <em>adj.</em> being responsible for one's own actions and being able to explain those actions</p>
<p><strong>regulate </strong>–<em> v. </em>to control an activity or process, especially by using rules or laws</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Italy’s Historic Trains Draw Visitors to Less Popular Areas (2024/8/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/italy-s-historic-trains-draw-visitors-to-less-popular-areas.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">31 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>As it moves across central Italy, an old train pulling <strong>carriages</strong> from the 1930s and 1950s crosses the forests of the Majella National Park and the Abruzzo highlands.</p>
<p>Across 100 kilometers, the Park Railway, also known as the Italian Transiberian, travels through valleys and tunnels and over old bridges called viaducts. It offers visitors a view of small, rural and hidden villages in the country.</p>
<p>It was the first of some 1,000 kilometers of rail line to have re-opened under a project by Fondazione FS, part of the state-controlled national rail company.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A passenger travels on board of a vintage train that departed from Sulmona on the way to Palena, Italy July 21, 2024. (REUTERS/Antonio Denti)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/88ef9117-d77a-4fac-98c3-f78d3a9017cb_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A passenger travels on board of a vintage train that departed from Sulmona on the way to Palena, Italy July 21, 2024. (REUTERS/Antonio Denti)</span></div>
<p><strong>“Timeless tracks” </strong></p>
<p>The project called "Timeless <strong>tracks</strong>" aims to take visitors to forgotten parts of Italy instead of the popular cities.</p>
<p>"These are tracks that have lived through different eras, they have carried soldiers to the front, cows to <strong>pasture</strong>... they were mistakenly considered unproductive during the 1960s and 70s but are now once again of value," Luigi Cantamessa, who heads Fondazione FS, told Reuters.</p>
<p><strong>Inspired</strong> by train travel in Switzerland, the project now carries 45,000 visitors a year across its 13 lines. Fondazione FS expects to open two new ones by 2026, both in the southern area of Sicily.</p>
<p>"What were considered to be the dry branches of Italy's train network, have now proved to be the green shoots," Cantamessa added.</p>
<p>Norma Pagiotti is a 28-year-old from Florence, Italy traveling on the train with two friends.</p>
<p>Pagiotti said, "People are used to cities and places, like Florence, that everyone knows.. but then there are other areas that need to be discovered. (This) is the right kind of <strong>tourism</strong> that does not spoil the <strong>authenticity</strong> of places,"</p>
<p>Caterina Quaranta, from southern Italy, used the term “nostalgic," meaning a longing for a past time, to describe riding the train.</p>
<p>“The train reminds me of my youth, I feel a bit nostalgic for the things of the past, which were simpler, now everything is fast, short-lived," Quaranta said.</p>
<p>Laura Colaprete, a local guide, said the trains draw Italians and foreigners, families and children, younger people who get off to hike and ride bicycles, and older people "who have time to spare.”</p>
<p><strong>The trip </strong></p>
<p>After climbing up almost 1,000 meters in<strong> altitude</strong>, the Transiberian's first stop is in Palena, a hill-top town known for its beautiful views over the national park.</p>
<p>Traditional folk music accompanies people getting off the train, with local foods such as lamb skewers and soft pancakes and products by local artisans awaiting them at the station.</p>
<p>"The train helps several small towns around here. This line was a dead line before," said Gino Toppi, 60, as he helped his wife with the food stand in the small station.</p>
<p>Milan's Bocconi University recently estimated that for every dollar spent by passengers on tickets, as much as three more are spent on food, tours and other purchases. The rail ticket costs between $32 and $76.</p>
<p>That helps to support the economy of villages that have long lost population due to the declining birth rate and younger people leaving for the bigger cities.</p>
<p>"There certainly are <strong>benefits</strong>, this is a way to show my products," said Annalisa Cantelmi, an herbalist, or herb grower. "These tourists are slowly discovering these new territories, their traditions and people," she added.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Giulia Segreti reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>carriage</strong> <em>– n.</em> a wheeled vehicle</p>
<p><strong>track</strong> <em>– n.</em> the parallel rails of a railroad</p>
<p><strong>pasture </strong><em>– n.</em> land used for grazing</p>
<p><strong>inspire</strong> <em>– v.</em> to influence, move, or guide</p>
<p><strong>tourism</strong> <em>– n.</em> the practice of traveling for fun</p>
<p><strong>authenticity</strong> <em>– n. </em>not false or imitation; true to one's own personality, spirit, or character</p>
<p><strong>altitude</strong><em> – n.</em> the vertical elevation of an object above a surface (such as sea level or land)</p>
<p><strong>benefit</strong> <em>– n.</em> something that produces good or helpful results or effects</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>In the US, Disasters Strike All Over the Country (2024/8/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/in-the-us-disasters-strike-all-over-the-country.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">31 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>When it comes to disasters in the United States, most people think of major storms and earthquakes that hit coastal areas. But a study from the nonprofit Rebuild by Design and New York University says disasters happen everywhere across the country.</p>
<p>The study looks at information on hundreds of federally declared disasters from 2011 to about 2021. It also examines the $60 billion that the Federal Emergency Management Agency, or FEMA, gave state and local governments.</p>
<p>The study finds that eight of the nine <strong>counties </strong>with the most federally declared disasters since 2011 are in Kentucky. One is in Vermont. These counties have several times the number of disasters as the national average of three in the past 13 years.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Buildings and homes are flooded in the aftermath of Hurricane Laura near Lake Charles, La., on Aug. 27, 2020. (AP Photo/David J. Phillip, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-7d69-08dcafccaab7_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Buildings and homes are flooded in the aftermath of Hurricane Laura near Lake Charles, La., on Aug. 27, 2020. (AP Photo/David J. Phillip, File)</span></div>
<p>A federal disaster is declared when a bad natural event is so costly that local government officials do not believe they can recover. So, the governor of the state asks the president to declare a disaster which frees federal money set aside for this purpose.</p>
<p>Amy Chester is director of Rebuild by Design. She said, “California and Louisiana and I would say now even Texas, Florida, for sure, they soak up all the oxygen when you hear about these giant storms.”</p>
<p>Chester added, “But what you're not hearing about are these storms that are happening all the time, and that's just becoming ...regular to places like Vermont.” Chester also noted Tennessee, Oklahoma, Mississippi, Iowa and Alaska as having a lot of disasters.</p>
<p>“We want to show that climate change is already here,” Chester said of the data, which covers 2011 to 2023. It does not include heat waves, lack of rain or diseases, like COVID-19.</p>
<p>Before she studied the data, Chester said she thought Vermont would be safe from climate change. Instead, it has many disasters.</p>
<p>“It's awful,” Chester said. “It just keeps happening to them.”</p>
<p>Vermont recently flooded again because of heavy rain from Hurricane Beryl.</p>
<p><strong>Disasters in unexpected places</strong></p>
<p>In July 2022, at least 40 people died, and 300 homes were damaged when a flood struck Floyd County in eastern Kentucky. It was the 13th time in 12 years that the federal government declared the rural county a disaster.</p>
<p>Judge Robbie Williams is the administrator of the county with about 35,0000 people. He said, “After that flood, I had 500 homeless people looking at me, ‘Judge what are we going to do'?” Williams added, “It's <strong>overwhelming</strong> and it's just a matter of time before it happens again.”</p>
<p>Then, in 2023, Floyd County was declared a disaster again for the 14th time since 2011. But Floyd County is not the nation's most disaster-<strong>prone</strong> county. Neighboring Johnson County has had 15 disasters declared by FEMA.</p>
<p>Floyd County's government received more than $35 million in FEMA disaster aid since 2011. But that is not a lot of money compared to other counties hit by hurricanes.</p>
<p>Five counties received more than $1 billion in FEMA aid. Three of them are in New York state. They are led by Manhattan's New York County, which got $8.9 billion after being struck by Hurricane Sandy in 2012.</p>
<p>FEMA notes that flooding is the most common disaster in the U.S. Since 2011, FEMA has paid more than $41 billion in aid following hurricanes, the most of any kind of disaster.</p>
<p>Susan Cutter is with the Hazards Vulnerability and Resilience Institute at the University of South Carolina. Cutter said: “What the data tell us is that the frequency and severity of disasters at local-state <strong>scales</strong> is increasing with rural, suburban, and urban places being affected nationwide.” She was not involved in Chester's research. But she added, “More needs to be done.”</p>
<p><strong>Geography and regulations</strong></p>
<p>In Floyd County, Judge Williams said geography and government <strong>regulations</strong> make it tough for the area. The county is in the mountains. People live in the narrow valleys, he said. When it rains, the creeks and rivers overflow.</p>
<p>“We're seeing historic levels of flooding,” Williams said. “It's only getting worse.”</p>
<p>Environmental regulations bar local officials from <strong>dredging</strong> the creeks. <strong>Silt</strong> from the mountains keeps building up, Williams said. Some creeks were about six meters deep but are now shallow enough to walk across, he said.</p>
<p>"The problem is there is nowhere for the rain to go,” Williams said.</p>
<p>Samantha Montano is a professor of emergency <strong>management</strong> at the Massachusetts Maritime Academy. Montano said what is more important is how state and local policies create or reduce the risk of future disasters.</p>
<p>In Floyd County, the local government is using FEMA money to buy the homes of 150 residents to move them out of a flood area, but some do not want to leave, Williams said.</p>
<p>“Until we get those homes out of these flood ways...we're still going to have these issues,” Williams added.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins. And I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Seth Borenstein reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>county</strong> <em>–n.</em> an area in a state that has its own local government</p>
<p><strong>overwhelming</strong> –adj. an amount too big to deal with effectively</p>
<p><strong>scale</strong> <em>–n. </em>a level or size of something in relation to other, similar things that are bigger or smaller</p>
<p><strong>regulation</strong> <em>–n.</em> a rule or law that governs a kind of activity or industry</p>
<p><strong>disaster-prone </strong><em>–adj.</em> likely to have a disaster</p>
<p><strong>dredging </strong><em>–n.</em> the process of removing mud from the bottom of a river or canal to make it deeper so boats can pass</p>
<p><strong>silt </strong><em>–n.</em> dirt that is carried by rivers and streams to lower areas of land</p>
<p><strong>management </strong><em>–n.</em> the effort of overseeing and controlling a business, government office or organization</p>
<p><strong>creek </strong><em>–n.</em> a small stream</p>
<p><strong>shallow</strong> <em>–adj.</em> not deep</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>European Parent Groups Aim to Ban Smartphones for Teens (2024/7/31)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/european-parent-groups-aim-to-ban-smartphones-for-teens.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">30 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>If parents say "no" when a child asks for a smartphone, the response they are likely to hear is, "Everyone has one. Why can't I?"</p>
<p>But what would happen if the child's friends did not have a mobile phone either?</p>
<p>That is the way that some parents in Europe are thinking.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A boy plays with his father's phone outside school in Barcelona, Spain, on June 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Emilio Morenatti)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-7c49-08dca76866aa_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A boy plays with his father's phone outside school in Barcelona, Spain, on June 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Emilio Morenatti)
</span></div>
<p>They are concerned by evidence that smartphone use among young children threatens their safety and mental health. They believe that the more parents join their movement, the more powerful their ideas become.</p>
<p>Parents in Spain, Britain and Ireland are using social media groups on services like WhatsApp and Telegram to talk about their plans. They want to keep smartphones out of schools. But for their plan to work, other parents have to refuse to buy children the devices before — or even into — their teenage years.</p>
<p>Elisabet García Permanyer got involved after she talked with another parent in a Barcelona park. Last year, she started a social media group to share information on the dangers of the internet with families at her children's school.</p>
<p>The group, called "<strong>Adolescence</strong> Free of Mobile Phones," quickly grew and now includes over 10,000 members. The most involved parents are asking other parents to agree not to get their children smartphones until they are 16.</p>
<p>"When I started this, I just hoped I would find four other families who thought like me, but it <strong>took off </strong>and kept growing, growing and growing," García Permanyer said. "My goal was to try to join forces with other parents so we could <strong>push back </strong>the point when smartphones arrive. I said, 'I am going to try so that my kids are not the only ones who don't have one.'"</p>
<p><strong>Spain</strong></p>
<p>Police and public health experts have also been voicing concerns about the kind of materials that children can see on their mobile devices. Spain's government took note of the problem and banned smartphones from elementary schools in January. Now they can only be turned on in secondary school, which starts at age 12, if a teacher deems it necessary for an educational activity.</p>
<p><strong>Britain</strong></p>
<p>In Britain last year, a 16-year-old girl named Brianna Ghey was killed by two teenagers. Her mother demanded that social media on smartphones be limited for children under 16.</p>
<p>Mother Daisy Greenwell, who lives in the area of Suffolk, England, and a friend, Clare Reynolds, set up a social media group called Parents United for a Smartphone-Free Childhood. It grew quickly and an organizer said it now has groups in every British county.</p>
<p><strong>Ireland</strong></p>
<p>In Greystones, Ireland, eight primary school leaders, or principals, wrote to parents, asking them not to buy their students smartphones. Then the parents themselves voluntarily signed written agreements, promising not to let their young children have the devices.</p>
<p>Thirty-eight-year-old Christina Capatina is a Greystones parent of two young daughters. She signed the agreement and said there were almost no smartphones in schools this school year.</p>
<p><strong>Unity is powerful</strong></p>
<p>Studies from Spain, Britain, and Ireland show that by the time children are 12, most have smartphones. In Spain, 25 percent of children have a cellphone by age 10, and almost 50 percent by age 11. At 12, this share rises to 75 percent. British media <strong>regulator</strong> Ofcom said 55 percent of children in Britain owned a smartphone between ages eight and 11, with the figure rising to 97 percent by age 12.</p>
<p>Over recent years, organizations, governments, and parents have been reporting that smartphone use by children is linked to <strong>bullying</strong>, mental health problems and loss of the <strong>focus</strong> necessary for learning. China moved last year to limit children's use of smartphones. France has a ban on smartphones in schools for children aged six to 15.</p>
<p>The possible dangers have produced school bans on smartphones and online safety laws. But those measures do not deal with what children do outside of school with mobile phones. Parents and schools that have pushed for changes in their communities saw that it became possible the moment they understood that they were not alone.</p>
<p>Rachel Harper is principal of St. Patrick's National School in Greystones. Harper wants parents to work with their local school to organize phone bans. She said, "There's a bit more strength that way, in that all the parents in the area are talking about it."</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p>And I'm Mario Ritter.</p>
<p><em>Joseph Wilson and Laurie Kellman reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>adolescence</strong> – <em>n</em>. the period of life when a child develops into an adult</p>
<p><strong>take off</strong> <em>– v. (phrasal) </em>to quickly become very popular</p>
<p><strong>push (something) back</strong> – v. (<em>phrasal) </em>to change (a planned event) to start at a later date or time</p>
<p><strong>bullying <em>–</em></strong><em>n.</em> the act of using threats and force to get others to do what you want them to do</p>
<p><strong>focus</strong> – <em>n. </em>the ability to direct your attention or effort at something specific</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Rising Demand for Cooling Systems in Africa Fuels Environmental Concerns (2024/7/31)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/rising-demand-for-cooling-systems-in-africa-fuels-environmental-concerns.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">30 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Rising demand for cooling systems in Nigeria and other African nations might be making existing pollution problems worse.</p>
<p>Cooling systems use gases called refrigerants. Such gases can affect the atmosphere if they escape. Some of these pollutants have been found to be more harmful than other kinds of <strong>greenhouse gases</strong>.</p>
<p>The Nigerian government has approved restrictions on the release of refrigerant gases into the environment. But enforcement efforts for the laws have been difficult.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A technician positions an R-22 refrigerant on an outdoor air conditioning unit in Lagos, Nigeria, Thursday, July 18, 2024. (AP Photo/Sunday Alamba)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-1223-08dcb09ee993_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A technician positions an R-22 refrigerant on an outdoor air conditioning unit in Lagos, Nigeria, Thursday, July 18, 2024. (AP Photo/Sunday Alamba)</span></div>
<p>Abiodun Ajeigbe leads an air conditioning business for Samsung, West Africa. He told The Associated Press (AP), “Those laws, those rules, nobody enforces them.”</p>
<p>Ajeigbe said one of the biggest problems is a lack of effective education and training about the possible harms of refrigerants. This means many cooling system <strong>installers</strong> might not follow legal requirements when removing old systems or putting new ones in.</p>
<p>Some trained workers do follow environmental rules governing the use of cooling refrigerants. But these kinds of installations cost more.</p>
<p>Industry experts and public records suggest the most common air conditioning systems in Africa use a kind of gas known by the trade name R-22. This refrigerant is said to be less harmful to the environment than older cooling chemicals known as chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs). CFC's have largely been removed from most modern cooling systems. That change was put in motion by the 1987 Montreal Protocol environmental treaty.</p>
<p>A document from the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) says R-22 is considered many times more damaging to the world's climate than carbon dioxide. For example, about one-half kilogram of R-22 is said to equal one ton of carbon dioxide, the most common greenhouse gas.</p>
<p>However, while carbon dioxide can stay in the atmosphere for more than 200 years, R-22 stays for about 12 years. R-22 cooling equipment is not as energy <strong>efficient</strong> as some other systems. And most of the electricity used to power R-22 coolers in Africa requires carbon-based fuels.</p>
<p>Nigeria is planning to ban R-22 refrigerants by January 1, 2030. But without enough enforcement, that target is not likely to be met, Samsung's Ajeigbe told the AP.</p>
<p>Some cooling systems use a group of refrigerants called hydrofluorocarbons (HFCs). These do not harm the <strong>ozone layer</strong> and are more energy efficient. But HFCs are said to be strong greenhouse gases and account for an estimated 2 percent of all human-caused warming in the atmosphere.</p>
<p>One of the most harmful HFCs, called R-410A, is used in the second most common kind of air conditioners in Africa, the AP reported. Sellers and installers of cooling equipment in Nigeria told the news agency that although HFC systems are less damaging to the environment, they are more costly to operate.</p>
<p>The same issues are affecting countries beyond Nigeria. In Ghana, the cooling industry also struggles to get companies and workers to obey current environmental rules.</p>
<p>Environmental officials in Ghana told the AP that “poor servicing practices” for cooling systems are common across the country. This is largely the result of the public choosing lower-trained installers who might not follow recommended <strong>standards</strong>.</p>
<p>In Kenya, demand for cooling systems is also growing as the population grows and electricity becomes more widely available. Cooling systems using R-22 are still common across the country. But the nation's Environmental Management Authority told the AP there have not been any new imports of the systems since 2021.</p>
<p>Workers dealing with cooling systems and refrigerants are required to get a <strong>license</strong>. But several installation workers told the AP that since such requirements are hard to enforce, environmentally unsafe methods are carried out.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>greenhouse gases</strong><em> - n.</em> gases in the Earth's atmosphere that can trap heat</p>
<p><strong>install </strong><em>– v.</em> put a piece of equipment somewhere and make it ready to use</p>
<p><strong>efficient </strong><em>– adj. </em>working well and not wasting time or energy</p>
<p><strong>ozone layer </strong><em>– n. </em>the layer of ozone high above the Earth's surface that prevents much of the ultraviolet radiation from the sun from reaching Earth's surface</p>
<p><strong>standard </strong>–n. an accepted way of doing something that is agreed upon by industry or government officials</p>
<p><strong>license </strong>–n. official permission to do an activity, such as driving a car, that usually involves a document</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Olympic Triathlon Delayed Because of Seine River Water Quality (2024/7/31)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/olympic-triathlon-event-delayed-because-of-seine-river-water-quality.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">30 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The organization supervising the Olympic triathlon event at the Paris Olympics has postponed the event because of water quality in the Seine River.</p>
<p>However, World Triathlon and city officials are hopeful the event, which includes swimming, bicycling, and running, can start on July 31.</p>
<p>World Triathlon is the sport's governing body, overseeing competitions and safety. Its technical and medical team met with the International Olympic Committee, and city and local French government officials. They decided to postpone the event because of water quality.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A ship sails past reproductions of artworks decorating the banks of the River Seineat the 2024 Summer Olympics, Tuesday, July 30, 2024, in Paris, France. (AP Photo/Vadim Ghirda)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-7c4e-08dcb0b7a1f7_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A ship sails past reproductions of artworks decorating the banks of the River Seineat the 2024 Summer Olympics, Tuesday, July 30, 2024, in Paris, France. (AP Photo/Vadim Ghirda)
</span></div>
<p><strong>How does water quality affect health?</strong></p>
<p>Tests in June showed unsafe levels of E. coli bacteria although results in July showed improvement.</p>
<p>Dr. Nicole Iovine is an infectious disease specialist at the University of Florida in Gainesville.<strong> </strong>She said while most kinds of E. coli are not harmful, high numbers can be dangerous. The presence of E. coli is a sign that human and animal waste is in water. The World Triathlon Federation considers E. coli levels higher than 900 colony-forming <strong>units</strong> per 100 milliliters to be unsafe.</p>
<p>Swimming in water with unsafe levels of bacteria can lead to feeling sick to the stomach and intestinal problems. Swimmers are likely to swallow water, which can lead to diarrhea. The bacteria can also infect the <strong>urinary tract</strong> or open cuts.</p>
<p>Iovine said, “The athletes are young, and they're in the best shape of anybody...But that doesn't mean they can't get sick from these things.”</p>
<p>Officials are hoping for sunny weather. The ultraviolet light in sunlight can kill bacteria and higher temperatures bring levels of E. coli and other bacteria in the river water to within safe limits.</p>
<p>French Sports Minister Amélie Oudéa-Castéra told French news media on Monday that officials are “absolutely <strong>serene</strong> about all this.” She said plans put in place to control the bacterial levels in the river have worked, but the weather was beyond their control.</p>
<p><strong>Why is the Seine River polluted?</strong></p>
<p>Swimming in the Seine River has been banned for more than 100 years. But Olympic officials wanted to have the swimming part of the triathlon event in the city's famous waterway. So, Paris officials spent $1.5 billion to clean up the Seine.</p>
<p>Paris is an ancient city. And like many old cities, it has what is known as a combined <strong>sewer</strong> system. That means the city's wastewater and storm water flow through the same pipes. When heavy rainfall happens, the pipes carry the extra “storm water” along with wastewater into the river instead of a sewage treatment center. As a result, untreated human waste goes directly into the river after heavy rains.</p>
<p>Iovine said bacteria, viruses and parasites get into the water through human waste. But other things too.</p>
<p>“It's also wildlife — rodents, for example. When it rains a lot, all of that from those animals can end up in the Seine,” she said.</p>
<p>To prevent the wastewater overflow, Paris officials built a huge <strong>basin</strong> next to the Austerlitz train station. It is supposed to capture extra rainwater to keep waste from flowing into the river. They also rebuilt parts of the sewer system and improved water treatment centers. However, heavy rain can still overwhelm the system.</p>
<p>The rain that took place during the weekend of the Olympic opening ceremonies filled the basin by 20 percent. So, officials said the pollution was likely coming from wastewater <strong>upstream</strong>.</p>
<p>If the water quality does not improve, officials are considering holding the event on August 2.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Pat Graham, Kate Brumback, and Devna Bose reported for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted them for VOA Learning English with additional AP material. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>unit </strong>–n. one amount of something</p>
<p><strong>urinary tract</strong> <em>–n. (medical) </em>the tubes that carry liquid waste from the kidneys out of the body</p>
<p><strong>serene</strong> <em>–adj.</em> peaceful and untroubled</p>
<p><strong>sewer </strong>–n. pipes used to carry wastewater</p>
<p><strong>basin </strong>–n. an area or container that holds water</p>
<p><strong>upstream </strong>–adj. the part of a river or stream that is closer to the source (opposite: downstream)</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Heat Can Be Good or Bad for Your Garden (2024/7/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/heat-can-be-good-or-bad-for-your-garden.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">29 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Summer brings very high temperatures to many parts of the United States. That can be both good news and bad news for <strong>gardens</strong> and gardeners.</p>
<p>Jessica Damiano writes about gardening for the Associated Press. She keeps a garden in New York, where summer temperatures can reach 32 degrees Celsius.</p>
<p>Recently, Damiano repeated a difficult truth for gardeners: weather has a lot to do with success, but it is out of our control.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image shows a nearly 6-foot tall tomato plant growing on Long Island, N.Y. on July 9, 2024. (Jessica Damiano via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-389f-08dca2a4ff28_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image shows a nearly 6-foot tall tomato plant growing on Long Island, N.Y. on July 9, 2024. (Jessica Damiano via AP)</span></div>
<p>There are measures that plant lovers can take to ease the effects of hot summer weather. One measure is to spread a thick layer of <strong>mulch</strong> over plant roots. This can help keep plant roots cool and will preserve water, or moisture, in the soil. When watering plants, use a lot of water and let it <strong>soak</strong> deep into the ground. You can water your garden less often if you provide a few deep soaks regularly. Light watering causes roots to spread near the surface of the soil.</p>
<p>If there is too much sun for young plants, don't be afraid to give them shade. Damiano said she has been known to place an umbrella on the ground to protect <strong>tender</strong> plants from the sun.</p>
<p><strong>The good news about heat</strong></p>
<p>Heat is not all bad for a garden. Some plants love heat. Damiano grows a kind of tomato called Big Boy. The plant, she says, has grown quickly in the summer heat. Zucchini, a form of squash, also does well.</p>
<p>Heat can also keep harmful insects away. Cabbage, onion and corn <strong>maggots</strong> prefer cooler weather and struggle in the heat. So do cutworms, which can be especially destructive to gardens.</p>
<p>Damiano says some of her <strong>perennial</strong> flowering plants have bloomed two weeks earlier than usual. For this reason, she decided to add late-blooming plants to her garden to ensure a good crop of flowers.</p>
<p>She reported that her hydrangea plants have never looked better. She has 12 of them, and they are blooming well. However, Damiano said that might not be the result of hot weather this summer. Instead, unusually heavy rains late last summer and fall may have helped <strong>buds</strong> to form. A smaller number of those buds were damaged by the <strong>mild</strong> winter weather. The result is a lot of blooms.</p>
<p><strong>And the downside</strong></p>
<p>Some plants suffer in the heat, including impatiens. The small flowers are not doing well.</p>
<p>But what Damiano dislikes are the creatures that become more active and numerous when temperatures rise.</p>
<p>Mosquitos are most active at sunrise and sunset, but they can bite at any time. Although heat theoretically slows their activity, hot conditions can help mosquitoes spread.</p>
<p>Damiano advises to prevent water from collecting in places around the garden or to put something called Bti in wet areas where mosquitos might lay eggs. Bti is a kind of bacteria that produces a substance poisonous to young mosquitos and a few other flying insects. It is natural, and the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) says it is safe for people and most other insects and animals as well.</p>
<p>Ticks present another problem. The creatures bite people and spread disease. Cold weather kills them, but they do well in hot weather. Normally found in the eastern U.S. and on the Pacific coast, ticks appear to be spreading to new areas. The EPA even said, “Climate change has <strong>contributed</strong> to the expanded <strong>range</strong> of ticks.”</p>
<p>Wearing long sleeves and pants and using special chemicals to keep ticks away can help protect against their bites.</p>
<p>Earwigs also like heat and humidity. They can make holes in plant leaves, Damiano said. But the “pincher bugs” also eat aphids, which are enemies of the garden. So are thrips and spider mites.</p>
<p>In addition to insects, heat and humidity are good conditions for slugs. These creatures have soft slimy bodies, and they eat plants.</p>
<p>Luckily, there are easy ways to control these garden problems. One is to spray soapy water onto soft-bodied insects like aphids, spider mites, thrips and whiteflies.</p>
<p>As for slugs, salt will kill them but is not good for garden soil. They do not like sharp surfaces, however, so adding crushed eggshells can be an effective control method. The eggshells break down and nourish the plants over time.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Jessica Damiano wrote this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>garden</strong><strong> </strong><em>–n. </em>a place where plants are raised for their beauty or as food</p>
<p><strong>mulch</strong> <em>–n.</em> usually organic material that is in small pieces and is used to cover the ground to prevent drying and enrich the soil</p>
<p><strong>soak </strong><em>–v.</em> to get very wet</p>
<p><strong>tender </strong><em>–adj.</em> very soft</p>
<p><strong>maggot </strong><em>–n.</em> the larval stage of flies and similar insects</p>
<p><strong>perennial </strong><em>–adj.</em> lasting for many years</p>
<p><strong>bud </strong><em>–n.</em> a growth on a plant from which a new branch or fruit will grow</p>
<p><strong>mild </strong><em>–adj.</em> not strong or sharp</p>
<p><strong>contribute </strong><em>–v.</em> to be involved in the cause of some outcome</p>
<p><strong>range </strong><em>–n.</em> the area where something is found or where it lives</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Research Farm Raises Pigs to Produce Organs for Humans (2024/7/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/us-research-farm-raises-pigs-to-produce-organs-for-humans.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists are raising pigs to produce human organs at a specialized research farm in the American state of Virginia.</p>
<p>A medical company called Revivicor runs the farm in the rural community of Blacksburg. The area is surrounded by the Blue Ridge Mountains. Workers at the farm follow intense measures in an effort to prevent infection and disease spread.</p>
<p>About 300 pigs of different ages live on the research farm. Some animals raised there have already provided the first genetically changed pig organs ever <strong>transplanted</strong> into humans.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A pig stands in a pen at the Revivicor research farm near Blacksburg, Va., on May 29, 2024, where organs are retrieved for animal-to-human transplant experiments. (AP Photo/Shelby Lum)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-78e8-08dcaa98599d_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A pig stands in a pen at the Revivicor research farm near Blacksburg, Va., on May 29, 2024, where organs are retrieved for animal-to-human transplant experiments. (AP Photo/Shelby Lum)</span></div>
<p>Individuals working at the center must undergo a series of safeguards aimed at preventing infections in the organs grown for people.</p>
<p>Matthew VonEsch is an executive with United Therapeutics, the parent company of Revivicor. He told The Associated Press the research farm was designed with the goal of protecting the pigs “against <strong>contamination</strong> from the environment and from people.”</p>
<p>David Ayares is the founder and chief scientific officer of Revivicor. He described the farmed pigs to the AP as “<strong>precious</strong> animals” because of their ability to help save human lives.</p>
<p>The research farm looks very different from a traditional animal farm. This is because of the strong security and cleanliness measures needed. It was built to meet U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) safety requirements.</p>
<p>For example, pigs living at the farm only drink water that is highly <strong>filtered</strong>. All food also gets disinfected.</p>
<p>Revivicor's farm aims to produce human organs that can be used in scientific experiments or actual transplants.</p>
<p>There is currently a great need in the U.S. for organ transplants. Thousands of people are waiting for a donor organ. But experts say there will never be enough human donors to fill that need.</p>
<p>Using animal-grown organs for human transplants is one possible way to deal with the shortage.</p>
<p>Scientists use genetic engineering methods to grow organs in animals. These organs behave more like human ones than animal ones, which reduces the chances that the body will reject the animal organs. Teams have been working for many years to grow more humanlike organs in pigs.</p>
<p>So far in the United States, four “<strong>compassionate</strong> use” transplants have happened. These cases involved last-minute experiments to transplant pig organs into humans who faced life-threatening conditions. Two transplants involved hearts and two involved kidneys. Revivicor provided both of the hearts and one of the kidneys.</p>
<p>All four patients died within a few months. Still, experts say each transplant offered the possibility for valuable, real-life research. The goal is to one day attempt to put pig organs into human transplant patients who are not quite as sick.</p>
<p>Revivicor's Ayares said the company is aiming to produce organs in the pigs that closely meet the size and needs of each patient. The idea is that such organs will perform better than human-donated organs because they are younger and free of disease.</p>
<p>Ayares added that transplant doctors who have received organs from Revivicor's farm say, “Oh my god, that's the most beautiful kidney I've ever seen.” He said the reaction is the same when they get “a pink healthy happy heart from a young animal.”</p>
<p>Officials at Revivicor say the biggest difficulties they face include overcoming the rejection of pig organs in humans and preventing animals from carrying unknown infection risks. Scientists try to deal with the rejection issue by employing different engineering methods to make the pig organs as humanlike as possible.</p>
<p>Genetic changes are made to the pig eggs that Revivicor receives. The engineered eggs are then <strong>nurtured</strong> in the lab with the hope of producing a healthy embryo. The embryos are then taken to the research farm to be put inside living pigs.</p>
<p>It is expected to take years of experimentation to prove whether animal organ transplants will work long-term in human patients. But if the efforts succeed, United Therapeutics plans to open additional research farms to produce up to 2,000 organs a year.</p>
<p>Ayares said the efforts are currently at a point where several studies have suggested “there's no immediate rejection” of the genetically engineered pig organs. He added, “The next two or three years are going to be super exciting.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>transplant</strong><em> – v.</em> to perform a medical operation in which an organ or other part that has been removed from the body of one person is put into the body of another person</p>
<p><strong>contaminate </strong><em>– n.</em> to make something dirty or poisonous</p>
<p><strong>precious </strong><em>– adj. </em>very important or valuable</p>
<p><strong>filter </strong><em>– v.</em> to pass a liquid or gas through a piece of equipment in order to remove solid pieces or other substances</p>
<p><strong>compassionate </strong><em>– adj. </em>showing compassion: a feeling of sympathy for others who are suffering</p>
<p><strong>nurture </strong><em>– v. </em>to care for or encourage the growth of something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>A Shared Video Raises Concerns about AI and Politics (2024/7/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/a-shared-video-raises-concerns-about-ai-and-politics.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">29 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A video shared on the social media service X is raising concerns about the power of artificial intelligence (AI) to mislead voters, with American elections about three months away.</p>
<p>The video causing concern shows U.S. Vice President Kamala Harris saying things she did not say. Harris is the likely Democratic Party presidential nominee. The video was changed using AI tools.</p>
<p>The video gained widespread attention after tech billionaire Elon Musk shared it on X last week. Musk did not write in his posting that the video was a parody. A parody is any work that <strong>imitates</strong> someone or something, with the purpose of being funny.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Tesla and SpaceX CEO Elon Musk addresses the European Jewish Association's conference in Krakow, Poland, Jan. 22, 2024." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-d89a-08dcaff0bf5e_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Tesla and SpaceX CEO Elon Musk addresses the European Jewish Association's conference in Krakow, Poland, Jan. 22, 2024.</span></div>
<p>People who saw the video thought it had the appearance of a real political advertisement created by the Harris campaign. But the video's <strong>audio</strong> has another voice that sounds like Harris but is not.</p>
<p>Harris began her presidential campaign after U.S. President Joe Biden said he would no longer seek reelection. Biden had already gained enough delegates in primary elections to be the party's candidate.</p>
<p>In the video shared by Musk, the voice that sounds like Harris says, “I, Kamala Harris, am you Democrat candidate for president...” It says Harris is a “<strong>diversity</strong> hire” because she is a woman and is not white. It also says she does not know the “first thing about running the country.” The video uses real “Harris for President” images. It also contains real video of things Harris has said in the past.</p>
<p>Mia Ehrenberg is a Harris campaign spokesperson. Ehrenberg wrote in an email to the Associated Press (AP): “We believe the American people want the real freedom, opportunity and security Vice President Harris is offering; not the fake <strong>manipulated</strong> lies of Elon Musk and Donald Trump.”</p>
<p>The widely shared video is an example of how AI-generated images, video and audio have been used to make fun of people or to mislead the public. AI-generated materials have increasingly targeted politics.</p>
<p>High-quality AI tools are now easier to find and use. Some people say there are not enough federal rules to control their use. Currently, states and social media services set rules for using AI for political purposes.</p>
<p>The fake video of Harris raises questions about how people should deal with videos that have been changed when they are parodies or <strong>satire</strong>.</p>
<p>A YouTube user known as Mr Reagan first shared the video. That user wrote on both YouTube and on X that the video was manipulated and that it was a parody.</p>
<p>Chris Kohls, the YouTube user known as Mr Reagan, pointed an AP reporter to another YouTube video he made early Monday in answer to the reaction of the parody video. In the new video, Kohls confirmed he used AI to make the fake ad and argued that it was clearly a parody.</p>
<p>However, Musk shared the parody ad by writing, “This is amazing.” He also included a “laughing” <strong>emoji</strong>. He did not clearly state that the video is a parody.</p>
<p>More than 123 million people have seen the video through Musk.</p>
<p>Musk's X social media service has a <strong>feature</strong> called “community notes.” It permits users to add <strong>context</strong> to messages that might be misleading. Some people using the feature have suggested that Musk's message should have said that the video was a parody. They say it might have violated X's policies, which bar “out-of-context media that may deceive or <strong>confuse</strong> people and lead to harm.”</p>
<p>The X policy makes exceptions for <strong>memes</strong> and satire, as long as such postings do not cause “significant confusion...”</p>
<p>The United States Congress has not passed a law on AI and politics. But federal agencies have made efforts to do so. The National Conference of State Legislatures says more than one-third of American states have passed their own laws <strong>regulating</strong> the use of AI in campaigns and elections.</p>
<p>The U.S. elections will take place on November 5.</p>
<p>I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>Ali Swenson reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>parody </strong>–n. any artistic work that imitates the style or behavior of another person with the purpose of being funny</p>
<p><strong>diversity</strong> <em>–n. </em>the condition of including many different kinds of things</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_Wgj54Mu9"><strong>manipulated</strong></a> <em>–adj.</em> changed in some way for a specific purpose</p>
<p><strong>satire </strong>–n. a way of using humor to show that someone or something is foolish</p>
<p><strong>feature </strong>–n. a quality, part or ability of a product that is worth noting</p>
<p><strong>context </strong>–n. the additional information necessary to understand a piece of writing, video, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_2alUJ6IZ">sound</a> or an image</p>
<p><strong>confuse </strong>–v. to use language or images to prevent people from understanding something<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>meme </strong>–n. an image that spreads quickly and becomes popular with certain people</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: New Evidence Suggests Earth-like Exoplanet May Hold Liquid Ocean (2024/7/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/study-new-evidence-suggests-earth-like-exoplanet-may-hold-liquid-ocean.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Researchers say new telescope observations suggest an Earth-like planet outside our solar system may hold a large liquid ocean.</p>
<p>The exoplanet is known as LHS 1140 b. Astronomers believe it sits about 48 light years away from Earth. A light year is the distance light travels in a year – about 9.5 trillion kilometers.</p>
<p>The research – led by astronomers at the University of Montreal in Canada – shows the possibility the exoplanet might hold the right conditions to support some form of life. A <a class="wsw__a" href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ad5afa">study</a> explaining the findings recently appeared in <em>The Astrophysical Journal Letters</em>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="New research led by the University of Montreal suggests exoplanet LHS 1140 b may contain a liquid ocean. This illustration depicts the exoplanet (left), Jupiter's moon Europa (center) and Earth (right). (B.Gougeon/University of Montreal)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-b1bc-08dcad92d46e_cx1_cy0_cw98_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">New research led by the University of Montreal suggests exoplanet LHS 1140 b may contain a liquid ocean. This illustration depicts the exoplanet (left), Jupiter's moon Europa (center) and Earth (right). (B.Gougeon/University of Montreal)</span></div>
<p>The study is based on observations collected in December 2023 by the James Webb Space Telescope. The American space agency NASA operates the orbiting observatory.</p>
<p>Researchers combined the information from the James Webb with existing data to make new estimates for the exoplanet's mass and size. These suggest that LHS 1140 b is “a promising super-Earth ice or water world,” the University of Montreal <a class="wsw__a" href="https://exoplanetes.umontreal.ca/en/astronomers-find-surprising-ice-world-in-the-habitable-zone-with-webb-data/">said</a> in a statement.</p>
<p>Some past studies had suggested the exoplanet might be a gas giant, also known as a mini-Neptune. But the researchers said the new study provides evidence that LHS 1140 b is more likely a super-Earth, a rocky planet bigger than Earth.</p>
<p>The new research supports a NASA-led study from October 2023 that <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/science-research/planetary-science/astrobiology/nasa-some-icy-exoplanets-may-have-habitable-oceans-and-geysers/">suggested</a> at least 17 observed exoplanets could hold oceans of liquid water. That study noted that sometimes water from these oceans likely breaks through large pieces of ice to form <strong>geysers</strong>.</p>
<p>Scientists had already identified LHS 1140 b as being within its star's “<strong>habitable</strong> zone.” Exoplanets found within this zone are believed to have temperatures that would permit water to exist in liquid form.</p>
<p>Measurements made by the James Webb data suggest the exoplanet “is less dense” than expected for a rocky, Earth-like body. The researchers estimated that 10 to 20 percent of LHS 1140 b's mass might be made up of water. The possibility of a large liquid ocean would be found on the side of the planet always facing the star that it orbits.</p>
<p>The new data collected by the James Webb showed the exoplanet might also have a nitrogen-rich atmosphere. This differs from earlier research that suggested a possible atmosphere that was mostly hydrogen.</p>
<p>Charles Cadieux is a doctoral student at the University of Montreal's Trottier Institute for Research on Exoplanets. He was the lead writer of the study.</p>
<p>Cadieux said in a statement, “Of all currently known temperate exoplanets, LHS 1140 b could well be our <strong>best bet</strong> to one day indirectly confirm liquid water on the surface of an <strong>alien</strong> world beyond our solar system.” He noted that if the study's findings can be confirmed, the data would represent “a major <strong>milestone</strong>” in the search for exoplanets that could possibly support life.</p>
<p>René Doyon is a project scientist at the University of Montreal. He helped lead the research. He <a class="wsw__a" href="https://exoplanetes.umontreal.ca/en/astronomers-find-surprising-ice-world-in-the-habitable-zone-with-webb-data/">said</a> more observations will be needed to confirm the current study's findings. “The current <strong>hint </strong>of a nitrogen-rich atmosphere <strong>begs</strong> for confirmation with more data,” Doyon said.</p>
<p>He estimated that at least one more year of observations will be needed “to confirm that LHS 1140 b has an atmosphere.”</p>
<p>The process of confirming whether carbon dioxide is present in the atmosphere and liquid water exists on the surface would likely require several years of observations, Doyon noted.</p>
<p>Ryan MacDonald is a NASA Sagan Fellow in the University of Michigan's Department of Astronomy who helped examine the James Webb data. He <a class="wsw__a" href="https://exoplanetes.umontreal.ca/en/astronomers-find-surprising-ice-world-in-the-habitable-zone-with-webb-data/">said</a>, “This is the first time we have ever seen a hint of an atmosphere on a habitable zone rocky or ice-rich exoplanet.”</p>
<p>With further data collection and investigation, MacDonald noted there is a good possibility “we might just have found evidence of air on this world.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from the University of Montreal, the University of Michigan and NASA. </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>geyser</strong><em> - n.</em> a hole in the ground from which hot water and steam come out</p>
<p><strong>habitable </strong><em>– adj.</em> able to support life</p>
<p><strong>best bet </strong><em>– idiom. </em>the action that is most likely to be successful</p>
<p><strong>alien </strong><em>– n. </em>relating to creatures from another planet</p>
<p><strong>milestone </strong><em>– n.</em> an important event in the development or history of something</p>
<p><strong>hint </strong><em>– n. </em>to suggest or indicate something in an indirect way</p>
<p><strong>beg </strong><em>– v. </em>to make a very strong and urgent request</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Insect Hurts Tunisia's Prickly Pear Industry (2024/7/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/insect-hurts-tunisia-s-prickly-pear-industry.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A small insect is hurting Tunisia's prickly pears, an important source of money for the North African country's economy.</p>
<p>Bassem Sahnoun, a farmer struggling to deal with the insect problem, used the term “insomnia,” meaning an inability to sleep, to describe the issue.</p>
<p>"Our biggest fear, which has caused me insomnia, is the fear of the cochineal insect that threatens our harvest," he said.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A view shows a prickly pear plantation infested with cochineal insects, in Sfax, Tunisia July 19, 2024. (REUTERS/Jihed Abidellaoui)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/c2411c63-98fe-4fd0-a3ae-02c4d574a276_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A view shows a prickly pear plantation infested with cochineal insects, in Sfax, Tunisia July 19, 2024. (REUTERS/Jihed Abidellaoui)</span></div>
<p>The insect is known to some as the prickly pear cochineal. Farmers and experts say it has damaged large areas and caused concerns about its economic effects since it was first discovered in the country in 2021.</p>
<p>The bug gets the<strong> sap</strong> from cactus pads, causing yellowing and eventual death of the plants.</p>
<p>Agricultural expert Faouzi Zayani inspected dying prickly pear trees. He said, "The cochineal insect affects the prickly pear tree. As you can see, the trees are dying, and consequently, we are losing the <strong>essence</strong> of things, which is the <strong>cultivation</strong> of prickly pears.”</p>
<p>Zayani said the insect was first discovered in Mexico. "It was present there, and they treated it and had prevention methods," he added. "Then it spread to Morocco in 2015. This insect also came to Tunisia in October 2021 in the city of Mahdia."</p>
<p>Zayani estimates that prickly pears represent about 12 percent of Tunisia's agricultural land, making it second only to olive trees in agricultural wealth.</p>
<p>The pears cover approximately 600,000 hectares and are an important source of money for thousands of people, particularly women who harvest and sell the fruit.</p>
<p>Sahnoun told Reuters, “This is our livelihood, it requires a lot of labor, and it's not just the farmer who <strong>benefits</strong> from it.”</p>
<p>The Tunisian government and international organizations are now taking steps to try to help deal with the insect's effects.</p>
<p>The Food and Agriculture Organization started a $500,000 emergency project to introduce biological control methods such as ladybugs, which are hunters of the insect.</p>
<p>The Tunisian Ministry of Agriculture is promoting <strong>sustainable</strong> control measures, including changes in agricultural methods, <strong>pruning</strong>, and cleaning in production areas.</p>
<p>"We must have a sustainable solution for the cochineal insect. This situation should not continue in this way," said Naima Mahfoudhi, an official at the ministry of agriculture.</p>
<p>At his farm, Sahnoun takes measures to clean and protect his healthy prickly pear trees. But it will be a difficult job if the crisis continues and keeps drying up prickly pear trees.</p>
<p>"It starts at the bottom of the tree," he said.</p>
<p>Selma Jridi, who owns prickly pear trees, says the problem is out of her control. She said, "God's will <strong>prevails</strong>, this is God's judgment... “</p>
<p>I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>Jihed Abidellaoui reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>sap</strong> <em>– n.</em> the fluid part of a plant</p>
<p><strong>essence</strong> <em>– n.</em> the individual, real, or ultimate nature of a thing</p>
<p><strong>cultivation</strong><em>– n.</em> the act of preparing for the raising of crops; the act of helping plants grow</p>
<p><strong>benefit</strong><em> – v.</em> to receive help or an advantage</p>
<p><strong>sustainable</strong> <em>-- adj.</em> Of or relating to a method of harvesting or using a resource so that the resource is not permanently damaged</p>
<p><strong>prune</strong><em> – v.</em> to cut off or cut back parts of a plant <strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>prevail</strong> <em>-- v.</em> to be or continue in use; to gain ascendancy through strength</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>In Tokyo, Brewer Uses Unusual Methods to Make Japan’s Sake (2024/7/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/in-tokyo-brewer-uses-unusual-methods-to-make-japan-s-sake.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A small space in Tokyo houses a container of <strong>fermenting sake</strong>.</p>
<p>The bacteria in the 670-litre container will take more than two weeks to turn the rice and water inside into Japan's traditional alcoholic drink.</p>
<p>But the bacteria are not only alive, they are listening too, said<strong> brewer</strong> Yoshimi Terasawa.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Yoshimi Terasawa, chief brewer at Tokyo Port Brewing, sprinkles the spores of koji fungus over cooled steamed rice as a part of brewing sake, a traditional rice wine, at the brewery in Tokyo, Japan July 9, 2024. (REUTERS/Kim Kyung-Hoon)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/be62b8c7-0eab-4d5e-94ba-a7facaeec365_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Yoshimi Terasawa, chief brewer at Tokyo Port Brewing, sprinkles the spores of koji fungus over cooled steamed rice as a part of brewing sake, a traditional rice wine, at the brewery in Tokyo, Japan July 9, 2024. (REUTERS/Kim Kyung-Hoon)</span></div>
<p>He suggested the kind of music coming from a loudspeaker below the tank determines how the drink will taste.</p>
<p>"The micro-organisms inside are activated by the <strong>vibrations</strong>, and the taste changes," said the 63-year-old chief brewer of Tokyo Port Brewing.</p>
<p>Music is among the unusual methods Terasawa is using at the only sake brewery in the heart of the capital city.</p>
<p>Fit into a narrow building, the small operation employs methods that promise to help the environment.</p>
<p>The brewery employs special machinery and processes that use less energy and labor than a traditional brewery in the countryside.</p>
<p>"Making sake on this kind of smaller scale makes it easier to keep the production environment constant," Terasawa said. He has 45 years of experience in the industry.</p>
<p>The company produces about 30 kiloliters of sake each year. That is enough to fill almost 42,000 720-ml bottles.</p>
<p>But changing tastes and Japan's aging population have reduced demand.</p>
<p>The government says the number of sake breweries has decreased two-thirds from its high point in the 1970s to just over 1,100 now.</p>
<p>More than half of sake breweries are not making a profit.</p>
<p>Other difficulties that sake breweries face include a shortage of workers as brewers retire, increased fuel costs and problems with the rice supply.</p>
<p>Terasawa said his small brewery offers an example of how to deal with those difficulties.</p>
<p>The process starts on the fourth floor, where he and an employee steam the rice for 70 minutes.</p>
<p>Then they let gravity move the rice through openings in the floors and ceilings to a <strong>mold-application</strong> room on the third floor. Fermentation, using <strong>tap water</strong>, takes place on the second level. Finally, the sake is put into bottles at ground level.</p>
<p>"In the future, small breweries like this will have a great deal of <strong>merit</strong>," Terasawa added.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Rocky Swift and Kyung Hoon Kim reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>ferment</strong><em> – v.</em> to undergo fermentation (the anaerobic breakdown of an energy-rich compound (such as a carbohydrate to carbon dioxide and alcohol) by the action of microorganisms (such as bacteria or yeast)</p>
<p><strong>sake</strong> <em>– n. </em>a Japanese alcoholic beverage of fermented rice</p>
<p><strong>brewer </strong>–<em> n.</em> a person who creates (or brews) alcoholic drinks</p>
<p><strong>vibration </strong><em>– n.</em> a quivering or trembling motion</p>
<p><strong>mold </strong><em>– n.</em> a growth produced especially on damp or decaying organic matter</p>
<p><strong>application</strong> <em>– n.</em> an act of administering or laying one thing on another</p>
<p><strong>tap water</strong> <em>–n</em>. water that comes from ordinary pipes and is not treated in any special way</p>
<p><strong>merit</strong> <em>–n.</em> value or worth</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Let's Talk about 'Going South' (2024/7/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/let-s-talk-about-going-south.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">27 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Today, we talk about those times when things do not go as planned. All the planning in the world does not guarantee that your plans will happen the way you had planned.</p>
<p>Things can happen that are outside of your control. To talk about those times when things go <strong>awry</strong>, American English has two directional expressions: <u>go south</u> and <u>go sideways</u>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Passengers crowd the international flights departure area of Rome's Fiumicino airport, July 19, 2024. Many flights were delayed or canceled due to the worldwide internet outage. This unexpected event caused many trips to " borgia="" go="" gregorio="" photo="" south.="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-5457-08dcacc51d98_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Passengers crowd the international flights departure area of Rome's Fiumicino airport, July 19, 2024. Many flights were delayed or canceled due to the worldwide internet outage. This unexpected event caused many trips to "go south." (AP Photo/Gregorio Borgia)</span></div>
<p><strong>To go south</strong></p>
<p>Let's start with <u>go south</u>. If something <u>goes south</u>, it stops working or falls apart. It can also mean that something decreases in value or loses quality. We often use it to describe a situation where everything has gone wrong.</p>
<p>If your career <u>goes south</u>, you need to look for a new job. If your new computer <u>goes south</u>, it stops working. If a relationship <u>goes south</u>, the two people are heading toward a <strong>breakup</strong>.</p>
<p>And if a trip <u>goes south</u>, one bad thing after another happens. You miss your plane, your passport gets stolen, and the hotel loses your <strong>reservation</strong>. That makes for a vacation that has <u>gone south</u>.</p>
<p>Now, let's hear two friends use this expression.</p>
<p><em>A: So, how is your friend's new bakery doing? She opened it earlier this year, right?</em></p>
<p><em>B: She did. But then she ran into trouble. Her investor pulled out. And then her head baker quit. So, her business <u>went south</u> pretty quickly after that. </em></p>
<p><em>A: Oh, I'm sorry to hear that. But I'm not surprised. You need a lot of money up front to start a business. And for a bakery ... you definitely need a baker.</em></p>
<p><em>B: Well it didn't help that another bakery with lower prices opened down the street. Her business was bound to <u>go south</u> after that. </em></p>
<p><strong>To go sidesways</strong></p>
<p><strong>Sideways </strong>is another direction you don't want your projects or efforts to go. As a direction word, sideways means to go to either side – not forward or backward.</p>
<p>As an <strong>idiomatic</strong> expression, to <u>go sideways</u> also means things do not go as planned. But this expression can be used a little differently from <u>going south</u>. Often when things <u>go sideways</u>, they go wrong in strange ways. In other words, things get <strong>weird</strong>.</p>
<p>Sometimes you want things to <u>go sideways</u>. For example, a good story often <u>goes sideways</u>. You think it's going to go in one direction but then there is a <strong>plot twist</strong>. Situations change and the story goes in an unexpected direction. Used this way, <u>going sideways</u> is a good thing.</p>
<p>But what about on a family camping trip? Let's hear this expression used in that situation.</p>
<p><em>A: How was your family camping trip? </em></p>
<p><em>B: It was okay. But some really strange things happened. Nature things...</em></p>
<p><em>A: Tell me more. What happened?</em></p>
<p><em>B: Well, the first night a raccoon stole all my food. The second night while I slept, spiders spun webs all over my tent while I slept. And then on the third day while I was swimming in the lake, a fish bit me!</em></p>
<p><em>A: That IS a lot of weird nature stuff. I didn't even know fish could bite.</em></p>
<p><em>B: Me neither! But I guess on a camping trip that's <u>gone sideways</u> ... anything is possible!</em></p>
<p>And that's the end of this Words and Their Stories.</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>awry </strong><em>-adv. </em>off the correct or expected course</p>
<p><strong>breakup </strong><em>-n. </em>to end a romance</p>
<p><strong>reservation </strong><em>-n. </em>an arrangement to have something (as a motel room or a seat on a plane) held for one's use</p>
<p><strong>sideways </strong><em>-adj. or -adv. </em>from one side viewed the stage sideways : with one side forward turn sideways : to one side</p>
<p><strong>idiomatic </strong><em>-adj. </em>of, relating to, or conforming to <strong>idiom</strong> <em>-n. </em>an expression that cannot be understood from the meanings of its separate words but must be learned as a whole</p>
<p><strong>weird</strong> <em>-adj. </em>very unusual or strange</p>
<p><strong>plot twist </strong><em>– n. </em>a writing device that introduces a big change in the direction or expected outcome of the plot in a story</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>New French Stamps Smell Like Baguettes (2024/7/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/new-french-stamps-smell-like-baguettes.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">26 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Visitors to Paris for the Olympics can now send a smell of France home with their picture <strong>postcards</strong> and letters.</p>
<p>The smell comes from a special stamp showing the country's famous bread called <strong>baguette</strong>. The sweet smell, however, may remind you of a French <strong>bakery</strong> more than an actual baguette.</p>
<p>The stamp was released in May for the day of Saint-Honoré, the <strong>saint</strong> of bakers. Postal worker Clarisse Briend said the baguette makes people think of France. And she hopes visitors will pick up the stamps along with other official Paris 2024 postcards and stamps. The stamp sells for more than $2 at area post offices.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="Visitors to Paris for the Olympics may pick up some unusual stamps. If you rub the stamp, you can smell the freshly baked bread that is famous in France." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-6476-08dcabf5f6b4_tv_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">Visitors to Paris for the Olympics may pick up some unusual stamps. If you rub the stamp, you can smell the freshly baked bread that is famous in France.</span></div>
<p>Pia Sch<i></i>246;ndienst is a German visitor coming from the Netherlands with her family. She bought the stamps and said she could not smell anything, but her son could smell a chocolate <strong>croissant</strong>.</p>
<p>"You just have to rub the stamp here like this with your nails," Clarisse Briend said. "You can smell the bread, the baguette."</p>
<p>At the Léonie Bakery in Paris, baker Yasin Robin smelled the stamp and said, “It smells like flan,” a dessert but not the baguette itself. Chief baker Harlem Gbodialo said he could smell something sweet on the stamp while the shop manager Jeanne Barrère compared it to vanilla.</p>
<p>Regardless, Gbodialo added that the bakery expects to have many visitors at their shop near the Champs <i></i>201;lysées. “On top of that the Olympic Games are going to start next week, so it'll boost our influence in terms of clients, and also the weather's been nicer lately, so all the <strong>factors</strong> are coming together to have a great period of Olympic Games, a great party for everyone,” he added.</p>
<p>Eating baguettes is not as popular as it once was, but France still makes around 16 million per day - or nearly 6 billion a year. One story explains that Napoleon Bonaparte's bakers created the long shape to make it easier for his troops to carry.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Elena Rodriguez, Nathan Frandino, and Helena Williams reported this story for Reuters. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>postcard </strong><em>– n. </em>a card on which a message may be sent by mail without an envelope and that often has a picture on one side</p>
<p><strong>baguette</strong> – n. a long, thin loaf of bread</p>
<p><strong>bakery</strong> – <em>n</em>. a place where bread, cakes, cookies, and other baked foods are made or sold</p>
<p><strong>boost </strong>– <em>v.</em> increase</p>
<p><strong>croissant</strong> – <em>n.</em> a type of roll that has a curved shape and that is usually eaten at breakfast</p>
<p><strong>factor </strong>– n. something that helps produce or influence a result; one of the things that cause something to happen</p>
<p><strong>saint</strong> – <em>n</em>. a person who is officially recognized by the Christian church as being very holy because of the way he or she lived</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Methodology, Strategy, Plan (2024/7/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/methodology-strategy-plan.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Bassam in Yemen about the usage of three words connected with project management.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-3609-08dcabe8a7c5_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>In project management, we face three confused terms: “methodology”, “strategy”, and “plan”. Could [you] please help me to know how [to] differentiate among them and use each one in a correct way?</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>Thank you for writing to us, Bassam. I'm happy to answer this question.</p>
<p>The main difference between these words is how general or <strong>specific </strong>they are. “Plan” usually has the most general meaning, “strategy” tends to be more specific, and “methodology” is the most specific.</p>
<p>In its most general sense, “plan” means the same thing as “goal.” For example, a company may have a “plan,” or “goal,” to expand its business into more countries. And the company's “strategy” is the specific steps it takes to reach that goal.</p>
<p>However, we sometimes use “strategy” in a general way. We could say the company's “strategy” is to expand its business into more countries. But when we use “strategy” in this general sense, we tend to express the reasons for the “strategy.” So, we might say:</p>
<p><em>The company hopes its <u>strategy</u> to expand into more countries will <u>lower production costs</u>.</em></p>
<p>Note that “plan” can sometimes be specific. For example, if police need to catch a criminal, they can list the things they need to do to catch that person. The police can call this list their “plan.”</p>
<p>Now let's look at the most specific term, “methodology.” This word often <strong>refers</strong> <strong>to</strong> the details of how people do research. For example, when scientists write research papers, they include a <strong>section</strong> called “methods,” or “methodology.” This section explains exactly how the scientists did their experiments or other research.</p>
<p>Project management methodology can differ depending on the goals or kind of research needed. For example, marketing researchers study what kind of products people want to buy, while companies study manufacturing costs to help them set prices.</p>
<p>So, it is important to remember that the words “plan” and “strategy” can be general or specific. And “methodology” is the specific method we use to help our “strategy” or “plan” be successful.</p>
<p>We hope today's lesson is helpful, Bassam.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, do you have a question about American English? Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>specific </strong><em>-adj. </em>exact or particular</p>
<p><strong>refer to </strong><em>-v. </em>relate to or point to the meaning or details of something</p>
<p><strong>section </strong><em>-n. </em>a part of a whole</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Indonesia's Nickel Mining Hurting Forests (2024/7/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/indonesia-s-nickel-mining-hurting-forests.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">25 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Indonesia aims to be the world's top nickel supplier. But its efforts to produce nickel have seriously harmed the country's forests, nonprofit groups say.</p>
<p><strong>Natural resources </strong></p>
<p>Indonesia is the world's third most rainforest-covered country, home to giant forest flowers and rare wild animals such as orangutans and elephants.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="A boat cruises past the Indonesia Weda Bay Industrial Park in Central Halmahera, North Maluku province, Indonesia, Saturday, June 8, 2024. Indonesia has been building out a vast industry for nickel. (AP Photo/Achmad Ibrahim)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f44029b7-d80f-4f12-89eb-d8db859fcfbf_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">A boat cruises past the Indonesia Weda Bay Industrial Park in Central Halmahera, North Maluku province, Indonesia, Saturday, June 8, 2024. Indonesia has been building out a vast industry for nickel. (AP Photo/Achmad Ibrahim)</span></div>
<p>Indonesia also has the largest reserves of nickel in the world. The metal lies in <strong>shallow</strong> <strong>deposits</strong> in the rain forest. Mining it is easy when the rainforest is cut down.</p>
<p>Until recently, Indonesia mostly sold its nickel deposits in untreated form. It did not have factories to process the metal. Unprocessed nickel sells for less than the processed product.</p>
<p>Ten years ago, Indonesian officials decided the country should stop selling its resources at such a low cost. Instead, officials said Indonesia would process the metal so it would sell at a higher price. This would result in more job openings, also, officials said.</p>
<p>A large nickel-processing project began. Indonesian President Joko Widodo pushed the project further by building nickel factories, or smelters, near electric vehicle battery factories. In addition to the new nickel plants, coal power plants were built also to serve the new industrial sites.</p>
<p><strong>Forest loss </strong></p>
<p>More than 740,000 square kilometers of Indonesian rainforest have been logged, burned or degraded, since 1950, reports the non-profit research group Global Forest Watch.</p>
<p>But at the sites where developers are building these smelters, the surrounding forest disappears twice as fast, a new study by the Indonesian nonprofit Auriga says.</p>
<p>The new study of rainforest loss, based on government data, shows deforestation rose from an average of 33 square kilometers around each nickel processing plant, or smelter, to 63 square kilometers.</p>
<p>Indonesia plans to build as many as 22 new plants. If plans go through deforestation will likely greatly increase.</p>
<p>“The damage to the environment is <strong>devastating</strong>,” said Timer Manurung of Auriga. “...Rivers are polluted, <strong>mangroves</strong> are cut to develop smelter areas, coastal areas and coral are being damaged by the smelters.”</p>
<p>The waste from coal power plants is another problem, he said. The Associated Press verified the methodology used in the Auriga report.</p>
<p><strong>Effects </strong></p>
<p>The area of Weda Bay is now one of the world's largest nickel production centers. Smelters and coal-fired power plants burn to process nickel ore into material for <strong>batteries</strong> and steel.</p>
<p>The village of Lelilef Sawai is now surrounded by the Weda Bay Industrial Park. There, the deforestation and its effects are clear. Local farmer Librek Loha remains in Lelilef Sawai, refusing to sell the land he has taken care of for forty years. Now orange dust often covers his plants and clean water is often lacking. The plants also grow more slowly, he said.</p>
<p>From his land, he can hear building sounds and see bright orange material flow into the sea. Research shows landslides are far more likely in deforested areas.</p>
<p>Max Sigoro, 54, is a traditional hunter and farmer. Bright lights and noise from construction scare the deer he used to hunt at night. He says he has lost nearly all the means he had to earn a living since the industrial park's growth.</p>
<p>PT Indonesia Weda Bay officials declined to speak to the Associated Press.</p>
<p>The company says it has planted more than 10 square kilometers of new trees. It says it plays an active part in supporting the living standards of local people, offering economic development. And, the industrial zone meets all environmental standards, PT Indonesia Weda Bay says.</p>
<p>The company also says it works to protect water and has launched coral and mangrove planting programs.</p>
<p>The Weda Bay project is just one of the industrial parks criticized by locals nearby. An industrial park on the island of Borneo and other projects in North Maluku are also under community protests.</p>
<p>Perhaps related to these public objections, European companies may be losing interest in nickel from Indonesia.</p>
<p>In recent weeks, the French mining company Eramet and German chemical giant BASF announced they were canceling plans to build a $2.6 billion nickel plant in Indonesia.</p>
<p>Indonesia has been seeking to work more with Tesla, which uses twice as much metal in its total production of batteries than the next highest auto competitor. The amount of nickel Tesla used in 2023 was up a third over the year before. Only 13 percent came from Indonesia last year. But Tesla's 2023 impact report noted Indonesia 18 times and warned the country's nickel will be very important.</p>
<p>Tesla did not answer an AP email requesting information about its use of nickel from Indonesia and deforestation.</p>
<p>Questions to Indonesia's Ministry of Environment and Forestry, Coordinating Ministry of Maritime and Investment Affairs and Ministry of Energy and Natural Resources also went unanswered.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p>And I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>Victoria Milko, Ed Davey, and Camille Fassett reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>shallow</strong> <em>– adj.</em> having little depth</p>
<p><strong>deposit </strong><em>– n.</em> a natural accumulation of something (ore, oil, etc.)</p>
<p><strong>battery</strong> <em>– n.</em> a cell that gives electricity</p>
<p><strong>devastating</strong> <em>– adj.</em> causing great damage or harm</p>
<p><strong>mangrove</strong> <em>– n.</em> tropical maritime trees or shrubs that send out many roots and form dense masses</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Learn about US Presidential Campaigns (2024/7/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/learn-about-us-presidential-campaigns.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Every four years, the United States holds an election for the president in November. This lesson aims to help teachers and learners understand the political processes and expressions used during the election campaign.</p>
<p><strong>The political parties</strong></p>
<p>Let us begin with the expression, political party. In elections, parties organize candidates who share party members' ideas about how government should operate. They try to win elections to gain and keep political power.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Images representing the Republican Party and the Democratic Party in the United States." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-253f-08dc81a74f05_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpeg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Images representing the Republican Party and the Democratic Party in the United States.</span></div>
<p>There are two major political parties in the U.S. They are the Democratic Party and the Republican Party. There are other small political parties at the national level. These include the Libertarian and Green parties.</p>
<p><strong>Primaries and caucuses</strong></p>
<p>Each of the U.S. states and territories holds votes early in the election year. In many states and territories, these votes are called <strong>primaries</strong>. You may know the word “primary” as an adjective meaning “happening or coming first” as in “primary school.” When speaking of elections, it is a noun, but it has a similar meaning – it is the first election in a voting process that takes place over one year.</p>
<p>You might also hear the term <strong>caucus</strong>. A caucus is also a kind of election, but it is held privately by the party and usually does not involve state election officials or equipment. The Iowa caucus was for a long time the first presidential contest during an election year.</p>
<p>In a primary or a caucus, voters choose the party's candidates for local and state offices as well as for national offices. The candidates who get the most votes become the candidates for the election in the fall.</p>
<p>Primaries can be “open” or “closed.” Anyone can take part in an open primary election — even members of another party. Only registered party members can vote in a closed primary.</p>
<p><strong>Delegates</strong></p>
<p>In some states, voters choose delegates in the primaries.<strong> </strong>State party organizations have different rules for choosing them. Delegates are people who will attend their party's convention, or general meeting.</p>
<p>When a delegate is elected to choose a particular candidate, we say the delegate is <strong>pledged</strong> to the candidate. To pledge is to promise something.</p>
<p><strong>Conventions</strong></p>
<p>Each party holds a national convention – a large meeting where the delegates officially <strong>nominate</strong> the candidate that the party supports for the presidential election. The verb “nominate” means to officially choose someone as a candidate for a position. You will hear some other forms of the word in election news.</p>
<p><strong>Nomination</strong></p>
<p>To describe the process of having the delegates choose a candidate, we use the noun form, “nomination.” At the convention, the candidate who gains the majority of delegates is called the “nominee.” The nominee gives a speech to accept the nomination.</p>
<p><strong>The party platform</strong></p>
<p>The party platform is a statement of the ideology of the party and its candidate. At the party convention, the organizing committee shares its platform. The platform is a statement of the policies that the party hopes to put in place during its candidate's term in office.</p>
<p><strong>The campaign trail</strong></p>
<p>Presidential candidates travel the country speaking to voters at a series of events called <strong>rallies</strong>. Reporters use the expression “campaign trail” to describe these events. This is a <strong>metaphor</strong> for progressing along a path toward a goal. The election campaign is sometimes called a “race,” another metaphor comparing the election campaign to a sporting competition.</p>
<p><strong>Debates</strong></p>
<p>Part of the campaign process is for the candidates to debate each other. These are televised events where a reporter asks questions that interest the public and gives each candidate a limited time to answer them. The form of the political debates is not the same as traditional <strong>academic</strong> debates, where teams compete under clear rules and time limits.</p>
<p><strong>Donors</strong></p>
<p>Presidential candidates and others who run for public office must find money to pay for those rallies, television advertising, and campaign workers. A common way to pay for a campaign is to ask for money. People who give to a candidate are donors. The Federal Election Commission makes rules about how much, when, and how donations can be made.</p>
<p><strong>Polls and the Polls</strong></p>
<p>Researchers get the opinions of voters in an effort to guess, or predict, the results of an upcoming election. They do this with <strong>polls</strong>, or public opinion studies. This word has two meanings in the elections. One is where a researcher might ask you about your party affiliation and which candidate you plan to support in a telephone call. Your party affiliation is the party you are registered with or that you support.</p>
<p>The other meaning of “poll” is the place where you go to vote on election day. We can also use “polling place.” Schools, religious centers and public buildings can be polling places. In them, voters <strong>cast </strong>their ballot secretly. That means they fill out their ballot without pressure from others in the room and turn in their ballot to be counted by poll workers.</p>
<p>In the last two election years of 2020 and 2022, people could send in their ballots by mail. But polling places remain important for processing and counting ballots.</p>
<p><strong>Privacy and politics</strong></p>
<p>Now that you have some of the expressions used to talk about the presidential campaign, you should use them with some care. It is not normal to ask someone what party he or she is a member of although many people will offer that information freely.</p>
<p>In some situations, such as among close friends, you will hear Americans talk about the candidates and voice their opinions openly. But when talking with a new <strong>acquaintance</strong> or a stranger, it is best to avoid asking about political affiliation.</p>
<p>Also, know that some workplaces have rules against political activity, and, in government, most political activity is not legal although people often share their opinions.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins. And I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Jill Robbins wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><em>_________________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>primary</strong> – <em>n.</em> an election in which members of the same political party run against each other for the chance to be in the general election</p>
<p><strong>caucus </strong><em>–n.</em> a political party meeting used to decide candidates and often delegates that is private and only open to party members</p>
<p><strong>pledge </strong>– <em>v</em>.<strong> </strong> to formally promise to give or do (something)</p>
<p><strong>platform</strong> – <em>n</em>. the official beliefs and goals of a political party</p>
<p><strong>sustainable</strong> – <em>adj</em>. involving methods that do not completely use up or destroy natural resources</p>
<p><strong>rally</strong> – <em>n. </em>a public meeting to support or oppose someone or something</p>
<p><strong>metaphor </strong><em>–n.</em> a word or term that means one thing that is used to represent a different thing usually because of a similarity</p>
<p><strong>academic </strong><em>–adj.</em> related to school or schooling</p>
<p><strong>poll </strong>–<em> n. </em>an activity in which several or many people are asked a question or a series of questions to provide information about what people think about something; a place for voting</p>
<p><strong>affiliation</strong> – <em>n.</em> the state of belonging to a particular religious or political group</p>
<p><strong>cast</strong> –<em> v. </em>to formally make (a vote)</p>
<p><strong>acquaintance</strong> – <em>n</em>. someone who is known but who is not a close friend</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Some Cubans Are Turning to Electric Bikes, Vehicles (2024/7/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/cubans-are-turning-to-electric-bikes-vehicles.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Cuba's capital, Havana, is famous for its colorful <strong>vintage</strong> cars. They fill the streets and are often popular subjects for visitors' photographs.</p>
<p>But these days, Cubans are just as likely to be found traveling around town quickly and quietly on electric scooters made with Chinese parts.</p>
<p>"Electric motorcycles are solving a lot of problems in Cuba, they are already used for almost everything," said Omar Cortina. He is a Cuban hotel worker who recently purchased his first electric vehicle -- a lime-green scooter powered by a lithium battery.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A view of the Caribbean Electric Vehicles (VEDCA) factory in Havana, Cuba, July 15, 2024. (REUTERS/Alexandre Meneghini)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-09a2-08dcab64d88b_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A view of the Caribbean Electric Vehicles (VEDCA) factory in Havana, Cuba, July 15, 2024. (REUTERS/Alexandre Meneghini)</span></div>
<p>Until recently, Cuba's roads had changed little in the years since former leader Fidel Castro's 1959 revolution. Old cars with old <strong>exhaust</strong> systems drove along uneven roads.</p>
<p>Today, electric vehicles are an increasingly common transportation choice. Between 2020 and 2022, Cuba-based companies produced more than 23,000 electric vehicles. That number comes from official government sources.</p>
<p><strong>Fuel is hard to find and expensive </strong></p>
<p>Fuel for <strong>combustion</strong>-powered engines has been hard to find for years in Cuba. People would wait in fuel lines for hours and sometimes even days.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, the price for gasoline increased to five times the usual price. That means a usual 40-liter tank of gas costs more than a state-worker's average monthly earnings. For most Cubans, that made purchasing gasoline nearly impossible.</p>
<p><strong>Public transportation is hardly any better</strong></p>
<p>But costly fuel is not the only problem.</p>
<p>There are fewer buses in Havana than there were in the past. This year, half the bus routes to points outside the capital were cut, state-run news agencies in Cuba report. Fuel and parts to repair old buses are also harder to find.</p>
<p>All these <strong>factors </strong>have helped to increase the demand for electric vehicles. Products from newly formed companies like Caribbean Electric Vehicles (Vedca) are helping to fill that demand.</p>
<p>Vedca is a <strong>joint venture</strong> between Chinese investor Tianjin Dongxing Industrial and Cuban state bicycle manufacturer Minerva. It has produced more than 2,000 scooters, bikes, and mini-tricycle trucks in Cuba with Chinese parts.</p>
<p>Juilo Oscar Perez is the company's director. Perez told reporters that electric vehicles are not just giving people another way of getting around. They are also solving fuel-related problems.</p>
<p>The company, Perez said, has also begun testing a new electric tractor and experimenting with other electric-powered heavy machinery.</p>
<p>Other small Cuban companies also sell electric bikes. Some bikes are basic while others are more costly. The government also recently began permitting imports of much costlier electric vehicles.</p>
<p>Imports of automobiles from the neighboring United States have risen to $24.6 million so far in 2024, the U.S.-Cuba Trade and Economic Council said. There is a growing number of Cubans who want more <strong>luxurious</strong> electric and <strong>hybrid </strong>automobiles, including Teslas.</p>
<p>But the number of Cubans who can pay for such vehicles is still small. For Omar Cortina, the hotel worker, just being able to get back and forth from work is enough of a selling-point.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Alien Fernandez reported this story for Reuters. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>vintage </strong><em>– adj. </em>dating from the past : old</p>
<p><strong>exhaust </strong><em>– n. </em>a system of pipes through which exhaust escapes</p>
<p><strong>internal combustion engines </strong><em>– n. </em>a heat engine in which the combustion that generates the heat takes place inside the engine proper instead of in a furnace</p>
<p><strong>factor </strong><em>– n.</em><strong> </strong>something that contributes to the production of a result</p>
<p><strong>joint venture </strong><em>– n. </em>a commercial enterprise undertaken jointly by two or more parties which otherwise retain their distinct identities</p>
<p><strong>upscale </strong><em>– adj. </em>relating to, being, or appealing to affluent consumers also :<strong> </strong>of a superior quality</p>
<p><strong>luxurious </strong><em>– adj.</em> characterized by opulence, sumptuousness, or rich abundance</p>
<p><strong>hybrid </strong><em>– adj. </em>a vehicle that uses both an internal combustion engine and one or more electric motors to power it.</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Businesses Recover from Major Worldwide Tech Outage (2024/7/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/businesses-recover-from-major-worldwide-tech-outage.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">24 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A major computer system outage affected a wide range of businesses around the world beginning late last week. But the cause of the outage was quickly identified and fixes were deployed to bring most businesses back online.</p>
<p>The problems were linked to a software <strong>update</strong> provided by cybersecurity company CrowdStrike. The outage affected computers using Microsoft's Windows operating system. The incident caused major flight delays and cancellations. It also affected banking, health care, media and other businesses.</p>
<p>Computers affected by the outage showed what is known in the technology industry as the “blue screen of death.” This warning tool is designed to inform Windows users that there is a problem and to block further activity to prevent wider system damage.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A technician works on an information display near United Airlines gates at Chicago O'Hare International Airport in Chicago, Friday, July 19, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-5837-08dcabf3cb29_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A technician works on an information display near United Airlines gates at Chicago O'Hare International Airport in Chicago, Friday, July 19, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster)</span></div>
<p>Officials at Texas-based CrowdStrike were quick to admit a software update containing a programming mistake was sent to <strong>customers</strong> and caused the outage. Once the problem was identified and a fix deployed, CrowdStrike said it centered on assisting customers to get systems back up as soon as possible.</p>
<p>Technology experts noted one issue with the latest outage was that the problematic software update could not be corrected <strong>remotely</strong>. Instead, individual machines had to be fixed, with bad files removed by technology workers.</p>
<p>CrowdStrike's main business is to provide solutions to help companies prevent internet attacks. However, company leaders made clear that the latest outage was only related to the software update and not part of any cybersecurity attack.</p>
<p>CrowdStrike continued to <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.crowdstrike.com/falcon-content-update-remediation-and-guidance-hub/">inform the public</a> about its latest correction efforts and <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Bn5eRUaMZXk">provided guidance</a> for some businesses to attempt to deal with the issue themselves.</p>
<p><strong>Disruptions around the world</strong></p>
<p>The outage <strong>disrupted</strong> operations at airlines, banks, hospitals and organizations around the world.</p>
<p>Among U.S. airlines, Delta officials said Monday it was forced to cancel more than 4,000 flights since the outage began last Friday. But other major carriers, including American Airlines and United, reported they had largely ended any flight disruptions.</p>
<p>Delta chief Ed Bastian apologized to the airline's customers for the continuing delays and cancellations. He said the company was working around the clock to fix all affected systems. Delta said about 60 percent of its main systems run on Microsoft Windows and therefore were left inoperable by the outage.</p>
<p>Some technology experts expressed concern that such outages can be extremely disruptive because the systems built to run most of the world's computers are provided by only a small number of companies.</p>
<p>Gregory Falco is an assistant professor of engineering at Cornell University in New York. He studies internet security issues. Falco told The Associated Press it is a problem that so many computers worldwide depend on the same technologies and providers. “We rely on very few companies, and everybody uses the same folks, so everyone goes down at the same time,” Falco said.</p>
<p>CrowdStrike is one of the largest cybersecurity service providers, especially in transportation, health care, banking and media. This is the reason it affected so many businesses in those industries. An <strong>irony</strong> of the outage was that companies normally look to CrowdStrike's tools to help prevent internet attacks that could bring their systems down and cause costly disruptions.</p>
<p>Falco noted that while fears of such a widespread outage have long existed, he thinks too few providers are becoming “even more <strong>entrenched</strong>” with certain technologies. "We like to think that we have a lot of players available. But at the end of the day, the biggest companies use all the same stuff.”</p>
<p>Richard Stiennon is a cybersecurity expert who has followed industry developments for 24 years. He told the AP he sees the software issue as a historic mistake by CrowdStrike. “This is easily the worst <strong>faux pas</strong>, technical faux pas or <strong>glitch</strong> of any security software provider ever,” Stiennon said.</p>
<p>He added that while the problem had an easy technical fix, it could still have lasting effects for some companies. This is because the outage required hands-on efforts to fix each affected computer and this can severely disrupt business operations.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters and CrowdStrike. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>update</strong><em> - n.</em> to add new information to an existing thing</p>
<p><strong>customer</strong><em> – n.</em> a person who buys goods or services</p>
<p><strong>remote </strong><em>– adv. </em>happening from far away</p>
<p><strong>disruption </strong><em>– n.</em> to interrupt something and stop it from continuing as it should</p>
<p><strong>irony </strong><em>– adj. </em>a situation in which the opposite happens than what was expected</p>
<p><strong>entrenched </strong><em>– adj. </em>ideas or things that have existed for a long time</p>
<p><strong>faux pas </strong><em>– n. </em>words or behavior that represent a social mistake or something not polite</p>
<p><strong>glitch </strong><em>– n. </em>a small problem or issue that prevents something from being successful or working as well as it should</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Climate Agency Again Reports Hottest Day Record on Earth (2024/7/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/climate-agency-again-reports-hottest-day-record-on-earth.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">24 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The European climate change service Copernicus said Monday broke the world's hottest day record that was just set a day earlier.</p>
<p>The European Union's Copernicus Climate Change Service said the daily global average temperature reached 17.15 degrees Celsius on Monday. Earlier <a class="wsw__a" href="https://nam10.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fpulse.climate.copernicus.eu%2F&amp;data=05%7C02%7Cmritter%40VOANews.COM%7C8ae53aa7ab624dfca32408dcabebe8ae%7Cba99e87c673541c2b1c1354eee3a8659%7C0%7C0%7C638574276940114952%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=2tj5diOprdzp%2B20db%2Br6YpouWVN0x2KmOXU%2B5x%2B1oOA%3D&amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" title="Original URL: https://pulse.climate.copernicus.eu/. Click or tap if you trust this link.">satellite data</a> published by Copernicus on Wednesday showed that Monday's temperature broke the previous day's record by 0.06 degrees Celsius.</p>
<p>Countries around the world from Japan to Bolivia to the United States are said to be having hot conditions.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - The setting sun illuminates the clouds over the Rocky Mountains after a third straight day of record-breaking heat Sunday, July 14, 2024, in Denver. (AP Photo/David Zalubowski)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-f00e-08dcabf81b4b_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - The setting sun illuminates the clouds over the Rocky Mountains after a third straight day of record-breaking heat Sunday, July 14, 2024, in Denver. (AP Photo/David Zalubowski)</span></div>
<p>Climate scientists say the world is now as warm as it was 125,000 years ago. They blame human-caused climate change for the warm temperatures.</p>
<p>Scientists cannot be certain that Monday was the hottest day in more than 100,000 years since data does not go back that far. But average temperatures have not been this high since long before humans developed agriculture, the Associated Press reports.</p>
<p>The temperature rise in recent years supports what climate scientists predicted would happen if humans kept burning oil, natural gas, and coal at an increasing rate.</p>
<p>Roxy Mathew Koll is a climate scientist at the Indian Institute of Tropical Meteorology in western India. Koll said, “We are in an age where weather and climate records are <strong>frequently</strong> stretched beyond our <strong>tolerance</strong> levels, resulting in <strong>insurmountable</strong> loss of lives and livelihood.”</p>
<p>Copernicus' early data shows the global average temperature on Monday, July 22, was 17.15 degrees Celsius. Before last summer, the previous recorded hottest day was in 2016 when the average temperature reached 16.8 degrees Celsius.</p>
<p>The European agency said what caused this week's high temperatures was a warmer-than-usual Antarctic winter. The same thing happened last year when a record was set in early July.</p>
<p>Copernicus records go back to 1940. Other global measurements by the United States and British governments go back to 1880. Many scientists also consider tree growth rings and ice samples. They say that information suggests that last year's record high temperatures were the hottest in about 120,000 years.</p>
<p>Now, temperatures reported in the first six months of 2024 have broken the earlier records.</p>
<p>Without human-caused climate change, scientists say that extreme temperature records would not be broken nearly as often.</p>
<p>Former head of U.N. climate negotiations Christiana Figueres said “We all <strong>scorch</strong> and <strong>fry</strong>” if the world does not immediately change course.</p>
<p>“One third of global electricity can be produced by solar and wind alone, but targeted national policies have to enable that transformation,” she said.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Seth Borenstein and Sibi Arasu reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>frequently </strong><em>–adv</em>. taking place often</p>
<p><strong>tolerance </strong><em>–n.</em> the ability to survive or withstand some event or pressure</p>
<p><strong>insurmountable </strong><em>–adj.</em> impossible to recover from</p>
<p><strong>sample</strong> <em>–n.</em> an amount of something that is taken for study usually in a laboratory</p>
<p><strong>scorch</strong> <em>–v. </em>to burn with a flame or high heat</p>
<p><strong>fry</strong><em> –v.</em> to cook using hot oil</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Athletes Have High Hopes for Paris Olympics, Cultural Activities (2024/7/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/athletes-have-high-hopes-for-paris-olympics-cultural-activities.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">24 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Paris is a popular place for visitors because of its food, art, and history. The city itself is likely to be central to the experience of the Olympic Games.</p>
<p>The athletes going to France have been making long lists of things they want to try, see and eat.</p>
<p>“I'm excited to just explore and just take in everything Paris has to offer, because me and my friends, we look at things and we get<strong> inspired</strong>,” said<strong> breaker </strong>Jeffrey Louis, also known as b-boy Jeffro.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Passengers in the back of a taxi film themselves as they leave the Eiffel Tower decorated with the Olympic rings ahead of the 2024 Summer Olympics, Wednesday, July 17, 2024, in Paris. (AP Photo/David Goldman, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/fef1eed7-5f26-466b-b8d0-7ae11831f6dc_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Passengers in the back of a taxi film themselves as they leave the Eiffel Tower decorated with the Olympic rings ahead of the 2024 Summer Olympics, Wednesday, July 17, 2024, in Paris. (AP Photo/David Goldman, File)</span></div>
<p>He added, “There's a lot of things that we want to try and just explore.”</p>
<p>Some athletes want to ride to the top of Gustave Eiffel's creation from the 1880s, the Eiffel Tower, maybe even dine at its restaurant. The Louvre Museum, with Leonardo da Vinci's painting, the Mona Lisa, the famous Venus de Milo statue, and many other objects are high on many lists of things to see.</p>
<p>Notre Dame Cathedral also is popular although repair work after a 2019 fire will not be completed until after the Summer Games.</p>
<p>“Such a big city. A beautiful city,” diver Andrew Capobianco said.</p>
<p>Athletes are also excited to try the food and drinks.</p>
<p>“Eat as many <strong>crepes </strong>as you can if you're in Paris,” track and field Paralympian Noelle Malkamaki said.</p>
<p>“Looking forward to <strong>macaroons</strong>, pastries, bread,” sitting volleyball Paralympian Nicky Nieves said.</p>
<p>Others are excited about coffee, meats, and sweet desserts such as crème br<i></i>251;lée. And some hope to drink the wines — from the Loire Valley, Bordeaux or Champagne.</p>
<p>There are those, such as breaker Sunny Choi or rower Michelle Sechser, who know they will need to wait to enjoy some of the food and drink.</p>
<p>“We do have weight-class restrictions; we have to weigh in two hours before a race,” Sechser said. “So, after racing's done, I'm most excited to get out and explore the Parisian food and really enjoy some French meals.”</p>
<p><strong>Canoe</strong> and <strong>kayak </strong>star Evy Leibfarth, the first American woman to qualify in three whitewater boating events at an Olympics, looks at the situation differently.</p>
<p>She makes sure to fill herself with foods that help with athletic performance. But she also does not want to deny herself too much.</p>
<p>“If I'm going to be thinking about my<strong> croissant</strong> the whole time I'm paddling, I may as well just eat it, you know? So, it's all about balance,” said Leibfarth, a 20-year-old from North Carolina. “It's just making sure that I'm getting the right amount of protein and the right amount of carbs before a race, while also balancing in the things that I want to eat.”</p>
<p>As she looked forward to her fifth trip to Paris, Leibfarth offered some words to Olympians headed for the first time to the City of Light — which is another name for Paris.</p>
<p>“Don't be afraid to just drop the recommendations and everything and just walk around and find things to do because that's the best I've done.”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Howard Fendrich and Eddie Pells reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted this story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>inspired </strong><em>– adj</em>. very clever or good; to be or become outstanding</p>
<p><strong>breaker</strong> <em>– n.</em> someone who breakdances</p>
<p><strong>crepe </strong><em>– n.</em> a small thin pancake</p>
<p><strong>macaroon</strong> <em>– n.</em> a kind of cookie made of egg, sugar, and almonds or coconut</p>
<p><strong>canoe<em> </em></strong><em>–n</em>. a light narrow boat with two sharp ends</p>
<p><strong>kayak </strong><em>– n.</em> a light narrow boat often has a closed top except for an opening in which the paddler sits</p>
<p><strong>croissant</strong> <em>– n.</em> a flaky, rich roll that comes in the shape of a crescent</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Groups Warn of Conflict Between Loggers, Tribe in Peru (2024/7/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/groups-warn-of-conflict-between-loggers-tribe-in-peru.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">23 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>An <strong>advocacy </strong>group for Indigenous peoples has released images of a <strong>reclusive </strong>Peruvian Amazon tribe's members searching for food outside of their usual area.</p>
<p>The group calls the pictures evidence that industrial tree cutting operations are “dangerously close” to the tribe's territory. The industry is also known as logging.</p>
<p>The group, Survival International, said the photographs and video it posted recently show members of the Mashco Piro looking for food near the community of Monte Salvado, on the Las Piedras River in Madre de Dios.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This June 2024 photo provided by Survival International shows members of the Mashco Piro along the Las Piedras River in the Peruvian Amazon near the community of Monte Salvado, in Madre de Dios province, Peru. (Survival International via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/ddcd5f24-caec-4240-ae69-8620452f17eb_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This June 2024 photo provided by Survival International shows members of the Mashco Piro along the Las Piedras River in the Peruvian Amazon near the community of Monte Salvado, in Madre de Dios province, Peru. (Survival International via AP)</span></div>
<p>Several logging companies hold timber agreements inside territory the tribe lives in, Survival International says. The group has long worked to protect what it says is the largest “uncontacted” tribe in the world. The nearness of logging operations raises fears of conflict between loggers and tribal members, as well as the possibility that loggers could bring dangerous diseases to the Mashco Piro, the group said.</p>
<p>Two loggers, one of whom died, were shot with <strong>arrows</strong> while fishing in 2022 in a reported fight with tribal members.</p>
<p>Cesar Ipenza is a lawyer who specializes in environmental law in Peru. He is not connected with Survival International.</p>
<p>Ipenza said the new images are evidence of a “worrying situation because we do not know exactly what is the reason for their departure (from the rainforest) to the beaches.”</p>
<p>Isolated Indigenous tribes may travel in August to collect turtle eggs to eat, he said.</p>
<p>“But we also see with great concern that some illegal activity may be taking place in the areas where they live and lead them to leave and be under pressure,” he said. “We cannot deny the presence of a logging <strong>concession</strong> kilometers away from where they live.”</p>
<p>Survival International called for the Forest Stewardship Council (FSC), a group that confirms <strong>sustainable</strong> forestry, to remove its approval of the operations of one of those companies, Peru-based Canales Tahuamanu. The FSC responded in a statement that it would do “a comprehensive review” of the company's operations to ensure it is protecting the rights of Indigenous peoples.</p>
<p>Canales Tahuamanu, also known as Catahua, has said in the past that it is operating with official permission. The company did not immediately answer a message seeking comment on its operations and the tribe.</p>
<p>A 2023 report by the United Nations' special reporter on the rights of Indigenous peoples said Peru's government had recognized in 2016 that the Mashco Piro and other isolated tribes were using territories that had been opened to logging.</p>
<p>The report expressed concern that the territory of Indigenous peoples had not been marked out “despite reasonable evidence of their presence since 1999.”</p>
<p>Survival International said the photos were taken June 26-27 and show about 53 male Mashco Piro on the beach. The group estimated as many as 100 to 150 tribal members would have been in the area with women and children nearby.</p>
<p>“It is very unusual that you see such a large group together,” Survival International researcher Teresa Mayo said in a talk with the Associated Press.</p>
<p>Ipenza, the lawyer, said Indigenous people usually move in smaller groups, and a larger group might be a “situation of alarm” even in the case of legal logging.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Steven Grattan reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>advocacy</strong> <em>– n.</em> the act or process of supporting a cause</p>
<p><strong>reclusive</strong> <em>– adj.</em> withdrawn or separate from society</p>
<p><strong>arrow</strong> <em>– n.</em> a sharp object with a slender shaft that is shot from a bow</p>
<p><strong>sustainable</strong> <em>– adj.</em> of or relating to a method of using a resource so that the resource is not permanently damaged</p>
<p><strong>concession</strong> <em>– n.</em> a grant of land or property in return for services or for a particular use</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers in Brazil Say Rain Uncovered Fossil of Old Dinosaur (2024/7/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/researchers-in-brazil-say-rain-uncovered-fossil-of-old-dinosaur.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">23 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists in Brazil say heavy rains helped them discover a <strong>fossil </strong>they believe came from one of the world's oldest dinosaurs.</p>
<p>Researchers found the fossil in May in Brazil's southern state of Rio Grande do Sul. They said the fossilized bones make up nearly a complete dinosaur skeleton.</p>
<p>A leader of the team, <strong>paleontologist</strong> Rodrigo Temp Müller, said the fossil is believed to be about 233 million years old. It was discovered next to a body of water in the area of Sao Joao do Polesine.</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-9525-08dc96c58dc8_cx0_cy3_cw0_w100_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>Müller is with Brazil's Federal University of Santa Maria in Rio Grande do Sul. He said heavy rains in the area had helped speed up the natural process of <strong>erosion</strong> that led to the discovery. Fossils are more likely to get <strong>exposed</strong> after rains because water washes away the dirt that covers them.</p>
<p>Details of the discovery have not yet been confirmed by other scientists or published in any scientific publications.</p>
<p>The researchers believe the dinosaur lived during the Triassic Period. The first dinosaurs are thought to have appeared at that time after Earth's largest mass <strong>extinction</strong> event about 252 million years ago. During the Triassic Period, all continents were part of a single land mass called Pangea.</p>
<p>The team thinks the dinosaur belonged to a group known as Herrerasauridae. A document received by The Associated Press explains this family of creatures once lived on land that now makes up present-day Brazil and Argentina. The document said the size of the bones suggests the dinosaur would have been around 2.5 meters long.</p>
<p>After about four days of <strong>excavation</strong> work, researchers transported a large piece of rock containing the fossil back to their laboratory. There, they carried out tests.</p>
<p>At first, Müller said he thought the team had only collected “a few <strong>isolated</strong> bones.” But after detailed testing, the researchers said they had almost a complete skeleton.</p>
<p>Müller told the AP his team was “very excited and surprised” by the discovery. He said the new find might be the second most complete skeleton found for this kind of dinosaur.</p>
<p>The researchers are carrying out studies to see whether the fossil belongs to an already-known <strong>species</strong> or a new kind. The effort is expected to take several months.</p>
<p>Brazil's Rio Grande do Sul state reported record rainfall earlier this year. Officials said the rain caused widespread flooding in May that led to at least 182 deaths. Some weather experts say climate change makes extreme weather events more likely. They say the burning of oil, gas and coal affects the climate.</p>
<p>Müller said other fossils appeared after the heavy rains. He noted these finds had launched a race against time to rescue the materials before they are ruined. For example, team members in the field said they had observed what appeared to be a leg bone and a pelvis bone. But they said these were in danger of being destroyed because of the rain.</p>
<p>Müller hopes the new discovery can help further explain the <strong>origins</strong> of dinosaurs. “Having new fossils that are so well <strong>preserved</strong> certainly helps us better understand this topic that is still much debated,” he said.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>fossil </strong><em>–</em><em> n.</em> something (such as a leaf, skeleton, or footprint) that is from a plant or animal which lived in ancient times and that you can be seen in rocks</p>
<p><strong>paleontologist </strong><em>– n.</em> a person who studies fossils as a way of getting information about the history of life on Earth</p>
<p><strong>erode </strong><em>– v. </em>to slowly decay over time</p>
<p><strong>extinction </strong><em>– n. </em>a situation in which something no longer exists</p>
<p><strong>excavate </strong><em>– v.</em> to remove earth covering very old objects buried in the ground in order to discover things about the past</p>
<p><strong>isolated </strong><em>– adj. </em>not near to other places</p>
<p><strong>species </strong><em>– n. </em>a group of animals or plants that are similar and can produce young animals or plants</p>
<p><strong>expose </strong><em>– v.</em> to remove what is covering something so that it can be seen</p>
<p><strong>origin </strong><em>– n. </em>where something begins or comes from</p>
<p><strong>preserve </strong><em>– v. </em>to keep something from decaying, being damaged or destroyed</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US States Push for Cell Phone Ban in High Schools (2024/7/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/us-states-push-for-cell-phone-ban-in-high-schools.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">23 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>More American states are pushing for cell phone restrictions in high schools. The move comes as teachers say it is a major problem in the classroom.</p>
<p>In July, Virginia became the latest in a growing number of U.S. states to restrict cell phone use in public schools. The state's governor, Glenn Youngkin, issued an executive order to establish guidance and policies for local school systems to follow by January.</p>
<p>Youngkin's order said, “Studies <strong>indicate</strong> that students who use their phones during class learn less and <strong>achieve</strong> lower grades.” It also <strong>cited</strong> an “alarming mental health crisis” among young people driven by the use of cell phones and social media.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A student places her cellphone into a phone holder as she enters class at Delta High School, Friday, Feb. 23, 2024, in Delta, Utah. (AP Photo/Rick Bowmer)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-0926-08dca5cbd3b3_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">FILE - A student places her cellphone into a phone holder as she enters class at Delta High School, Friday, Feb. 23, 2024, in Delta, Utah. (AP Photo/Rick Bowmer)</span></div>
<p>Last year, Florida became the first state to restrict the use of cell phones in school. A law that took effect in July requires all Florida public schools to ban student cell phone use during class time and block social media on the school's <strong>wi-fi</strong>.</p>
<p>The states of Indiana and Ohio passed their own laws this year. Several others, including Oklahoma, Vermont, and Kansas, have also recently introduced what is being called “phone-free schools” legislation. New York Governor Kathy Hochul said she will push for legislation to ban cell phone use in the coming legislative session in 2025.</p>
<p><strong>Cell phone distraction</strong></p>
<p>In a recent public study, the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.pewresearch.org/short-reads/2024/06/12/72-percent-of-us-high-school-teachers-say-cellphone-distraction-is-a-major-problem-in-the-classroom/">Pew Research Center reported</a> that 72 percent of U.S. high school teachers say cell phone <strong>distraction</strong> is a major problem in the classroom.</p>
<p>Teachers report less of a problem with younger students. About 33 percent of middle school teachers and six percent of elementary school teachers see cell phone use as problematic.</p>
<p>The Associated Press (AP) reported that a California teacher complained of students watching Netflix during class. In Maryland, a teacher said students used <strong>gambling</strong> apps to place <strong>bets</strong> during the school day.</p>
<p>Many educators in the U.S. said students used social media, listened to music, and shopped online during the school day.</p>
<p>James Granger is a science teacher at a Los Angeles-area high school. He told the AP, “Students used to have an understanding that you aren't supposed to be on your phone in class. Those days are gone.” Granger added, “The only solution that works is to physically remove the cellphone from the student.”</p>
<p>Some students say such policies take away their independence and cut off their main method of communication with family and friends. Opposition also has come from parents who fear being cut off from their kids if there is a school emergency.</p>
<p>Jaden Willoughey is a student at Delta High School in rural Utah. He shares the concern about being out of contact with his parents if there is an emergency. But he also sees the upside, or good result, of turning in his phone at school.</p>
<p>At Delta High School, students are required to leave their phones at the door when entering every class. “It helps you focus on your work, and it's easier to pay attention in class,” Jaden said.</p>
<p>Kim Whitman is a leader of the Phone-Free Schools Movement, a group that advises schools. She told the AP she urges educators to make exceptions for students with special educational and medical needs.</p>
<p><strong>Back in Virginia</strong></p>
<p>Back in Virginia, school systems have been increasingly banning or severely restricting students' phone use.</p>
<p>For example, Loudoun County Public Schools, in northern Virginia, passed a new policy last month that generally bans elementary school students from using phones during the school day.</p>
<p>Middle school students are permitted to use their phones before or after school, but they are expected to store their phones in their <strong>lockers</strong>. In high school, students are expected to silence their phones and place them in storage during instructional time.</p>
<p>In Richmond, Virginia, the school system started a cell phone ban last year in some of its high schools and middle schools.</p>
<p>Jason Kamras is head of the Richmond school system. He said, “We saw more student <strong>engagement</strong> in class and fewer distractions throughout the day.” Additionally, he said, “Students reported spending more time talking with their <strong>peers</strong>.”</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Hai Do wrote this report for VOA Learning English based on reporting from the Associated Press and Pew Research.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>indicate </strong>–v. to show or suggest something is the case</p>
<p><strong>achieve</strong> <em>–v. </em>to reach a goal or do something that is notable</p>
<p><strong>cite</strong> <em>–v.</em> to quote the direct words of someone else or facts that come from a source</p>
<p><strong>wi-fi </strong><em>–n.</em> <em>(technology)</em> a short distance wireless connection</p>
<p><strong>distraction </strong>–n. the condition of having one's attention taken up by something that is not important at the time; a thing that is causing a loss of attention</p>
<p><strong>gambling </strong><em>–n.</em> the activity of playing games of chance for money</p>
<p><strong>bet </strong>–n. the act of putting money at risk in an effort to win more money</p>
<p><strong>locker </strong><em>–n.</em> a space, especially in schools, where people can put things and secure them with a lock</p>
<p><strong>engagement </strong><em>–n.</em> the condition of taking part in an activity, like a class, and being involved in it</p>
<p><strong>peer </strong><em>–n.</em> a person who is equal with others and like them at work, in school, or in several other situations</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Ukrainian Companies Develop Robotic Vehicles to Fight Russia (2024/7/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/ukrainian-companies-develop-robotic-vehicles-to-fight-russia.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Many new Ukrainian businesses are reportedly developing unmanned military vehicles for the country's war against Russia.</p>
<p>The operations often happen in empty <strong>warehouses</strong> or secret, underground factories, the Associated Press (AP) reports.</p>
<p>The weaponized vehicles reportedly aim to ease shortages of soldiers and equipment.</p><div class="contentImage"><img a="" alt="Andrii Denysenko, CEO of design and production bureau " an="" anton="" at="" by="" corn="" drone="" field="" friday="" ground="" in="" june="" northern="" odyssey="" photo="" prototype="" shtuka="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-bc6e-08dca6af8ada_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg" stands="" ukraine="" ukrprototyp=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Andrii Denysenko, CEO of design and production bureau "UkrPrototyp", stands by Odyssey, an 800-kilogram (1,750-pound) ground drone prototype, at a corn field in northern Ukraine, Friday, June 28, 2024. (AP Photo/Anton Shtuka)</span></div>
<p>Workers at laboratories in hundreds of workshops are using technology tools to build robot fighters to battle Russian forces, the AP said.</p>
<p>The AP reported that an estimated 250 new defense companies are currently involved in the production of war vehicles across Ukraine. The news agency noted that such operations can look similar to rural car repair shops.</p>
<p>Andrii Denysenko heads one of the new companies, or startups. He told the AP his employees can put together an unmanned ground vehicle, called the Odyssey, in just four days. The vehicle has a selling price of $35,000, which is about 10 percent less than an imported model.</p>
<p>Denysenko asked the AP not to publish details about his business to protect the operation and the people working there.</p>
<p>The work area is divided into small rooms for <strong>welding</strong> and body work. Workers produce the main structure, paint the vehicles green and then fit them with basic electronics, power systems and cameras and sensors.</p>
<p>Ukraine's military is considering several different models of new unmanned air, ground and sea vehicles produced by the startups. A fourth branch of Ukraine's military – the Unmanned Systems Forces - joined the army, navy and air force in May.</p>
<p>Engineers get production ideas from stories in defense magazines or online videos to produce less costly models. Weapons or smart elements can be added later.</p>
<p>“We are fighting a huge country, and they don't have any resource limits,” said Denysenko. “We understand that we cannot spend a lot of human lives. War is mathematics.”</p>
<p>Reporters from the AP watched the car-sized Odyssey vehicle spin and kick up dust as it rolled through a field of corn during a demonstration in the north of the country last month.</p>
<p>The 800-kilogram test model, or prototype, looks like a small tank. Developers of the vehicle say it can travel up to 30 kilometers on one battery charge. The prototype acts as a rescue-and-supply vehicle but could be changed to carry a <strong>remotely </strong>operated heavy machine gun or to clear landmines.</p>
<p>A Ukrainian government fundraising website for the Unmanned Systems Forces states that teams of robots “will become <strong>logistics</strong> devices, tow trucks, minelayers and deminers, as well as self-destructive robots.” “The first robots are already proving their effectiveness on the battlefield," the statement adds.</p>
<p>Mykhailo Fedorov is Ukraine's deputy prime minister for digital <strong>transformation</strong>. He is urging citizens to take free online courses and build military <strong>drones</strong> at home. Fedorov has called on Ukrainians to make a million drone flying machines per year.</p>
<p>“There will be more of them soon,” the Unmanned Systems Forces website said. "Many more.”</p>
<p>Denysenko's company is working on other projects as well. One is a motorized <strong>exoskeleton</strong> designed to increase a soldier's strength. Another carrier vehicle would be able to transport a soldier's equipment and even help him move uphill. “We will do everything to make unmanned technologies develop even faster. (Russia's) murderers use their soldiers as cannon <strong>fodder</strong>, while we lose our best people,” Fedorov wrote in a message published online.</p>
<p>Human Rights Watch and other international rights groups are calling for a ban on weapons that do not involve human decision making. This concern has been shared by others, including the U.N. General Assembly, American businessman Elon Musk and the founders of the Google-owned, London-based startup DeepMind.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>warehouse <em>–</em></strong><em>n.</em> a large building that provides centralized storage for a lot of goods and products that are then shipped to customers</p>
<p><strong>weld </strong><em> v.</em> to join pieces of metal together by heating them until they almost melt and then pressing them together</p>
<p><strong>remote </strong><em>– adj.</em> happening from far away</p>
<p><strong>logistics </strong><em>– n. </em>the practical arrangements for something</p>
<p><strong>transformation </strong><em>– n.</em> to completely change from one system to another, usually in an effort to improve it</p>
<p><strong>drone </strong><em>– n.</em> an unmanned, flying vehicle</p>
<p><strong>exoskeleton </strong><em>– n. </em>an artificial external supporting structure</p>
<p><strong>fodder </strong><em>– n.</em> people or things that are useful for the stated purpose</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Grow Your Own Tea Plants Year-round (2024/7/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/grow-your-own-tea-plants-year-round.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>People who grow their own food are familiar with planting tomatoes, peppers, squash, herbs, berries and other common fruits and vegetables.</p>
<p>However, they may not think of growing plants for drinks.</p>
<p><strong>Gardening </strong>expert Jessica Damiano recently wrote about plants you can grow to make tea. Damiano, who writes for the Associated Press, says that growing your own tea plants in the garden can provide enough leaves and flower <strong>buds</strong> to keep your tea pot filled year-round.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image provided by the Missouri Botanical Garden shows a hedge of Camellia sinensis plants. The plant's leaves are used to make white, green, black and oolong teas. (Missouri Botanical Garden via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-965b-08dc9c4106d0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image provided by the Missouri Botanical Garden shows a hedge of Camellia sinensis plants. The plant's leaves are used to make white, green, black and oolong teas. (Missouri Botanical Garden via AP)</span></div>
<p>And the plant to grow, she says, is camellia sinensis (var. sinensis), also known as the “tea plant.”</p>
<p>These <strong>evergreen</strong> plants are easy to grow in any amount of sunlight, from deep <strong>shade</strong> to full sun. However, ideal growing conditions are part sun to light shade. They require well-draining soil with a slightly <strong>acidic</strong> pH.</p>
<p>Young plants will take about two years to produce enough leaves for tea. In five years, one plant should provide enough for an average tea drinker. If you need more tea, Damiano says to plant more camellia sinensis.</p>
<p>Camellia sinensis is called the “tea plant” because white, green, black, and oolong teas all come from this plant. Their differences come from harvesting practices and after-harvest treatments.</p>
<p>For white tea, pick the flower buds before they fully open. Heat the buds in a pan over low heat, moving them often for about 10 minutes. Cool them and store in an airtight container.</p>
<p>For green, black and oolong tea, pick two or three of the youngest leaves from each stem, along with the leaf bud from each stem tip. Do this every 10 to 12 days as new growth develops.</p>
<p>Preparing green, oolong, or black tea all have different processes.</p>
<p><strong>Green tea</strong></p>
<p>For making green tea, briefly <strong>steam</strong> leaves over boiling water. Then put the leaves on a clean towel and let them sit for five minutes. Roll up the leaves in the towel gently to remove extra water. Remove the leaves from the towel, separate them, and place them on a baking sheet. Heat in an oven or toaster oven set to 148 degrees Celsius (300 degrees Fahrenheit) for 10 to 15 minutes or until the leaves are completely dry. <strong>Brew</strong> immediately or cool and keep them in an airtight container for future use.</p>
<p><strong>Oolong tea</strong></p>
<p>For making oolong tea, put the leaves in one layer on a baking tray. Put the tray in a sunny outdoor spot to let the leaves <strong>wilt.</strong> After 30 to 60 minutes, move the tray into the shade and move the leaves every hour for 8 to 10 hours. Next, place the leaves in a wide pan and cook them over low heat for 15 minutes, moving gently as needed to prevent burning. Let the leaves cool. And roll each leaf individually to keep its oils and flavors. They should be completely dry before storing in an airtight container.</p>
<p><strong>Black tea</strong></p>
<p>To make black tea, place leaves on a baking sheet in the sun for 10 to 12 hours to remove only 50 to 75 percent of the water. Then, cut the leaves into long pieces and roll into small balls. Place the balls in a warm room between 25 and 26 degrees Celsius (78 to 80 degrees F) that is not too dry of a room until they turn reddish-black. Then, dry them in an <strong>oven</strong> at 93 degrees Celsius (200 degrees F) for 5 minutes. Lower heat to 60 degrees C (140 degrees F) and continue drying for an additional hour. Cool and store in an airtight container.</p>
<p>Native<strong> </strong>to China, camellia sinensis var. sinensis is cold-hardy. That means it can survive in cold weather. However, it may need some protection to survive cold winters.</p>
<p>The same is true for another variety of this flower, camelia sinensis var. assamica. Native to India, this kind is more like a tree.</p>
<p>You will have to research which kinds of camellia sinensis can grow in your area.</p>
<p>On its website, the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://internationalcamellia.org/en-us/caring-for-camellias/winter-protection-of-camellias">International Camellia Society</a> gives you suggestions for how to protect these plants during a cold weather.</p>
<ul>
<li>Mulching: Apply a thick layer of mulch around the base to protect the roots.</li>
<li>Covering: Use a cloth to cover the plant during extreme cold.</li>
<li>Watering: Water the plant well before the first freeze.</li>
<li>Location: Plant your camellia in a sheltered spot, such as near a building, to protect it from cold winds.</li>
<li><strong>Pruning</strong>: Avoid pruning late in the season. New growth may not survive colder weather.</li>
</ul>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo. And I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Jessica Damiano reported this story for the Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>garden </strong><em>– v.</em><strong> </strong>to grow<strong> </strong>herbs, fruits, flowers, or vegetables</p>
<p><strong>bud </strong><em>– n. </em>a small growth at the tip or on the side of a plant stem that later develops into a flower, leaf, or new shoot</p>
<p><strong>evergreen </strong><em>– adj. </em>having foliage that remains green and functional through more than one growing season</p>
<p><strong>shade </strong><em>– n. </em>space sheltered from the heat and bright light of the sun</p>
<p><strong>acidic </strong><em>– adj. </em>Acidic soil tends to have mineral deficiencies that can affect plant growth. By definition, acidity is the characteristic of soil that has a pH level of less than 6.5 (a reading of 5.5 means the soil is very acidic).</p>
<p><strong>steam </strong><em>– v. </em>the invisible vapor into which water is changed when heated to the boiling point</p>
<p><strong>brew </strong><em>– v. </em>to prepare (as tea) by soaking in hot water</p>
<p><strong>wilt </strong><em>– v. </em>to lose or cause to lose freshness and become limp</p>
<p><strong>oven</strong> <em>– n. </em>a chamber used for baking, heating, or drying<em> </em></p>
<p><strong>prune </strong><em>– v.</em> to cut off or cut back parts of for better shape or more fruitful growth</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Democrats Back Harris as Biden Leaves Presidential Race (2024/7/23) | 拜登退选 民主党改推哈里斯</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/democrats-back-harris-as-biden-leaves-presidential-race.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>Democratic Party lawmakers, some governors, and financial donors are supporting U.S. Vice President Kamala Harris to be the party's presidential nominee.<br/>民主党议员、部分州长和财政捐助者开始支持美国副总统卡玛拉·哈里斯成为该党的总统候选人。</p><p>The move came shortly after President Joe Biden said on Sunday that he would not seek the presidency again. Biden made the surprise announcement on the social media website X. He also endorsed, or threw his support to, Harris.<br/>此举是在乔·拜登总统周日表示他不会寻求连任不久后做出的。拜登在社交媒体网站X上宣布了这一出人意料的消息。他还支持哈里斯。</p><p>Harris, who is 59 years old, quickly announced that she would seek the nomination. She said, “I will do everything in my power to unite the Democratic Party – and unite our nation – to defeat Donald Trump.”<br/>现年59岁的哈里斯很快宣布她将寻求提名。她说：“我将尽我所能团结民主党，团结我们的国家，打败唐纳德·川普。”</p><p>Last week, former President Donald Trump accepted the nomination of the Republican Party in the Midwestern city of Milwaukee, Wisconsin. He chose Ohio Senator J.D. Vance as his vice-presidential nominee.<br/>上周，前总统唐纳德·川普在威斯康星州中西部城市密尔沃基接受了共和党的提名。他选择俄亥俄州参议员J.D.万斯作为他的副总统候选人。</p><p>Biden's decision<br/>拜登的决定</p><p>Biden's decision to leave the 2024 race followed rising calls from Democrats urging him to “pass the torch” to a new generation.<br/>拜登决定退出2024年的竞选，此前民主党人呼吁他将“火炬”传递给新一代。</p><p>In his June 27 debate against Trump, the 81-year-old president often appeared to be unable to complete his thoughts. He also failed to press his case against the 78-year-old Trump or defend his work in The White House. Despite concerns from Democrats about his debate performance and decreasing electoral support, Biden said he would stay in the race.<br/>在6月27日与川普的辩论中，这位81岁的总统似乎经常无法自圆其说。他也没有对78岁的川普提起诉讼，也没有为自己在白宫的工作辩护。尽管民主党人对他的辩论表现和选举支持率下降表示担忧，但拜登表示他将继续参加竞选。</p><p>But on Sunday, he said in a statement, “I believe it is in the best interest of my party and the country for me to stand down and to focus solely on fulfilling my duties as president for the remainder of my term.” Biden's term ends in six months in January. Biden added that he plans to address the nation about his decision later this week.<br/>但周日，他在一份声明中表示，“我认为我退选，并在剩余任期内专注于履行总统职责，符合我的政党和国家的最佳利益。”拜登的任期将于明年1月结束，为期六个月。拜登补充说，他计划本周晚些时候就自己的决定向全国发表讲话。</p><p>In a statement, Harris spoke about Biden's withdrawal. She said, Biden “is doing what he has done throughout this life of service: putting the American people and our country above everything else.”<br/>哈里斯在一份声明中谈到了拜登的退出。她说，拜登“正在做他在整个从政生涯中所做的事情：把美国人民和我们的国家置于一切之上。”</p><p>The decision came just weeks before the start of the Democratic National Convention in Chicago on August 19. That is the event where the Democratic Party officially decides on its nominee. Before Biden's withdrawal, the party was considering a virtual vote for delegates before the convention.<br/>这一决定是在8月19日芝加哥民主党全国代表大会开始前几周做出的。这是民主党正式决定其候选人的大会。在拜登退出之前，该党正考虑在大会前对代表进行虚拟投票。</p><p>Harris' many firsts<br/>哈里斯的许多第一</p><p>Before becoming vice president, Harris served as Attorney General, a top law enforcement position, in the state of California. In 2017, she was elected to the U.S. Senate. Biden chose her in 2020 as a running mate after her own presidential campaign failed to gain enough support.<br/>在成为副总统之前，哈里斯曾担任加利福尼亚州检察总长。2017年，她当选为美国参议院议员。2020年她在总统竞选中未能获得足够，之后拜登选择她作为竞选伙伴。</p><p>If Harris is nominated by the Democratic Party to replace Biden, she would be the first Black woman and South Asian major party presidential nominee in the 248-year history of the United States.<br/>如果哈里斯被民主党提名接替拜登，她将成为美国248年历史上第一位黑人女性和南亚裔的主要政党总统候选人。</p><p>Harris's public approval rating has largely followed the president's approval numbers. Some opinion studies say Harris has a little more support than Biden when compared to Trump.<br/>哈里斯的公众支持率在很大程度上沿袭了拜登总统的支持率。一些民意研究表明，在与川普的较量中，哈里斯的支持率略高于拜登。</p><p>As vice president, one of her early assignments was to deal with the causes of migration in the country's southern border with Mexico. Harris also oversaw the administration's efforts on voting rights and election reforms. With a divided Congress, however, Harris was not able to achieve results.<br/>作为副总统，她早期的任务之一是处理该国与墨西哥南部边境的移民问题。哈里斯还监督了政府在投票权和选举改革方面的努力。然而，由于国会意见分歧，哈里斯未能取得成果。</p><p>Since the U.S. Supreme Court overturned federal protections for abortion rights in June 2022, Harris has been the leading voice to push for greater access.<br/>自2022年6月美国最高法院推翻联邦对堕胎权的保护以来，哈里斯一直是推动获得更大堕胎权的主要声音。</p><p>To mark the second anniversary of the court decision, Harris told supporters in Maryland, "This is a fight for freedom: the fundamental freedom of a woman to make decisions about her own body and not having her government tell her what to do."<br/>为了纪念法院判决两周年，哈里斯在马里兰州告诉支持者，“这是一场争取自由的斗争：女性对自己的身体做出决定的基本自由，而不是让政府告诉她该怎么做。”</p><p>I'm Jill Robbins.<br/>我是吉尔·罗宾斯。(21VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Evidence of ‘Rotten Egg’ Gas Found on Jupiter-like Exoplanet (2024/7/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/evidence-of-rotten-egg-gas-found-on-jupiter-like-exoplanet.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists say they have found evidence that the smelly molecule hydrogen sulfide exists in the atmosphere of a Jupiter-like planet. Hydrogen sulfide is the chemical compound that gives <strong>rotten</strong> eggs their bad smell.</p>
<p>The planet is called HD 189733b. It is an exoplanet, a term used to describe planets that exist outside of our own solar system. It was discovered in 2005.</p>
<p>Scientists had already identified similarities between HD 189733b and Jupiter, the oldest and largest planet in our solar system. But the exoplanet was previously not thought to hold hydrogen sulfide.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="An artist's concept of the planet HD 189733 b, located 64 light-years from Earth, orbiting close to its host star. (Roberto Molar Candanosa/Johns Hopkins University/Handout via REUTERS)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-da7f-08dca1bdb585_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">An artist's concept of the planet HD 189733 b, located 64 light-years from Earth, orbiting close to its host star. (Roberto Molar Candanosa/Johns Hopkins University/Handout via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>Astronomers who study this gas giant have said it is deep blue in color and that severe conditions exist in the atmosphere.</p>
<p>It has winds that can blow up to two kilometers per second. The exoplanet is believed to reach temperatures up to 930 degrees Celsius on the side facing the star that it orbits. Scientists also say it rains glass, which can be blown by fierce winds.</p>
<p>The weather on HD 189733b is so extreme, the American space agency NASA once <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/image-article/rains-of-terror-exoplanet-hd-189733b/">described</a> the planet as a “<strong>nightmare</strong> world.”</p>
<p>New observations by NASA's James Webb Space Telescope suggest that this is the first exoplanet where hydrogen sulfide has been identified. Scientists say the discovery has helped give them a better understanding of this stormy world.</p>
<p>The finding was recently explained in a study <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07760-y">appearing</a> in the publication <em>Nature</em>.</p>
<p>One of the leaders of the research was astrophysicist Guangwei Fu of Johns Hopkins University in Maryland. He told Reuters, “This is not a planet we humans want to visit, but a valuable target for furthering our understanding of planetary science."</p>
<p>Fu said HD 189733b is known as a “hot Jupiter” planet. However, it orbits 170 times closer to its star than Jupiter does to the sun. It completes one orbit every two days. Jupiter takes about 12 years to orbit the sun.</p>
<p>Fu noted that hot Jupiters are not found often. "About less than one in 100 star systems have them," he said.</p>
<p>Fu said he thinks the newly discovered “<strong>stinky</strong> smell” just adds another interesting element to what is already known about the planet. It is 64 light-years from Earth, in the <strong>constellation </strong>Vulpecula. A light-year is the distance light travels in a year, about 9.5 trillion kilometers.</p>
<p>It is closer to Earth than many exoplanets. This makes it “bright and easy for detailed studies,” Fu said. He noted, for example, that hydrogen sulfide would have been much harder to find on planets that are further away.</p>
<p>The Webb telescope – which became operational in 2022 – is able to observe a wider <strong>range</strong> of radiation wavelengths than earlier telescopes. This permits more detailed examinations of exoplanet atmospheres.</p>
<p>"Our research finds that HD 189733b is more similar to Jupiter than previously known," said Arizona State University astrophysicist Luis Welbanks. He was a member of the research team. "This planet is very much like Jupiter, but just hotter."</p>
<p>Jupiter, too, has small amounts of hydrogen sulfide in its atmosphere. But the exoplanet is about 10 percent larger than Jupiter in diameter and mass.</p>
<p>The Webb observations also confirmed earlier evidence showing the exoplanet has water and carbon dioxide in its atmosphere.</p>
<p>"With these three molecules, we are able to count the amount of oxygen, carbon and sulfur the planet has,” Welbanks said. That information, he added, gives scientists a chance to learn more about how the planet may have formed. It should also provide data on whether it is different from planets in our solar system.</p>
<p>Welbanks said the scientists are clearly not searching for life on such a hot, <strong>harsh</strong> planet. However, he noted that understanding its atmosphere permits them to “understand how physics and chemistry behave under different environments and to begin to put together the '<strong>recipe</strong>' for forming planets."</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Reuters reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>rotten</strong> <em>- adj.</em> suffering from decay</p>
<p><strong>nightmare </strong><em>– v.</em> a frightening or unpleasant experience</p>
<p><strong>stinky </strong><em>– adj. </em>having or producing an unpleasant smell</p>
<p><strong>constellation </strong><em>– adj. </em>a group of stars that forms a particular shape in the sky and has been given a name</p>
<p><strong>range </strong><em>–n.</em> a series of numbers or values that include the highest and lowest</p>
<p><strong>harsh </strong><em>– adj. </em>unpleasant, unkind or more severe than is necessary</p>
<p><strong>recipe </strong><em>– n. </em>a set of instructions explaining how to prepare and cook food</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Japanese Scientists Make Robot Face ‘Smile’ with Lab-Grown Skin (2024/7/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/japanese-scientists-make-robot-face-smile-with-lab-grown-skin.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">21 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Japanese scientists have found a way to attach living skin tissue to robotic faces and make them "smile." This breakthrough could be helpful not only in robotics, but also in <strong>cosmetics</strong> and medicine.</p>
<p>Researchers at the University of Tokyo started the process by growing human skin cells in the shape of a face. Then, they used attachments that are similar to the <strong>ligaments</strong> in a human to pull the tissue into a wide smile.</p>
<p><strong>First step to other breakthroughs</strong></p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="Robot scientists in Japan have created a robot face using tissue they grew in a lab. They see it as an important step toward developing more life-like robots." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-f9ad-08dca7414e13_w268_r1.jpg.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">Robot scientists in Japan have created a robot face using tissue they grew in a lab. They see it as an important step toward developing more life-like robots.</span></div>
<p>Lead researcher Shoji Takeuchi is a professor at the University of Tokyo. He said the result is an important step towards building more life-like robots. Using the attachments, he said, “it became possible to <strong>manipulate</strong> living skin for the first time.”</p>
<p>The study about the smiling robot appeared last month in <em>Cell Reports Physical Science</em>. It represents 10 years of research by Takeuchi and his lab on how to best combine biological and artificial machines.</p>
<p>Living tissue is better for this application than metals and plastics, Takeuchi said. He noted that brains and muscles are more <strong>efficient</strong> in use of energy and the skin can repair itself.</p>
<p>In the future, the researchers aim to add more elements to the lab-grown skin, including a <strong>circulatory</strong> system and nerves. That could lead to safer testing methods for cosmetics and drugs <strong>absorbed</strong>, or taken in, through the skin.</p>
<p>It could also produce more realistic and functional coverings for robots. The remaining issue is how people react to machines that appear almost lifelike, but do not look exactly like humans.</p>
<p>"There's still a bit of that <strong>creepiness</strong> to it," Takeuchi said about the robot.</p>
<p><strong>The uncanny valley</strong></p>
<p>He added, "I think that making robots out of the same materials as humans and having them show the same expressions might be one key to overcoming the <strong>uncanny</strong> valley."</p>
<p>The “uncanny valley” is an idea that relates to how humans react to robots or other machines that act like humans. “Uncanny” is an adjective that means “being beyond what is normal or expected.”</p>
<p>Japanese robotics scientist Masahiro Mori published a work, <em>Bukimi No Tani</em>, or “Uncanny Valley” in 1970. It proposed how people would react to lifelike robots, or androids.</p>
<p>Mori thought that at first, people would have <strong>positive</strong> feelings about robots that look a little bit like humans. But as robots got closer to being realistic human models, he believed those feelings would become more <strong>negative</strong>.</p>
<p>Those negative feelings are the so-called low point, or “valley,” in a chart that represents the relationship between the human-like appearance of robots and humans' feelings toward and acceptance of such robots.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Rocky Swift reported this story for Reuters. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English with additional information from the Brittancia Dictionary.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>cosmetic</strong> – <em>n</em>. a substance (such as a cream, lotion, or powder) that you put on your face or body to improve your appearance</p>
<p><strong>ligament</strong> – <em>n. </em>a tough piece of tissue in your body that holds bones together or keeps an organ in place</p>
<p><strong>eerie </strong>– adj. strange and mysterious</p>
<p><strong>manipulate</strong> – <em>v</em>. to move or control (something) with your hands or by using a machine</p>
<p><strong>circulatory</strong> – <em>adj</em>. of or relating to the circulation of blood through the body</p>
<p><strong>creepy</strong> – <em>adj.</em> producing a nervous shivery apprehension; annoyingly unpleasant</p>
<p><strong>affinity</strong> – n. an attraction to or liking for something</p>
<p><strong>uncanny valley</strong><em> – n.</em> the unsettling feeling that comes when robots start to resemble humans a little too closely.</p>
<p><strong>positive </strong>– <em>adj</em>. thinking about the good qualities of someone or something</p>
<p><strong>negative</strong>– <em>adj</em>. thinking about the bad qualities of someone or something</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Turkey’s Export of TV Shows Also Fuels Tourism (2024/7/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/turkey-s-export-of-tv-shows-also-fuels-tourism.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">21 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Turkey has become a leading exporter of television shows in recent years.</p>
<p>Millions of people are watching Turkish TV <strong>dramas</strong> known as Dizi. Many of the shows involve the nation's famous historical and cultural places.</p>
<p>Experts say the success of the television dramas has created a billion-dollar industry that continues to expand. Between 2020 and 2023, demand for Turkish TV series increased by 184 percent. That number comes from Los Angeles-based research company Parrot Analytics.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A production team is filming scenes of a Turkish drama with actor Paris Baktas and actress Yagmur Yuksel, Turkey, Tuesday, April 30, 2024. (AP Photo/Khalil Hamra)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-ab4e-08dca66d8ee2_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A production team is filming scenes of a Turkish drama with actor Paris Baktas and actress Yagmur Yuksel, Turkey, Tuesday, April 30, 2024. (AP Photo/Khalil Hamra)
</span></div>
<p>Izzet Pinto is chief of the Turkish media company Global Agency. “We reach over 400 million <strong>viewers</strong> every night around the world,” he said. Global Agency exports Turkish dramas to world markets. Pinto noted, “The soft power we create with Turkish dramas cannot be even compared to what could be done in politics.”</p>
<p>The Turkish drama <em>Deli Yurek</em> was the first to be exported. Turkey sent it to Kazakhstan in 2001. But it was the love story series called <em>Gumus </em>that brought fame to Turkish dizis. The story is about a traditional woman who must <strong>adapt</strong> to life in the city. Gumus grew hugely popular in the Middle East.</p>
<p>In 2006, viewers in Europe's southeastern Balkans area enjoyed <em>A Thousand and One Nights</em>, a series based on Middle Eastern folktales. The stories were set in modern-day Istanbul. Turkish TV also produced the show <em>Magnificent Century</em>, a popular historical drama based on the life of Ottoman Sultan Suleyman the Magnificent.</p>
<p>Turkey was once an importer of Latin American TV dramas known as telenovelas. Now, it is exporting TV shows to Latin American countries. In 2018, Venezuelan President Nicolás Maduro visited the set of the Turkish drama <em>Resurrection: Ertugrul</em>.</p>
<p>Haley Uganadi founded a website for fans of Turkish TV series called Dizilah. About 1.5 million people from the United States, Canada, Greece, India and Pakistan visit her website monthly.</p>
<p>Uganadi said the popularity of the dramas comes from their subjects. She said they are about family, friendship and love and usually involve rich people in Istanbul or historical stories.</p>
<p>Uganadi said the shows offer “something for everyone,” and added, “I see <strong>reflections</strong> of my mom, myself and my siblings” in them.</p>
<p>Pinto of Global Agency agrees that Turkish dramas are right for everybody. “There is no <strong>nudity</strong>, no cursing or bad words, not much hate,” he said, “So, it becomes watchable for the family.”</p>
<p>As Turkey's industry grows, it is expanding the themes of its series. For example, the series <em>Red Roses</em> explores issues affecting a family that is culturally Western and a <strong>fictional</strong> Islamic brotherhood.</p>
<p>During a recent period between filming, actor Ozcan Deniz told the Associated Press that <strong>diversification</strong> is important for industry growth.</p>
<p>He said, “Countries that were not able to transform (into) a different <strong>genre</strong> are now lagging behind in the export of series.” He added, “Turkey has now caught this momentum, but if it cannot diversify, if it cannot also tell different things, it will end somewhere.”</p>
<p><em>Resurrection: Ertugrul</em> is an example of the growing success of Turkish series. Mehmet Bozdag is a producer and writer. He said the first show of the series had over 157 million views on the Urdu language YouTube channel of Turkish state broadcaster TRT. Another series, <em>Foundation: Osman</em>, was broadcast in over 110 countries.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Robert Badendieck reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>drama </strong>–n. a story about a serious or realistic subject</p>
<p><strong>soft power</strong> <em>–n. </em>influence among nations that is not based on military strength but on cultural and non-tangible qualities</p>
<p><strong>viewer</strong> <em>–n.</em> a person who watches television</p>
<p><strong>reflection </strong><em>–n.</em> a similarity</p>
<p><strong>fictional </strong><em>–adj.</em> something from stories that is not real</p>
<p><strong>nudity </strong><em>–n.</em> the state of having no clothes on</p>
<p><strong>diversification </strong><em>–n.</em> the idea of being involved in several different areas to protect against losing too much if one area fails to produce</p>
<p><strong>flourish </strong><em>–v.</em> to grow and expand in health and wealth</p>
<p><strong>genre </strong><em>–n. (art)</em> a specific kind of art form with certain qualities</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Be Careful What You 'Bank On' (2024/7/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/be-careful-what-you-bank-on.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">20 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories</em> from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>On today's show, we take you to the bank.</p>
<p>Banks help us manage our money. When we make <strong>deposits</strong>, we put money in; when we make <strong>withdrawals</strong>, we take money out. Banks help us reach important life goals. We can borrow money from a bank to buy a house. A bank can loan us money to start a business.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Customers use ATMs at a Bank of America branch office in Boston, Oct. 16, 2009. (AP Photo/Lisa Poole, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-6a82-08dca75452eb_cx3_cy0_cw91_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Customers use ATMs at a Bank of America branch office in Boston, Oct. 16, 2009. (AP Photo/Lisa Poole, File)</span></div>
<p>So, we need to trust our banks. And that need for trust gives us some idiomatic expressions in American English that are connected to banks.</p>
<p>The first is simply <u>to bank on something.</u> If you bank on something, you trust it will happen. In fact, you count on it happening. Sometimes we use this expression to mean our strategy <strong>depends</strong> on something to happen.</p>
<p>Here are some examples:</p>
<p><em>When a city hosts the Olympics, they <u>bank on</u> drawing large crowds to see the games. </em></p>
<p><em>To win the election, the politician is <u>banking on</u> voters finding out about his opponent's <strong>scandals</strong>.</em></p>
<p>We often use this expression in a set phrase: to <u>bank on</u> the fact that something will happen.</p>
<p>For example, you can <u>bank on the fact that</u> a famous person caught doing something wrong will soon give a public apology. It is certain to happen.</p>
<p>You can <u>bank on the fact that </u>if I see chocolate cake, I will eat it. It is a given. It will happen.</p>
<p>If you are very sure something will happen, it's <u>like money in the bank.</u></p>
<p>When we have <u>money in the bank</u>, we count on it to be there when we need it. Banks offer guarantees that they will protect our money. So, if something is <u>like money in the bank</u>, it is a guarantee. It is a certainty.</p>
<p>When we say “<u>you can take that to the bank</u>,” we mean something is a sure thing. It is true or certain to happen.</p>
<p>We finish today's show with one more expression, which sounds like a funny situation.</p>
<p>If you <u>laugh all the way to the bank,</u> you make a lot of money with very little effort.</p>
<p>This expression also can mean that you are happy about making money from something that others think is unfair or even bad.</p>
<p>In other situations, it means that you make money from something that others think is a waste of time.</p>
<p>For example, when a woman started a <strong>organic</strong> homemade dog food business, her friends thought it was a <strong>silly</strong> idea. They even laughed at her idea. But it ended up being very successful and made her very rich. So, now she is the one laughing – <u>laughing all the way to the bank!</u></p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>.</p>
<p>If you want to learn English, the stories and programs at VOA Learning English can help you out. You can take that to the bank!</p>
<p>Until next time ... I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>deposit </strong><em>– n. </em>money deposited in a bank</p>
<p><strong>withdrawal </strong><em>– n. </em>an act or instance of withdrawing</p>
<p>especially : a removal of money from a bank account</p>
<p><strong>depend </strong><em>– v. </em>to place reliance or trust : to rely for support</p>
<p><strong>scandal </strong><em>– n. </em>a situation or event that is thought to be shocking and immoral and that everyone knows about : reports about actions or events that cause shock and disapproval:</p>
<p><strong>organic </strong><em>– adj. </em>relating to, producing, dealing in, or involving foods produced with the use of feed or fertilizer obtained from plants or animals and without the use of laboratory-made fertilizers, growth substances, antibiotics, or pesticides</p>
<p><strong>silly</strong> <em>– adj. </em>not showing common sense or good judgment</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>UN: World Population Expected to Reach 10.3 Billion in 2080s (2024/7/21) | 联合国预计全球人口本世纪80年代达峰</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/un-world-population-expected-to-reach-10-3-billion-in-2080s.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<p>The United Nations is predicting the world's population will reach 10.3 billion in the 2080s.<br/>
联合国预测，到本世纪80年代，世界人口将达到103亿。</p>
<p>The prediction appears in a new U.N. report. The report also suggests that the population will then slightly decrease to about 10.2 billion by the end of the century.<br/>
这一预测出现在一份新的联合国报告中。报告还表明，到本世纪末，人口将略微减少到约102亿。</p>
<p>John Wilmoth is head of the U.N. Population Division, which prepared the report. He told The Associated Press (AP) that there is a high probability that the world's population will reach its height, or peak, within the current century. He said the probability of that happening is about 80 percent. Wilmoth described that estimate as “a major change” compared to predictions from 10 years ago. At that time, the estimated probability was about 30 percent.<br/>
约翰·威尔莫斯是联合国人口司司长，该部门负责编写这份报告。他告诉美联社，世界人口很可能在本世纪内达到最高点。他说，这种情况发生的可能性约为80%。威尔莫斯将这一估计描述为与10年前预测相比的“重大变化”。当时估计发生这种情况的概率约为30%。</p>
<p>U.N. Assistant Secretary-General for Economic Development Navid Hanif recently spoke about the report at a briefing. He said the expectation that the world's population in 2100 will be lower than previously thought has “important policy implications for the sustainability of our planet.”<br/>
联合国负责经济发展的助理秘书长纳维德·哈尼夫最近在一次简报会上谈到了这份报告。他说，预计2100年世界人口将低于此前的预期，这“对我们地球的可持续性具有重要的政策影响”。</p>
<p>The world's population has continued to grow during the past 75 years, from an estimated 2.6 billion in 1950 to 8 billion in November 2022. Since then, it has increased about 2.5 percent to 8.2 billion.<br/>
在过去的75年里，世界人口持续增长，从1950年的估值26亿增长到2022年11月的80亿。自那以后，这一数字增长了约2.5%，达到82亿。</p>
<p>The report notes the population has already peaked in 63 countries and territories. These include China, Germany, Japan and Russia. Within this grouping, the total population is estimated to drop 14 percent over the next 30 years.<br/>
报告指出，有63个国家和地区的人口已经达到峰值。这些国家包括中国、德国、日本和俄罗斯。预计未来30年这一组国家的总人口将下降14%。</p>
<p>In another 48 countries and territories, the population is predicted to peak between 2025 and 2054. Those countries include Brazil, Iran, Turkey and Vietnam.<br/>
预计另外48个国家和地区的人口将在2025年至2054年间达到峰值。这些国家包括巴西、伊朗、土耳其和越南。</p>
<p>For the remaining 126 countries and territories, the population is expected to increase through 2054. The countries in this grouping include the United States, India, Indonesia, Nigeria and Pakistan. The report said these areas would see their populations peak in the second half of the century or later.<br/>
其余126个国家和地区的人口预计将一直增长到2054年。这一组国家包括美国、印度、印度尼西亚、尼日利亚和巴基斯坦。报告称，这些地区的人口将在本世纪下半叶或之后达到峰值。</p>
<p>For nine of these nations, the U.N. estimates the populations will double between 2024 and 2054.<br/>
联合国估计，其中9个国家的人口将在2024年至2054年间翻一番。</p>
<p>Wilmoth said these differences are notable. But he said, “it's important to understand that all populations are following a similar path.”<br/>
威尔莫斯说，这些差异是显著的。但他说，“重要的是要明白，所有国家的人口都走在类似的道路上。”</p>
<p>The U.N. report suggests the earlier population peak is predicted for several reasons.<br/>
联合国的报告表明，预测人口峰值提前有多个原因。</p>
<p>The report noted that worldwide, women are having an average of one less child than they did in 1990. In addition, the average number of live births per woman is below 2.1 in over half of all countries and territories. This is a level experts have identified as being necessary for a country's population to keep its size without migration.<br/>
报告指出，全世界妇女平均比1990年少生一个孩子。此外，在超过一半的国家和地区，每名妇女的平均活产数低于2.1。专家们认为，这个数字是一个国家在没有移民的情况下保持人口规模所必需的水平。</p>
<p>Wilmoth said the report shows that nearly 20 percent of the world has “ultra-low” fertility, with women having fewer than 1.5 live births.<br/>
威尔莫斯说，报告显示，世界上近20%的国家拥有“超低”生育率，女性活产不到1.5个。</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.<br/>
我是布莱恩·林恩。(21VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Church Bells in Spanish Town Ring Out a Return to Tradition (2024/7/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/church-bells-in-spanish-town-ring-out-a-return-to-tradition.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p class="MsoBodyText">The sound of <strong>church</strong> bells around the world is usually made by machine. But before newspapers, radio, telephones, television and the internet, bell ringing by hand communicated important information within small communities across Europe.</p>
<p>Now, a small school of bell ringers in northeastern Spain wants to recover the art of hand, or manual, bell ringing. The school's founder and leader, Xavier Pallàs, says there is a whole language of bell ringing to rescue and return to use.</p>
<p>The Vall d'en Bas School of Bell Ringers effort comes two years after the international community recognized the import of manual bell ringing in Spain. The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization, UNESCO, added the practice to its Humanity's Intangible Cultural Heritage list in 2022.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="View of the bell tower of the 12th-century Sant Rom&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;224; church, where students of the Vall d'en Bas School of Bell Ringers perform playing bells, in the small Spanish village of Joanetes, Spain, June 29, 2024. (AP Photo/Emilio Morenatti)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/79708420-3b0e-4a55-b62b-96a4f718cd7f_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">View of the bell tower of the 12th-century Sant Rom<i>&amp;#</i>224; church, where students of the Vall d'en Bas School of Bell Ringers perform playing bells, in the small Spanish village of Joanetes, Spain, June 29, 2024. (AP Photo/Emilio Morenatti)</span></div>
<p><strong>A method of messaging for centuries</strong></p>
<p>Pallàs' students have learned how to ring out calls for village celebrations, warnings of bad weather or fire, religious services, and deaths. Pallàs says bells could still "help mark the <strong>rituals</strong> that we need."</p>
<p>The change to mechanical ringing devices over the past century has flattened the bells' songs and muted their messaging powers, the teacher said. If the bells are played with expertise, he added, the sound can signal a time for celebrating or mourning. The sound can even signal when to run to the aid of a neighbor in need.</p>
<p>"For centuries, the tolling of church bells was our most important communication method," said Pallàs. He spoke inside the <strong>belfry </strong>that also serves as classroom, in the town of Joanetes.</p>
<p>"Machines cannot reproduce the richness of the sounds that we used to hear, so there has been a simplification and unification of bell ringing. The language has been lost little by little until now, when we are finally recognizing its worth."</p>
<p><strong>Reconnecting with the past</strong></p>
<p>Manual church bell ringing has continued in Eastern Orthodox countries. But most Christian churches in Western Europe today use electronic bell ringing systems.</p>
<p>The students at Vall d'en Bas include women and men from <strong>diverse</strong> professional backgrounds. One student was in his 20s. Several students were retirees.</p>
<p>All spent the past few months researching bell <strong>sequences</strong>, documenting their history and learning to play them.</p>
<p>Roser Sauri jumped at the chance to reconnect with her childhood. She worked to recover and play the sequence that had sounded in her grandfather's village to announce his baptism.</p>
<p>"The bells formed a part of my life," said Sauri, who now works in artificial intelligence.</p>
<p><strong>Honoring humans and God</strong></p>
<p>Juan Carles Osuna and two other students recently tolled for the death of a woman. That meant <strong>swinging</strong> the largest of the bells. It weighs 429 kilograms.</p>
<p>"It's an emotional experience,” Osuna said. “You feel your blood pumping. You feel the strength, and how you are communicating with everyone in earshot.”</p>
<p>He added, "For me it is an honor, it's a way to honor both humans and God."</p>
<p><strong>Dreaming of bell ringers across Spain</strong></p>
<p>Xavier Pallàs says he has a full class lined up for the fall and about 60 more people on an admission wait list. He believes that a recovery of bell ringing in a neighborhood or town's life could help strengthen local communities.</p>
<p>The school leader said, "This is a means of communication that reaches everyone inside a local community and can help it come together at <strong>concrete</strong> moments."</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><em>______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>church</strong> - <em>n. </em>a building for public holy services, especially of Christian belief</p>
<p><strong>ritual </strong>- <em>n. </em>ceremony, especially of religious tradition</p>
<p><strong>belfry </strong>- <em>n. </em>a bell tower</p>
<p><strong>diverse </strong>- <em>adj. </em>involving many different kinds of related or similar things</p>
<p><strong>sequence </strong>- <em>n. </em>the order in which things are or should be connected, related, or dated</p>
<p><strong>swing </strong>- <em>v. </em>to move quickly in a sweeping curve</p>
<p><strong>concrete </strong>- <em>adj. </em><strong> </strong>belonging to or based on actual experience; not abstract</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Who’s and Whose (2024/7/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/who-s-and-whose.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Mei Jen in China about the usage of two words that sound the same.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-8d3b-08dca12051c6_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>I have some question(s) about the words <em>whose </em>and <em>who's</em>. I sometimes have confusion when I hear. I am not always sure what word I am hearing. Can you please share with me your advice?</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>Thank you for writing to us Mei Jen. I'm happy to answer this question.</p>
<p>The easiest way to know which word you are hearing is to listen for the words that follow it.</p>
<p><strong>Who's</strong></p>
<p>We contract, or join together, the two words <em>who is</em> to make the contraction “who's.” Often, the next word you hear after “who's” is a verb, as in these examples:</p>
<p><em>Who's going to help us?</em></p>
<p><em>Who's making all that noise?</em></p>
<p><em>Who's using this computer?</em></p>
<p>Sometimes, you will hear a prepositional phrase or a noun phrase after the contraction “who's.”</p>
<p><em>Who's in the office today?</em></p>
<p><em>Who's the director of that film?</em></p>
<p>Last, we can contract the word “who” with the verb “has." So, the sentence “Who has already seen this film?” sounds like this:</p>
<p><em>Who's already seen this film?</em></p>
<p><strong>Whose</strong></p>
<p>Now, let's look at the possessive “whose," spelled w-h-o-s-e.</p>
<p>We use it to ask about who owns or has something. So, you should listen for a noun after the pronoun “whose," or you can listen for the adjectives “this,” “that,” “these,” or “those.”</p>
<p>For example, if we see a book on a desk and we do not know who owns it, we can ask either of the following questions:</p>
<p><em>Whose book is this?</em></p>
<p><em>Whose book is that?</em></p>
<p>You can hear the noun “book,” and you can also hear the adjectives “this” and “that” at the end of the question.</p>
<p>We use the word “this” if we are close to the book. If we are farther away from the book, we use the word “that.”</p>
<p>We use the adjectives “these” and “those” for plural things.</p>
<p><em>Whose shoes are these?</em></p>
<p><em>Whose bags are those?</em></p>
<p>We can also place the contraction “who's” and the possessive “whose” at the beginning of a noun clause. The noun clause begins after the main verb of the sentence, as in these examples:</p>
<p><em>I want to know who's going to drive the bus.</em></p>
<p><em>I want to know whose idea this was. </em></p>
<p>You can learn more about the possessive “whose,” including its use in relative clauses, in this Everyday Grammar on <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/everyday-grammar-the-mysterious-word-whose-/4479936.html">The Mysterious Word ‘Whose'</a>.</p>
<p>We hope today's lesson is helpful, Mei Jen.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, do you have a question about American English? Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.<em> </em></p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
