<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>VOA Special English</title>
        <link>https://www.21voa.com/special_english/</link>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <itunes:category>ESL</itunes:category>
        <itunes:author>VOA</itunes:author>
        <description>美国之音（以下称VOA）的英语节目，按播音速度可分为两种：Standard English （标准英语）和 Special English（特别英语）。

Special English 又叫“慢速英语”，是VOA 专为全世界非英语国家初学英语的听众安排的一种简易、规范的英语广播节目。该节目创始于50年代末期，是VOA 的专家们研究如何与世界各地的英语学习者进行交际的产物。它正式开播于1959年10月。当时只面向欧洲和中东，但由于这个节目适合许多国家英语学习者的需要，所以它的广播对象不久就扩大到世界其他地区，并很快在全世界范围内产生了广泛的影响。现在这个节目对欧洲、非洲和拉丁美洲每晚广播一次，对加勒比地区每晚广播一次（星期天除外），对东南亚广播次数最多，每天上午两次，晚上三次。

30多年来，VOA 为了办好Special English节目，进行了大量的调查研究工作，对播音速度、内容及用词范围都作了具体规定，基本上达到了既能为英语学习者提供信息，又不损害英语本身风格的目的，使之成为VOA 独具特色，拥有最大量听众的节目。

美国著名词汇学家S. B. Flexmer 指明了Special English的三条标准，也就是它所“特别”的地方：

1、它是一种由美国人最常用的1500个基本单词为主体构成的美国英语；

2、它用简短、明晰的句子写作和广播；

3、它以每分钟90个单词的速度，即2/3的Standard English（标准英语）速度进行广播。

Special English的节目可分为两大类：一类是新闻节目；一类是专题节目。

1．新闻节目

VOA Special English 的新闻广播向听众提供世界范围内的政治、经济、军事、外交、国际关系、宗教、天气以及各种重大事件和珍闻奇事等各个方面的信息，每天向东南亚地区广播五次，早上两次，晚上三次，每逢半点播出。

Special English新闻节目每次长约十分钟，大都播出十条左右新闻，近一千个单词，每条新闻多为一分钟，但偶尔也有长达两分钟的要闻。除头条新闻外，每条新闻都由一个电头引导，这样显得结构分明，条理清晰，适宜初学英语的人收听。在节目结束之前，播音员常常用三四句话重播其中三条新闻的提要以加深听众对要闻的印象。

Special English新闻中70%左右的内容与同时整点播出的Standard English新闻相同，但相同新闻的先后次序有所变动。每次节目的开头和结尾大同小异，格式比较固定。

2．专题节目（一）

Special English的专题节目（Feature Programs）,从时间上看，可分为两大类：一是每五分钟一次的专题，二是每十五分钟一次的专题。本节先介绍每项五分钟一次的专题材节目。

Special English五分钟一次的专题材节目安排在Special English新闻节目之后和（或）每十五分钟一次的专题材节目之前播出，每星期播七次。根据内容，可分为三个小类，即：Science Report（科学报道），逢星期一、三、五播出，每天播六遍；Agriculture Report（农业报道），逢星期二、四播出，每天播六遍；Words And Their Stories（词语掌故），逢星期六和星期天播出，每天播五遍。这三个专题材各具特色，具有相对的独立性，听众每听完一个节目，都会获得一个完整的印象。

Science Report（科学报道）这一专题材节目每周向听众介绍三篇有关现代科学技术最新发展情况的报道，涉及物理、化学、天文至高无上理、生物、环卫、心理、教育、医学和计算机等方面。适宜理工科大学生和科技工作者收集信息，积累资料，学习科技英语。

Agriculture Report（农业报道） Agriculture Report是为农业科技工作者和生产者安排的一个专题。它专门报道世界各国，特别是美国现代农业生产的最新成文汇报总务科 学家对农业生产某一方面的研究进展，以及他们对影响农业生产的某一自然现象进行分析和研究的近况。此外，它还经常向听众介绍发展中国家家业生产的一些有益经验等内容。

Words And Their Stories（词语掌故）这一专题节目，旨在向学习英语的听众介绍美国英语中生动有趣的词语和惯用法，并从科学研究和通俗词源学的角度来解释它们的含意、产生的背景及其在使用过程中的演变情况等。它通过讲故事的形式讲解每一个词语。这是VOA Special English中的优秀节目之一，是学习美国英语的极好材料。通过收听这一节目，听众不仅能学到娓娓动听的掌故和地道的美国英语，而且能增加美国的社会文化背景知识，历史传统与现状的了解。

VOA 为了更好地办好这个节目，便于听众收听学习，于1978年编辑出版了一本名为Words And Their Stories的书，共收集一百篇故事，作者是Herbert Sutcliffe, Harold Bermen 及VOA 该节目的部分编辑人员。在每次的实际广播中，播音员都以此书为蓝本，再根据需要对原稿进行适当增删。按每周两个故事计算，此书的一百个故事还不能满足一年的播音需要。于是编辑们就是重播部分词语掌故的同时，不断增加许多新的词语掌故，及时将词源学家的最新研究成果和不断增加的新词汇介绍给听众。收听实践证明，初学者在收听过程中必然会遇到许多人名、地名和一些较难的句子，有时甚至在听完之后还很难理解所播词语的确切含义及其汉语意思，为此，听众可参看1983年由中国对外翻译出版公司出版的该书英汉对照本中的有关部分。

3．专题节目（二）

VOA Special English的专题节目，除上节谈的五分钟一次的以外，还有本节要介绍的每十五分钟一次的节目。这类节目共有七个不同的小专题，以星期为单位循环，每天分四次复播出一个专题，但星期日和星期六的两个专题材每晚只播三遍，每次节目约十分钟，继每次五分钟的专题节目之后播出。

这类专题节目的基本结构是，在特定的伴声中先报告当次节目的名称，并扼要介绍其主要内容，然后播送节目正文。最后，在伴乐声中报告节目主持人和撰稿人的姓名，以邀请听众在下周的这个时间继续收听该节目而结束。

People in America（美国人物志） 这是有关美国历史名人的一个专题节目，每逢星期天晚上播出。它向听众介绍在美国历史上产生过重大影响、起过重要作用、作出了突出贡献的科学、文学、政治、或其他各方面的历史人物。节目一般都对他们的生平事迹进行简要的叙述，对其贡献作出评介，类似人物小传。有的重要人物事迹很多，必须用两次或几次的节目时间进行联播。对这样的节目要坚持收听，才会获得完整的印象。

TThis is America（今日美国） This Is America向听众介绍美国人民的生活、学习、工作和娱乐情况，是英语学习者解美国社会的一条渠道。该专题大都一个节目一个整体，每逢星期一晚播出。

Science in the News（科学新闻） 这一专题材主要对新近的科学技术新闻进行综述或摘要广播。向听众介绍世界各国在自然、医学、疾病、原子能、航天等方面的科研动态、成果、突破性进展及存在的困难。涉及当今世界人们普遍关心的重大问题，如核事故、航天飞机爆炸、自然灾害、环境污染和爱滋病等等。每逢星期二播出，每次播一到五条新闻摘要。

Explorations（自然探索） 每逢星期三晚上，听众可以收听到Explorations这一专题节目。该专题既涉及人类遨游太空、探索原子、研究自身、改造自然的现代技术，也报道发展中国家开发新资源，利用新工艺改善人民生活等方面的成就，其侧重点在各种科技实验和简易实用技术方面。该节目一般安排一段时间播一个系列，每次播出一个主题，以便能将某项新技术的研究和应用的全过程介绍给听众，电台还乐意为感兴趣的听众提供所需的文字材料。

The Making of a Nation（建国史话） 这一专题节目向听众介绍美利坚合众国从十三个殖民地区域到现代工业国的孕育、诞生以及形成超级大国的历史过程，并以历史为线索，特定的历史时期为单位，以重大的历史事件为主题材来叙述各个党派、各届总统和政府的历史作用与贡献。这是每个英语学习者都应了解的基本知识。The Making of a Nation每逢星期四播出。这是个系列节目，坚持收听，则有助于系统了解美国的历史概况。

American Mosaic（美国万花筒） American Mosaic是一个radio magazine（广播杂志）节目。该节目题材广泛、内容丰，展示着美国社会文化生活中比较轻松愉快的生活画面；听众收听该节目就如同在阅读一本图文并茂的杂志。它每次有三到五个小节目，涉及音乐、图书、技术和教育等方面的内容。我们既可以从中欣赏到著名歌唱的优秀歌曲，对美国音乐有所了解，又可以获取一些生动有趣的现代美国社会生活知识，随着播音员那亲切悦耳的声音步入美国风景如画的大好河山；同时还能听到世界各地的听众提出的有关英语语方文学等方面的问题和电台的解答。

American Stories（美国故事） 这一专题材节目安排在每星期六晚上播出。这样能使听众在学习和工作之余，得以轻松一下头脑。我们可以通过这一美国文学的“窗口”，接触各种流派、各类名家的文学作品。了解美国英语的时代特色，欣赏、学习美国人民运用语方的技巧，并从那些佳作名篇中获得艺术享受。该节目对短篇故事采取一次播一篇的方式，对中、长篇小说则先进行简写加工，再分几次播出全文。在播出故事正文之前，播音员常常先介绍故事的主要情节。对需要分几次节目时间播出的中长篇，在播第二或以后各部分之前，主持人还先重述已播部分的故事梗概，以唤起听众的回忆，使故事听起来更加连贯。</description>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers: Female Family Ties Important to Social Networks  (2025/1/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/researchers-female-family-ties-important-to-social-networks.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>A recent study suggests that female family ties were central to social networks in ancient Celtic society before the Roman invasion.</p>
<p>Genetic evidence from a late Iron Age cemetery in Britain shows that women were closely related. At the same time, unrelated men were more likely to come into the community from other places, likely after marriage.</p>
<p>For the study, researchers examined ancient DNA from 57 burial places in Dorset in southwestern England. People used the cemetery from around 2100 years ago to around 1800 years ago.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This photo provided by Bournemouth University in January 2025 shows burials being investigated at an Iron Age Celtic cemetery as part of the Durotriges tribe project dig in Dorset, southwest England. (Bournemouth University via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/06785e4f-fca7-41a3-9537-b62600ac24ec_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This photo provided by Bournemouth University in January 2025 shows burials being investigated at an Iron Age Celtic cemetery as part of the Durotriges tribe project dig in Dorset, southwest England. (Bournemouth University via AP)</span></div>
<p>The results showed that two-thirds of the individuals descended from a single maternal lineage.</p>
<p>Lara Cassidy of Trinity College Dublin was one of the study's co-writers. Cassidy suggested to the Associated Press (AP) that the results were surprising, or in her words, “jaw-dropping.”</p>
<p>She said that such a finding had “never been observed before in European prehistory.”</p>
<p>The study appeared recently in the scientific publication <em>Nature.</em></p>
<p>The research suggests that women stayed in the same circles throughout life. They kept social networks and likely inherited or managed land and property.</p>
<p>Cassidy told the AP that the findings suggest, “it's your husband who is coming in as a relative stranger, dependent on a wife's family for land and livelihood.”</p>
<p>Such a way of living is called matrilocality. The researchers said it is historically rare.</p>
<p>Guido Gnecchi-Ruscone is with the Max Planck Institute in Germany. Gnecchi-Ruscone was not part of the study.</p>
<p>He said researchers studying burial places in Britain and Europe have only discovered the opposite behavior. He said in those communities, women left their homes and families to join their husband's family group.</p>
<p>He said such a way of living, known as patrilocality, has been observed in other ancient time periods. These include the Neolithic period which started more than 10,000 years ago to the early Medieval period more than 1000 years in the past.</p>
<p>Cassidy said in studies of pre-industrial societies from around 220 years ago to the present, researchers found that men join their wives' extended family households only eight percent of the time.</p>
<p>But researchers already knew there was something special about the role of women in Iron Age Britain. A group of tribes with closely related languages and art that is often described as Celtic lived in England before the Roman invasion about 2000 years ago.</p>
<p>Valuable objects have been found buried with Celtic women. Roman writers, including Julius Caesar, wrote with disrespect about their relative independence and fighting abilities.</p>
<p>The network of strong female family connections that the researchers found does not necessarily mean that women also held official positions of political power.</p>
<p>Study co-writer Miles Russell of Bournemouth University in England researches ancient societies. He said the findings do suggest that women had some control of land and property and strong social support. Such a situation made Britain's Celtic society more “egalitarian” than the Roman world, Russell said.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Christina Larson reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>cemetery </strong><em>– n.</em> a burial ground</p>
<p><strong>descended from </strong><em>–v. (phrasal)</em> to be related by birth to an ancestor</p>
<p><strong>maternal </strong><em>– adj. </em>of or related to the mother</p>
<p><strong>lineage</strong> <em>– n. </em>a group of individuals descending from a common ancestor</p>
<p><strong>inherit</strong> <em>–v.</em> to receive property or something of value because of a family relationship</p>
<p><strong>manage </strong><em>–v</em>. to oversee or look over</p>
<p><strong>extended family</strong> <em>– n.</em> a large group of people who are related by blood or marriage who consider themselves as a large family</p>
<p><strong>egalitarian </strong><em>–adj.</em> aiming to make people in a society more equal than they are</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Meta Ends Third-party Fact-Checking, Adds ‘Community Notes’ System  (2025/1/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/meta-ends-third-party-fact-checking-adds-community-notes-system.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Facebook parent company Meta recently announced changes to the way it tries to identify misinformation and harmful material published on its social media services.</p>
<p>Meta chief Mark Zuckerberg <a class="wsw__a" href="https://about.fb.com/news/2025/01/meta-more-speech-fewer-mistakes/">explained</a> in a video that the company had decided to make the changes because the old system had produced “too many mistakes and too much <strong>censorship</strong>.”</p>
<p><strong>Issues with Meta moderation</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - The Facebook logo is seen on a cell phone in Boston, USA, Friday, Oct. 14, 2022. (AP Photo/Michael Dwyer, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/2ac5b816-9f18-48ba-9521-fb24fec5d49b_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - The Facebook logo is seen on a cell phone in Boston, USA, Friday, Oct. 14, 2022. (AP Photo/Michael Dwyer, File)</span></div>
<p>Zuckerberg said the <strong>moderation</strong> system Meta had built needed to be “complex” to examine huge amounts of <strong>content</strong> in search of material that violated company policies.</p>
<p>However, he noted the problem with such systems is they can make a lot of errors. The Meta chief added about such systems, “Even if they accidentally censor just one percent of posts, that's millions of people.”</p>
<p>So, he said the company had decided to move to a new system centered on “reducing mistakes, simplifying our policies, and restoring free expression.”</p>
<p><strong>“Community Notes” system</strong></p>
<p>The new method turns over content moderation duties to a “Community Notes” system. The company said this system aims to “empower the community” to decide whether content is acceptable or needs further examination.</p>
<p>The changes will be effective for Meta's Facebook, Instagram and Threads services. Meta said the new system would become available first to U.S. users in the coming months.</p>
<p>Meta's former moderation system involved the use of independent, third-party fact-checking organizations. Many of these were large media companies or news agencies. The efforts included digital tools as well as human workers to fact-check content and identify false, <strong>inappropriate</strong> or harmful material.</p>
<p>Meta said the third-party moderation method ended up identifying too much information for fact-checking. After closer examination, a lot of content should have been considered “<strong>legitimate</strong> political speech and debate.”</p>
<p>Another problem, the company said, was that the decisions made by content moderators could be affected by their personal beliefs, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_6ywWHIXG">opinions</a> and <strong>biases</strong>. One result was that “a program intended to inform too often became a tool to censor.”</p>
<p>Meta's new Community Notes system is similar to the method used by the social media service X. A statement by Meta <a class="wsw__a" href="https://about.fb.com/news/2025/01/meta-more-speech-fewer-mistakes/">said</a> changes to this system will have to be made by users, not anyone from the company.</p>
<p>Meta said, “Just like they do on X, Community Notes will require agreement between people with a <strong>range</strong> of <strong>perspectives</strong> to help prevent biased ratings.” The company also invited any users to register to be among the first to try out the system.</p>
<p><strong>How did fact-checkers react to Meta's change?</strong></p>
<p>The International Fact-Checking Network (IFCN) criticized Meta's latest decision. It said the move threatened to "undo nearly a <strong>decade</strong> of progress."</p>
<p>The group rejected Zuckerberg's claim that the fact-checking program had become a "tool to censor" users. It noted, that "the freedom to say why something is not true is also free speech."</p>
<p>Milijana Roga<i></i>269; is executive editor of the Serbian fact-checking outlet Istinomer. She told Reuters news agency that she thinks Meta's decision would end up hurting the media industry. Roga<i></i>269; noted that research suggests that many citizens use Meta services as their main source for information. Removing independent fact-checkers “further <strong>hinders</strong> access to <strong>accurate</strong> information and news," Roga<i></i>269; said.</p>
<p><strong>How effective are Community Notes?</strong></p>
<p>Not a lot of research has been done on how effective Community Notes systems are. But one effort carried out by the University of California and Johns Hopkins University found in 2024 that community notes entered on X for COVID-19 misinformation were accurate. The research showed the notes used<strong> </strong>both moderate and high-quality sources and were attached to widely read posts.</p>
<p>However, the number of people taking part in that study was small. Also, the effects the system had on users' opinions and behavior is unknown.</p>
<p>A 2023 study, from the <em>Journal of Online Trust and Safety,</em> said it was harder for users to agree when they examined content related to political issues.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story, based on reports from Meta, The Associated Press and Reuters.</em></p>
<p><strong>____________________________________</strong>_________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>censorship </strong><em>– n. </em>the system or practice of censoring information contained in books, movies, the internet, etc.</p>
<p><strong>moderate</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to make sure the rules of an internet discussion are not broken</p>
<p><strong>content </strong><em>–n.</em> writing, audio and visual material found online</p>
<p><strong>inappropriate </strong><em>–adj</em>. something that is not right in a particular situation and which depends on people's opinions</p>
<p><strong>legitimate </strong><em>– adj. </em>something real</p>
<p><strong>bias </strong><em>– adj. </em>a situation in which you support or oppose something in an unfair way because you are influenced by personal opinions</p>
<p><strong>range </strong><em>–n.</em> all elements of a series of objects or numbers</p>
<p><strong>perspective</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n. </em>the way person thins about something</p>
<p><strong>decade </strong><em>– n. </em>a period of 10 years<em> </em></p>
<p><strong>hinder </strong><em>– v. </em>to make it difficult to do something</p>
<p><strong>accurate </strong><em>– n. </em>true or correct<em> </em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Red Coloring Linked to Cancer Risk Banned in US Foods  (2025/1/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/red-coloring-linked-to-cancer-risk-banned-in-us-foods.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has banned a chemical widely used to color some food products red. The ban of the coloring chemical, called dye, came nearly 35 years after it was removed from skin products because of a possible cancer risk.</p>
<p>A group of food safety and health supporters issued a <strong>petition</strong> in 2022 seeking to have the FDA ban Red No. 3 in food.</p>
<p>The earlier ban was ordered in 1990, after two studies showed Red No. 3 caused cancer in male rats eating high levels of the chemical. At the time, however, the FDA only acted to ban the coloring mixture in products put on the skin or in drugs taken by mouth.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This image shows a pile of candy corn in Westchester County, N.Y., Oct. 23, 2023. " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/180ce991-0d5d-4e08-bc3a-8f328f0a5d77_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This image shows a pile of candy corn in Westchester County, N.Y., Oct. 23, 2023. </span></div>
<p>Health activists had long sought FDA approval to expand the ban to food products. In November, nearly two dozen members of Congress sent a letter demanding that FDA officials ban Red No. 3.</p>
<p>Some of the most common products containing Red No. 3 include sweets, icing, strawberry milk, maraschino cherries, strawberry protein drinks, as well as some gummy vitamins and medications.</p>
<p>The FDA said food manufacturers will have until January 2027 to remove the dye from their products.</p>
<p>Other countries still permit certain uses of the dye. But any imported products will still have to meet the new U.S. requirement. Red No. 3 is already banned for food use in Europe, Australia and New Zealand, except in certain kinds of cherries.</p>
<p>The dye will be banned in California starting in January 2027. And lawmakers in Tennessee, Arkansas and Indiana have also proposed limits on certain dyes, especially from foods offered in public schools.</p>
<p>Jim Jones is the FDA's deputy commissioner for human foods. He <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.fda.gov/food/hfp-constituent-updates/fda-revoke-authorization-use-red-no-3-food-and-ingested-drugs">noted</a> that even though the agency had established the new ban, “the way that FD&amp;C Red No. 3 causes cancer in male rats does not <strong>occur</strong> in humans." FDA officials said the ban was enacted because of a U.S. rule called the Delaney Clause. This legal policy requires the FDA to ban any additive found to cause cancer in people or animals.</p>
<p>Dr. Peter Lurie is director of the <strong>consumer</strong> activist group the Center for Science in the Public Interest. He helped lead the latest effort to remove Red No. 3 from food products. Lurie told The Associated Press, "This is a welcome, but long <strong>overdue</strong>, action from the FDA.”</p>
<p>The International Association of Color Manufacturers has repeatedly said Red No. 3 is safe in levels usually taken in by humans. The group pointed to research carried out by scientific experts from the United Nations and the World Health Organization. One study, released in 2018, confirmed the safety of Red 3 in food.</p>
<p>Some food manufacturers have already changed their products to remove Red No. 3. One example is Sensient Food Colors, a St. Louis-based supplier of food colors and flavorings. In its place, the company uses beet juice, a dye made from insects and other coloring mixtures.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jonel Aleccia reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>petition </strong>–<em> n.</em> an official request for someone in authority to do something</p>
<p><strong>occur</strong> – <em>v. </em>to happen</p>
<p><strong>consumer</strong> –<em> n. </em>a person who buys goods or services</p>
<p><strong>overdue</strong> – <em>adj</em>. not appearing or presented by a stated, expected, or required time</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Make a Memory Palace to Improve Your English  (2025/1/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/improve-your-english-with-a-memory-palace.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Alice Bryant</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>
Sherlock Holmes is an imaginary private detective created by British writer Arthur Conan Doyle in the late 1880s. Doyle's stories about the detective have been turned into movies and television shows.</p>
<p>One of Sherlock Holmes' great skills is a powerful memory. In a recent BBC television series, the character uses a memory technique called a “mind <strong>palace</strong>” or “memory palace.”</p>
<p>On one show, for example, Holmes has been severely wounded in a shooting and retreats into his mind to search for ways to survive. He visits rooms in his mind palace, looking for helpful memories. In one room, he finds his childhood dog, and the memory helps calm the detective.</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/142EFFF5-F4C5-4CAE-A8C1-C76F629E3DD6_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>The memory palace idea was not a BBC creation. The method for remembering has existed for thousands of years. Many language educators today teach their students how to use the method to improve their language skills.</p>
<p>But what exactly is a memory palace? It is a real structure, such as a home or building, that you can picture in your head. You then imagine placing things you want to remember inside the structure.</p>
<p>You can use a memory palace to remember words, <strong>phrases</strong>, facts, or even the order of events. If you can see the inside of a house or building in your mind, you can make your own memory palace. On today's Education Tips, we will show you how.</p>
<p><strong>Making your palace</strong></p>
<p>Start with a list of words or phrases that you want to remember. Then, close your eyes and choose a physical space that you know well, such as your home, a school you attended, or a current or former workplace. If your chosen space has only one or two rooms, do not worry. You can also use things like doors, passageways, steps or other permanent places along the physical path.</p>
<p>The next step is to imagine walking through the space using the path that you would normally take through it. As you walk through, put objects that you want to remember at specific places along the path. Leave the objects there to pick up later when you visit your memory palace.</p>
<p>Now, let's try this technique by using six <strong>ingredients</strong> for a pizza: flour, water, dry yeast, tomato sauce, cheese and basil.</p>
<p>Close your eyes and picture a home.</p>
<p>First, you open the front door and see a bag of flour on the floor. The bag is broken and some of the flour has spilled. You are worried that you might <strong>slip</strong>, so you carefully step over the area.</p>
<p>Second, you walk into your bedroom. On top of your bed sits a cup of water. The cup is shaped like an upside-down piece of pizza. You think about how funny that is and laugh about it.</p>
<p>Third, as you enter the living room, you see a very large <strong>spoon</strong> of dry yeast sitting on the <strong>sofa</strong>. The spoon is watching a cooking show on television.</p>
<p>Fourth, while standing in the living room, you notice the room has a strange smell to it. You look above the television and see a block of cheese hanging on the wall.</p>
<p>Fifth, you walk into the <strong>kitchen</strong> and see two tomatoes chasing each other around the room. Suddenly, they crash and explode, covering the floor in red.</p>
<p>And sixth, you open the back door and go outside. There, you see a group of very tall green basil plants. In a funny voice, the tallest plant says, “Choose me! Choose me!”</p>
<p>Did you notice anything strange about the palace? It was full of extraordinary and humorous imagery. We will say more about that in a few minutes.</p>
<p>But first, let's check how well our technique worked. See if you can answer these questions:</p>
<p>1-What was on the wall above the television?</p>
<p>2-Where were the tomatoes and what were they doing?</p>
<p>3-Which object was sitting on the bed?</p>
<p>4-Where was the yeast and what was it doing?</p>
<p>5-Which ingredient spoke and what did it say?</p>
<p>6-What did you see when you opened the front door?</p>
<p>My <strong>guess</strong> is that you remembered everything in our memory palace. That's good news.</p>
<p><strong>Make memory strong</strong></p>
<p>Experts offer some advice for making strong memory palaces.</p>
<p>For instance, if you want to remember a lot of words, memory trainer Anthony Metivier suggests first <strong>drawing</strong> a simple map of your memory palace. Then, number the places along your path where you will put the things that you want to remember. You can put more than one thing in each room or area. Later, you will add the mental imagery.</p>
<p>English teacher James, of the YouTube channel JamesESL English Lessons, has additional advice. In his video on memory palaces, he says that there are three <strong>keys</strong> to a strong memory palace. They are: emotion, movement, and connections between the object and something permanent.</p>
<p>Both he and Metivier say imagining things in a humorous or crazy way improves your ability to remember them. These experts also agree that connecting images to actions or movement will create lasting memories. For instance, the tomatoes were chasing each other and the basil spoke.</p>
<p>And finally, teacher James suggests placing the objects next to or on something permanent in your palace. Beds, sofas, floors, walls, doors – all of these are permanent. The block of cheese was on the wall, for example.</p>
<p>Now, it's your turn. Pick a list of English words or phrases that you have trouble remembering and try this method on your own.</p>
<p>Let us know how it goes.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell. And I'm Alice Bryant.</p>
<p><em>Alice Bryant wrote this story for Learning English. Caty Weaver was the editor. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>palace</strong> – n. a very large and impressive house</p>
<p><strong>ingredient</strong> – n. one of the things that are used to make a food or product</p>
<p><strong>slip</strong> – v. to lose your balance, especially on a slippery surface</p>
<p><strong>phrase</strong> – n. a group of two or more words that express a single idea but do not usually form a complete sentence</p>
<p><strong>spoon</strong> – n. an eating or cooking tool that has a small shallow bowl attached to a handle</p>
<p><strong>sofa</strong> – n. a long and comfortable piece of furniture on which a person can sit or lie down</p>
<p><strong>kitchen</strong> – n. a room in which food is cooked</p>
<p><strong>guess</strong> – n. an attempt to give an answer about something when you do not know much about it or are not sure about it</p>
<p><strong>key</strong> – n. something that is necessary in order to do or achieve something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Nepal Supreme Court Bans Large Business Development in Protected Areas  (2025/1/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/nepal-supreme-court-bans-large-business-development-in-protected-areas.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Nepal's Supreme Court has struck down disputed laws that permit waterpower centers,<strong> </strong>visitor housing such as hotels, and other business development in protected natural areas. Environmental defenders say the January 15 ruling is a victory for efforts to protect the country's natural areas.</p>
<p>Nepal has recognized one fifth of its territory as protected natural areas. The country has 12 national parks and six conservation areas. They include lowland areas such as Chitwan National Park. The park is home to many wild animals such as tigers and rhinos. Other protected areas include Sagarmatha National Park, home to Mount Everest.</p>
<p>Waterpower, or hydropower, and <strong>tourism</strong> represent major economic sources for Nepal. Last year, its government passed laws to permit development of large projects in some parts of national parks, forests and other protected areas.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Nepalese mahouts walk their elephants through the Rapti River from Chitwan National Park in Sauraha, Chitwan, 170 kilometers (106 miles) south from Katmandu, Nepal, Monday, Dec. 26, 2011. (AP Photo/Niranjan Shrestha)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/d2b7f940-ad4b-4cf5-9896-01131f6606fb_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Nepalese mahouts walk their elephants through the Rapti River from Chitwan National Park in Sauraha, Chitwan, 170 kilometers (106 miles) south from Katmandu, Nepal, Monday, Dec. 26, 2011. (AP Photo/Niranjan Shrestha)</span></div>
<p>Padam Bahadur Shrestha is a Nepalese environmental activist who took legal action against the laws. He told Agence France Press that the laws' passage showed that the government lacked <strong>insight</strong> and was only seeking to please business investors.</p>
<p>Shrestha praised the Supreme Court's ruling, saying it "<strong>preserves </strong>ecology and <strong>biodiversity</strong>.”</p>
<p>Nepal is recognized worldwide for its actions to protect its wild animal and plant life.</p>
<p>Nepal's environmental protection laws have helped the local tiger population increase from 121 animals in 2010 to 355 in 2023. And while only about 100 one-horned rhinos were living in Nepal in the 1960s, their number increased to 752 in 2021.</p>
<p>Nepal also increased its tree cover by almost 100 percent between 1992 and 2016. Wood industry activities, or logging, had deforested many areas of the country for tens of years earlier.</p>
<p>Rampreet Yadav is a former <strong>conservation</strong> officer of Chitwan National Park, Nepal's largest protected area. He said the recent laws “should never have been passed."</p>
<p>"If development projects are <strong>allowed</strong> in protected areas, they will destroy our nature and animal habitats," he added.</p>
<p>The Nepalese government wants to develop its hydropower industry, especially along rivers in the Himalayan mountains. Last October, it signed agreements with India and Bangladesh to export thousands of <strong>megawatts</strong> of hydropower.</p>
<p>Nepal also earns much money from tourism. Last year, around one million foreign visitors came to Nepal, and the government has been spending money on the development of its airports.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith adapted this story based on reporting from Agence France Press. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>tourism </strong>– <em>n. </em>the practice of traveling for recreation</p>
<p><strong>insight </strong>– <em>n. </em>the power or act of seeing into or understanding a situation</p>
<p><strong>preserve </strong>– <em>v.</em> to keep safe from injury, harm, or destruction</p>
<p><strong>biodiversity </strong>– <em>n.</em> biological variety in an environment as indicated by numbers of different species of plants and animals <strong>conservation</strong> – <em>n.</em> planned management of a natural resource to prevent exploitation, destruction, or neglect</p>
<p><strong>allow </strong>– <em>v. </em>to permit; to let</p>
<p><strong>megawatt </strong>– <em>n.</em> one million watts</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>No Soil Needed to Grow Air Plants at Home  (2025/1/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/no-soil-needed-to-grow-air-plants-at-home.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">20 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>If you are looking for houseplants that do not take up a lot of space and are easy to grow, air plants might be the right choice.</p>
<p>There are more than 500 different <strong>species </strong>of air plants. Officially they are known as Tillandsia. These plants are native to places in<strong> </strong>North and South America that support year-round plant growth. Air plants belong to the same family as the pineapple.</p>
<p>Instead of soil, these plants attach themselves to things like trees, rocks and buildings. They do not cause problems for the objects they grow on. Air plants do not have roots. They depend on specialized cells – called trichomes – to permit their leaves to take in water and nutrients.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image provided by Drift in Air Plants shows a Tillandsia xerographica air plant in Bakersfield, California. (Jennifer Tuttle/Drift in Air Plants via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/38950b6c-8cd1-4636-8a34-17153f9148cb_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image provided by Drift in Air Plants shows a Tillandsia xerographica air plant in Bakersfield, California. (Jennifer Tuttle/Drift in Air Plants via AP)</span></div>
<p>Associated Press gardening writer Jessica Damiano has experimented with air plants and offers these guidelines for people wanting to grow them.</p>
<p><strong>Sunlight</strong></p>
<p>Air plants require bright, indirect light. So, they should be placed near an east- or west-facing window, but not directly in front of it. Direct sunlight can burn the plant's leaves.</p>
<p><strong>Watering</strong></p>
<p>In homes with average <strong>humidity</strong> levels, put air plants in a bowl of room-temperature water once a week for 30 to 60 minutes. In homes with drier air, this process can be repeated when needed.</p>
<p>Lightly shake the plants to remove extra water. Then, place them upside-down on a cloth to dry for several hours. This step is necessary to prevent water from collecting on the plant's leaves, which can cause damage.</p>
<p>If using chlorinated water, it is best to let the liquid sit for 12 to 24 hours to permit the chemical to <strong>dissipate</strong> before watering plants. Air plants are especially sensitive to chlorine.</p>
<p><strong>Feeding the plants</strong></p>
<p>Growers should feed their air plants with any all-purpose houseplant, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_eTz32nqz">bromeliad</a> or orchid fertilizer. The substance should be added to the soaking water monthly to provide added nutrients. Use about half the amount suggested by the fertilizer manufacturer.</p>
<p><strong>Life cycle</strong></p>
<p>Air plants <strong>bloom</strong> only once. The resulting pink, coral, purple or white flowers are a signal that the plants are nearing death. However, air plants produce offshoots, known as “pups.” These can be separated into new plants once they grow to about one-third the size of the parent.</p>
<p><strong>So many choices</strong></p>
<p>Notable air plants include Spanish moss which can be found hanging from large trees in tropical or subtropical areas. In the home, Spanish moss is grown in a humid environment, such as a bathroom.</p>
<p>Another kind is Tillandsia <em>ionantha</em>, which is also known as the sky plant. It is a <strong>shaggy</strong>-looking plant with green bracts. Bracts are leaf-like structures that grow from the area just beneath a flower. The tops of <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_lnnkCrAw">bracts</a> can turn pink or purple before flowering.</p>
<p>Tillandsia <em>caput-medusae</em> is named for its similarity to the snake-haired head of Medusa, from Greek mythology. The plant is popular because of its long, wavy leaves that grow upward from a fat, round base.</p>
<p>Perhaps the most unusual species of Tillandsia is the <a class="wsw__a" name="_Hlk187660007">Xerographic</a> air plant. This kind is known as the King of Air Plants. It can grow up to about one-half meter. The plant's long, thin silver leaves <strong>curl </strong>downward to produce a round shape that sets it apart from other air plants.</p>
<p><strong>How to show your Tillandsia</strong></p>
<p>You can place air plants in just about any spot that provides the required sunlight and good air flow.</p>
<p>Glass containers or <strong>terrariums</strong> are popular choices. But growers can also put air plants inside seashells or on rocks. One could even create a floating Tillandsia garden by hanging several plants from <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_dYc5qcDC">fishing</a> line.</p>
<p>The plants can also be attached to natural wood pieces with wire or glue. Some choose to grow them inside hanging <strong>frames</strong>. When choosing placement possibilities, the main thing to keep in mind is to make sure you are fully meeting all the plant's needs.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>______________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>species </strong><em>– n. </em>a group of animals or plants that are similar and can produce young animals or plants</p>
<p><strong>humidity</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a measurement of how much water is in the air</p>
<p><strong>dissipate </strong>–v. to dry up, disappear through evaporation or by becoming less and less dense</p>
<p><strong>bloom </strong><em>– v. </em>when a flower fully opens</p>
<p><strong>shaggy </strong><em>– adj. </em>having or covered with long, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_yT73SHaK">rough</a> and messy hair</p>
<p><strong>curl</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v. </em>when something moves in a circular direction</p>
<p><strong>terrarium </strong><em>– n. </em>a container, often made of glass, that is used to keep small plants in</p>
<p><strong>frame </strong><em>– n. </em>a border that surrounds and supports a picture, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_rJDKPMgA">door</a> or window</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Learn to Have Better Balance and Prevent Falls as You Age  (2025/1/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/learn-to-have-better-balance-and-prevent-falls-as-you-age.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">20 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>To age well, doctors say we should remember the importance of good balance. It matters when you wash yourself, put clothing on and, generally, move around in your home and elsewhere. As we age, good balance permits us to live more independently.</p>
<p>Difficulties with balance can be dangerous. The United States Centers for Disease Control reports that three million older people in America seek medical care for fall-related injuries each year. But we can prevent some falls, said Roopa Anmolsingh. She is a geriatrician, a doctor who specializes in treating old people. She is also the creator of the balance class program at Cleveland Clinic in Ohio. She said that "Some people have a <strong>misconception</strong> that part of getting old is, you're going to fall. That's not true. You can control how you fall, or if you fall."</p>
<p>To prevent falls, geriatricians say people should start asking themselves questions about their balance as early as 50 years old. Here are the questions:</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A couple walk on a sidewalk in Santiago, Chile, Wednesday on May 3, 2017. " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e26a4513-386c-4b2e-b739-68d383c6ac29_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A couple walk on a sidewalk in Santiago, Chile, Wednesday on May 3, 2017. </span></div>
<p><strong>Do I ever feel unsteady?</strong></p>
<p>If you feel<strong> </strong>unsteady, or lose balance, from time to time, ask your doctor to check all your body systems that can affect balance. Along with muscle and bone problems, unsteadiness can also result from poor blood pressure, inner-ear problems, nervous system issues and more.</p>
<p>Maybe you do not have unsteadiness but wonder about your skill at balancing. You can test yourself easily and at home to find out if you need any medical intervention.</p>
<p>Stand next to a wall or something that can provide support if needed. Raise one leg. Can you hold that position for 10 seconds? Now try the other leg. If you can stand on each leg alone for 10 seconds, you should be fine, said Greg W. Hartley, a professor of physical therapy specializing in geriatrics at the University of Miami in Florida.</p>
<p>"If you can't do that, then you should probably go see a physical therapist," he said. A physical therapist treats people with conditions or injuries that affect body movement.</p>
<p>Another at-home test is called TUG, for "timed up and go." Hartley suggests doing this test with supervision. You begin the test from a seated position. Then, stand up and start a timer immediately. Walk three meters, turn and walk back to your seat. Stop the timer as soon as you sit down. If the test takes you longer to complete than 15 seconds, your risk for falling is very high. But, if you do it in 12 seconds or less, your fall risk is almost zero.</p>
<p>Also, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.ncoa.org/tools/falls-free-checkup/">The National Council on Aging offers an online set of questions</a> to predict your risk of a fall.</p>
<p><strong>What can I do to improve balance?</strong></p>
<p>Because muscle mass lessens in most people during their 30s, geriatricians say the best way to keep good balance is to stay physically active throughout life. Anmolsingh says it is never too late to act on that advice.</p>
<p>Activities including<strong> tai chi</strong> and <strong>yoga </strong>are good for older adults because they involve controlled movements while <strong>shifting</strong> body weight. There also are simpler exercises people can work into their everyday lives.</p>
<p>Anmolsingh says standing on one foot while waiting in line at a store is good. Or, at home, sit down and stand up several times straight without using a support. Another easy exercise is the three-way leg lift. Hold on to a support, then lift a leg to the front, then to the side and then to the back.</p>
<p><strong>How often should I do the exercises?</strong></p>
<p>The National Institute of Aging says people should spend at least 150 minutes per week in general physical activity to improve balance and overall health.</p>
<p>Hartley said exercises done on a usual basis help train the brain to react correctly when you start to fall.</p>
<p>"Just like an athlete needs to do repetition to train for a sport, you're doing repetition to train for everyday balance activities," he said.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Albert Stumm reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>misconception</strong> – <em>n</em>. a wrong or mistaken idea</p>
<p><strong>tai chi </strong>- <em>n</em>. a Chinese form of exercise that uses very slow and controlled movements</p>
<p><strong>yoga</strong> – <em>n</em>. a system of exercises for mental and physical health</p>
<p><strong>shift</strong> – <em>v</em>. to move or to cause (something or someone) to move to a different place, or position</p>
<p><strong>athlete</strong> – <em>n</em>. a person who is trained in or good at sports, games, or exercises that require physical skill and strength</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers Use Lasers to Study Ancient Peruvian Mummies   (2025/1/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/researchers-use-lasers-to-study-ancient-peruvian-mummies.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>For more than 5,000 years, humans have covered themselves with permanent artistic designs known as tattoos.</p>
<p>In a recent study, researchers used lasers to uncover highly complex designs of ancient tattoos on <strong>mummies </strong>from Peru.</p>
<p>The skin of the mummies and the black liquid, or ink, used to make the tattoos permitted researchers to observe fine details. These marks are not <strong>visible</strong> to the human eye, said study co-writer Michael Pittman of the Chinese University of Hong Kong.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This August 2024 photo provided by researchers shows a mummified human from Peru's Chancay culture. (Tom Kaye via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/ba4e6410-471c-4273-9ddd-20ed618142ee_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This August 2024 photo provided by researchers shows a mummified human from Peru's Chancay culture. (Tom Kaye via AP)</span></div>
<p>The researchers examined around 100 mummies dating to around 775 years ago. The mummies were from coastal Peru's Chancay culture, which grew and developed before the Inca empire and the arrival of Europeans.</p>
<p>All the individuals had some form of tattoos on the back of their hands, knuckles, arms or other body parts. The study paid careful attention to four individuals with “<strong>exceptional</strong> tattoos” — designs of shapes such as triangles and diamonds, said Pittman.</p>
<p>It was not clear how the tattoos were created. But they are “of a quality that stands up against the really good electric tattooing of today,” said Aaron Deter-Wolf of the Tennessee Division of Archaeology. Deter-Wolf was not involved in the research.</p>
<p>The study results appeared recently in the publication <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.2421517122" target="_blank">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</a>.</p>
<p>Using lasers that make skin <strong>glow</strong>, “we basically turn skin into a <strong>light bulb</strong>,” said study co-writer Tom Kaye of the nonprofit Foundation for Scientific Advancement based in Sierra Vista, Arizona.</p>
<p>The findings were “helpful to learn about new non-destructive technologies that can help us study and document sensitive archaeological materials,” such as mummies, said Deter-Wolf.</p>
<p>The oldest known tattoos ever discovered are on the remains of a Neolithic man who lived in the Italian Alps around five thousand years ago. Many mummies from ancient Egypt also have tattoos, as do remains from cultures around the world.</p>
<p>People have used tattooing for many reasons throughout history. The marks can show cultural or individual identity, social standing, and more. Tattoos also have been used for protection against disease or to deepen relationships with spirits or gods, suggested Lars Krutak. Krutak, who works at the Museum of International Folk Art in Santa Fe, New Mexico, was not involved in the research.</p>
<p>Designs on ancient <strong>textile</strong> and stone products are more commonly found in good condition for study than are ancient tattoos. But ancient tattoos when studied can provide information about art forms that would not otherwise be available, suggested Martin Smith of Bournemouth University. Smith was not involved in the recent study.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Christina Larson reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>mummy</strong><em> – n.</em> human remains that are in good condition or very well preserved</p>
<p><strong>visible</strong> <em>– adj.</em> capable of being seen</p>
<p><strong>exceptional</strong> <em>– adj.</em> superior, rare, much better than average</p>
<p><strong>glow</strong> <em>– v. </em>to shine as if filled with light</p>
<p><strong>light bulb</strong><em> – n.</em> an electric lamp</p>
<p><strong>textile</strong> <em>– n</em>. woven cloth, fibers, or yarn</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Two New Private Spacecraft Launch to the Moon  (2025/1/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/two-new-private-spacecraft-launch-to-the-moon.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Two private spacecraft are on their way to the moon to carry out separate <strong>missions</strong>.</p>
<p>The landers launched January 15 from the American government's Kennedy Space Center in Florida. The private company SpaceX used its Falcon 9 launch vehicle to fly the landers into space. The two separated from Falcon 9 about one hour into the flight.</p>
<p>Mission leaders said the launch went exactly as planned, with no problems reported. The trip to the moon will take some time. One spacecraft is expected to land on the <strong>lunar</strong> surface in early March, while the other should touch down in late May or early June.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket lifts off from pad 39A with a payload of a pair of lunar landers at the Kennedy Space Center in Cape Canaveral, Fla., Wednesday, Jan. 15, 2025. (AP Photo/John Raoux)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f1a72312-cf15-428d-85fe-f619ae15b872_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket lifts off from pad 39A with a payload of a pair of lunar landers at the Kennedy Space Center in Cape Canaveral, Fla., Wednesday, Jan. 15, 2025. (AP Photo/John Raoux)</span></div>
<p>In February 2024, the first private spacecraft completed the first U.S. moon landing in more than 50 years. The lander, called Odysseus, was developed by the Texas-based company Intuitive Machines. The spacecraft experienced some technical problems but was able to carry out several science experiments before powering down permanently on the moon in late March.</p>
<p>For this current mission, Texas-based Firefly Aerospace developed Blue Ghost, one of the two landers launched. The other, named Resilience, belongs to Japanese company ispace. Both are designed to collect data and materials to support several planned moon missions – some including astronauts – in coming years.</p>
<p>The Blue Ghost lander is targeting a landing site near a volcanic structure called Mons Latreille. It is a 480-kilometer basin that sits in the northeast quarter of the near side of the moon.</p>
<p>The American space agency NASA says the 2-meter-tall Blue Ghost is carrying 10 NASA science and technology instruments. They aim to “gather valuable scientific data studying Earth's nearest neighbor,” the agency said.</p>
<p>NASA's Artemis program aims to send astronauts to the moon for the first time since the Apollo 17 mission in 1972. The next planned flight in that program is <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/mission/artemis-ii/">Artemis II</a>, which is set to launch in April 2026. In that mission, four astronauts will fly NASA's Orion spacecraft more than 400,000 kilometers on a trip around the moon.</p>
<p>Nicola Fox is the associate administrator for NASA's Science Mission Directorate in Washington D.C. She said in a statement the agency's cooperation with private companies is “a critical part of bringing humanity back to the moon.”</p>
<p>Fox added that NASA chose the new experiments partly because of information learned from NASA's Apollo space program, which began in the 1960s. She said the current mission seeks to ensure “the safety and health of our future science instruments, spacecraft, and, most importantly, our astronauts on the lunar surface.”</p>
<p>Blue Ghost's equipment includes a tool to collect dirt and another to dig a hole for measuring temperatures below the lunar surface. The spacecraft is also carrying a device built to measure light <strong>reflections</strong> to be used with lasers to better measure the distance between Earth and the moon.</p>
<p>In addition, Blue Ghost is carrying instruments to examine the structure and density of areas beneath the lunar surface. Other equipment will seek to capture X-ray images of the edge of Earth's magnetic field.</p>
<p>The ispace lander Resilience is carrying an exploring vehicle, called a rover, to the moon. The five-kilogram rover is designed to collect lunar soil and other materials from the surface.</p>
<p>Resilience is also <a class="wsw__a" href="https://ispace-inc.com/news-en/?p=6795">carrying equipment and instruments</a> to complete several experiments for Japanese companies and other organizations. One of the experiments will test an <strong>electrolysis</strong> device designed to separate water into hydrogen and oxygen. Such a device could help future astronauts better use water resources on the moon and produce rocket fuel.</p>
<p>Other experiments set for the Resilience mission include food production tests and the deployment of a “deep space radiation probe.” The instrument is designed to collect detailed measurements of <strong>ionizing</strong> radiation in space.</p>
<p>NASA has said it is paying $101 million to Firefly for the mission and another $44 million for the experiments. Officials from ispace did not report how much its mission would cost.</p>
<p>It is the second moon mission for ispace. During the last one, Japan's space agency JAXA successfully launched its SLIM spacecraft to the moon in January 2024. But the lander touched down imperfectly, causing some communication and power problems.</p>
<p>However, Japanese space officials reported they had stayed in communication with SLIM through late April. During this time, they said the spacecraft was able to collect valuable data about the landing and surrounding area.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from NASA, The Associated Press and Agence France-Press</em></p>
<p><strong>______________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>mission </strong><em>– n. (space exploration) </em>the flight of a spacecraft to its target along with tasks expected to be carried out</p>
<p><strong>lunar </strong><em>– n. </em>of, relating to, or resembling the moon</p>
<p><strong>reflect </strong><em>– v. </em>if a surface reflects heat, light, etc., it sends the light, etc. back and does not absorb it</p>
<p><strong>electrolysis </strong><em>– n. </em>use of an electric current to cause chemical change in a liquid</p>
<p><strong>ionize</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v. </em>to cause to form an ion: an atom or small group of atoms that has an electrical charge because it has added or lost one or more electrons</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Knee Jerk and Gut Reactions: When We Are Not in Control  (2025/1/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/knee-jerk-when-you-are-not-in-control.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>In life, some of our decisions and actions are well thought out. They involve research, examination, and time for thought. And other decisions and actions are not well thought out. We make them quickly, without thinking, almost like a pure physical reaction.</p>
<p>We can call these decisions, actions or reactions <u>knee-jerk</u><strong>.</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Liberty Barros holds her Guinness World Records' certificate for achieving the fastest 20-meter back bend knee-lock walk in 22.53 seconds, in London, Britain, November 10, 2022. (REUTERS Photo/Maja Smiejkowska)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/000b0000-0aff-0242-eba6-08dac35060f3_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Liberty Barros holds her Guinness World Records' certificate for achieving the fastest 20-meter back bend knee-lock walk in 22.53 seconds, in London, Britain, November 10, 2022. (REUTERS Photo/Maja Smiejkowska)</span></div>
<p>This term comes from a medical process. Meriam Webster defines the noun "knee jerk" as “an <strong>involuntary </strong>forward kick produced by a light blow on the tendon below the kneecap.” It is an involuntary action. It's <strong>automatic.</strong></p>
<p>The words “involuntary” and “automatic” are important when understanding the term “knee jerk” and when to use it. Knee-jerk reactions seem to happen automatically without a decision-making process.</p>
<p>We often use “knee jerk” as an adjective.</p>
<p>Like hitting your kneecap to move your leg, knee-jerk reactions or statements also seem like an involuntary <strong>reflex</strong>.</p>
<p>"Knee jerk" also describes predictable<strong> </strong>behavior. Again, hit the knee, the leg will kick every time. So "knee jerk" describes someone who always reacts quickly and without enough thought.</p>
<p>For example, let's say you are on a team with someone who never faces responsibility for their mistakes in the game. If brought to account, the player always blames the dropped ball on other teammates. You can say that player is having a knee-jerk reaction to criticism. They have a <u>go-to</u> response. It's like a reflex they can't control.</p>
<p>We often use knee-jerk in a criticizing or <strong>negative </strong>way.</p>
<p>Now, a <u>gut reaction</u> also happens without thinking. But it is a bit different than a knee-jerk response. A gut reaction is a feeling. When we have a gut reaction, our <strong>instincts </strong>are telling us that something may not be right. Gut reactions are instinctual warnings.</p>
<p>So, we also use this expression a bit differently than "knee jerk." We usually talk about our own gut reactions or impulses, not others.</p>
<p>Here is an example:</p>
<p>One day, I was hiking on a mountain in California. I had hiked for about two hours and was near the top. The view, I was told, was truly beautiful. I couldn't wait to see it! Then, suddenly, I had a strange feeling. Something just didn't feel right. I can't explain why, but my gut instinct was to turn around and head back down the mountain. I later found out that a dangerous bear had been sighted in the same area that I had fled. I am so thankful I listened to my gut instinct.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Words and Their Stories</em>. Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>__________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>involuntary </strong><em>-adj. </em>not normally under the control of the will</p>
<p><strong>automatic</strong> <em>-adj.</em> largely or wholly involuntary :acting or done without conscious thought or intention</p>
<p><strong>reflex </strong><em>-n. </em>an automatic response to a stimulus in which a nerve message passes from a sense organ to the spinal cord and then to a point of action (as a muscle or gland) often without first passing to the brain</p>
<p><strong>negative </strong><em>-adj. </em>not positive or helpful</p>
<p><strong>instinct </strong><em>-n. </em>behavior that is based on automatic actions</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>The Inauguration of the US President Through Time  (2025/1/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/the-inauguration-of-the-us-president-through-time.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>On January 20, the United States president is sworn into office in Washington D.C.</p>
<p>The inauguration is an important ceremony that officially marks the start of an administration. As part of the event, the incoming president speaks to the nation and announces U.S. policy goals.</p>
<p>This year, expanded security measures will stretch across much of Washington. The city's mayor, Muriel Bowser, announced major street closures and special transportation measures to increase security during inauguration events.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Security fencing surrounds Capitol Hill as snow blankets the region ahead of a joint session of Congress to certify the votes from the Electoral College in the presidential election, in Washington, Monday, Jan. 6, 2025. (AP Photo/J. Scott Applewhite)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/15bad3a6-524d-44d4-8c40-b9fd009973b9_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Security fencing surrounds Capitol Hill as snow blankets the region ahead of a joint session of Congress to certify the votes from the Electoral College in the presidential election, in Washington, Monday, Jan. 6, 2025. (AP Photo/J. Scott Applewhite)</span></div>
<p>The Associated Press reports Washington D.C.'s National Guard will deploy 7,800 soldiers to help with security. The Secret Service is reportedly under additional pressure because of two attempts on the life of incoming President Donald Trump last year. In one of those attempts, Trump received minor injuries.</p>
<p>The Library of Congress has saved many historical documents and objects from past ceremonies. Here are some facts and firsts about U.S. presidential inaugurations:</p>
<p><strong>Inaugural firsts: </strong></p>
<p>George Washington did not take the <strong>oath </strong>to become the first U.S. president in January nor was the event held in Washinton, D.C. His first inaugural <strong>address </strong>was given to a joint session of Congress gathered in Federal Hall in New York City, on April 30, 1789. New York City was the nation's first capital.</p>
<p>Washington began a tradition that stood for many years of kissing The Bible after taking the oath of office. The Museum of the Bible <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.museumofthebible.org/book-minute/washingtons-inauguration" target="_blank">says</a> on its website that four other presidents – Warren Harding,</p>
<p>Dwight Eisenhower, Jimmy Carter and George H. W. Bush – used Washington's Bible in their ceremonies. Bush had hoped to use Washington's Bible for his first inauguration in 2001, but weather delayed shipping so he ended up using a family Bible instead.</p>
<p>Washington's second inaugural address set another mark: it was the shortest at 135 words.</p>
<p>For 144 years, the inauguration was not held in the winter, but mostly in March.</p>
<p>John Adams, the nation's second president, was the first to receive the oath from the Chief Justice of the U.S. Supreme Court. His swearing in took place in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, the nation's second capital.</p>
<p>Thomas Jefferson was the first president to be inaugurated in Washington, D.C. He walked to and from the ceremony instead of riding in a <strong>carriage</strong>. The U.S. Marine Band played at the event for the first time and has done so in every ceremony since.</p>
<p>In 1825, John Quincy Adams, son of John Adams, broke with tradition. He was the first president to long wear pants instead of traditional shorter pants with stockings. The man who replaced Adams, Andrew Jackson, was the first to receive the oath on the East Portico of the Capitol Building. John Quincy Adams refused to attend.</p>
<p>In 1837, Martin Van Buren was the first of a new generation of presidents to not have British ancestry. His parents were Dutch and he was born a citizen of the United States.</p>
<p>William Henry Harrison set an unhappy first: On Inauguration Day in 1841, he gave the longest-ever speech without wearing warm clothes. He became sick and died weeks into his term.</p>
<p>Abraham Lincoln gave his first inaugural speech surrounded by heavy security as the nation neared war between the North and South. His second address, in 1865, was shortly after the end of the U.S. Civil War. He urged Americans “With <strong>malice</strong> towards none; with <strong>charity</strong> for all” to “<strong>bind up</strong> the nation's wounds.” In 2009 and 2013, Barrack Obama took his oath on Lincoln's Bible.</p>
<p>In 1909, William Howard Taft's inauguration was notable for taking place inside the Senate Chamber because of a huge snowstorm. It took about 6,000 men to clear snow for the parade.</p>
<p>The inaugural ceremony of Calvin Coolidge in 1925 was the first to be broadcast on radio. And the first president to have a televised inaugural ceremony was Harry Truman in 1949.</p>
<p>Franklin D. Roosevelt's second inauguration was the first to take place on January 20th. The 20th Amendment to the Constitution moved the event's date because of improved transportation methods.</p>
<p>In 1953, Dwight Eisenhower broke the tradition of kissing The Bible and instead gave a prayer.</p>
<p>Robert Frost was the first poet to every speak at an inaugural event. Frost <strong>recited</strong> his poem <em>The Gift Outright</em> for John Kennedy's 1961 swearing-in. Kennedy was the first Roman Catholic president. Joe Biden was the second.</p>
<p>After Jimmy Carter's inauguration, he and first lady Rosalynn Carter walked down Washington D.C.'s Pennsylvania Avenue to the White House instead of riding inside a car.</p>
<p>Ronald Reagan's inaugurations set two marks that may also never be equaled. At noon on Reagan's first inauguration, the temperature was nearly 13 degrees Celsius. That was the warmest Inauguration Day ever. Then, on his second in January 1985, the temperature was nearly minus 14 degrees Celsius – the coldest day ever for the event.</p>
<p>This year, January 20 will mark only the second time a U.S. president has been inaugurated for a second term that did not follow the first. Donald Trump first took the oath of office in 2017. He joins Grover Cleveland, who was inaugurated in 1885 and 1893. Cleveland is known as the 22nd and 24th President. Trump is set to be both the 45th and 47th President of the United States.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr. And I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted this story for VOA Learning English from Library of Congress materials. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>oath</strong> <em>–n.</em> a public promise by a government official to fulfill his or her duty</p>
<p><strong>address </strong><em>–n.</em> a speech before a lot of people for a major event in public life</p>
<p><strong>carriage</strong> <em>–n.</em> a vehicle with wheels that is pulled by horses</p>
<p><strong>malice</strong> <em>–n.</em> a desire to cause harm to others</p>
<p><strong>charity</strong> <em>–n. </em>the willingness to give to others with a good heart</p>
<p><strong>bind up </strong><em>–v. (phrasal)</em> to wrap a wound in cloth or a bandage so it will heal</p>
<p><strong>recite</strong> <em>–v.</em> to give a speech or reading of a written work from memory and not to read it</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What Is Art Deco and Why Is It Popular Again?  (2025/1/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/what-is-art-deco-and-why-is-it-popular-again.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Art Deco is an international artistic <strong>style</strong> that was popular in the 1920s and 1930s.</p>
<p>Now, interest in the style and its qualities is growing. A new generation is enjoying the style's roots and turning it into something new.</p>
<p>A public showing, or exhibition, at the Museum of the City of New York provides a look at the style that helped define the city 100 years ago.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt=" This image provided by the Museum of the City of New York shows a postcard featuring the Empire State Building, from left, the RCA Building, and the Chrysler Building. (Museum of the City of New York via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/109dd6c2-c5fb-4357-ac6b-7c78d81c96af_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption"> This image provided by the Museum of the City of New York shows a postcard featuring the Empire State Building, from left, the RCA Building, and the Chrysler Building. (Museum of the City of New York via AP)</span></div>
<p>Famous Art Deco buildings include the Chrysler Building, the Empire State Building, Rockefeller Center and Radio City Music Hall.</p>
<p>The public showing, called “Art Deco City: New York Postcards from the Leonard A. Lauder Collection,” also has clothing and film clips from the time.</p>
<p>In London, the Victoria and Albert Museum has a collection of day and evening clothing, jewelry and more. The collection comes from Les Ballets Russes, a dance company that had a major effect on <strong>fashion</strong>.</p>
<p>And in Paris, organizers of the 2024 Olympics created Art Deco <strong>posters</strong> last year to celebrate the games and mark the one hundred years since the 1924 Olympics, which Paris also hosted.</p>
<p><strong>A style of the 1920s and 30s </strong></p>
<p>Experts have different opinions about Art Deco. Design writer Arricca Elin Sansone, for example, said last year in Elle Décor magazine: “Ask three historians to define the term Art Deco, and you'll likely get three <strong>varying</strong> answers.”</p>
<p>Appearing after World War I, the first Art Deco era had a spirit of creativity and freedom. With the aim of appearing modern, the style became one of the most important forms of design in the 1920s and early 1930s.</p>
<p>The Art Deco style is believed to have first appeared at the 1925 International Exhibition of Modern Decorative and Industrial Arts, in Paris.</p>
<p>The early 1930s saw the development of the style in Miami where South Beach's Art Deco District is popular with visitors and a center for design.</p>
<p>In some large cities, low-rise buildings of two or three floors turned into landscapes of high-rise skyscrapers. Public and private spaces showed <strong>themes</strong> involving geometrical designs and luxurious materials.</p>
<p>In transportation, faster cars and better trains suggested a new age while jazz music urged people to celebrate.</p>
<p><strong>“A fashionable renaissance” </strong></p>
<p>The same energy can be found in today's fashion shows and red-carpet events for stars. Some of today's colorful clothing suggests the Jazz Age, another name for the period when Art Deco was popular. Stars like Zendaya, Gigi Hadid, Beyoncé and Demi Lovato have used elements of the Deco era in new ways.</p>
<p>“The aesthetic of the 1920s is enjoying a fashionable renaissance,” said Kirsty Thatcher of the Australian fashion magazine Russh. A “renaissance” represents a rebirth of something from the past.</p>
<p>New York-based interior designer Vanessa DeLeon told the Associated Press, “The boldness and elegance of Art Deco are what appeals to me.”</p>
<p>Jamie Watkins and Tom Kennedy of the London design company Divine Savages include Art Deco elements in their collections of products for the home. Watkins suggested: “It's no wonder we're drawn to it again.”</p>
<p>Lynda Klich is the co-organizer or curator of the exhibition at the Museum of the City of New York. Klich noted that postcards were the social media of their day. Travelers at the time busily wrote messages to friends and family. New York's famous Art Deco buildings appear in over 250 postcards. There is also a selection of clothing from the 1920s, shoes and other objects.</p>
<p>“Art Deco was the look that sold the city to the world,” said co-curator Lilly Tuttle.</p>
<p>The exhibition in New York City runs through February 17.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Kim Cook reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>style </strong><em>–n. </em>a particular form of design that is repeated through a period because it is popular</p>
<p><strong>fashion </strong><em>– n.</em> the popular or dominant style (as in clothing or dress) during a particular time</p>
<p><strong>poster</strong> <em>–n.</em> a large picture that is often used to advertise for a show or movie</p>
<p><strong>vary</strong> <em>– v. </em> to have or show differences between items or things</p>
<p><strong>theme </strong><em>– n.</em> a special quality or characteristic; a subject or topic of artistical representation</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Apply and Application  (2025/1/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/apply-and-application.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Krystyna in Poland. Here is Krystyna's question:</p>
<p><em>Dear Teacher,<br/>
I would like to know of different ways to use words such as “apply” and “application” for getting jobs or other purposes.</em></p>
<p><em>Thank you, </em><em>Krystyna</em><em>.</em></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Ask a Teacher: Apply and Application" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/2ca81581-0bba-4ddd-b3f5-fd0855406dac_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Ask a Teacher: Apply and Application</span></div>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Krystyna.</p>
<p>The word “apply” is a verb, and the word “application” is a noun. We can use both words when discussing the process of looking for a job.</p>
<p>We say we “apply for a job” when we go through the official process of asking an employer for work. To do this, we usually have to complete a job application. The application is a <strong>form</strong>, either online or on paper, that gives the employer information about the person applying for the job.</p>
<p>We commonly use the phrasal verb “fill out” to express the act of completing an application. Consider the following examples:</p>
<p><em>You must fill out this application first. </em></p>
<p><em>Did you fill out the application?</em></p>
<p>While we say “apply for” when trying to get a job, we say “apply to” when we are trying to get accepted into a school or other program, as in the following example:</p>
<p><em>She applied to three medical schools in California. </em></p>
<p>However, we say “apply for” when we are trying to get financial aid or special awards.</p>
<p>The expression “apply to” also has another meaning. It can mean that something relates to something else, or that something is true for all people or things. Listen to the following examples:</p>
<p><em>The new rule only applies to people who work more than 40 hours each week.</em></p>
<p><em>The right of freedom of speech should apply to all citizens. </em></p>
<p>The word “application” has other meanings besides a form people fill out. Among these is a computer program that does a specific task, or kind of work. From this meaning, we get the term “Apps,” which we use in our smartphones and computers.</p>
<p>There also is another expression with the verb “apply.” If you “apply yourself,” that means that you are working hard over a period of time to complete a project or develop a skill.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? Are you applying yourself to your study of English? We want to hear from you! Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please let us know where you are from, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.<em> </em></p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>form </strong>–n. a document or application that people add information to for official use</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>People in China Swim in Freezing River for Health, Happiness  (2025/1/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/people-in-china-swim-in-freezing-river-for-health-happiness.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the Health &amp; Lifestyle report.</p>
<p>Even as temperatures kept dropping in China's northeastern “ice city” of Harbin, excitement rose among a group of swimmers who enjoy jumping into freezing waters.</p>
<p>The daily event, known as ice swimming, is a winter tradition in Harbin. Swimmers train daily throughout the year to get their bodies ready for the unusual swim. Reporters from The Associated Press recently visited the city and spoke with some of the swimmers.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A woman jumps into a pool cut from the ice on the Songhua River in Harbin in northeastern China's Heilongjiang province, Tuesday, Jan. 7, 2025. (AP Photo/Andy Wong)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/6d1a4494-79e3-42ba-ab34-b82c042182c8_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A woman jumps into a pool cut from the ice on the Songhua River in Harbin in northeastern China's Heilongjiang province, Tuesday, Jan. 7, 2025. (AP Photo/Andy Wong)</span></div>
<p>To create a pool in the Songhua River, the swimmers first had to break a 10-centimeter thick cover of ice. Then they removed the ice pieces, took off all clothes except bathing suits and prepared to enter. One by one, they jumped into a freezing, 10-meter-long pool.</p>
<p>Some of the swimmers reported that their legs and arms quickly went <strong>numb</strong> after entering the water. The outside temperature was about minus 13 degrees Celsius and the water temperature remained near freezing.</p>
<p>One of the swimmers was Chen Xia. She came from Zhejiang province about 1,700 kilometers <strong>further </strong>south. She decided to jump into the river even though she had a cold. Chen said the winter waters where she lives are warmer than those in Harbin.</p>
<p>She said the experience strengthened her <strong>confidence</strong> in winter swimming. She has been taking part in the activity for about 20 years.</p>
<p>The 56-year-old Chen said the freezing waters made her skin feel like small <strong>pins </strong>were attacking her body. But, she added that the experience still brought her happiness. “I felt <strong>prickling</strong> all over my body. But it still made me feel <strong>blissful,</strong>” she said.</p>
<p>Yu Xiaofeng lives in Harbin, a city that sits near the border with Russia. The 61-year-old said winter swimming in the city dates back to the 1970s. At that time, locals saw Russian Orthodox religious believers being <strong>baptized </strong>in the river. Later in 1983, an official winter swimming group was established in Harbin.</p>
<p>The city also holds an ongoing winter celebration known for its huge, detailed ice and snow <strong>sculptures.</strong></p>
<p>Winter swimming is considered a sport in China. But it gained popularity much faster in Harbin than in other parts of the country. Today, Yu said the city is considered a “holy land” for winter swimming.</p>
<p>Yu said the winter swimmers appear to have better health than others. She added that she has felt a great sense of family and joy in the community during her 30 years of winter swimming.</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" name="_Hlk187425130">While the AP reporters did not <strong>quote</strong> medical experts for this story, some of the swimmers said they believe ice swimming is good for their health. During the COVID-19 pandemic, the group even came up with a new saying to describe the experience. They would rather “suffer through winter swimming than line up at the hospital,” Yu said. </a></p>
<p>You Decang is a 76-year-old winter swimmer who said he believes the activity helps keep him healthy. He noted that he has never caught a cold. You added, “If I go just one day without winter swimming, I feel quite <strong>uncomfortable</strong>.”</p>
<p>And that's the Health &amp; Lifestyle report. I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Andy Wong reported this story for The Associated Press. Olivia Zhang and Caroline Chen contributed to this report. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>numb </strong><em>–v. </em>to cause (a part of the body) to lose sensation</p>
<p><strong>further </strong><em>–adj.</em> going or extending beyond</p>
<p><strong>confidence </strong><em>-n. </em>a feeling or consciousness of one's powers or of reliance on one's circumstances</p>
<p><strong>pin </strong><em>–n. </em>a piece of wood, metal, or plastic used especially for fastening things together or for hanging one thing from another</p>
<p><strong>prickling</strong> <em>–v. </em>to cause or feel a slight stinging or tingling sensation : <strong>prickle</strong> <em>–n. </em>a tingling sensation</p>
<p><strong>blissful </strong><em>–adj.</em> full of, marked by, or causing complete happiness</p>
<p><strong>baptize </strong><em>–v. </em>to dip in water or sprinkle water on as a part of the ceremony of receiving into the Christian church</p>
<p><strong>sculpture </strong><em>–n. </em>a three-dimensional work of art (such as a statue)</p>
<p><strong>quote </strong><em>–v. </em>to speak or write (a passage) from another usually with credit acknowledgment</p>
<p><strong>uncomfortable </strong><em>–adj.</em> feeling discomfort</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>European and Japanese Spacecraft Examines Mercury’s Pole   (2025/1/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/european-and-japanese-spacecraft-examines-mercury-s-pole.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>A spacecraft recently sent back some of the best close-up pictures yet of the planet Mercury's north pole.</p>
<p>The European and Japanese robotic explorer went as close as 295 kilometers above Mercury's night side before passing directly over the planet's north pole.</p>
<p>The European Space Agency (ESA) released images that show craters with deep <strong>shadows</strong> on our solar system's smallest planet.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image provided by European Space Agency shows close-up photos of Mercury showing northern plains taken by the European-Japanese spacecraft BepiColombo. (European Space Agency via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1b134ccd-29d1-420d-ba79-2a92b79db447_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image provided by European Space Agency shows close-up photos of Mercury showing northern plains taken by the European-Japanese spacecraft BepiColombo. (European Space Agency via AP)</span></div>
<p><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.esa.int/Science_Exploration/Space_Science/BepiColombo/Top_three_images_from_BepiColombo_s_sixth_Mercury_flyby" target="_blank">ESA noted</a> that the edges, or rims, of the <strong>craters</strong> called Prokofiev, Kandinsky, Tolkien and Gordimer create permanent shadows. As a result, these unlit craters are some of the coldest places in the Solar System even though Mercury is the closest planet to the sun.</p>
<p>Cameras also took images of neighboring volcanic plains known as Borealis Planitia. <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.esa.int/Science_Exploration/Space_Science/BepiColombo/Top_three_images_from_BepiColombo_s_sixth_Mercury_flyby" target="_blank">ESA noted</a> that these are “Mercury's largest <strong>expanse</strong> of ‘smooth plains' and were formed by the widespread <strong>eruption</strong> of...lava 3.7 billion years ago.”</p>
<p>Also appearing in the images released by ESA is Mercury's largest impact crater, the Caloris Basin, which covers more than 1,500 kilometers.</p>
<p>This was the sixth and final flyby of Mercury for the BepiColombo spacecraft since its launch in 2018. The recent move put the spacecraft on a path to enter orbit around Mercury late next year. The spacecraft holds two orbiters, one from Europe and the other from Japan, that will circle the planet's poles.</p>
<p>In a statement <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.esa.int/Science_Exploration/Space_Science/BepiColombo" target="_blank">on its website</a>, ESA noted that Mercury, a small, dry planet, is “the least explored planet of the inner Solar System. Learning more about Mercury will<strong> shed light</strong> on the history of the entire Solar System.”</p>
<p>The spacecraft is named for the late Giuseppe (Bepi) Colombo, an Italian mathematician. Colombo played a part in NASA's Mariner 10 mission to Mercury in the 1970s and, 20 years later, in the Italian Space Agency's special satellite project that flew on the U.S. Space Shuttle.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Marcia Dunn reported this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>shadow </strong><em>– v. </em>to cast a shadow (a dark figure cast upon a surface when a body blocks the rays of a light)</p>
<p><strong>crater</strong> <em>– n.</em> a low area or depression formed by an impact</p>
<p><strong>expanse </strong><em>– n.</em> a great extent or distance of something that is spread out</p>
<p><strong>erupt</strong> <em>– v. </em>to force out or release suddenly (often lava or steam that is pent up)</p>
<p><strong>shed light </strong><em>–idiom </em>to expand or increase knowledge</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>AI Tools Drive Many New Products at the CES 2025 Electronics Show  (2025/1/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/ai-tools-drive-many-new-products-at-the-ces-2025-electronics-show.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>At this year's CES show in Las Vegas, Nevada, crowds from around the world came to see the latest products built with artificial intelligence (AI).</p>
<p>CES is produced by the Virginia-based Consumer Technology Association. It presents the latest electronic product offerings or <strong>features</strong>, targeting <strong>consumers</strong>. More than 138,000 people attended the event which ended last weekend.</p>
<p>More than 4,000 companies presented products at CES 2025. Here is a look at some of the top products shown at this year's 2025 show:</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="People attend the CES tech show Wednesday, Jan. 8, 2025, in Las Vegas. (AP Photo/John Locher)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/06541e25-8545-408e-8856-94495d91b3a3_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">People attend the CES tech show Wednesday, Jan. 8, 2025, in Las Vegas. (AP Photo/John Locher)</span></div>
<p><strong>Smarter TVs?</strong></p>
<p>CES is historically an event at which large electronics manufacturers introduce their latest and greatest televisions. This year was no different.</p>
<p>South Korean TV makers LG and Samsung both announced new smart models with built-in AI tools. Others – including Japan's Panasonic and China's Hisense and TCL – also released TV models with new AI tools.</p>
<p>Korean manufacturer LG <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.lg.com/global/mobility/media-center/press-release/lg-presents-its-latest-innovations-powered-by-affectionate-intelligence-at-ces2025">said</a> its latest models are equipped with AI technologies designed to <strong>autonomously </strong>improve picture brightness, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_vPy43zj4">sharpness</a> and sound quality. The AI improvements are powered by the company's own <em>a11</em> processer technology.</p>
<p>LG also announced new updates for its Magic Remote device controller, saying new AI tools were added to provide more detailed search and interactive possibilities with users.</p>
<p>Samsung introduced a system called Samsung Vision AI for its line of OLED and QLED TV models. The company <a class="wsw__a" href="https://news.samsung.com/global/samsung-electronics-unveils-samsung-vision-ai-and-new-innovations-at-first-look-2025-delivering-personalized-ai-powered-screens-to-enrich-everyday-life">said</a> the AI tools are meant to turn the TVs into more “intelligent” assistive devices and to help “simplify and <strong>enrich</strong> everyday living” for its users.</p>
<p>One example is a feature that permits users to click on different <strong>screen</strong> elements to receive immediate information about what they see. The company said another tool makes it possible to activate live language <strong>translations</strong> on-screen.</p>
<p><strong>Transport and personal robots</strong></p>
<p>Several companies at CES introduced robotic transport vehicles designed to travel over many kinds of surfaces or <strong>terrain</strong>.</p>
<p>One model was built by Kubota, a Japanese maker of farm and building equipment. The company demonstrated how the KATR four-wheeled robot uses <strong>hydraulics</strong> to control the vehicle's four legs independently. This design seeks to keep the robot secure and level even when working on hills or in rocky areas.</p>
<p>Kubota says the vehicle – which is able to carry loads up to 240 kilograms – is small enough to be transported in most pickup trucks.</p>
<p>Chinese developer Unitree Robotics showed off a dog-like robot model called Go2. The robot was designed with a series of cameras, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_snKF8D5S">sensors</a> and AI tools. The company says this permits Go2 to make smooth movements and automatically follow its owner. It is able to carry small loads on its back and can also be used in security operations involving businesses or individuals.</p>
<p>Demonstrations at CES showed Go2 doing tricks, like standing on two legs, dancing and giving high fives to visitors. The company produces several other dog-like models, as well as <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.unitree.com/h1">humanoid robot</a>s.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p><strong>Aircraft carrier vehicle</strong></p>
<p>The latest flying car designs are also a yearly favorite at CES. But this year, Chinese automaker XPENG took its presentation a step further by introducing a combination truck and flying vehicle.</p>
<p>The company calls the system a Land Aircraft Carrier. It includes a large transport van with enough space to transport a <strong>vertical </strong>landing flying vehicle inside. The idea is for users to be able launch the flying vehicle from anywhere the van can go. The flying car is fully autonomous and can carry two people at a time.</p>
<p>Chinese media reported the company – which also offers several traditional vehicles on its website – plans to sell the combination for about $300,000. XPENG said it will aim to increase production for all its vehicles in the coming year.</p>
<p><strong>Self-charging vehicle</strong></p>
<p>California-based Aptera Motors demonstrated a new electronic vehicle model with a built-in <strong>charging </strong>system. The company <a class="wsw__a" href="https://aptera.us/vehicle/#innovation">explains</a> on its <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_qo7S5aBu">website</a> that the vehicle has solar panels on its surface to capture energy from the sun. When charged this way, Aptera claims the car can travel up to 64 kilometers in a single day without being plugged in to a power source. On a full charge, the company says the vehicle can travel up to 640 kilometers.</p><p><strong>Salt enhancing spoon</strong></p>
<p>Japanese drink producer Kirin Holdings introduced <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.kirinholdings.com/en/newsroom/release/2024/1225_02.html">a new product</a> that aims to strengthen, or enhance, the taste of salt in food products without increasing the amount of salt. The spoon-shaped device uses electricity to increase saltiness. The company <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.ces.tech/ces-innovation-awards/2025/electric-salt-spoon/">says</a> the tool – which can be taken anywhere – sends a weak electric current through the top of the device to food.</p>
<p><strong>Power-assisted skis</strong></p>
<p>French electric sports equipment maker SQ-Motors presented an all-terrain electric board that can move on roads and snow. The company calls its invention the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.sq-motors.com/store/p/sternboard">Sternboard</a>. It is a three-wheeled board with an electric motor in the back.</p>
<p>First designed to be an electric skateboard, a version was developed to move on snow. The powered boards have reached speeds of more than 60 kilometers per hour in tests.</p>
<p>But the snow versions are not designed for speed. They seek to provide users with the ability to go up hills or move long distances over level land.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, AFP and online sources. </em></p>
<p><strong>_______________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>consumer </strong><em>– n. </em>a person or group which buys products for personal use and not for business</p>
<p><strong>feature –</strong>n. a quality of a product that its manufacturer wants possible buyers to know about</p>
<p><strong>autonomous</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj.</em> able to do a task or job without assistance</p>
<p><strong>enrich </strong><em>– v. </em>to increase the quality of something</p>
<p><strong>screen </strong>–n. a flat device that shows electronic images or video</p>
<p><strong>translate </strong><em>– v. </em>to change words from one language to another</p>
<p><strong>terrain</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n. </em>a particular kind of land</p>
<p><strong>hydraulics </strong><em>– n. </em>a system that uses liquid to mechanically move or lift equipment or parts</p>
<p><strong>vertical </strong><em>– adj. </em>not flat but positioned up and down</p>
<p><strong>charge –</strong>v. to put electrical power into a power source, like a battery, to do mechanical or electronic work</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Greenland Holds Important Position in a Warming World  (2025/1/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/greenland-holds-important-position-in-a-warming-world.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Greenland is the world's largest island and a self-governed territory of Denmark. About 57,000 people live there, mainly along its coasts. Most of Greenland lies north of the Arctic Circle, under thick <strong>sheets</strong> of ice.</p>
<p>The island plays a large part in the weather experienced by billions of people every day and in climate changes around the planet, experts say.</p>
<p>American President-elect Donald Trump is expressing interest in buying Greenland from Denmark. He said something similar during his first term in office as well. The United States has a large military base on the island.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Greenland ExplainerFILE - An iceberg floats in the Scoresby Sund, on Sept. 12, 2023, in Greenland. (AP Photo/Chris Szagola, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/2bb09175-b438-481b-bd11-f4542312284a_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Greenland ExplainerFILE - An iceberg floats in the Scoresby Sund, on Sept. 12, 2023, in Greenland. (AP Photo/Chris Szagola, File)</span></div>
<p><strong>Greenland's valuable resources</strong></p>
<p>Geologists say Greenland has huge amounts of oil and natural gas below the ice and valuable elements known as rare earth minerals. Rare earth minerals are needed in communication technologies, including phones.</p>
<p>Most of these resources are trapped under Greenland's ice. However, warming temperatures in recent years have increased melting on the island. As more ice melts, some of these resources may become easier to reach.</p>
<p>Geoff Dabelko is a security and environment professor at Ohio University. He thinks other countries are becoming interested in Greenland because China is currently the supplier of more than half of the world's rare Earth minerals.</p>
<p><strong>Melting ice </strong></p>
<p>From 1992 to 2020, Greenland lost an average of 169 billion metric tons of ice each year, with losses reaching 444 billion metric tons in 2019.</p>
<p>Mark Serreze is director of the National Snow and Ice Data Center in Boulder, Colorado. He told The Associated Press that melting from Greenland will be a central issue through the 21st century. That is because melting ice adds to rising sea levels. Serreze noted that the amount of melting will likely increase in the future.</p>
<p>Greenland also serves as the engine for an important ocean current that influences Earth's climate in many ways, including storm activity. The current is called the Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation, or AMOC. The current is slowing down because more fresh water from Greenland's melting ice is entering the ocean, Serreze said.</p>
<p>A shutdown of the current could lead to long-term freezes in Europe and parts of North America.</p>
<p>“If this <strong>global</strong> current system were to slow <strong>substantially</strong> or even collapse . . .as we know it has done in the past — normal temperature and <strong>precipitation</strong> <strong>patterns</strong> around the globe would change <strong>drastically</strong>,” said climate scientist Jennifer Francis of the Woodwell Climate Research Center, a non-profit based in the American state of Massachusetts.</p>
<p>She added that the changes would have very damaging effects on farming and ecosystems.</p>
<p>As more ice melts, Greenland is also changing color from the white of ice to the blue and green of water and land. These darker colors hold more heat from the sun and can increase the speed of warming.</p>
<p>Greenland lies in between northern Canada, northern Europe, and Russia. That area may become more valuable to countries if melting in the Arctic Ocean continues to increase and more ships pass through the area.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Seth Borenstein wrote this story for The Associated Press. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>__________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>sheet </strong><em>-n. </em>a wide layer over the surface of something else</p>
<p><strong>global </strong><em>-adj. </em>referring to the whole world</p>
<p><strong>substantially </strong><em>-adv. </em>very much, greatly</p>
<p><strong>precipitation </strong><em>-n. </em>rain, snow, or other forms of water that falls from clouds</p>
<p><strong>pattern </strong><em>-n. </em>an event or shape that repeats in the same way</p>
<p><strong>drastically </strong><em>-adv. </em>very much, in an extreme way</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Students with Disabilities Praise Assistive Technology Using AI  (2025/1/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/students-with-disabilities-praise-assistive-technology-using-ai.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">14 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Assistive technology involves special equipment and computer software that is meant to help people with disabilities.</p>
<p>The latest assistive technology is being powered by artificial intelligence (AI), which might help many students who have difficulties with speaking, reading, writing, and working with language. Although many schools are struggling with how and where to use AI, some are welcoming AI <strong>applications</strong> for students with disabilities.</p>
<p>The U.S. Education Department requires schools to provide assistive technology to students with disabilities under the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act, a U.S. federal law.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Makenzie Gilkison sits in the lobby at Greenfield Central High School, Tuesday, December 17, 2024, in Greenfield, Indiana." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/9f3e5af8-c4c9-4a75-aaa6-ca1a3bfb5641_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Makenzie Gilkison sits in the lobby at Greenfield Central High School, Tuesday, December 17, 2024, in Greenfield, Indiana.</span></div>
<p>The Education Department has told school officials they must consider whether students need tools like text-to-speech and <strong>alternative</strong> communication devices. New rules from the Department of Justice also require schools and other government organizations to make apps and online <strong>content</strong> available to people with disabilities.</p>
<p><strong>Concerns about assistive technology</strong></p>
<p>However, there is concern about how to make sure that students using assistive technology are still learning.</p>
<p>Students can use AI to organize thoughts into an outline, <strong>summarize</strong> complex reading material, or even <strong>translate</strong> the works of William Shakespeare into today's English. A computer can read materials aloud for students who have vision and reading problems. More and more, those voices produced by machine sound closer to human voices.</p>
<p>Alexis Reid is an educational <strong>therapist</strong> in the Boston area who works with students with learning disabilities. Reid said, "I'm seeing that a lot of students are kind of exploring on their own, almost feeling like they've found a <strong>cheat code</strong> in a video game."</p>
<p>But Reid said it is far from cheating: "We're meeting students where they are."</p>
<p>Ben Snyder is a 14-year-old freshman from Larchmont, New York, who was recently told he has a learning disability. He has been increasingly using AI to help with homework. He sometimes uses AI to explain math problems.</p>
<p>He likes a program called Question AI. One day, he asked the program to help him write an outline for a book report. He finished the work in 15 minutes. Usually, it would have taken him an hour and a half to create the same outline. But he said he would not use AI to write the report. "That's just cheating," Ben said.</p>
<p>Paul Sanft is director of a Minnesota-based center where families can use assistive technology tools and borrow devices. He knows some people will use the technology to do the work they should be doing by themselves. “That's always going to happen," Sanft said. "But I don't think that's the biggest concern with people with disabilities, who are just trying to do something that they couldn't do before."</p>
<p>The U.S. National Science Foundation is providing financial support for AI research and development. One group receiving support is called the National AI Institute for Exceptional Education and is linked to the University of Buffalo in New York state. It is developing tools to help children with speech and language disabilities.</p>
<p>Venu Govindaraju is the director of the institute. He said speech-to-text technology is not as good at understanding children's voices, particularly if there is a speech problem. He said AI technology is not good at understanding children's handwriting either.</p>
<p><strong>The case of Makenzie Gilkison</strong></p>
<p>Makenzie Gilkison had trouble spelling words. The 14-year-old from near Indianapolis, Indiana, has a condition called <strong>dyslexia</strong>. It makes reading difficult. "I just <strong>assumed</strong> I was stupid," she said, thinking of her early grade school years.</p>
<p>Last year, Gilkison was named to the National Junior Honor Society, an organization that supports leadership and academic success among middle school students. She said she improved her school performance by using a special AI-powered <strong>chatbot</strong>, a word prediction program and other tools that read for her.</p>
<p>"I would have just probably given up if I didn't have them," she said.</p>
<p>In September, Makenzie's school system started using chatbots to help special education students in high school. She said teachers sometimes struggled to provide students with the help they needed. The students were happy when they heard about the program. Until recently, students needed to wait for someone to help them, unable to move ahead on their own.</p>
<p>"Now we don't need to wait anymore," she said.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p>And I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Heather Hollingsworth reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>application </strong>– <em>n</em>. a computer program that does a series of linked tasks</p>
<p><strong>content </strong>– <em>n. </em>materials such as writing, sound and video</p>
<p><strong>summarize </strong>– <em>v</em>. to make a shorter version of a piece of writing that includes important points</p>
<p><strong>translate </strong>– <em>v</em>. to change a piece of writing from one language into another</p>
<p><strong>therapist </strong>–<em>n</em>. a person who treats others using methods that do not include drugs or medical operations</p>
<p><strong>cheat code </strong>–<em>n</em>. a series of commands that can change the way a computer game operates</p>
<p><strong>dyslexia</strong> – <em>n</em>. a condition in the brain that makes it hard for a person to read, write, and spell</p>
<p><strong>assume</strong> – <em>v.</em> to think that something is true or probably true without knowing that it is true</p>
<p><strong>alternative</strong> – <em>adj</em>. not usual or traditional</p>
<p><strong>chatbot </strong>–<em>n</em>. a computer program designed to produce writing or speech that is similar to that of a human</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Historians Remember President Jimmy Carter’s Efforts to Aid Afghan Rebels  (2025/1/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/historians-remember-president-jimmy-carter-s-efforts-to-aid-afghan-rebels.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">14 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Many historians say U.S. President Ronald Reagan helped defeat the former Soviet Union and end the Cold War. Reagan's efforts included giving support to rebel groups fighting the Soviets in Afghanistan in the 1980s.</p>
<p>U.S. support for Afghan rebels began earlier under the administration of President Jimmy Carter. Carter ordered secret <strong>nonlethal</strong> aid to rebel groups six months before the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan. The Soviet Union invaded in December of 1979.</p>
<p>Carter worked on cooperation with the Soviet Union by seeking approval of the SALT II (Strategic Arms Limitation Talks) agreement on nuclear weapons. At the same time, his policies and statements pushed against Soviet goals.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="U.S., Ambassador to the USSR, Thomas Watson meets with Secretary of State Cyrus Vance, left, and President Jimmy Carter in the Oval Office of the White House in Washington, Jan. 4, 1980. (AP Photo/Dennis Cook)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/d0208aa8-6edc-4216-ad08-425f3ffdda68_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">U.S., Ambassador to the USSR, Thomas Watson meets with Secretary of State Cyrus Vance, left, and President Jimmy Carter in the Oval Office of the White House in Washington, Jan. 4, 1980. (AP Photo/Dennis Cook)</span></div>
<p>David Gibbs is a history professor at the University of Arizona. Gibbs said, “I think people's image of Carter as a deeply religious man, a deeply moral man, is very much influenced by the activities he's done after he left office. [But] he definitely...had a side that was very willing to use force, including nuclear weapons.”</p>
<p><strong>US aid to rebels</strong></p>
<p>A communist takeover in Afghanistan in April 1978 brought down the government of President Mohammad Daoud Khan.</p>
<p>In the summer of 1979, Carter signed a secret order known as a “presidential finding” that permitted the U.S. Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) to give nonlethal aid to rebels. The rebels were fighting Afghanistan's Soviet-supported communist government.</p>
<p>Carter's order stayed secret until the 1990s. It became known after several Carter administration officials, including former national security adviser Zbigniew Brzezinski, communicated its existence.</p>
<p><strong>The ‘Afghan Trap' </strong></p>
<p>Some historians have called Carter's plan to aid rebel groups the “Afghan Trap.”</p>
<p>They said the trap aimed to force the Soviets into a long war similar to America's fight in Vietnam during the 1960s and early 1970s.</p>
<p>In 1998, Brzezinski denied to the French magazine <em>Le Nouvel Observateur</em> that the Carter administration had a plan to get the Soviets into a long war in Afghanistan. However, he also called such a program “an excellent idea.”</p>
<p><strong>Other explanations of U.S. aid</strong></p>
<p>Conor Tobin is an historian at the University College Dublin in Ireland who has studied the Afghan Trap idea. He said most experts do not believe the aid was part of a plan to make the Soviets fight. Tobin said there is not enough evidence to support the Afghan Trap idea.</p>
<p>Tobin also said the Carter administration decided to first wait to see how the situation in Afghanistan would develop after the 1978 government overthrow. But that policy ended with the kidnapping and killing of U.S. Ambassador Adolph Dubs in February of the next year.</p>
<p>Brzezinski then ordered a new plan for Afghanistan. Tobin said Brzezinski asked an administration official to consider the question: “Should we help any <strong>insurgents</strong>?”</p>
<p>Tobin said U.S. government officials thought military aid to rebels would cause a strong Soviet reaction. This judgment led the Carter administration to give nonlethal aid instead.</p>
<p>“The decision-making process demonstrated <strong>caution</strong>, rather than an effort to <strong>induce</strong> an invasion,” Tobin wrote.</p>
<p>Tobin wrote <a class="wsw__a" href="https://academic.oup.com/dh/article-abstract/44/2/237/5699276?redirectedFrom=fulltext&amp;login=false">in an article</a>, “The Myth of the ‘Afghan Trap,'” about the concerns of U.S. officials. He said, instead of trying to push the Soviets into a fight, Brzezinski worried the Soviets would slowly expand their power in Afghanistan.</p>
<p>“The <strong>objectives</strong> in mid-1979 were essentially to do something, anything, to <strong>counter</strong> the Soviet advance in Afghanistan,” Tobin said.</p>
<p><strong>The Carter Doctrine</strong></p>
<p>In 1979, another development raised concerns<br/>
in Washington. Even if Carter did not want armed conflict in Afghanistan, he took a strong position against Soviet efforts to control the Persian Gulf. That body of water lies between Saudi Arabia and Iran, two major oil producers.</p>
<p>During a speech to the U.S. Congress in 1980, Carter warned that the U.S. was prepared to use “any means necessary” to prevent a Soviet takeover of the Persian Gulf area.</p>
<p>On December 28, 1979, the day after the Soviets invaded Afghanistan, Carter gave permission to supply weapons and training for the rebels.</p>
<p>Carter lost the 1980 election to Reagan who mostly continued Carter's Afghan policy for several years before greatly increasing the secret aid program. The aid reached several hundred million dollars a year, and the Soviet military left Afghanistan in defeat in 1989.</p>
<p>Jimmy Carter died at the age of 100 on December 29, 2024.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith. And I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Masood Farivar wrote this story for VOA News. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>__________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>nonlethal </strong>–adj. related to things that are not weapons with the ability to cause death</p>
<p><strong>insurgent </strong>–n. a person in rebellion against civil power or a government</p>
<p><strong>caution </strong>–n. concern or care when faced with a risky situation</p>
<p><strong>induce </strong>–v. to influence a person or group to act or to believe something</p>
<p><strong>objective </strong>–n. a goal or an aim</p>
<p><strong>counter </strong>–v. to act against a force, movement or person</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Advice on Successfully Keeping New Year’s Promises  (2025/1/14)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/advice-on-successfully-keeping-new-year-s-promises.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">13 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle Report</em>.</p>
<p>As the new year begins, some people see an opportunity for change and improvement.</p>
<p>Experts say January can be a good time to think about self-improvement. Many people make resolutions. But these promises we make to ourselves require effort to become part of our daily lives. They are meant to last a long time.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - The 2025 New Year's Eve numerals are displayed in Times Square, Wednesday, Dec. 18, 2024, in New York. (AP Photo/Julia Demaree Nikhinson, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/273d4048-06a1-4d7f-9bfa-5423c126d3dd_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - The 2025 New Year's Eve numerals are displayed in Times Square, Wednesday, Dec. 18, 2024, in New York. (AP Photo/Julia Demaree Nikhinson, File)</span></div>
<p>Studies have shown that up to 70 percent of people who make New Year's resolutions quit their plans within months.</p>
<p>Recently, experts gave advice on keeping New Year's resolutions to the Associated Press.</p>
<p><strong>Start small</strong><br/>
It is difficult to make big changes. Behavioral health experts suggest breaking big goals into smaller targets. For example, if your goal is to improve your health, you could start with small changes. For some meals, you could trade unhealthy foods for heathy ones, or you could exercise for 10 minutes each day.</p>
<p>Once you start reaching smaller goals, the bigger one might not seem so <strong>daunting</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Be realistic</strong><br/>
Psychologist Lynn Bufka suggests being realistic about resolutions. She is with the American Psychological Association based in Washington, D.C.</p>
<p>“It's quite daunting to say that you want to lose 50 pounds and thus, will never eat <strong>dessert</strong> again,” she said. “It might be more helpful to say, you're only going to have dessert<strong> </strong>on the weekends and for special <strong>occasions</strong>.”</p>
<p><strong>Mindset change</strong><br/>
Think about what your resolution is helping you to <strong>achieve</strong>. Do not think about what you are giving up. This can be a powerful way to change your mindset.</p>
<p>Bufka said that thinking <strong>positively</strong> about your end goal and the <strong>benefits</strong> of your changed behavior can increase your motivation, or drive to succeed.</p>
<p>Bufka gave this example. “If I put money in a jar for what I would have spent on chocolate every day, that starts to add up,” she explained.</p>
<p><strong>Make specific goals</strong><br/>
A study of New Year's resolutions published in 2020 found that people who pay attention to specific goals are more successful than those simply trying to give up bad <strong>habits</strong>.</p>
<p>In a group of more than 1,000 people, scientists found the most popular resolutions involved exercise, weight loss and eating habits. Other resolutions had to do with self-improvement, personal finance, and ways to take care of mental health and to reduce <strong>stress</strong>.</p>
<p>Among the 55 percent of people who said they had kept their resolutions after one year, nearly 60 percent of them had made resolutions involving goals. This is compared with 47 percent who chose to avoid behaviors.</p>
<p><strong>Involve other people</strong><br/>
Involving others in your efforts might also help. Other people can offer support and hold you <strong>accountable</strong>. When we are held accountable, we are responsible for our actions.</p>
<p>Someone who decides to start exercising more, for example, might join a running group or sign up for a gym class with friends. This can also make exercising more fun.</p>
<p><strong>Use technology</strong><br/>
Experts also suggest using planners to help you keep your resolutions. For example, you can plan your activities for a specific period every morning or evening.</p>
<p>Use reminders and timers on your smartphone. And use group texts for group activities.</p>
<p><strong>Be kind to yourself</strong><br/>
Changing our behavior is difficult, so do not expect <strong>perfection</strong>. There will be times when it feels impossible to keep your resolution, and you will want to give up.</p>
<p>“A great resolution might be, ‘I will be less judgmental with myself,'” said Tamara Russell of the British Psychological Society. “Research shows that the more we develop self-<strong>compassion</strong>, the more compassionate we can become towards others.”</p>
<p><strong>Review and make changes</strong><br/>
To better keep resolutions, Russell suggests reviewing each week. Ask yourself: what has worked? What has not?</p>
<p>She said, “Study your own behavior like a scientist.” Russell added that we should not be afraid to change our resolutions.</p>
<p><strong>Choose the right time</strong><br/>
The last piece of advice might be the most important.</p>
<p>If January 1 feels like a bad time to create a new resolution, make the changes when it makes sense for you.</p>
<p>Russell said it makes “no sense at all” to make resolutions connected to the <strong>calendar</strong> year. Winter is usually a time of rest for much of the natural world.</p>
<p>She said that spring is the season of growth and renewal. So, depending on your life's situation, spring might be a better time for most people to make changes.</p>
<p>And that's the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> <em>Report</em>. I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p>
<em>Maria Cheng reported this story for The Associated Press from New York City. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>daunting </strong><em>–adj.</em> something that causes people to lose confidence or to be afraid</p>
<p><strong>dessert </strong><em>–n.</em> a sweet food eaten at the end of the meal</p>
<p><strong>occasion </strong><em>–n.</em> an event or happening</p>
<p><strong>achieve </strong><em>–v.</em> to reach a goal or to complete a task</p>
<p><strong>positively </strong><em>–adv. </em>in a good way</p>
<p><strong>benefit </strong><em>–n.</em> a good result from an action or deed</p>
<p><strong>habit </strong><em>–n.</em> a repeated behavior that might be good or bad</p>
<p><strong>stress </strong><em>–n. </em>a state of worry or mental tension caused by a difficult situation</p>
<p><strong>accountable </strong><em>-adj.</em> to be held responsible</p>
<p><strong>perfection </strong><em>–n.</em> a state in which nothing is wrong, there is no error or mistake</p>
<p><strong>compassion </strong><em>–n.</em> a deep feeling of sympathy for others</p>
<p><strong>calendar </strong><em>–n.</em> a document that shows the day and months of the year from the start to the finish</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Doctors Concerned about Return of Iodine Deficiency  (2025/1/14)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/doctors-concerned-about-return-of-iodine-deficiency.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">13 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>A century ago, iodine deficiency affected children across much of the United States. The problem mostly disappeared during the 1900s after iodine was added to common foods. But doctors are now seeing higher iodine deficiency rates. The rises are blamed on dietary changes and new food manufacturing methods.</p>
<p><strong>What is iodine? </strong></p>
<p>Iodine is an element found in seawater and in some soils — mostly in coastal areas. A French chemist accidentally discovered the substance in 1811. Iodine's name comes from a Greek word meaning violet-colored.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Iodized salt is displayed for a photograph in Philadelphia on Monday, Jan. 6, 2025. (AP Photo/Jonathan Poet)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f2b3fb6f-94d1-471f-a5b5-f372b1965e46_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Iodized salt is displayed for a photograph in Philadelphia on Monday, Jan. 6, 2025. (AP Photo/Jonathan Poet)</span></div>
<p>Later in the 1800s, scientists began to understand that people need iodine to control their<strong> metabolism</strong> and stay healthy. The element is also important for a child's brain development.</p>
<p>One sign of iodine deficiency is an increase in size, or swelling, of the neck. This growth in the neck is known as a goiter. It can appear when the thyroid gland grows to make up for too little iodine to produce hormones that control certain body processes.</p>
<p>In the early 1900s, goiters were commonly seen in children in some parts of the United States. Some of the children showed other <strong>symptoms</strong> in addition to goiters. These included being smaller or experiencing deafness.</p>
<p><strong>Adding iodine to salt </strong></p>
<p>In the past, public health experts realized they could not solve the iodine deficiency problem by feeding everyone seaweed and seafood. But they learned iodine can be included with table salt.</p>
<p>This form of salt, known as iodized salt, first became available in 1924. By the 1950s, more than 70 percent of U.S. households used iodized table salt. Bread and some other foods also had iodine. As a result, iodine deficiency in the U.S. became rare.</p>
<p>But diets have changed over the years. Processed foods now make up a large part of the American diet. Although these foods contain a lot of salt, it is not iodized. Leading bread makers also no longer add iodine. And for people who do salt their food, it is popular now to use kosher salt, Himalayan rock salt or other products that do not contain iodine.</p>
<p>“People have forgotten why there's iodine in salt,” said Dr. Elizabeth Pearce of Boston Medical Center. She is a leader in the Iodine Global Network, a nongovernmental agency working to end conditions linked to iodine <strong>deficiency</strong>. Pearce noted there had been a reported 50 percent drop in U.S. iodine levels studied during the 1970s through the 1990s.</p>
<p><strong>How much iodine is enough? </strong></p>
<p>While most Americans are getting enough iodine through diet, doctors worry this is not the case for women and children – the two groups most likely to be hurt by iodine deficiency.</p>
<p>The American Academy of Pediatrics and other medical groups advise that all pregnant and breastfeeding women get 150 micrograms of iodine each day.</p>
<p>In the last 15 years or so, U.S. researchers have increasingly reported seeing mild iodine deficiency in pregnant women. A Michigan State University study of about 460 pregnant women found about 25 percent of them were not getting enough. That study's lead writer, Jean Kerver, noted that many vitamins for pregnant women do not contain iodine. As a result, doctors suggest that pregnant or breastfeeding women check <strong>labels</strong> to make sure the vitamins or supplements they take have iodine.</p>
<p>Some studies have linked even mild iodine deficiency to a lower score on an intelligence test known as an intelligence quotient (IQ) test. But experts say there has not yet been enough research to establish exactly how the U.S. population is being affected by iodine deficiency.</p>
<p>Dr. Monica Serrano-Gonzalez of Brown University said she and other doctors had seen five cases of iodine deficiency in children visiting a local health center in Providence, Rhode Island. “We're concerned this may be increasing, especially in patients with restricted diets.”</p>
<p>Serrano-Gonzalez called for increasing publicity about the problem in order to prevent it from getting worse. She said, “This needs to be on people's radar.”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Mike Stobbe reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>__________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>deficiency</strong> <em>– n.</em> a shortage of substances that are important or necessary for health</p>
<p><strong>metabolism </strong><em>– n.</em> all the chemical processes in the human body, especially the ones that use food</p>
<p><strong>symptom </strong><em>– n.</em> a physical feeling or problem that shows a person has a particular disease</p>
<p><strong>label<em> </em></strong><em>– n. </em>written or printed material placed on a product to give more information about its contents</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>NASA Says Spacecraft Made Closest-Ever Pass to Sun  (2025/1/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/nasa-says-spacecraft-made-closest-ever-pass-to-sun.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>NASA says a spacecraft that has been examining the sun's outermost atmosphere recently got closer to our Earth's star than any past explorer has.</p>
<p>The American space agency <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/science-research/heliophysics/nasas-parker-solar-probe-makes-history-with-closest-pass-to-sun/">announced</a> its Parker Solar Probe passed within 6.1 million kilometers of the sun's outer <strong>corona</strong> on December 24. Mission leaders established communication with the spacecraft after the operation and said the orbiter was safe.</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/us-space-agency-spacecraft-to-study-the-sun-up-close/4519399.html">NASA launched</a> the Parker Solar Probe in August 2018. Its mission is to study the sun's powerful corona and solar wind. Solar wind is created by a continuous flow of charged particles, called plasma, into space from the corona.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image made available by NASA shows an artist's rendering of the Parker Solar Probe approaching the Sun. (Steve Gribben/Johns Hopkins APL/NASA via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/971A6A95-9035-4350-A016-397FE05D7016_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image made available by NASA shows an artist's rendering of the Parker Solar Probe approaching the Sun. (Steve Gribben/Johns Hopkins APL/NASA via AP)</span></div>
<p>In 2021, NASA announced the orbiter had passed into the solar atmosphere for the first time. Researchers said at the time, the spacecraft had successfully “touched” the sun. Parker was believed to be about 13 million kilometers from the center of the sun when it crossed over into the sun's outer atmosphere.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p><a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/science-research/heliophysics/nasas-parker-solar-probe-makes-history-with-closest-pass-to-sun/">In a statement</a>, NASA's Associate Administrator Nicky Fox praised the spacecraft's latest pass-by of the sun. “Flying this close to the sun is a historic moment in humanity's first mission to a star,” she said. Fox leads the agency's Science Mission Directorate at NASA Headquarters in Washington, D.C.</p>
<p>The Parker Solar Probe is believed to have traveled at speeds up to 692,000 kilometers per hour during the mission. NASA said this was “faster than any human-made object has ever moved.”</p>
<p>Fox said she hopes data collected by the spacecraft can help scientists better understand how the sun behaves and influences other elements in our solar system and beyond. “By studying the sun up-close, we can better understand its <strong>impacts</strong> throughout our solar system, including on the technology we use daily on Earth and in space.”</p>
<p>Fox added that such studies can provide valuable information “about the workings of stars across the universe to aid in our search for <strong>habitable</strong> worlds beyond our home planet.”</p>
<p>NASA's statement noted the agency's earlier preparation and operations were all leading up to the latest mission. To help it get into the right position, the Parker Solar Probe received assistance from several <strong>flybys</strong> of the planet Venus. The last flyby happened on November 6, 2024.</p>
<p>These gravitational assists had put the spacecraft “an ideal distance” from the sun every three months, NASA explained. This distance was “close enough to study our sun's mysterious processes,” but not “to become <strong>overwhelmed</strong> by the sun's heat and damaging radiation.”</p>
<p>Developers of the spacecraft say it was built with a <strong>shield</strong> made with carbon material to protect it from the extreme heat released by the sun's corona. The shield was designed to survive temperatures reaching 1,400 degrees Celsius. NASA says the data-gathering instruments are placed behind the shield.</p>
<p>Nour Rawafi is the project scientist for Parker Solar Probe at NASA's Johns Hopkins Applied Physics Laboratory in Maryland. His team designed, built, and operates the spacecraft. He said Parker had performed as planned although it operates in “one of the most extreme environments in space.”</p><p>Rawafi added that the mission had brought “a new <strong>golden era</strong> of space exploration, bringing us closer than ever to unlocking the sun's deepest and most <strong>enduring</strong> mysteries.”</p>
<p>Dr. Joseph Westlake is director of NASA's <strong>Heliophysics</strong> Division, the part of the agency that studies the sun. Westlake noted that his team is preparing for more flybys in the future and hopes to capture more valuable data. Already, flybys of Venus have gathered information about the natural radio waves coming from Venus.</p>
<p>In 2023, scientists announced they had learned new information about solar wind from data collected by Parker. Data showed that solar wind can reach speeds up to 1.6 million kilometers per hour. Solar wind forms a large magnetic barrier known as the heliosphere. It protects Earth and other planets from the continuous flow of high-energy particles from the sun's corona.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Agence France-Presse and NASA. </em></p>
<p><strong>_______________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>corona </strong><em>– n. </em>the outer atmosphere of a star, such as the sun</p>
<p><strong>impact</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> the effect that a person, event or situation has on someone or something</p>
<p><strong>habitable </strong><em>– adj. </em>able to support life</p>
<p><strong>flyby </strong><em>–n.</em> a term used by space agencies to describe when a spacecraft uses the gravity of a planet to increase its speed or change direction</p>
<p><strong>overwhelm </strong><em>– v. </em>to produce an effect that is too strong or extreme</p>
<p><strong>shield</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n. </em>a large, flat object used for protection against dangerous or unpleasant things</p>
<p><strong>golden era </strong><em>– n. </em>a period during which something or someone was particularly successful, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_WN3tU6wB">good</a> or special</p>
<p><strong>endure </strong><em>– v. </em>to make it through a difficult time or situation</p>
<p><strong>heliophysics</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n. </em>relating to an area of space that is influenced by the sun or solar wind</p>
<p><strong>delve </strong><em>– v. </em>to examine something in detail to find information</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How Does Drinking Alcohol Affect Your Health?  (2025/1/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/how-does-drinking-alcohol-affect-your-health.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Past research suggested drinking alcohol in moderate amounts could be good for the heart. But a growing number of public health experts now advise people to limit alcohol intake as much as possible to improve health.</p>
<p>One of those experts is Dr. Timothy Naimi. He is with the Canadian Institute for Substance Use Research at the University of Victoria in British Columbia. Naimi told The Associated Press, "Drinking less is a great way to be healthier."</p>
<p>Earlier this month, U.S. Surgeon General Dr. Vivek Murthy called for changing his agency's existing health warning on alcoholic drinks to include cancer risks. Such a change would require approval from Congress.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Mixed drinks are displayed at a bar in Baltimore on Wednesday, Feb. 8, 2023. " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1bfcb880-8cfa-4038-8141-7fde340c1aa7_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Mixed drinks are displayed at a bar in Baltimore on Wednesday, Feb. 8, 2023. </span></div>
<p><strong>What is the harm in drinking alcohol?</strong></p>
<p>The Surgeon General's proposed change is linked to research suggesting that drinking alcohol raises the risk of several types of cancer – including colon, liver, breast, mouth and throat.</p>
<p>Alcohol breaks down in the body into a substance called acetaldehyde. This chemical can damage cells and stop them from repairing themselves. The process can create conditions for cancer to grow.</p>
<p>Naimi said estimates show thousands of U.S. deaths could be prevented each year if people followed government dietary guidelines on drinking alcohol. The guidelines advise men to limit themselves to two drinks or fewer per day and women to one drink or fewer per day. An example of one drink would be equal to one 12-ounce can of <strong>beer</strong>, a 5-ounce glass of <strong>wine</strong> or one serving of <strong>liquor</strong>.</p>
<p>U.S. Surgeon General Murthy noted there are about 100,000 alcohol-related cancer cases in the United States each year. And, about 20,000 alcohol-related cancer deaths are reported yearly. "As you consider whether or how much to drink, keep in mind that less is better when it comes to cancer risk," Murthy <a class="wsw__a" href="https://x.com/Surgeon_General/status/1875150696884084803">wrote</a> on the social media service X.</p>
<p><strong>What about limited drinking?</strong></p>
<p>Medical experts say the idea that moderate drinking can cause health improvements, or benefits, came from imperfect studies. The research compared groups of people based on how much they drank, with amounts usually measured at only one point in time. Since some earlier studies did not follow rules about what groups were measured, researchers say they did not effectively prove cause and effect.</p>
<p>Naimi said people who report drinking moderately generally have higher levels of education, higher earnings and better resources for health care. He explained that when those elements are considered, “The benefits <strong>tend</strong> to disappear."</p>
<p>Another problem, Naimi noted, was that most studies did not include younger people. Almost half of people who die from alcohol-related causes do so before the age of 50. Naimi said the studied groups did not effectively represent all drinkers. This likely created “an appearance” of a benefit for moderate drinkers that is not real, he added.</p>
<p><strong>What do international guidelines say?</strong></p>
<p>Health guidelines related to alcohol intake have wide differences from country to country. But the overall message today is that drinking less is better for health.</p>
<p>Britain, France, Denmark, Holland and Australia recently examined new evidence and lowered their guidelines for safe amounts of alcohol. Ireland plans to begin requiring cancer warnings on alcohol containers starting in 2026.</p>
<p>Carina Ferreira-Borges is an adviser on alcohol for the World Health Organization in Europe. She said scientists had changed their minds from earlier research. This is because more recent studies suggest drinking alcohol is linked “to over 200 health conditions, including cancers, <strong>cardiovascular</strong> diseases and injuries."</p>
<p>Naimi said, "The simple message that's best supported by the evidence is that, if you drink, less is better when it comes to health."</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Carla K. Johnson </em><em>reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>beer</strong> – <em>n</em>. an alcoholic drink made from malt and flavored with hops</p>
<p><strong>wine </strong>– <em>n</em>. an alcoholic drink made from the juice of grapes</p>
<p><strong>liquor</strong>– <em>n</em>. a strong alcoholic drink such as vodka or whiskey</p>
<p><strong>tend</strong> – <em>v</em>. to be likely to do a particular thing</p>
<p><strong>cardiovascular</strong> – <em>adj</em>. <em>medical</em>. of or relating to the heart and blood vessels</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>The Story of Jack Frost  (2025/1/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/the-story-of-jack-frost.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By
Anna Matteo<br/>
<span class="datetime">11 January, 2025</span><br/>
</span>
<p>Now, from VOA Learning English, it's time for Words and Their Stories.</p>
<p>If this is your first time with us, this program explores words and expressions commonly used in American English. We take a look at where they come from and how best to use them.</p>
<p>So, as winter officially comes to half the world, today we celebrate an expression that means winter is coming.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="Ice crystals cover glass in Detroit, Monday, Jan. 21, 2019. Falling temperatures replaced the weekend's falling snow Monday as bitter cold and gusty winds swept across the eastern United States. (AP Photo/Paul Sancya)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/64933768-3190-43e3-a8b0-1cc544caa6fc_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">Ice crystals cover glass in Detroit, Monday, Jan. 21, 2019. Falling temperatures replaced the weekend's falling snow Monday as bitter cold and gusty winds swept across the eastern United States. (AP Photo/Paul Sancya)</span></div>
<p>When temperatures drop and a <strong>cold snap </strong>comes, that means one thing: <strong>Jack Frost</strong> has arrived!</p>
<p>Jack Frost represents the coming of dark, cold days. He is the personification of winter, a human form of winter weather. So, when we say, “Jack Frost is nipping at your nose,” we mean that you feel the cold, icy effects of winter on your face.</p>
<p>When a frost or deep freeze comes, you had better <strong>bundle up</strong>! You should wear enough clothing to stay warm.</p>
<p>Now, Jack Frost does, indeed, bring the cold of winter. But he can also create beauty in nature. Some traditions claim that Jack Frost is responsible for leaving ice and snow on windows, trees, the ground...anywhere it will stick.</p>
<p>While we know frost is a natural event, it is fun to think that an imaginary creature named Jack Frost (or another name in some other cultures) changed the world into a <strong>winter wonderland</strong>!</p>
<p>That is what poet Hannah Flagg Gould (1789-1865) must have been thinking when she wrote a poem called The Frost.</p>
<p>Here are parts of that poem.</p>
<p>THE FROST looked forth, one still, clear night,</p>
<p>And he said, “Now I shall be out of sight; ...</p>
<p>Then he went to the mountain, and <strong>powdered</strong> its crest,</p>
<p>He climbed up the trees, and their <strong>boughs</strong> he dressed</p>
<p>With diamonds and pearls...</p>
<p><strong>A conversation</strong></p>
<p>With all of its beauty and extremes, winter is a great subject for songs and poetry. But now, let's listen to how we use these wintry expressions in conversation:</p>
<p>Brrr! It is freezing outside. This <strong>cold snap</strong> came out of nowhere!</p>
<p>I don't care how cold it is. I'm going on a hot date!</p>
<p>Is that all you're wearing? You need to <strong>bundle up</strong> or <strong>Jack Frost will be nipping at more than your nose</strong>!</p>
<p>I'll be fine. I'm wearing my new coat.</p>
<p>That it is NOT a winter coat. I mean, it looks great, but it's much too thin. You will <strong>catch a cold</strong>. I know. You can wear my new down coat. It keeps you warm up to minus 30 degrees Celsius!</p>
<p>I'm going on a date...not exploring the Arctic Circle! Thanks. But I am not wearing that big, thick black coat. Besides, the taxi will take me from door-to-door.</p>
<p>But what if something goes wrong? What if the car <strong>skids</strong> on the ice and is involved in an accident? You'll have to walk to the restaurant. You might <strong>freeze to death</strong>!</p>
<p>No, I won't. I'll just call an Uber to come and get me.</p>
<p>And what if that vehicle runs out of fuel? Then you'll have to walk to get more.</p>
<p>No, the Uber driver will. I'll just call another car.</p>
<p>What if that new Uber driver is a pregnant woman and she goes into labor? You'll have to help. You'll have to wait outside in the cold until help arrives! And the roads are already covered with five centimeters of snow! It could take the <strong>ambulance </strong>an hour to get to you! If you're wearing that thin coat...you'll<strong> catch your death</strong>!! The <strong>EMT</strong>s will find you <strong>frozen solid </strong>like a block of ice!!</p>
<p>Stop! Stop!! You win! Give me your coat!</p>
<p>Good decision.</p>
<p>Here's my ride ...</p>
<p>Don't forget gloves...a hat...and a scarf! Okay, good bye. Have fun!</p>
<p>And that's the end of this Words and Their Stories.</p>
<p>Until next time!</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p>Anna Matteo wrote this story for VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>_______________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>cold snap </strong>– n. a brief period of very cold weather</p>
<p><strong>nip </strong>– v. to injure or make numb with cold</p>
<p><strong>shiver </strong>– v. to shake slightly (as from cold or fear)</p>
<p><strong>wonderland </strong>– n. an imaginary place of delicate beauty or magical charm</p>
<p><strong>powdered </strong>– v. to sprinkle or cover with or as if with fine particles of something</p>
<p><strong>bough </strong>– n. a branch of a tree</p>
<p><strong>skid </strong>– v. to fail to grip the roadway</p>
<p><strong>ambulance </strong>– n. a vehicle equipped for transporting the injured or sick</p>
<p><strong>EMT </strong>– n. a person who is trained to provide emergency medical services to patients who are being taken to a hospital : short for Emergency Medical Technician</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Remaining, Remainder, and Rest of  (2025/1/11)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/remaining-remainder-and-rest-of.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">10 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Ann. Here is part of Ann's question:</p>
<p><em>Dear Teachers,<br/>
<br/>
I don't really understand the difference between "remaining," "remainder" and "rest" when using these words to describe what is left of something. </em></p>
<p><em>For example, . . . can I replace "the remaining countries" by "the remain" or "the rest"? </em></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Remaining, Remainder, and Rest of" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/7fec96d9-b0b6-44bf-b18e-0a0dc96e9647_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Remaining, Remainder, and Rest of</span></div>
<p><em>Thank you, Ann.</em></p>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Ann.</p>
<p>English has many words that share the same meaning or that are close in meaning. So, you might wonder why we usually use one word instead of another that is very similar to it.</p>
<p>We often use one word instead of another because of grammar. Let's look at how this works by considering the last part of your question. You asked:</p>
<p><em>can I replace "the remaining countries" by "the remain" or "the rest"? </em></p>
<p>The answer is no. That's because the word “remain” is a verb, and the term “the rest” is a quantifier. To describe the word “countries,” we need to use an adjective. The <em>-ing</em> ending on the word “remaining” makes it an adjective when we place it before a noun.</p>
<p>If you want to use the words “the rest” to describe a noun, you need to use four words. These four words are “the rest of the.” These four words mean the same thing as the two words “the remaining.” The following example shows this:</p>
<p><em>The rest of the countries use more land for farming.</em></p>
<p>Now let's look at the first part of your question:</p>
<p><em>I don't really understand the difference between "remaining," "remainder" and "rest" when using these words to describe what is left of something. </em></p>
<p>The word “remainder” is a noun, but when we use it to describe what is left of something, we change it to a quantifier. To do this, we usually say or write the four words “the remainder of the.” In this way, it works the same way as the quantifier “the rest of the.”</p>
<p>However, we use the quantifier “the rest of the” much more often, especially in spoken English, than “the remainder of the.”</p>
<p>Also, you should know that as a noun, “the remainder” is a term used in mathematics. It can mean the decimal fraction that remains when one number is divided by another number that is not one of its <strong>factors</strong>. For example, six-tenths, or .6, is the remainder when 33 is divided by five. It can also be what is left over from the process of subtraction.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? We want to hear from you! Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please let us know where you are from, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>__________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>factor </strong><em>–n. (math)</em> any of two or more numbers that, when multiplied, produce a product</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Danish-Swedish Farmdog Is American Kennel Club’s Newest Breed  (2025/1/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/danish-swedish-farmdog-is-american-kennel-club-s-newest-breed.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>The American <strong>Kennel </strong>Club, or AKC, has named another kind of dog to its registry.</p>
<p>Say hello to the Danish-Swedish farmdog. Or maybe say "hej," the word for hello in Swedish and Danish.</p>
<p>AKC officials announced the addition to its list on January 2. The recognition means the breed now may compete for many best in show prizes. It also will probably create wider interest in the small, lively dogs. Fans of the breed are happy for the honor, but some also worry about the effect increased attention will have on the dog.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image provided by the American Kennel Club shows a Danish-Swedish Farmdog, the latest dog in the American Kennel Club's lineup of recognized breeds. " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/2724a052-7bb3-4abc-9beb-6b1c8a2cb6e3_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image provided by the American Kennel Club shows a Danish-Swedish Farmdog, the latest dog in the American Kennel Club's lineup of recognized breeds. </span></div>
<p>Carey Segebart is one of the people who worked to get Danish-Swedish farmdogs recognized by the AKC. "We're excited about it. We're looking forward to it," she said. She plans to show one of her own at a dog show this month near her home in the American state of Iowa.</p>
<p>Still, she thinks more attention can have both good and bad results for the breed. "We don't want the breed to just explode too quickly," she said.</p>
<p>The Danish-Swedish Farmdog Club of America says the breed, DSF for short, goes back centuries in parts of what are now Denmark, southern Sweden and some other European countries.</p>
<p><strong>Fun little dogs</strong></p>
<p>"They're interesting, fun little dogs," said Segebart, who has owned them since 2011 and is the club's incoming president. She said they will try anything and “succeed at most everything."</p>
<p>In their homelands, the dogs' main job was to control small animals called rodents. However, they also can <strong>herd</strong>, act as watchdogs and be playful with children. The club says some Danish-Swedish farmdogs have even performed in <strong>circuses</strong>.</p>
<p>After Denmark and Sweden became more developed in the 20th century, DSF fans decided to make the breed official in both nations. Kennel clubs there began registering the breed in 1987.</p>
<p>In the United States, many of the about 350 Danish-Swedish farmdogs nationwide already compete in <strong>agility</strong>, obedience or other<strong> </strong>sports that are open to all dogs, including mixed breeds.</p>
<p>Until now, the dogs could not enter the traditional breed-by-breed judging that leads to best in show prizes at major dog shows. They may appear later this year at two major televised events, the National Dog Show and the AKC National Championship.</p>
<p>The Danish-Swedish farmdog is the AKC's 202nd breed and "a wonderful addition to a family that is able to provide it with the exercise and mental <strong>stimulation </strong>that it needs," said the AKC's Gina DiNardo.</p>
<p>Danish-Swedish farmdog lovers talked for several years about whether they should try to get AKC recognition and the attention that is likely to come with it, Segebart said. The number of people wanting to buy a young farmdog, or puppy, has grown quickly over the last ten years. The wait for a DSF puppy is usually a year or more, she said.</p>
<p>Fans of the breed worry that its appealing, relatively easy-care nature could make it quickly become too popular for its own good. They are not the first to worry. Similar concerns surround the French bulldog, which the AKC now says is the most popular breed in the country. Breeding for desired qualities has led to many health problems for the dogs.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins</p>
<p><em>Jennifer Peltz reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>kennel – </strong>n. a place where dogs or cats are kept while their owners are away; an establishment for the breeding or boarding of dogs or cats</p>
<p><strong>rodent </strong>– <em>n</em>. a small animal (such as a mouse, rat, squirrel, or beaver) that has sharp front teeth</p>
<p><strong>herd </strong>– <em>v</em>. to gather and move (a group of animals)</p>
<p><strong>agile </strong>– <em>adj</em>. able to move quickly and easily</p>
<p><strong>canine </strong>– <em>adj</em>. of or relating to dogs</p>
<p><strong>stimulate </strong>– <em>v</em>. to make (a living thing) excited or interested in something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Small Businesses Say US TikTok Ban Would Hurt Them  (2025/1/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/small-businesses-say-us-tiktok-ban-would-hurt-them.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>As the date nears for a possible U.S. ban on the video sharing service TikTok, some small companies are saying such a ban would hurt their business.</p>
<p>The U.S. Justice Department has <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/tiktok-asks-court-to-block-us-ban-seeks-us-supreme-court-hearing/7896146.html">ordered</a> TikTok's China-based parent, ByteDance, to sell the social media <strong>app</strong> by January 19 or face the ban. Lawyers for ByteDance and TikTok have sought legal action to temporarily block the Justice Department's order.</p>
<p>The Supreme Court is expected to consider the matter in January. President-elect Donald Trump, who takes office January 20, has asked the Supreme Court to delay a ban to permit solving the problem through “political means.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE PHOTO: Illustration shows TikTok app logo. (Reuters image)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/be5db508-d144-4fc7-b816-2ab0fdaaf4d2_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE PHOTO: Illustration shows TikTok app logo. (Reuters image)</span></div>
<p>U.S. officials have long warned that TikTok presents national security concerns. The government accuses ByteDance of sharing user data with China's government. Critics have said China could also use TikTok to spread misinformation and that material published on the service can harm the mental health of young users.</p>
<p>TikTok has repeatedly denied the accusations. The company has said it sees the app as an important tool to support Americans' right to free speech.</p>
<p>Industry experts have said a U.S. ban on TikTok could affect millions of small businesses that use the service to grow.</p>
<p>TikTok launched in the United States in 2016. Since then, many small business owners have been using it in different ways. These include marketing and advertising campaigns to introduce new products. Many companies also sell goods directly through the app.</p>
<p>TikTok's own estimates suggest small businesses currently using the service would lose more than $1 billion in revenue in a single month if the ban goes into effect.</p>
<p>One example of how TikTok can be used to quickly grow a business is the experience of Desiree Hill. She is the owner of Crown's Corner Mechanic in Conyers, Georgia.</p>
<p>She told the Associated Press that sharing videos of her work on TikTok helped spread the word online about her business. As a result, the app made her services so popular she was able to open her own shop with five employees 18 months ago.</p>
<p>“Every day I get at least two to three <strong>customers</strong> that have seen me on TikTok, watched my videos and wanted to become a customer,” Hill said.</p>
<p>If a ban on TikTok is established, many businesses would likely move to other services to reach customers. Instagram Reels, Snapchat and YouTube Shorts are three possibilities. Many small companies already use those apps. But business experts say it might be harder to get teens who have long used TikTok to start using other apps.</p>
<p>Another way for businesses to reduce the effects of a ban would be for them to build a strong base of customers who are willing to provide their contact emails or phone numbers. That permits owners to reach out directly to users with new offers and other marketing messages.</p>
<p>Hill, of Crown Corner Mechanics, worries that other services would not reach as many possible customers as TikTok. She said she is already using YouTube, Instagram and Facebook, but has not been getting the same results.</p>
<p>“I am worried because there is no preparation for this,” Hill told the AP. She added, “If I lose TikTok, I will lose a large part of my business or I will lose my ability to grow anymore.”</p>
<p>Crystal Lister uses TikTok for her business, called Mommy and Me: The Listers, in Cypress, Texas. The company offers <strong>interactive</strong> educational training in subjects including technology and science. Now, she is seeking to move her offerings to YouTube and Instagram Reels but says TikTok is easier to use.</p>
<p>“It is going to be a <strong>challenge</strong> if TikTok is banned because we're losing kind of all the <strong>functionality</strong> you want,” Lister said. These could include video creation methods and the ability to spread product details through social media. “So we'll have to use many other platforms to <strong>supplement</strong> what TikTok did in one.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_______________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>app </strong><em>– n. </em>a small computer program that can be put onto a mobile phone or other electronic device</p>
<p><strong>customer</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a person or organization that buys goods or services from a shop or business</p>
<p><strong>interactive </strong><em>– adj. </em>involving communication between people</p>
<p><strong>challenge </strong><em>– n. </em>something difficult that tests one's ability or determination</p>
<p><strong>functionality</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n. </em>the way something works</p>
<p><strong>supplement </strong><em>– v. </em>to add things to make something larger or better</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Pope Francis Names First Woman to Lead Major Vatican Office  (2025/1/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/pope-francis-names-first-woman-to-lead-major-vatican-office.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Pope Francis has named the first woman to lead a major office of the Roman Catholic Church. On Monday, he chose an Italian <strong>nun</strong>, Sister Simona Brambilla, to head the department responsible for all the church's religious orders.</p>
<p>The appointment is the latest effort by Francis to give women more leadership positions in governing the church. In the past, women have been named to secondary leadership positions in some church offices. But the pope's latest appointment is the first time a woman has been named head of a department of the central governing body of the Roman Catholic Church.</p>
<p>Official media for the church reported "Sister Simona Brambilla is the first woman <strong>prefect</strong> in the Vatican." A prefect is a chief government officer in the church. Since the Vatican – the place in Rome where the church is headquartered – is officially considered a country, prefect leaders serve like officials in other governments.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Pope Francis kisses the baby Jesus as he presides over an Epiphany mass in St.Peter's Basilica, at the Vatican, Monday, Jan. 6, 2025. " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/b37d5e3b-e1b9-4e95-9c75-1ef6698ecf37_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Pope Francis kisses the baby Jesus as he presides over an Epiphany mass in St.Peter's Basilica, at the Vatican, Monday, Jan. 6, 2025. </span></div>
<p>The position held by the 59-year-old Brambilla is one of the most important in the church. It is officially known as the Dicastery for the Institutes of Consecrated Life and Societies of Apostolic Life. This means Brambilla is now responsible for every Catholic religious order churchwide.</p>
<p>Pope Francis also named a male church official, <i></i>193;ngel Fernández Artime, as a co-leader to Brambilla. The reason for having a co-leader is that only men can lead religious services, known as masses, in the Roman Catholic Church.</p>
<p>Brambilla has been a member of the Consolata Missionaries religious order. Since last year, she had served as secondary leader in the religious orders department. She will be replacing the current prefect, retiring Cardinal Joao Braz de Aviz, who is 77 years old.</p>
<p>Brambilla is a <strong>nurse</strong> who worked as a <strong>missionary</strong> in Mozambique and led a religious order from 2011-2023. In 2023, Francis appointed her to be <strong>secretary</strong> of the religious orders department.</p>
<p>Francis made Brambilla's appointment possible with reforms made in 2022 to the church's founding constitution. The changes permit individuals who are not <strong>authorized</strong> to lead church services, including women, to head a dicastery and become prefects. While the constitutional changes give women more possibilities to serve, they are still not permitted to officially lead church services.</p>
<p>Catholic women already do much of the church's work in schools and hospitals and teach many young members. But Francis has continued a longtime ban on women being local church leaders, called priests. He also does not support women becoming deacons, a position just below a priest.</p>
<p>However, under Pope Francis' leadership, there has been a marked increase in the number of women working in church positions since he was elected in 2013. The <em>Vatican News</em> reports the percentage of women in leadership positions rose from 19.3 percent in 2013 to 23.4 percent today.</p>
<p>Among the women holding high leadership positions are Sister Raffaella Petrini, the first-ever female secretary general of the Vatican City State. She is responsible for the territory's health care system, police force and Vatican Museums.</p>
<p>Another nun, Sister Alessandra Smerilli, is the second-in-command in the church's development office. Several other women have been appointed to under-secretary positions. These include a French nun, Sister Nathalie Becquart, who serves as an advisor to the pope.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Nicole Winfield </em><em>reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>nun</strong> – <em>n</em>. a woman who is a member of a religious community and who usually promises to remain poor, unmarried, and separate from the rest of society in order to serve God</p>
<p><strong>prefect</strong> – <em>n</em>. a chief officer or government official who is responsible for a particular area in some countries</p>
<p><strong>nurse</strong> – <em>n</em>. a person who is trained to care for sick or injured people and who usually works in a hospital or doctor's office</p>
<p><strong>missionary</strong> – n. a person who is sent to a foreign country to do religious work (such as to convince people to join a religion or to help people who are sick or poor)</p>
<p><strong>secretary</strong> – <em>n</em>. a government official who helps a minister, an ambassador, or the like</p>
<p><strong>authorize</strong> – <em>v</em>. to give official permission to do something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Jimmy Carter Pushed Climate Change Concerns 45 Years Ago  (2025/1/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/jimmy-carter-pushed-climate-change-concerns-45-years-ago.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>When Jimmy Carter ran for president, he wanted the color green to be used in his campaign instead of red, white and blue.</p>
<p>Green showed up on almost everything related to his campaign. It was meant to show the importance he placed on environmental policy.</p>
<p>Nearly 50 years later, environmental activists celebrate the <strong>legacy</strong> of Carter, who died on December 29 at the age of 100. They say he was concerned about protecting the environment and climate issues.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - President Jimmy Carter speaks against a backdrop of solar panels at the White House, June 21, 1979, in Washington." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/303a18da-47c7-4e3a-bb52-4c0aeb42d9bd_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - President Jimmy Carter speaks against a backdrop of solar panels at the White House, June 21, 1979, in Washington.</span></div>
<p>Manish Bapna leads the Natural Resources Defense Council. Bapna said Carter was ahead of his time because he was calling for cuts in gas <strong>emissions</strong> before anyone else was talking about "climate change."</p>
<p><strong>Wearing sweaters and setting standards</strong></p>
<p>Former Vice President Al Gore received the 2007 Nobel Peace Prize for helping to put the climate crisis on the political <strong>agenda</strong>. Gore called Carter "a lifelong <strong>role model</strong> for the entire environmental movement."</p>
<p>President Carter approved the first U.S. <strong>efficiency</strong> <strong>standards</strong> for passenger vehicles and household <strong>appliances</strong>. He created the U.S. Department of Energy which supported energy research. He more than doubled the amount of wilderness area under National Park Service control.</p>
<p>Carter asked Americans to save energy through personal sacrifice, including driving less and turning down their heat in winter during worldwide fuel shortages. He reduced the temperature in the White House in the winter. He wore a <strong>sweater</strong> during his talks to the nation instead of a traditional suit. He pushed renewable energy aiming to reduce dependence on oil and gas.</p>
<p><strong>Dealing with climate change</strong></p>
<p>Carter left office in 1981 shortly after receiving a report linking the use of oil, coal and gas, called fossil fuels, to rising <strong>carbon dioxide</strong> levels in Earth's atmosphere. Carter's top environmental advisers urged "immediate" cuts to the burning of carbon fuels to reduce what scientists called "carbon dioxide pollution."</p>
<p>The report called for limiting worldwide average temperature increases to 2 degrees Celsius above pre-industrial levels. Thirty-five years later, the 2015 Paris climate agreement set a similar goal.</p>
<p><strong>The goal of energy independence</strong></p>
<p>Although Carter wanted to depend more on renewable energy, his push toward U.S. energy independence aided the oil industry.</p>
<p>Steven Nadel is head of the American Council for an Energy-Efficient Economy. He said Carter had the right idea to support research and development organized by the Energy Department.</p>
<p><strong>Stewarding God's creation</strong></p>
<p>Carter's environmental interests began in his boyhood when he hunted and fished and worked on his father's farmland.</p>
<p>Randall Balmer is a professor at Dartmouth College in New Hampshire. Balmer has written about Carter's faith, saying Carter saw himself as a caretaker of the natural resources that God created.</p>
<p><strong>Condemning consumerism</strong></p>
<p>Carter won the presidency at a time of energy shortages, partly caused by unrest in the Middle East. Nadel wrote that national security and economic interests came together with Carter's religious beliefs and love of nature.</p>
<p>Carter called the energy crisis "the moral <strong>equivalent</strong> of war." As inflation increased and gasoline shortages spread, Carter called for individual sacrifice and action on renewable energy.</p>
<p>"Human identity is no longer defined by what one does, but by what one owns," Carter said in 1979. He also said: "But we've discovered that owning things and <strong>consuming</strong> things does not satisfy our longing for meaning."</p>
<p>More than 100 million Americans watched Carter's speech. Years later, Carter said it predicted future calls for strong, direct action on energy.</p>
<p>Jay Inslee is the governor of Washington state. Inslee said: "You can say the Carter presidency is still producing results today." Inslee ran a 2020 presidential campaign that pushed for climate action. "I've learned in politics that timing is everything,” he noted.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Bill Barrow reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>legacy </strong>– <em>n</em>. something that happened in the past or that comes from someone in the past</p>
<p><strong>emissions </strong><em>– n. (pl.) </em>gases released as a result of industrial or biological processes</p>
<p><strong>agenda </strong>– <em>n</em>. a list of things to be considered or done</p>
<p><strong>role model </strong><em>– n. </em>someone who another person admires and tries to be like</p>
<p><strong>efficiency standard </strong><em>– n. </em>requirements put in place by governments on the auto industry to produce vehicles that use fuel more effectively with the aim of using less fuel</p>
<p><strong>appliance</strong><em> – n. </em>a machine used in the home that does housework such as washing clothes or dishes</p>
<p><strong>sweater</strong><em> – n. </em>a piece of warm clothing worn on the upper body</p>
<p><strong>equivalent</strong><em> - n. </em>having the same value, use, or meaning</p>
<p><strong>consume</strong><em> – v. </em>to use fuel, time, resources, or similar things</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Learn New Skills with Microcredentials  (2025/1/8)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/learn-new-skills-with-microcredentials.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">07 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>In today's workplace, what you learned in the usual college <strong>courses</strong> may not be very useful later in life.</p>
<p>For example, in the field of information technology, workers might never use BASIC, the computer language that was taught in the 1990s. But they might need to know Python or SQL.</p>
<p>The answer for students or workers is a professional certificate program, or what is called microcredential.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Education Tips: Learn New Skills with Microcredentials" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/59f26be1-5c9b-45c6-bc3e-7467f7ed3ae6_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Education Tips: Learn New Skills with Microcredentials</span></div>
<p><strong>What is microcredential?</strong></p>
<p>UNESCO, the world's education agency, defines microcredential as professional <strong>certification</strong> that centers on a set of learning outcomes in a narrow field. It is completed over a shorter time than a traditional university program, from a week to a month.</p>
<p>The most popular fields in which microcredentials appear are data <strong>analytics</strong>, information technology support and <strong>cybersecurity</strong>. The courses are often developed by technology businesses like Google, Salesforce, Meta, Intuit and IBM. The businesses provide a certificate when a student finishes the course.</p>
<p>Coursera, an online educational service, recently released a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.coursera.org/enterprise/resources/pdf/micro-credentials-report-2024-us-pdf">report</a> on how microcredentials are preparing students for jobs and affecting higher education schools. It says that 51 percent of colleges in the United States that offer microcredentials also provide school credit and more plan to do so in the next few years.</p>
<p>Some colleges include one or more courses leading to microcredentials as part of their usual programs. At Hawaii Pacific University, school leaders say including professional certifications in its business program has sharply increased the number of interested students.</p>
<p><strong>How to find the right microcredential?</strong></p>
<p>For students, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://credentialfinder.org/search">Credential Finder</a> offers a way to search for the right microcredential offerings by field of study or industry.</p>
<p>For example, if you are studying information science, you may take <a class="wsw__a" href="https://grow.google/certificates/en_us/certificates/data-analytics/">Google Data Analytics</a> or an <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.coursera.org/professional-certificates/ibm-data-analyst/paidmedia?utm_medium=sem&amp;utm_source=bg&amp;utm_campaign=B2C_NAMER_ibm-data-analyst_ibm_FTCOF_professional-certificates_country-US-country-CA&amp;campaignid=662841685&amp;adgroupid=1243548970907697&amp;device=c&amp;keyword=ibm%20data%20analyst%20professional%20certificate&amp;matchtype=e&amp;network=o&amp;devicemodel=&amp;adposition=&amp;creativeid=&amp;hide_mobile_promo&amp;msclkid=e9a725d2690f1868403942b623c61bcf&amp;utm_term=ibm%20data%20analyst%20professional%20certificate&amp;utm_content=Course%20Related">IBM Data Analyst</a> course. If you are working toward a degree in business administration, you may take a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://grow.google/certificates/en_us/certificates/project-management/">Google Project Management</a> course. Your university program's advisors should be helpful in identifying the best certificate programs for your area of study.</p>
<p>Be sure to check with your country's government for more information on special training programs. One example is Ukraine, which is aiming to meet its shortage of skilled workers with its <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.coursera.org/enterprise/articles/ukraine-reskill-initiative-cm">ReSkill UA <strong>initiative</strong></a>. It provides help with finding training and employment.</p>
<p><strong>How much do microcredentials cost?</strong></p>
<p>Many of the course providers permit learners to use the materials for free, but to earn a certification, payment is required.</p>
<p>Coursera has a monthly fee of $59 or a yearly fee of $399 for its Coursera Plus membership. For courses that universities offer for credit, the payment will depend on the price set by the school.</p>
<p>The languages available in Coursera are English, German, Spanish, French, Russian and Portuguese (Brazilian). Other available languages include Japanese, Korean, Chinese (traditional and simplified) and Arabic.</p>
<p>The online education service also provides <strong>automatic</strong> translation of course materials in Swedish, Greek, Polish, Bahasa Indonesian, Italian, Turkish, Thai and Kazakh.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Jill Robbins wrote this story for Learning English using materials from Coursera, UNESCO and university sources.</em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>course</strong> - <em>n. </em>a series of classes about a particular subject in a school</p>
<p><strong>certification</strong> – <em>n</em>. official approval to do something professionally or legally</p>
<p><strong>analytic</strong> – <em>adj. </em>of or relating to the careful study of something; of or relating to analysis of something</p>
<p><strong>cybersecurity</strong> – <em>n</em>. the state of being protected against the criminal or unauthorized use of electronic data, or the measures taken to achieve this</p>
<p><strong>automatic</strong> – <em>adj.</em> <em>of a machine or device</em>. having controls that allow something to work or happen without being directly controlled by a person</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Do Weighted Blankets Have Health Benefits?  (2025/1/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/do-weighted-blankets-have-health-benefits.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the Health &amp; Lifestyle report.</p>
<p>When her husband gave her a weighted <strong>blanket</strong> to help her sleep, Rhonda James did not think it would work. In other words, she was skeptical. But five minutes after covering herself with the blanket, she was asleep.</p>
<p>“It felt like a really big <strong>hug</strong>,” said James. She is a banker who lives in Charleston, South Carolina.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Weighted blankets are on display in a mattress sales showroom in New York City, New York, Dec. 4, 2024. (AP Photo/Mary Conlon)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f00e0efb-fe89-480a-8173-110a81e926d6_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Weighted blankets are on display in a mattress sales showroom in New York City, New York, Dec. 4, 2024. (AP Photo/Mary Conlon)</span></div>
<p>As temperatures drop, a weighted blanket can be a popular choice to help you keep warm. But some people say the extra pressure of the cover also helps to ease their worries and fall asleep faster.</p>
<p>However, research on the effectiveness of weighted blankets is limited. The Associated Press recently reported on what is known about weighted blankets.</p>
<p><strong>First, what is a weighted blanket?</strong></p>
<p>Weighted blankets are filled with small glass balls,<strong> </strong>cotton or another filling. This makes them heavier than usual blankets.</p>
<p>Scientists may not know exactly how the blankets <strong>comfort</strong>, but they have a few ideas.</p>
<p>The heavy, even feeling from a weighted blanket may calm the brain's fight-or-flight <strong>response</strong>, said Dr. Neal Walia. He is a sleep medicine expert at University of California, Los Angeles Health.</p>
<p>He said, “The evenly <strong>distributed</strong> weight on you tells your body..." you are in a "...calm environment.'”</p>
<p>The extra pressure also may cause the brain to release the hormone oxytocin. Sometimes called the “love hormone,” the body creates oxytocin during loving moments, such as hugging. Oxytocin can also lower <strong>anxiety</strong>, Walia said.</p>
<p><strong>How do you use a weighted blanket?</strong></p>
<p>For most healthy adults, experts say to choose a blanket that is about 10 percent of your body weight.</p>
<p>However, the blankets are not good for everyone.</p>
<p>For example, some people may find them too hot to use, especially during warmer weather.</p>
<p>People with breathing problems or disorders such as sleep apnea should check with a doctor before using a weighted blanket.</p>
<p>Experts say to not use weighted blankets for children under three years old. The weight can limit their movement and breathing.</p>
<p>Some people may not be able to buy them. They can be costly. A quality weighted blankets can cost between $50 to over $300. This depends on the size, weight and material.</p>
<p>Some people use them for other reasons than sleep. Rhonda James gets under her blanket to <strong>relax</strong> as she watches television or drinks a glass of wine.</p>
<p>Lucy Taylor, a writer from Wales, also uses a weighted blanket. Her anxiety increases during the winter. So, she uses her blanket during cold months to fall asleep. She says when her body is relaxed, her mind relaxes too.</p>
<p><strong>Can weighted blankets improve sleep?</strong></p>
<p>There is little scientific research on whether weighted blankets help with sleep, anxiety, or other health issues. The studies that exist involve small groups of people. And most of the study subjects are people with conditions including sleep problems, long-term pain, and mental and developmental disorders.</p>
<p>A study on 120 people with insomnia, an inability to get enough sleep, found that the weighted blankets helped them sleep better compared to a light blanket.</p>
<p>Another study considered 67 children with the developmental and brain disorder autism<strong>.</strong> That research found that weighted blankets did not affect the children's sleep at all. However, it also found that the study subjects liked the weighted blankets more than non-weighted blankets.</p>
<p>A third study on 94 adults with <strong>chronic</strong> pain found that a heavier weighted blanket did not affect sleep. But it was better at reducing pain than a lighter blanket.</p>
<p>So, there is not much scientific evidence to support health improvement claims about weighted blankets. However, in most cases they also cannot hurt, sleep experts say.</p>
<p>Dr. Daniel Barone is a sleep medicine expert at Weill Cornell Medicine in New York City. He suggests the use of weighted blankets to his patients after they try other traditional treatments and medicines.</p>
<p>“If it doesn't hurt and it may help, it's worth a shot,” he said.</p>
<p>And that's the Health &amp; Lifestyle report.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Adithi Ramakrishnan reported this story for The Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>blanket </strong><em>-n.</em><strong> </strong>a large warm usually rectangular covering used for beds</p>
<p><strong>hug </strong><em>-n. </em>to press (someone) tightly in one's arms especially as a sign of affection</p>
<p><strong>comfort </strong><em>-v. </em>to give strength and hope to</p>
<p><strong>response </strong><em>-n. </em>a reaction of a living thing to a stimulus</p>
<p><strong>distribute </strong><em>-v. </em>to spread out so as to cover something</p>
<p><strong>anxiety </strong><em>-n. </em>fear or nervousness about what might happen</p>
<p><strong>relax</strong> <em>-v. </em>to make or become loose or less tense</p>
<p><strong>chronic </strong><em>-adj. </em>continuing or occurring again and again for a long time</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Buddhist Women in Nepal Practice Kung Fu for Self-Defense, Strength  (2025/1/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/buddhist-women-in-nepal-practice-kung-fu-for-self-defense-strength.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Buddhist <strong>nuns</strong> in Nepal are once again performing martial arts for the public after a five-year break caused by the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
<p>The women recently put on a show for onlookers at their religious community, called a monastery, outside the capital Kathmandu. The performance was attended by reporters from Reuters news agency.</p>
<p>Members of the hilltop Druk Amitabha Monastery are part of the 1,000-year-old Drukpa religious organization. The group gives nuns equal status to male community members called monks.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A Kung Fu nun demonstrates her skills during the reopening of the nun's center at Druk Amitabha Mountain Nunnery in Kathmandu, Nepal Dec. 30, 2024." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/ec64e9c2-cd4d-4365-a497-d789cea521a1_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A Kung Fu nun demonstrates her skills during the reopening of the nun's center at Druk Amitabha Mountain Nunnery in Kathmandu, Nepal Dec. 30, 2024.</span></div>
<p>The Drukpa lineage includes the only female <strong>order</strong> in the male-led Buddhist monastery system. The nun community was established in 2009 and now has 300 members between the ages of six and 54.</p>
<p>The nuns come from Bhutan, India and Nepal. They are all trained in kung fu, the ancient Chinese style martial art that promotes self-defense and strength.</p>
<p>In their recent performance, the nuns were seen moving their hands quickly and kicking their legs high, with some holding swords. Hundreds of people gathered to watch the performance and cheered the group on.</p>
<p>Usually, such religious organizations expect nuns to cook and clean and not practice any form of martial arts. But one monk, Gyalwang Drukpa, decided to train women in kung fu to improve their health and spiritual well-being. He has a position just slightly below the Dalai Lama in the Tibetan Buddhist leadership.</p>
<p>Jigme Jangchub Chosdon is a 23-year-old nun who came from Ladakh in India. She told Reuters, “We do kung fu to keep ourselves mentally and physically fit, and our aim is to promote women's empowerment and gender equality."</p>
<p>Another performer was 24-year-old Jigme Yangchen Gamo, a nun from Ramechhap in Nepal. She said, "With the <strong>confidence</strong> from kung fu, I really want to help the community, young girls to build their own strength."</p>
<p>The nuns' website explains that the combination of gender equality, physical strength and respect for all living things represents the order's return to its "true spiritual roots."</p>
<p>In the past, the nuns have traveled long distances on foot and by bike in the Himalayas to raise money for disaster relief and to promote environment-friendly living.</p>
<p>Another member of the group is Jigme Konchok Lhamo, a 30-year-old nun from India. She said her main goal for the future is to reach <strong>enlightenment</strong> like Lord Buddha, who founded Buddhism 2,600 years ago.</p>
<p>She added, "But for now as I am a normal person... I think I will be focusing more on helping others. Helping others is our religion."</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Gopal Sharma </em><em>reported this story for Reuters.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>nun</strong> – <em>n</em>. a woman who is a member of a religious community</p>
<p><strong>order</strong> - <em>n</em>. a religious organization whose members usually live together and promise to follow special rules and traditions</p>
<p><strong>confidence</strong> – <em>n</em>. a feeling or belief that you can do something well or succeed at something</p>
<p><strong>enlightenment </strong>- <em>n.</em> <em>Buddhism</em>. a final spiritual state marked by the absence of desire or suffering</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Explainer: South Korea’s Constitutional Court to Consider Presidents’ Ouster  (2025/1/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/explainer-south-korea-s-constitutional-court-to-consider-presidents-ouster.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">06 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>The <strong>impeachment </strong>late last month of South Korea's acting President Han Duck-soo has deepened political division in the country. He had replaced President Yoon Suk Yeol, who was impeached earlier in December.</p>
<p>Two impeachments suspending the country's top two officials in a short period of time has never happened before in South Korea. Now, the deputy prime minister and finance minister, Choi Sang-mok, is the new temporary leader.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="Wreaths sent by supporters of impeached South Korean President Yoon Suk Yeol are displayed outside the Constitutional Court in Seoul, South Korea, Friday, Dec. 27, 2024. (AP Photo/Ahn Young-joon)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/7cd09d3e-6f0d-4a4c-bde2-cce7811be0d8_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">Wreaths sent by supporters of impeached South Korean President Yoon Suk Yeol are displayed outside the Constitutional Court in Seoul, South Korea, Friday, Dec. 27, 2024. (AP Photo/Ahn Young-joon)</span></div>
<p>When he took power, Choi quickly ordered the military to increase readiness in the event of an act of aggression by North Korea. Diplomats communicated with important partners including the United States and Japan.</p>
<p>Duyeon Kim is an expert with the Center for a New American Security in Washington, D.C. Kim said: “(Han's) impeachment now creates an <strong>opportunity </strong>for<strong> external</strong> threats.”</p>
<p><strong>How Han was impeached</strong></p>
<p>Before Yoon declared martial law on December 3, Han Duck-soo was the prime minister and the second highest official in South Korea. Lawmakers impeached Yoon on December 14 over his martial law order.</p>
<p>Han tried to ease the concerns of South Korea's major diplomatic partners and to calm its financial markets. However, he became involved in a political dispute with the opposition Democratic Party, or DP.</p>
<p>DP lawmakers demanded that Han immediately appoint three justices to seats on the Constitutional Court to rule on Yoon's impeachment. The court normally has nine justices. Currently three seats remain open. Han refused to fill the open seats. He said he would not appoint justices without the approval of both the DP and the governing People Power Party, or PPP.</p>
<p>Choi Jin is director of the Institute of Presidential Leadership based in Seoul. He said Han lacked a good reason not to appoint the justices. But Choi said the DP should not have moved to impeach Han so quickly.</p>
<p><strong>International surprise</strong></p>
<p>Han's impeachment came as South Korean officials told international partners that the situation was returning to normal. Officials in Japan, Europe and the United States had been surprised by Yoon's declaration of martial law.</p>
<p>Duyeon Kim said: “South Korea is now in a far more serious crisis of leadership and governance,” adding that, “Han had the experience and <strong>credentials</strong> to deal with both security and financial crises....”</p>
<p>Kim expressed concern that the leadership situation would harm the economy, culture and industry.</p>
<p><strong>What might happen?</strong></p>
<p>The governing party argues that Han's impeachment is “<strong>invalid</strong>” because it is based on a simple majority of the 300-member National Assembly. The PPP says a two-thirds majority is necessary. It has brought a case before the Constitutional Court to consider the impeachment vote of Yoon.</p>
<p>The Constitutional Court has 180 days to decide on the legality of both impeachments.<br/>
<br/>
Han called his impeachment “regrettable,” but said he respects the assembly's decision. If Yoon is ousted, then a national election must take place within 60 days.</p>
<p>Yoon faces several separate investigations into possible wrongdoing linked to his martial law declaration. DP leader Lee Jae-myung is favored to win a possible presidential election.</p>
<p>However, Lee faces legal cases as well. He was found guilty of election law violations in November. He is appealing the ruling.<br/>
<br/>
If Lee becomes president, his trials would be suspended because South Korean law does not permit a sitting president to face legal action for most crimes.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter Jr.</p>
<p><em>Hyung-Jin Kim reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>__________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>impeachment </strong><em>–n. (political)</em> an action that is defined in a country's constitution that is part of a process for removing the executive officer from power for a crime or wrongdoing</p>
<p><strong>opportunity</strong> <em>–n.</em> a good chance for advancement or progress</p>
<p><strong>external </strong><em>–adj.</em> not inside something but outside of it</p>
<p><strong>invalid</strong> <em>–adj.</em> being without foundation or force in fact, truth, or law</p>
<p><strong>credentials</strong> <em>–n. (usually pl.)</em> qualities or abilities that make someone able to do something; documents that state a person is permitted to do a certain job</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>2024 Another Big Year for Space Exploration  (2025/1/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/another-big-year-for-space-exploration.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>As we enter the new year, we take a look back at some of the biggest space stories of 2024.</p>
<p><strong>Historic private moon landing</strong></p>
<p>Nearly one year ago, a private spacecraft completed the first U.S. moon landing in more than 50 years. The American space agency NASA announced the space lander, called Odysseus, had touched down on the lunar surface February 22.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image provided by Intuitive Machines shows its Odysseus lunar lander over the near side of the moon following lunar orbit insertion, Feb. 21, 2024. The lander guided itself to the surface Feb. 22." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-ae7d-08dc34065d95_cx0_cy15_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image provided by Intuitive Machines shows its Odysseus lunar lander over the near side of the moon following lunar orbit insertion, Feb. 21, 2024. The lander guided itself to the surface Feb. 22.</span></div>
<p>Odysseus was developed by the Texas-based company Intuitive Machines. The spacecraft carried out several science experiments before powering down permanently on the moon in late March.</p>
<p>NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/news-release/nasa-accelerates-space-exploration-earth-science-for-all-in-2024/#:~:text=With%20a%20look%20back%20at,study%20Jupiter's%20icy%20moon%20Europa%3B">said</a> Odysseus had successfully captured data to help the agency “better understand the moon's environment and improve landing <strong>precision</strong> and safety.”</p>
<p><strong>Japanese moon landing</strong></p>
<p>Japan's space agency JAXA announced in January 2024 that its SLIM spacecraft had successfully landed on the moon. But the lander touched down the wrong way up, causing some communication and power problems.</p>
<p>Japanese space officials <a class="wsw__a" href="https://global.jaxa.jp/press/2024/08/20240826-1_e.html">reported</a> that they stayed in communication with SLIM through late April. They said the spacecraft was able to collect valuable data about the touchdown and surrounding area.</p>
<p>One purpose of the mission was to demonstrate new <strong>precision</strong> landing technology. JAXA said the experiment was successful because SLIM was able to land within 10 meters of its planned target.</p>
<p><strong>Chinese moon landing and return</strong></p>
<p>In May, China launched its Chang'e 6 spacecraft to the moon's far side. In late June, Chinese space officials announced the spacecraft had returned to Earth with rock and soil <strong>samples</strong> collected on the lunar surface.</p>
<p>The successful return made China the first country to ever collect and bring back lunar samples from the far side of the moon. The area is known as the far side because it always faces away from Earth.</p>
<p><strong>Europe's asteroid exploration mission</strong></p>
<p>In October, the European Space Agency (ESA) <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/europe-launches-spacecraft-to-explore-asteroid-hit-by-nasa/7818115.html">said</a> it had successfully launched a spacecraft, called Hera, to explore an <strong>asteroid</strong> struck in an earlier NASA test <strong>mission</strong>. Hera's trip to the asteroid is expected to take about two years.</p>
<p>Hera is headed to the asteroid Dimorphos. NASA crashed its DART spacecraft into the space rock in 2022, about 11 million kilometers from Earth. NASA said its mission successfully showed it was possible to change the orbit of asteroids that might threaten Earth in the future.</p>
<p>Hera aims to closely examine Dimorphos to get more details on how the strike by DART affected the asteroid. The data that NASA collected is to be used together with information gathered by ESA to develop future planetary defense plans.</p>
<p><strong>Europa Clipper to explore Jupiter's moon</strong></p>
<p>NASA announced the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/centers-and-facilities/jpl/nasas-europa-clipper-millions-of-miles-down-instruments-deploying/">successful launch</a> of its Europa Clipper spacecraft in October. The explorer is designed to search for possible signs of life on Jupiter's moon Europa.</p>
<p>Jupiter is the largest planet in our solar system and has numerous moons. But icy Europa has been identified by scientists as a good candidate for having the right conditions to support life. Several studies have suggested the moon likely contains a large ocean beneath its icy surface.</p>
<p>NASA said the Europa Clipper would fly past Mars, then back toward Earth, “using the gravity of each planet to increase its <strong>momentum</strong>.” These kinds of “gravity assists” are expected to provide the needed push to get the spacecraft to Jupiter by 2030.</p>
<p><strong>Boeing's crew flight to the ISS</strong></p>
<p>In early June, Boeing successfully carried out a test mission for NASA by transporting two American astronauts – Butch Wilmore and Suni Williams – to the International Space Station (ISS).</p>
<p>The two were expected to stay in space for only a week. But ongoing technical issues with the Starliner spacecraft prevented a return trip.</p>
<p>NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/news-release/nasa-decides-to-bring-starliner-spacecraft-back-to-earth-without-crew/">announced</a> plans in August to have Starliner return to Earth without the astronauts. The current plan is for Wilmore and Williams to return on a SpaceX Dragon spacecraft sometime in late March or April.</p>
<p><strong>SpaceX landing demonstration</strong></p>
<p>SpaceX has now completed six launch tests of its huge Starship rocket system. Four of those tests were carried out in 2024. The last test took place in November.</p>
<p>The Starship rocket and spacecraft system is designed to be a completely reusable vehicle to transport astronauts and supplies. It has successfully demonstrated that ability in its most recent experimental flights.</p>
<p>During one of the tests in October, Starship's Super Heavy <strong>booster</strong> rocket was <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/spacex-calls-new-starship-test-a-success-captures-rocket-at-landing/7824353.html">"caught“ and secured</a> by a huge structure that includes metal arms. A short time later, Starship's second <strong>stage</strong> safely <strong>splashed down</strong> in the Indian Ocean.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>precision</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> the quality of being very correct or exact</p>
<p><strong>sample </strong><em>–n.</em> an amount of a substance that is taken for tests or scientific study</p>
<p><strong>asteroid</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a rocky object that goes around the sun</p>
<p><strong>mission </strong><em>–n. (space exploration)</em> the flight of a spacecraft to its target along with tasks expected to be carried out</p>
<p><strong>momentum </strong><em>– n. </em>the force that makes something continue to move</p>
<p><strong>booster </strong><em>– n.</em> an engine on a spacecraft that gives extra power for the first part of a flight</p>
<p><strong>stage </strong><em>–n.</em> part of a rocket that contains engines and fuel, but which is left behind when the rocket reaches a certain distance above the Earth</p>
<p><strong>splash down </strong><em>–v.</em> when a spacecraft reenters the Earth's atmosphere and lands in a body of water</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>'Kicking Off' a New Year  (2025/1/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/kicking-off-a-new-year.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>One of the most popular sports in the United States is American football. In the U.S., “football” is a sport that involves a lot of contact. What people around the world call “football,” Americans call soccer.</p>
<p>For today's show, we talk about some <strong>idioms</strong> and expressions that come from American football.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="The Las Vegas Raiders kick off to the New Orleans Saints to start an NFL football game, Monday, Sept. 21, 2020, in Las Vegas. (AP Photo/Isaac Brekken)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/d7e9fe96-79df-43ae-861c-931b29774b48_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">The Las Vegas Raiders kick off to the New Orleans Saints to start an NFL football game, Monday, Sept. 21, 2020, in Las Vegas. (AP Photo/Isaac Brekken)</span></div>
<p>The American sport mainly involves carrying or throwing the ball. But there are times when a player must use their feet to kick the ball. The kicker can kick <strong>field goals</strong> to get points. In addition to that, the game starts with a <strong>kickoff</strong> and, after scoring points, a team will kick off to the other side, beginning their turn on offense.</p>
<p><strong>Kicks and punts</strong></p>
<p>The term <u>kickoff</u> is commonly used to describe the start of an event or project. For example, we could say experts from all over the world attended the kickoff of the new language museum.</p>
<p>You can use it as a phrasal verb, as well. For example, people often like to “kick off” the new year with a resolution, or promise to yourself, to reach a goal or to do something.</p>
<p>Football also has the term “punt.” Punting is another sort of kick a team uses when they cannot score. The punter kicks a ball with the top of his foot. “Punt,” like “kick,” can be both a noun and a verb.</p>
<p>When you punt the ball, you put it in play for the other team. The same can be said for punting in life. When we punt something, we give our task, job, or responsibility to someone else. For example, if I'm not good at a certain task or I just don't want to do it, I can <u>punt</u> it to someone else.</p>
<p>It can also mean <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_wnKZgr9H">to delay</a> a decision. If I'm not sure about taking a trip, for example, I can punt the decision until later. Another way to say this in American English is to <u>table</u> it. If you are not ready to think about something, it can or must wait until later.</p>
<p>In football, the kicker not only starts the game with a kickoff but also kicks field goals. To do this, the kicker must kick the football between the <strong>goalposts </strong>at either end of the football field. If he succeeds, his team gets three points.</p>
<p>Kicking a field goal can be difficult if the kicker is far from the goalposts or if the weather in an outdoor <strong>stadium </strong>is windy, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_JPUiMEq5">rainy</a> or snowy.</p>
<p>But imagine if the goalposts were moving? That would make kicking the ball between them much more difficult.</p>
<p><strong>To move the goalposts</strong></p>
<p>We can face this problem in everyday life. Imagine if you are given a task at work with specific goals to reach. For example, if you are a social media manager you could be asked to increase followers by 10,000 by the end of the month. But when the end of the month comes, your boss tells you that now you need to add 20,000 followers, not 10,000.</p>
<p>In this case, your boss has moved the goalpost.</p>
<p>Sometime a person moves the goalposts on purpose. They have a reason for doing so. If the goalposts keep moving, it is difficult or even impossible to reach the goal. So, if you say that someone has “moved the goalposts,” you are accusing them of changing the rules or end goals to make it difficult for you to succeed.</p>
<p>We can also say <u>to move the target</u> to mean the same thing. A <u>moving target</u> is a changing goal or result. A desired goal, end, or objective that changes all the time is difficult or perhaps even impossible to reach.</p>
<p>Both expressions – to move the goalposts and to move the target – can be used in the same way and in similar situations. However, <u>moving the goalposts</u> is a <strong>classic</strong> football expression. While <u>moving the target</u> can <strong>refer</strong> to several sports.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Words and Their Stories</em>. Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>idiom </strong><em>–n.</em> a word or expression that does not mean what the dictionary definition of the word or words would suggest</p>
<p><strong>field goal </strong><em>–n.</em> a three-point score in American football that is made by kicking the ball through goalposts</p>
<p><strong>kickoff </strong><em>–n.</em> the start of something; the beginning kick of an American football game</p>
<p><strong>goalpost </strong><em>–n.</em> one of two upright poles that exist in a goal which is used in several field sports including American football and soccer</p>
<p><strong>stadium </strong><em>–n.</em> a very large structure that surrounds a playing field or court where people can sit and watch a sports competition or a performance</p>
<p><strong>classic </strong><em>–adj.</em> one of the best examples of something</p>
<p><strong>refer </strong><em>–v.</em> to have a connection to or be related to something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Bosnia's ‘Balkan Blues’ Music Honored by UNESCO  (2025/1/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/bosnia-s-balkan-blues-music-honored-by-unesco.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Every Friday, musician Enes Salman performs the Sevdalinka, an ancient form of love song from Bosnia and Herzegovina.</p>
<p>Sevdalinka was recently included in UNESCO's National Inventory of Intangible Cultural Heritage. UNESCO is The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization.</p>
<p>Sevdalinka is often called the Balkan Blues. It is a somewhat sad form of urban love song that dates to the 1500s. It is a mix of South Slavic spoken poetry and music of the Ottoman Empire.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Bosnian musician Enes Salman plays the accordion while performing the traditional love song Sevdalinka, in Sarajevo, Bosnia and Herzegovina, December 20, 2024. (REUTERS/Amel Emric)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/55956078-c9e1-4aa7-9cf7-9b05b9a1702c_cx7_cy14_cw84_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Bosnian musician Enes Salman plays the accordion while performing the traditional love song Sevdalinka, in Sarajevo, Bosnia and Herzegovina, December 20, 2024. (REUTERS/Amel Emric)</span></div>
<p>Salman is among only a few musicians keeping the tradition alive.</p>
<p>"I have been playing and singing Sevdalinka since I was 14," he said before a recent performance.</p>
<p>Sevdalinka is often performed <strong>a cappella</strong>. That means it is sung without musical instruments. Sometimes the performer sings with traditional instruments like a lute. This form, or <strong>genre</strong>, of music has been carried from generation to generation through performances at family gatherings.</p>
<p>In recent years, younger musicians have brought modern versions of Sevdalinka to <strong>audiences</strong> around the world.</p>
<p>One of them is Damir Imamovic. His father and grandfather were famous Sevdalinka performers. In 2020 and 2021, Imamovic won awards from two world music publications, <em>Songlines</em> and <em>Transglobal</em>, for best European album.</p>
<p>Imamovic supports Sevdalinka internationally through his SevdahLab project. The project helped build support for the music's inclusion on UNESCO's World Heritage list.</p>
<p>"I realized how little the public knows about the Sevdalinka genre<strong> </strong>and wanted to <strong>reveal </strong>the story behind that music," he said.</p>
<p>Zanin Berbic is a 28-year-old <strong>ethno-musicologist</strong>. He works as a <strong>curator </strong>in the music department of Bosnia's Regional Museum in Sarajevo, organizing, protecting, and bringing attention to music. He also plays saz, a long-necked lute used in Ottoman classical music. He said that Sevdalinka tells the story of Bosnia's history.</p>
<p>Berbic said, "Most of my days I spend either singing or playing Sevdalinka songs or reading or talking about them. Sevdalinka is my life," he said.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Daria Sito-Sucic reported this story for Reuters from Sarajevo. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>a cappella </strong>–<em>foreign term</em> <em>(music)</em> singing without musical instruments</p>
<p><strong>genre </strong>–n. a form of art that is distinct from others</p>
<p><strong>audience </strong>–n. people who listen to a performance in a theater, on television or a public place</p>
<p><strong>ethno-musicology </strong><em>-n. </em>the study of music in a sociocultural context; the study of ethnic music</p>
<p><strong>curator </strong>–n. a person who oversees a collection of certain kinds of objects</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How to Summon Others  (2025/1/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/how-to-summon-others.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we consider part of a message from Henry.</p>
<p>Here is one of Henry's questions:</p>
<p><em>Greetings VOA Learning English team. I am a regular listener of your learning English program.... </em></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Ask A Teacher: How to Summon Others" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/966087de-8dad-4a4d-87f4-9917002665ce_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Ask A Teacher: How to Summon Others</span></div>
<p><em>I would like to ask this question about the correct or proper way to summon someone (i.e., asking someone to come and see you .... at home, school or work) in English: </em></p>
<p><em>What expressions are used in summoning someone? </em></p>
<p>Thank you for your question, Henry. It is an important and useful one.</p>
<p>To summon means to call for a person or persons to be present, often for an important meeting.</p>
<p>Please note that there are many ways to summon others. In this lesson, we will present a few general ways.</p>
<p><strong>Summoning others directly </strong></p>
<p>When we speak to others directly, we can summon them with the following:</p>
<p><em>Could you come here, please? </em></p>
<p>We might also be more exact about the meeting place. For example, a supervisor or <strong>principal</strong> might say:</p>
<p><em>Could you come to my office, please? </em></p>
<p>You might also be more exact with what you would like to do. For example, you might ask:</p>
<p><em>Could I talk to you for a moment? </em></p>
<p>These questions are very general, <strong>polite</strong>, and useful in a lot of situations.</p>
<p>But the way in which we summon others can differ depending on the situation, how familiar people are with each other, and the rank or status the speakers have.</p>
<p>For example, consider a situation at home or school.</p>
<p>A parent or teacher might summon a child or student with language like this:</p>
<p><em>Come over here! </em></p>
<p>Generally, this kind of a summons is followed by scolding, or criticism.</p>
<p><strong>Summoning others indirectly </strong></p>
<p>So far, we have considered how English speakers might directly summon another person. But what do we say if we ask another person to communicate the information for us?</p>
<p>When an <strong>intermediary </strong>communicates the information, they might use the very general formula:</p>
<p><em>_____ would like to see you. </em></p>
<p>or</p>
<p><em>____ wants to see you. </em></p>
<p>We can use an example to clarify this point.</p>
<p><em>Boss: Tanya, could you ask Joe to come see me? </em></p>
<p><em>Tanya: Sure. </em></p>
<p><em>Tanya: Joe, the boss would like to see you. </em></p>
<p><em>Joe: Ok. I'll be there right away. </em></p>
<p>Our examples can be used in a number of situations.</p>
<p>At school, a teacher might say, “The principal would like to see you” or “The principal wants to see you.”</p>
<p>At home, a brother or sister might say, “Mom would like to see you” or “Mom wants to see you.”</p>
<p>English speakers usually consider the structure “would like” to be a little more polite and <strong>formal</strong>.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? We want to hear from you! Send us an email at 21voa.com. Please let us know where you are from, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>!</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>John Russell wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>__________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>principal</strong> <em>– n.</em> the chief or leader of a school</p>
<p><strong>polite</strong> <em>–adj. </em>showing good manners or behavior that shows respect and formality</p>
<p><strong>intermediary </strong><em>–n.</em> a person who aids the communications of two parties which are not communicating directly with each other</p>
<p><strong>formal </strong><em>– adj.</em> following established custom or rule</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Game Born in Mexican Prisons Brings People Together  (2025/1/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/game-born-in-mexican-prisons-brings-people-together.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>On a Sunday afternoon in Mexico City's Roma neighborhood, Rosa María Espinosa joins about 80 men in a park to play poleana. The almost 100-year-old game was created in a Mexican prison and requires luck and thinking skill.</p>
<p>Poleana still carries a <strong>stigma</strong> connected to its birth as a prison game. However, it is growing popular as people from different backgrounds discover its appeal.</p>
<p>Espinosa says she like the excitement of the game. “But sometimes,” she adds, “the <strong>dice</strong> aren't lucky.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="People play poleana, a board game invented in prison, before a tournament in Mexico City, Sunday, Nov. 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Ginnette Riquelme)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/691d74a0-0918-466f-b32f-e80e6eebabdf_cx0_cy7_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">People play poleana, a board game invented in prison, before a tournament in Mexico City, Sunday, Nov. 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Ginnette Riquelme)</span></div>
<p><strong>Playing for freedom</strong></p>
<p>Poleana is played with four people and a square wooden box with a sunken center for dice rolling. Each player has four pieces that they race around the box. They use dice combinations and math to govern how to move their pieces <strong>strategically</strong>. At the same time, they must also try to block moves by their competitors.</p>
<p>The board represents the limits of a prison and getting out of it before others. Winning freedom is the game's goal.</p>
<p>“People used to say, ‘these <strong>folks</strong> know how to play because they've been to prison,'” said the 62-year-old Espinosa. “Thank God I've never been, but I like to play.”</p>
<p>That was the first time she had competed against anyone besides her family or friends. She usually plays on Tuesdays and Sundays in the small church in her apartment building.</p>
<p><strong>Ancient roots</strong></p>
<p>Alejandro Olmos studies ancient cultures at the National Anthropology and History School. He has studied and played poleana for years.</p>
<p>He has followed the game's roots to the Indian game chaupar (or pachisi). He found evidence of the connection dating back 1400 years. After British colonization of India, the game spread to Western countries under different names, including Ludo, Aggravation and Parcheesi.</p>
<p>In 1915, the American company Parker Brothers marketed a similar game. Parker Brothers named it “Pollyanna” after a popular 1913 children's book by Eleanor H. Porter.</p>
<p>Sometime around 1940, the game spread to prisons in Mexico City, including Lecumberri. That prison's physical structure is very similar to the design of the game board. So experts say Lecumberri may have been the birthplace of modern poleana and its new set of rules.</p>
<p>Olmos said that in Mexico, “the game <strong>reflects </strong>the roughness of prison life: mistakes are not pardoned.”</p>
<p><strong>Poleana breaks out</strong></p>
<p>Six years ago, Jonathan Rulleri started a family business marketing poleana. His goal was to bring together people from different backgrounds.</p>
<p>One of the early difficulties was establishing common rules for the game, which in Rulleri's words, “has been spreading from below, from prison to the street and from the street into neighborhoods.”</p>
<p>The 37-year-old man learned to play while serving a sentence in a prison outside Mexico City, the capital. After his release, he struggled to find work.</p>
<p>He and his wife launched a food <strong>delivery</strong> service. However, the business proved unsuccessful. This led him to accept an offer to make a poleana board for a friend. Then came another offer. Soon he began to post his creations on social media. He said they gave up the food business and started making poleanas instead.</p>
<p>The business, Poleana Cana'da Frogs, has organized 55 poleana <strong>tournaments</strong>. They are family-friendly, including people of all ages.</p>
<p>“We want to remove the game's stigma ...” Rulleri said.</p>
<p>In the 1980s, the game began to spread beyond the prisons and into Mexico City's neighborhoods. Tepito is one of the neighborhoods where people are almost always playing poleana.</p>
<p>Fernando Rojas is 57 years-old and learned poleana when he was 18. But it was in prison where he really got good at the game.</p>
<p>“It really helps you escape the reality of being a prisoner and that's how it started,” Rojas said. “No one can understand what it's like to be a prisoner ... you don't see the end of your sentence. There are people who have to do drugs as their way to escape. Poleana is very important in prison.”</p>
<p>Now the game helps Rojas cope with life's difficulties. “We all have problems, in prison and in the street,” he said. “So a lot of people come here for a <strong>distraction</strong>.”</p>
<p>While luck plays a part in the game, math understanding is also important.</p>
<p>That is why Diego González and Dana López are very happy that their 7-year-old son Kevin is learning to play poleana. He has fun and his math skills are improving.</p>
<p>González also runs a family business making poleana boards. He started the business after serving a three-year sentence 10 years ago. His boards are popular birthday and Christmas gifts. Some are personalized and might include images of loved ones who have died, or playful pictures for players who are children.</p>
<p>Sales of the board game sharply increased during the COVID-19 pandemic. People were stuck at home and found that the game was a good way to pass the time.</p>
<p>“They realized it's not a bad game," González said, “it's a game of strategy and getting the family together.”</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p>And I'm Mario Ritter Jr.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>stigma </strong><em>– n.</em> a set of negative and unfair beliefs that a society or group of people have about something</p>
<p><strong>dice </strong><em>– n.</em> small cubes marked on each face with from one to six spots</p>
<p><strong>strategically </strong><em>– adv. </em>to use a careful plan or method<strong> </strong>to achieve a goal : <strong>strategy </strong><em>– n.</em> the art of making or employing plans or tricks to achieve a goal</p>
<p><strong>reflect </strong><em>– v.</em> to make (something) manifest or apparent: to show<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>delivery </strong><em>– n.</em> the transport and handing over of something to someone</p>
<p><strong>tournament </strong><em>– n.</em> a series of games or contests that make up a single unit of competition</p>
<p><strong>distraction </strong>– n. something that directs one's attention away from something else</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Program Helps Pakistani Women Learn to Ride, Gain Independence  (2025/1/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/program-helps-pakistani-women-learn-to-ride-gain-independence.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Laiba Rashid is a 22-year-old Pakistani student in a special training program in the city of Lahore. The program, called Women on Wheels (WOW), teaches women how to operate two-wheelers, or motorcycles. Rashid hopes her life will change after she learns how to ride a motorcycle.</p>
<p>Although the program is 7 years old, it is still rare to see women ride motorcycles. In the Islamic nation, it is more common to see women driving cars or riding in the back of two-wheelers operated by a male relative. The WOW program is offered free by the Lahore traffic police.</p>
<p>"I hope this will change my life because I am dependent on my brother to pick me up and drop me to college," Rashid said on her first day at WOW.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Humaira Rafaqat teaches women how to ride a bike while wearing an abaya, during a training session as part of the " by="" department="" in="" lahore="" mehboob="" nida="" october="" on="" organized="" pakistan="" police="" program="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e467115f-af02-4786-97a9-e362e57259f7_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg" the="" traffic="" wheels="" women=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Humaira Rafaqat teaches women how to ride a bike while wearing an abaya, during a training session as part of the "Women on Wheels" program organized by the traffic police department in Lahore, Pakistan, October 1, 2024. (REUTERS/Nida Mehboob)</span></div>
<p>She said she wants to buy a motorcycle to go to college, adding that, before, there were no women drivers in her family. "Now everybody is <strong>convinced</strong> that women should be independent in their movement to schools, jobs and markets," she said.</p>
<p>Bushra Iqbal Hussain is a social activist and director of Safe Childhood. Hussain said women driving two-wheelers has been a cultural and religious <strong>taboo</strong>. But, she said, more women are now changing the culture like they did in the 1980s with regular cars to reduce their dependence on men to move around.</p>
<p>The WOW program has been in operation since 2017. But it has become increasingly popular in recent months as car prices have greatly increased and motorcycles offer a less costly choice.</p>
<p>The <strong>cheapest</strong> four-wheel vehicle in Pakistan costs about $8,265 compared to about $1,345 for a Chinese-made two-wheeler. The average yearly income per person in Pakistan is $1,696.</p>
<p>Sohail Mudassar is a traffic official in Lahore. He said the WOW program has trained at least 6,600 women, and Rashid's group was the 86th since it started. Female trainer Humaira Rafaqat added, "Young women are quick learners because they are <strong>enthusiastic</strong> and take risks."</p>
<p><strong>Breaking glass ceiling</strong></p>
<p>One of them, Ghania Raza, is a 23-year-old who is working toward a doctorate in criminology. She said learning to ride a two-wheeler gave her a deep sense of achievement and empowerment: "It was like breaking a <strong>glass</strong> <strong>ceiling</strong>," she said.</p>
<p>Shumaila Shafiq is a 36-year-old mother of three and a part-time clothing designer. She said she has been riding her husband's motorcycle to the market and other places after training in the program.</p>
<p>Shafiq has also designed a short-length <strong>abaya </strong>for Muslim women to wear while operating a motorcycle. She said the long abaya is dangerous because it may get caught in the wheels of the motorcycle.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Mubasher Bukhari </em><em>reported this story for Reuters.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>convinced</strong> – <em>adj.</em> completely certain or sure about something; persuaded</p>
<p><strong>taboo</strong> – <em>n</em>. not acceptable to talk about or do</p>
<p><strong>cheap </strong>- <em>adj</em>. not costing a lot of money</p>
<p><strong>enthusiastic</strong> – <em>adj</em>. feeling or showing strong excitement about something : filled with or marked by enthusiasm</p>
<p><strong>glass ceiling</strong> – <em>n.</em> an upper limit to achievement by a group of people</p>
<p><strong>abaya</strong> - <em>n.</em> a simple, loose, robe-like dress worn by conservative Muslim women</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Questions, Answers about Holiday Activities  (2025/1/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/questions-answers-about-holiday-activities.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Imagine you are talking to an American. You are<strong> curious</strong> to know about what they did during the holidays of Christmas and New Year's. How can you ask about these or other holidays? How can you build a discussion about the holiday season?</p>
<p>In this Everyday Grammar, we will explore how you can form common questions and answers about the holidays.</p>
<p>Let's start with some important terms and ideas.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Questions, Answers about Holiday Activities " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/03370000-0aff-0242-0573-08daef5fd062_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Questions, Answers about Holiday Activities </span></div>
<p><strong>Holidays</strong></p>
<p>The Christmas and New Year's holidays are important in the United States. Common good wishes during the season include “Merry Christmas” and “Happy New Year!”</p>
<p>But how do you build a discussion around the subject of such holidays?</p>
<p>You can start with yes or no questions, which involve the helping verb “do.” The structure is generally:</p>
<p><em>Do+ subject + celebrate + the holiday.</em></p>
<p>For example, you might ask</p>
<p><em>Do you celebrate Christmas?</em></p>
<p>Or</p>
<p><em>Do you celebrate New Year's Eve?</em></p>
<p>The person you ask these questions to might answer with a yes or a no.</p>
<p>Both answers can lead to interesting discussions. But <strong>for the sake of</strong> today's report, let's <strong>assume</strong> the answer is “yes.”</p>
<p><strong>Open-ended questions</strong></p>
<p>You can follow up with more detailed questions about what the person did for Christmas and New Year's.</p>
<p>You might need to ask open-ended questions – questions that are not asking for a yes or no answer.</p>
<p>The word “what” is often commonly used to ask open-ended questions about basic actions. We combine “what” with the helping verb “do” to form the following structure:</p>
<p><em>What + do + subject + do + rest of the sentence</em></p>
<p>Notice that the verb “do” appears twice in the structure. Here is how one might use this structure to ask about holiday activities:</p>
<p><em>What did you do for Christmas?</em></p>
<p>or</p>
<p><em>What did you do on New Year's Eve?</em></p>
<p>Note that the first example of “do” is in its past tense form – “what did...” This is because we are asking about an event in the past.</p>
<p><strong>Answers</strong></p>
<p>You could hear answers that go in a few different directions. One of the most common answers will involve the simple past forms of the verbs go, see, or visit.</p>
<p>For example, a person might say “I went to my grandparent's house,” or “We saw our cousins,” or “We visited my brother.”</p>
<p>Note that the person could be speaking for themselves and use the subject pronoun “I,” or they could be speaking for their family and use the subject pronoun “we.”</p>
<p><strong>Practice</strong></p>
<p>Now let's work with these ideas.</p>
<p>Ask a yes or no question about the holiday<strong> Hanukkah</strong>. It is a Jewish holiday around the end of the year.</p>
<p>Pause the audio to consider your answer.</p>
<p>Here is one possible answer:</p>
<p><em>Do you celebrate Hanukkah?</em></p>
<p>For this next question, imagine that you celebrated New Year's Eve in New York City's Times Square. How would you use the verb “see” if someone asked you about what you did?</p>
<p>Pause the audio to consider your answer.</p>
<p>Here are a few possible answers:</p>
<p><em>I saw crowds and <strong>decorations</strong>.</em></p>
<p>Or,</p>
<p><em>I saw the ball drop.</em></p>
<p>There are, of course, other answers. What is important is that you use the past form “saw,” as in “I saw...”</p>
<p>The next time you hear Americans discuss the holiday season, pay careful attention to the kinds of questions and answers that they give. Such questions and answers are not only useful for talking about holidays but for many other activities as well!</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>John Russell wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>curious </strong>–adj. wanting to learn more about a subject or issue</p>
<p><strong>for the sake of</strong> –phrase for the purpose of</p>
<p><strong>assume</strong> – v. to think that something is true or probably true without knowing that it is true</p>
<p><strong>Hanukkah</strong> – n. an eight-day Jewish holiday that is celebrated in November or December</p>
<p><strong>decoration </strong>– n. something that is added to something else to make it more attractive</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Use Ancient Genes to Estimate Contact Between Humans, Neanderthals  (2025/1/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/scientists-use-ancient-genes-to-estimate-contact-between-humans-neanderthals.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Scientists have used ancient genes to learn more details about contact between Neanderthals and humans tens of thousands of years ago.</p>
<p>Results of two recent studies estimate the two groups likely met and began mating about 45,000 years ago.</p>
<p>Modern humans – also known as Homo sapiens – began in Africa hundreds of thousands of years ago and later started spreading to Europe, Asia and other places. Scientists believe that at some point, they met and mated with Neanderthals. The mixing of these groups had a major influence on humans' <strong>genetic code</strong>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image provided by Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology shows an artist's illustration of ancient humans from Ranis, Germany and the Czech Republic traveling together 45,000 years ago.(Tom Bj&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;246;rklund/Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4146b084-23f5-4f15-a2b7-430df9e86fb5_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image provided by Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology shows an artist's illustration of ancient humans from Ranis, Germany and the Czech Republic traveling together 45,000 years ago.(Tom Bj<i>&amp;#</i>246;rklund/Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology via AP)</span></div>
<p>However, scientists do not know exactly when or how the two groups interacted. But the two new studies provide some additional details about the timing of this contact.</p>
<p>One group of scientists examined genetic material from three female and three male Homo sapien individuals who lived around 45,000 years ago. Reuters news agency reported that research involved the oldest genes from Homo sapiens ever examined, or sequenced.</p>
<p>Some of the genes came from bones found in a <strong>cave</strong> in the central German village of Ranis. Other material came from a woman believed to have lived at around the same time in a cave in a mountainous area of what is now the Czech Republic.</p>
<p>Researchers estimated the period of mixing between Neanderthals and humans at about 49,000 to 45,000 years ago. The findings were recently published in a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-08420-x">study</a> in <em>Nature</em>.</p>
<p>A second group of researchers examined genetic material from 300 present-day and ancient Homo sapiens. This included 59 individuals who lived between 2,000 and 45,000 years ago. That <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adq3010">study</a>, published in the journal <em>Science</em>, estimated the period of mixing at about 50,500 to 43,500 years ago.</p>
<p>The scientists said their new findings on the mixing and mating of the groups suggested the activities happened a little more recently than thought in the past. They believe the contact continued over many generations.</p>
<p>Priya Moorjani was co-writer of the study appearing in <em>Science</em>. She is an assistant professor of molecular and cell biology at the University of California, Berkeley. She told Reuters, “Genetic data from these <strong>samples </strong>really helps us paint a picture in more and more detail.”</p>
<p>The team noted that it is difficult to know the exact nature of the interactions between Homo sapiens and Neanderthals based on the examined data. The researchers also could not confirm exactly where the mixing and mating happened. However, they believe it was most likely somewhere in the Middle East.</p>
<p>The researchers noted most modern humans still have genetic material from Neanderthals that accounts for an estimated one to two percent of their DNA. They said modern-day genetic <strong>traits</strong> linked to skin color, hair color and even nose shape can relate back to the Neanderthals. Our genetic makeup also includes links to another group of human ancestors called Denisovans.</p>
<p>Moorjani noted that the history of Neanderthals living outside Africa for thousands of years likely gave them a greater ability to deal with climate and diseases in new environments. “Some of their genes may have been <strong>beneficial</strong> to modern humans,” she added.</p>
<p>Rick Potts is director of the Smithsonian Institution's Human Origins program. He was not involved in the new research. Potts told The Associated Press he hopes future genetic studies can help scientists learn even more details about the interactions of Neanderthals and modern humans.</p>
<p>He said, “Out of many really<strong> compelling </strong>areas of scientific investigation, one of them is: well, who are we?”</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters and Nature. </em></p>
<p><strong>_______________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>genetic code</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> information from DNA or RNA that is used to create an organism's proteins</p>
<p><strong>cave </strong><em>– n. </em>a large hole in the side of a mountain or underground</p>
<p><strong>sample </strong><em>– n. </em>a small amount of something that gives you information about the thing it was taken from</p>
<p><strong>trait</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n. </em>a quality, good or bad, in someone's character</p>
<p><strong>beneficial </strong><em>– adj. </em>helpful or useful</p>
<p><strong>compelling</strong> <em>– adj.</em> demanding attention</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>AI Tools Often Used for Fake Product Reviews  (2025/1/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/ai-tools-often-used-for-fake-product-reviews.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Artificial intelligence (AI) tools that permit people to produce online <strong>reviews </strong>have put sellers, service providers and buyers in unfamiliar territory, public protection groups and researchers say.</p>
<p>False, or fake, reviews have long appeared on many popular websites such as Amazon and Yelp. The reviews are often traded on private social media groups between fake review dealers and businesses willing to pay. Sometimes, businesses get good reviews in exchange for offering buyers rewards such as gift cards.</p>
<p>But AI tools, popularized by OpenAI's ChatGPT, permit people to produce reviews faster and in greater numbers, technology industry experts say.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Online customer reviews for a product are displayed on a computer on April 17, 2019 in New York.(AP Photo/Jenny Kane)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4854bda8-e5a7-4daa-9de2-c68a53e04021_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Online customer reviews for a product are displayed on a computer on April 17, 2019 in New York.(AP Photo/Jenny Kane)</span></div>
<p><strong>Where are AI-generated reviews appearing? </strong></p>
<p>Fake reviews are found across a wide range of industries, from e-commerce and travel to services such as home repairs, medical care and music lessons.</p>
<p>The Transparency Company is a technology company and public protection group that uses software to detect fake reviews. The company said it started to see AI-generated reviews appear in large numbers in mid-2023. The reviews have increased quickly ever since.</p>
<p>For a recently released report, The Transparency Company examined 73 million reviews in three areas: home, legal and medical services. Nearly 14 percent of the reviews were likely fake. The company expressed a “high degree of confidence” that 2.3 million reviews were partly or entirely AI-produced.</p>
<p>Last September, the Federal Trade Commission (FTC) took legal action against the company behind an AI writing tool and content producer called Rytr. The FTC accused Rytr of offering a service that could pollute the marketplace with fake reviews.</p>
<p>The FTC, which banned the sale or purchase of fake reviews in 2024, said some of Rytr's buyers used the tool to produce hundreds and perhaps thousands of reviews. The reviews appeared in support of garage door repair companies, sellers of copied designer handbags and other businesses.</p>
<p><strong>What are companies doing? </strong></p>
<p>Major companies are developing policies for how AI-generated content fits into their systems for removing fake reviews. Some companies already employ special programs and investigative teams to find and remove fake reviews. Still, the companies are giving users some ability to use AI.</p>
<p>Spokespeople for Amazon and Trustpilot, for example, said they would permit buyers to post AI-assisted reviews as long as the buyers represent their true experience. Yelp has taken a more cautious approach, saying its rules require reviewers to write their own reviews.</p>
<p>The Coalition for Trusted Reviews, which Amazon, Trustpilot, Glassdoor, Tripadvisor, Expedia and Booking.com launched last year, said that even though people may put AI to illegal use, the technology also presents “an <strong>opportunity</strong> to push back against those who seek to use reviews to <strong>mislead </strong>others.”</p>
<p>The FTC's rule banning fake reviews, which took effect in October, permits the agency to fine businesses and individuals who take part in fake reviews. Tech companies hosting such reviews are protected from the penalty. This is because they are not legally responsible under U.S. law for the content that outsiders post on their websites.</p>
<p>Tech companies, including Amazon, Yelp and Google, have <strong>sued</strong> fake review dealers they accuse of selling fake reviews on their sites. The companies say their technology has blocked or removed a large number of suspect reviews and suspicious accounts. However, some experts say they could be doing more.</p>
<p>“Their efforts thus far are not nearly enough,” said Kay Dean, a former federal criminal investigator who runs a public protection group called Fake Review Watch. “If these tech companies are so committed to eliminating review <strong>fraud</strong> on their platforms, why is it that I, one individual who works with no automation, can find hundreds or even thousands of fake reviews on any given day?”</p>
<p><strong>Finding fake reviews </strong></p>
<p>Consumers can try to find fake reviews by watching out for a few possible warning signs, researchers say. Overly good or bad reviews are suspect. Highly specialized terms that repeat a product's full name or model number are another possible <strong>clue.</strong></p>
<p>When it comes to AI, research done by Balázs Kovács, a Yale professor, has shown that people cannot tell the difference between AI-created and human-written reviews. Some AI <strong>detectors</strong> may also be fooled by shorter texts, which are common in online reviews, the study said.</p>
<p>However, there are some AI clues that online shoppers and service seekers should keep in mind. Panagram Labs says reviews written with AI are often longer, highly structured and include “empty descriptors.” Empty descriptors include general phrases and attributes or characteristics. The writing also often includes overused phrases or opinions like “the first thing that struck me” and “game-changer.”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p>And I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Haleluya Hadero reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>___________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>review </strong>-- n. an evaluation or assessment of a product or service</p>
<p><strong>opportunity </strong><em>-- n.</em> a good chance for progress</p>
<p><strong>mislead </strong>– v. to lead in a wrong direction or into a mistaken action</p>
<p><strong>sue </strong><em>-- v. </em><strong> </strong>to seek justice from someone by legal process</p>
<p><strong>fraud</strong> -- n. intentional changing of truth in order to get another person to part with something of value</p>
<p><strong>automation</strong> – n. automatically controlled operation of a system by and electronic device that takes the place of human labor</p>
<p><strong>clue </strong><em>-- n. </em>an idea; a piece of evidence that leads one toward a solution</p>
<p><strong>detect</strong><em>-- v. </em>to find or discover the true nature of something; to discover something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Some on Indonesian Islands Fear Mining Damage to Environment  (2025/1/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/some-on-indonesian-islands-fear-mining-damage-to-environment.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Indonesia has the world's largest known supply of nickel and major supplies of valuable minerals, including cobalt and bauxite. However, the mining industry there is being criticized for not protecting the environment and some Indonesian island people.</p>
<p>The Southeast Asian country is involved in mining that produces materials important to the manufacture of stainless steel and electric vehicle <strong>batteries</strong>, among other things.</p>
<p>Indonesia is aiming to expand its mining and processing industries. But the development could face opposition from international and local groups.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A nickel mine is visible on top of a hill above a village on Kabaena Island, Indonesia, Thursday, Nov. 14, 2024. (AP Photo/Yusuf Wahil)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/95ee8fb0-2641-46e1-bba3-362740d73267_cx0_cy7_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A nickel mine is visible on top of a hill above a village on Kabaena Island, Indonesia, Thursday, Nov. 14, 2024. (AP Photo/Yusuf Wahil)</span></div>
<p>Nickel processing centers are becoming more common in parts of Indonesia. Sometimes, the plants are near the sea where many boats line up to carry ore, a mineral combination that contains nickel. Sometimes, these plants are near schools or places where local people fish or farm.</p>
<p>The World Resources Institute, based in Washington D.C., says from 2001 to 2020, 1.4 million hectares of trees were cut down around the world. Indonesia is estimated to have had the highest loss.</p>
<p>Amanda Hurowitz is a director with Mighty Earth. The environmental group is also based in Washington, D.C. Hurowitz said that, on the island of Kabaena, mining companies have cleared 3,700 hectares of forest in the last 22 years.</p>
<p>Fishermen who used to fish off the island have said the waters are filled with sediment from the mines. People in farming communities also say they are affected. They say sugar cane, sugar palms and clove trees do not grow well anymore.</p>
<p>Amal Susanto is a sugar palm farmer. He said: “That's the effect: The growth of the sugar palm trees will not be as good because of the influence of mining.” Susanto lives in an area where permits have been approved but mining has not yet begun.</p>
<p>People living in the area have reported health problems. Some told the Associated Press (AP) that they suffered from itchy skin, <strong>sore</strong> throat and other difficulties.</p>
<p>The Indonesia-based nonprofit group Satya Bumi sent water, dust and shellfish from the area to a laboratory this year. The group said the results showed dangerous levels of nickel, lead and cadmium. These substances are linked to mining.</p>
<p>Kathrin Shilling is an assistant professor and biology researcher at Columbia University in New York City. She studied the lab results. Shilling told the AP, “If people on this island are using the river water as drinking water...you cannot escape basically any of the exposure to those <strong>toxic</strong> metals.”</p>
<p>Kabaena is not the only place affected. To the north, on a larger island, Torobulu is another place where mining damage can be seen.</p>
<p>The mining problems continue although Indonesia's constitutional court ruled in March of this year that small islands such as Kabaena should have special protection. However, a researcher from Satya Bumi said the government is still approving mining permits.</p>
<p>The group Mighty Earth said 150 hectares of forest have been cleared on Kabaena since April 1. And it said over half of that was on land controlled by the mining company Tonia Mitra Sejahtera. The company and Indonesia's Ministry of Energy and Mineral Resources did not answer requests for comment from the AP.</p>
<p>Amiruddin is a 53-year-old fisherman on Kabaena Island. He said the results of the government permits for mining have affected many people.</p>
<p>“All residents here have felt the impact,” he said.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Yusuf Wahil and Victoria Milko reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>__________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>batteries</strong> –n. a device that chemically stores power and can produce electrical current<br/>
<strong>sore</strong> –adj. painful<br/>
<strong>toxic</strong> –adj. something that is poisonous</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How Serious Is Bird Flu Outbreak?  (2024/12/31)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/how-serious-is-bird-flu-outbreak.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">30 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>California officials have declared a state of emergency over the spread of bird flu. It is affecting milk cows in that state and causing illnesses in some people in other U.S. states.</p>
<p>The avian influenza virus, or bird flu, has spread among wild birds, farm birds and many mammal <strong>species</strong>.</p>
<p>The virus is known as Type A H5N1. It was identified for the first time in U.S. milk cows in March. Since then, bird flu has been found in about one third of U.S. states.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This colorized electron microscope image released by the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases on March 26, 2024, shows avian influenza A H5N1 virus particles. (CDC/NIAID via AP, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1c9e72b8-5e9c-4427-bc4d-1024fc984586_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This colorized electron microscope image released by the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases on March 26, 2024, shows avian influenza A H5N1 virus particles. (CDC/NIAID via AP, File)</span></div>
<p>The U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) is following the number of cases and is reporting the latest details on its <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cdc.gov/bird-flu/situation-summary/index.html" target="_blank">website</a>. Most of the illnesses have been mild. Health officials said that one person in Louisiana was hospitalized with the nation's first known severe illness caused by the virus.</p>
<p>California Governor Gavin Newsom said he declared the state of emergency so state workers could take faster action.</p>
<p>California officials have been testing milk tanks. They said they have found the virus in hundreds of <strong>herds</strong>. The virus was recently found in Southern California <strong>dairy</strong> farms. It was found in the state's Central Valley in August.</p>
<p><strong>What is the risk to the general public?</strong></p>
<p>Officials with the CDC repeated that the public has a low risk of getting the virus. There are no reports of person-to-person infection and no signs that the virus has changed to spread easily among humans.</p>
<p>Flu experts say it is too soon to know how the situation will change. But some experts are worried because flu viruses are <strong>mutating</strong> all the time and small genetic changes could take place.</p>
<p><strong>Are cases becoming more serious?</strong></p>
<p>Health officials said the first known case of severe illness in the U.S. was found in a patient in Louisiana. The person is older than 65 and has other medical problems. Officials said the person showed severe breathing problems after being near a group of sick birds. The CDC said that the Louisiana case is the first confirmed U.S. infection connected with <strong>backyard</strong> birds, or birds kept near a home.</p>
<p>Almost all the earlier infections in the U.S. have been in farmworkers dealing with infected dairy cattle or birds. In two cases — an adult in Missouri and a child in California — health officials have not learned how they became infected.</p>
<p>Angela Rasmussen is a virus expert at the University of Saskatchewan in Canada. She said as more people become infected, more severe illnesses will be reported. Rasmussen said, "I <strong>assume</strong> that every H5N1 virus has the <strong>potential</strong> to be very severe and deadly."</p>
<p>The World Health Organization says on its website that from 2003 to November 2024 about 142 people died from the H5N1 virus around the world. Most of the deaths were in Southeast Asia.</p>
<p><strong>How can people protect themselves?</strong></p>
<p>People who have contact with dairy cows, commercial <strong>poultry</strong> or with backyard birds are at higher risk than other people. CDC and other experts said those people should use breathing, eye, and hand protection, especially if the animals appear ill or if they die.</p>
<p>The CDC said in July that it would buy $5 million in vaccines for farmworkers to protect against seasonal flu. If someone becomes infected with two flu types at the same time, it might permit the bird flu virus to mutate and to become more dangerous.</p>
<p><strong>How else is bird flu spread?</strong></p>
<p>The H5N1 virus can also be spread in raw, or <strong>unpasteurized</strong>, milk. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration says pasteurized milk is safe to drink because the heat treatment kills the virus.</p>
<p>But high levels of the virus have been found in unpasteurized milk. Health officials urge people to avoid drinking raw milk. It can spread other germs in addition to bird flu.</p>
<p>The U.S. Agriculture Department has increased its testing of raw milk across the country to identify and contain avian flu. Federal officials ordered milk testing which began this month in 13 states.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Jonel Aleccia reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>mild </strong><em>–adj.</em> having little effect on a person, not severe at all</p>
<p><strong>herd </strong><em>–n</em>. a group of animals such as cattle or sheep</p>
<p><strong>dairy</strong> <em>– adj.</em> of or relating to a type of farming that deals with the production of milk and foods made from milk</p>
<p><strong>mutate </strong>- <em>v</em>. to cause (a gene) to change and create an unusual characteristic in a plant or animal</p>
<p><strong>backyard</strong> – <em>n</em>. the general area near and around someone's home</p>
<p><strong>assume </strong><em>–v.</em> to take something as correct without confirming that it is correct or right</p>
<p><strong>potential</strong> – <em>n</em>. a chance or possibility that something will happen or exist in the future</p>
<p><strong>poultry</strong> – <em>n</em>. birds (such as chickens and ducks) that are raised on farms for their eggs or meat</p>
<p><strong>pasteurized</strong> – <em>adj</em>. put through a process in which a liquid (such as milk or cream) is heated to a temperature that kills harmful germs and then cooled quickly</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Top Technology Stories of 2024  (2024/12/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/top-technology-stories-of-2024.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Throughout 2024, we saw further development of artificial intelligence (AI) systems and new legal action brought against technology companies. Here is a look back at some of the biggest tech stories we covered in 2024.</p>
<p><strong>AI continues to expand</strong></p>
<p>During the year, companies continued developing and deploying new AI tools.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Google, Microsoft and Alphabet logos and AI Artificial Intelligence words are seen in this illustration from May 4, 2023. (REUTERS/Dado Ruvic/Illustration)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/3ae36539-6083-4186-917d-a0367dde2d0c_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Google, Microsoft and Alphabet logos and AI Artificial Intelligence words are seen in this illustration from May 4, 2023. (REUTERS/Dado Ruvic/Illustration)</span></div>
<p>Among these were a new set of AI offerings announced by American software company Microsoft. Officials <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/microsoft-s-ai-agents-aim-to-take-over-many-human-duties/7876418.html">explained</a> the new tools included “personal agents” designed to help users complete business activities with little or no human involvement.</p>
<p>Microsoft says it designed the agents to expand on so-called chatbots – AI tools that work by themselves to produce human-level writing or discussions. The company said it expects a full release of the agents sometime in 2025.</p>
<p>In September, technology company Apple <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/apple-launches-new-iphone-built-for-ai-/7780192.html">announced</a> it was launching several new iPhones equipped with special <strong>chips</strong> to support AI operations. Apple chief Tim Cook said the new models had been “designed for Apple Intelligence from the ground up.”</p>
<p>We reported in October about an effort by researchers to use AI to improve existing weather prediction models. One system works by combining past weather predictions with modern methods to provide the most complete picture of weather and climate data.</p>
<p><strong>More warnings AI's possible dangers</strong></p>
<p>In California, three legislative measures were <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/new-california-laws-aim-to-prevent-ai-harm-during-elections/7797015.html">enacted</a> to ban the use of AI tools to create false images and videos during election campaigns. One main goal was to fight deepfakes. These are pieces of video or audio created to make it appear that people in it are saying or doing things they never said or did. Deepfakes were used in several world election campaigns in 2024.</p>
<p>In May, an international gathering of major AI developers and top government officials in Seoul <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/business-political-leaders-agree-to-safely-develop-deploy-ai/7622826.html">agreed</a> on measures that aim to ensure that AI systems are safely built and deployed. Attendees from 16 different technology companies signed a promise to develop AI technology in ways that limit possible public harms.</p>
<p><strong>US legal moves against tech companies</strong></p>
<p>About one year ago, an American jury <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/jury-rules-google-app-store-operates-as-monopoly/7396589.html">found</a> that Google's app store operates as an illegal monopoly. Then in August 2024, a federal judge ruled that Google had violated trade laws by operating its search engine as a <strong>monopoly</strong>. The ruling accused Google of paying smartphone makers to ensure that its search engine was set as the <strong>default</strong> system on new devices.</p>
<p>As part of the case, the U.S. government proposed in November a series of measures to limit Google from anti-competition business activities. Google criticized the court's ruling as an example of government overreach. U.S. officials have long warned that TikTok presents national security concerns.</p>
<p>Earlier this month, video sharing service TikTok <a class="wsw__a" href="file:///C:/Users/ckweaver/Downloads/TikTok%20has%20asked%20a%20U.S.%20appeals%20court%20to%20temporarily%20block%20a%20law%20requiring%20its%20parent%20company,%20ByteDance,%20to%20divest%20itself%20of%20the%20popular%20video%20sharing%20service,%20or%20face%20a%20U.S.%20ban">asked</a> a U.S. appeals court to block a law requiring its Chinese parent, ByteDance, to <strong>divest</strong> itself of TikTok or face a U.S. ban. The request came after the same court had upheld a law forcing ByteDance to sell TikTok by January 19 or face the ban. Lawyers for ByteDance and TikTok are seeking to have the U.S. Supreme Court rule on the case.</p>
<p><strong>Self-driving tech</strong></p>
<p>In May, U.S.-based Aurora Innovation <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/driverless-trucks-set-to-hit-us-highways/7595728.html">said</a> it was preparing to launch a series of driverless trucks to transport goods on a major public highway. Company officials said it planned to begin the service in Texas, with 20 tractor-trailers transporting goods between Dallas and Houston. The company hopes to expand the service to thousands of tractor-trailers within three to four years.</p>
<p><strong>Flying taxis</strong></p>
<p>In October, the U.S. Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/us-agency-issues-final-rules-for-flying-air-taxis/7837729.html">announced</a> it had issued final rules for operating air taxis. It also set training and approval requirements for pilots. The FAA said air taxis belong to a kind of aircraft known as Advanced Air Mobility (AAM) flyers. They generally operate on their own on electrical power, with <strong>vertical</strong> take-off and landing abilities.</p>
<p>FAA Administrator Mike Whitaker said such aircraft represent “the first new <strong>category</strong> of aircraft in nearly 80 years.” He added that the new rules are meant to mark the beginning of possible widespread AAM operations across the U.S. in the future.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>chip </strong><em>– n. </em>a very small slice of silicon containing electronic circuits (as for a computer)<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>monopoly</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> complete control of the entire supply of goods or of a service in a certain area or market</p>
<p><strong>default </strong><em>– adj. </em>what exists or usually happens if no changes are made</p>
<p><strong>divest </strong><em>– v. </em>to sell something, especially a business or part of a business</p>
<p><strong>vertical</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj. </em>pointing straight up from a surface</p>
<p><strong>category </strong><em>– n. </em>a group of people of things of a similar kind</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Large Chilean Frog at Risk from Climate Change  (2024/12/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/large-chilean-frog-at-risk-from-climate-change.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A large frog <strong>species</strong> that lived alongside dinosaurs and is considered a "living fossil" is now losing ground in its native Chile.</p>
<p>Climate change and human actions are damaging the creature's living environment, or habitat.</p>
<p>The Helmeted Water Toad is one of the largest frogs in the world, growing up to over 30 centimeters in length and weighing up to one kilogram.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A Chilean frog (Calyptocephalella gayi) sits on a tree trunk in a wetland in the middle of a neighbourhood in the city of Quilpue, Chile, December 8, 2024. (REUTERS/Rodrigo Garrido)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a53e07d4-4c39-4163-8378-d60c5aa4e176_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A Chilean frog (Calyptocephalella gayi) sits on a tree trunk in a wetland in the middle of a neighbourhood in the city of Quilpue, Chile, December 8, 2024. (REUTERS/Rodrigo Garrido)</span></div>
<p>The <strong>amphibian</strong> has experienced little genetic change for millions of years. But now its future is at risk, scientists say.</p>
<p>"It's sad that a species that managed to coexist with dinosaurs, that managed to resist a mass <strong>extinction</strong>, is now threatened by human beings," said Melissa Cancino. Cancino is an animal doctor and founder of Proyecto Anfibia, a group that works on amphibian research and education in Chile.</p>
<p>The Helmeted Water Toad's environment covers a large part of the country, but its population is suspected to have decreased by at least 30 percent since 1990. The creature is identified as "<strong>vulnerable</strong>" on the International Union for Conservation of Nature's (IUCN) Red List.</p>
<p>Climate change, habitat changes, environmental decline and pollution have all caused the Helmeted Water Toad's numbers to decline, Cancino said. Poor water and waste management have also threatened the frog's living environment.</p>
<p>Matias Faundez, another member of Proyecto Anfibia, has seen the damage first hand.</p>
<p>"This <strong>estuary</strong> runs through the whole city, and has plenty of illegal run-offs," he said as he walked through a stream outside of Valparaiso. "Even so," he added, "the frog manages to survive."</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Rodrigo Gutierrez reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>species </strong><em>– n.</em> a class of animals having common attributes and a common name</p>
<p><strong>amphibian</strong><em> – n. </em>any of a class of cold-blooded animals (such as frogs) that have gilled aquatic young and air-breathing adult</p>
<p><strong>vulnerable</strong> <em>– adj.</em> open to attack or damage</p>
<p><strong>extinction</strong><em> – n.</em> the act of completely dying off</p>
<p><strong>estuary</strong><em> – n.</em> a part of the sea at the lower end of a river</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>A Guide to Recovering Overgrown Garden  (2024/12/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/a-guide-to-recovering-overgrown-garden.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>What is the best way to repair an overgrown <strong>garden</strong>?</p>
<p>Garden expert for the Associated Press Jessica Damiano believes she knows the answer.</p>
<p>Here are some of her suggestions for making big improvements. Planning in the autumn and winter months can help you see something much more beautiful next winter:</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This May 2023 image provided by Jessica Damiano shows a neglected, overgrown property on Long Island, New York. (Jessica Damiano via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1154133e-0c4a-4403-ba45-0462282d41c4_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This May 2023 image provided by Jessica Damiano shows a neglected, overgrown property on Long Island, New York. (Jessica Damiano via AP)</span></div>
<p><strong>Decide what to clear away</strong></p>
<p>First, take a notebook with you and walk around the garden. Look carefully at each part. Try to decide which plants can be saved, which to throw away, and which ones require attention. Make a list as soon as you can.</p>
<p>Dead plants, <strong>weeds</strong> and invasive plants should be first to go. If the weather permits, dig them out, removing as much of their root systems as possible. Otherwise, wait until spring to do this before planting.</p>
<p>Next, remove and give away healthy plants that you do not want. Online groups and neighborhood web pages are places to find people to receive the plants. Many people will even be willing to do the digging if it means getting a free plant.</p>
<p>If the garden is full of plants, shrubs, trees and vines that have grown wild, you might need to use a <strong>chainsaw</strong> or heavy machine.</p>
<p><strong>Define any new beds</strong></p>
<p>If there are a lot of weeds or if you want to create new garden beds, you can cover the existing <strong>vegetation</strong> rather than dig it up. Decide the size and shape of the area you want to make into a new bed.</p>
<p>Cover that area with <strong>cardboard</strong> or lots of newspaper. Put about seven centimeters of <strong>compost</strong> and five centimeters of <strong>mulch</strong> on top of it. You can start in the autumn and leave it there over the winter until planting time in the spring.</p>
<p>When it is time to plant, cut holes in the cardboard or paper big enough for the roots of your plants. The covering over the ground will keep most weeds from growing. Some weeds may break through and require pulling or more cardboard, Damiano said.</p>
<p><strong>How and when to prune</strong></p>
<p>Healthy but overgrown or unproductive deciduous <strong>shrubs</strong> can be brought back to life by <strong>pruning</strong>. “Deciduous” means that the plants lose their leaves during the winter season. The best time to prune many plants is when their branches are bare in late winter.</p>
<p>Choosing a pruning method will require weighing appearance against the time it will take to recover. The fastest and most severe method would be to cut the whole plant down just above ground level. Although extreme, many shrubs can deal with this form of pruning and will <strong>bounce back</strong> stronger.</p>
<p>If keeping the plant looking normal is important, prune each branch or stem individually at uneven heights. It is also possible to cut back one-third of the plant's branches each year for three years. That method would have the least severe effect but requires the most patience.</p>
<p>Evergreen trees and shrubs should only undergo light pruning such as the shortening of individual branches. Take care to avoid pruning too much or creating holes in evergreen plants and trees. With the exception of yews, they do not regrow from such damage.</p>
<p><strong>Looking to the dirt</strong></p>
<p>Now that you have taken care of pruning, turn your attention to the soil.</p>
<p>Test the soil's pH, or its acidity level. Do this to make sure the soil is good for the plants you plan to add. Test <strong>kits</strong> are available at local garden stores and online. In the United States, a cooperative extension service might provide soil testing and soil-amendment advice for a small cost. Cooperative extension services are part of a Department of Agriculture system that includes some universities. It aims to help farmers and people interested in plants.</p>
<p>If the soil is hard, break it up with a machine or hand tools. Finally, spread five to seven centimeters of compost over the area. As it breaks down, nutrients will work their way into the soil.</p>
<p><strong>Planting considerations</strong></p>
<p>After completing these steps, it will be time to plant your new garden. Choose new trees, shrubs or <strong>perennials</strong>, that will not grow wildly. Dig holes as deep as their roots but two times as wide and space them out to their expected full-grown sizes. Native plants are good because they need little added water or special care.</p>
<p>Plant groundcover – short, spreading plants – to cover the ground and keep weeds from growing and the soil from drying out. It might take one or two years, but a step-by-step approach will make gardening a joy again.</p>
<p>And, perhaps best of all, you will see something beautiful when you look outside from your home.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jessica Damiano reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>garden</strong> <em>– n.</em> a plot of ground where herbs, fruits, flowers, or vegetables are grown</p>
<p><strong>weed </strong><em>–n.</em> an undesirable plant that grows grow thickly and crowds out more desirable plants</p>
<p><strong>chain saw </strong><em>– n.</em> a tool with sharp metal teeth that cuts through wood</p>
<p><strong>vegetation </strong><em>–n.</em> <strong> </strong>plant life or total plant cover (as of an area)</p>
<p><strong>cardboard</strong> <em>– n.</em> a material made from cellulose fiber (as wood pulp) like paper but usually thicker</p>
<p><strong>compost</strong> <em>– n.</em> <strong> </strong>a mixture that consists largely of decayed organic matter and is used for fertilizing and conditioning land</p>
<p><strong>mulch </strong><em>– n.</em> a covering (as of straw or sawdust) spread over the ground to protect the roots of plants from heat, cold, or evaporation, prevent soil loss, control weeds, enrich the soil, or keep fruit (as strawberries) clean</p>
<p><strong>shrub</strong> <em>– n.</em> a woody plant that has several stems and is smaller than most trees</p>
<p><strong>prune </strong><em>– v. </em>to cut off the parts of a woody plant that are dead or not wanted</p>
<p><strong>bounce back </strong><em>–v. (phrasal)</em> to return quickly to a normal condition after a difficult situation or event</p>
<p><strong>kit </strong><em>–n.</em> a set of tools or supplies</p>
<p><strong>perennial </strong><em>– n.</em> a plant that lives for several years usually with new leafy growth produced from the base each year</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Expressions for New Year's Resolution  (2024/12/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/expressions-for-new-year-s-resolution.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>During a new year, many of us decide to try something new. With a new year's <strong>resolution</strong>, we resolve to do something we have not done in the past.</p>
<p>Sometimes new things are risk-free – like eating healthier food or getting more exercise.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Fireworks are seen over Victoria Harbour at midnight on New Years Sunday Jan. 1, 2023 in Hong Kong. (AP Photo/Anthony Kwan)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/022a0000-0aff-0242-fa57-08daeb62d345_cx5_cy7_cw91_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Fireworks are seen over Victoria Harbour at midnight on New Years Sunday Jan. 1, 2023 in Hong Kong. (AP Photo/Anthony Kwan)</span></div>
<p>Sometimes we decide to learn a new skill, like a language or a musical instrument. Again, these things are not risky, nor do they have bad <strong>consequences</strong>. If you do not learn how to play the guitar, nothing bad will happen — probably.</p>
<p>However, sometimes we need to <strong>shake up</strong> our lives and do something different that <em>does</em> have consequences. That means there are risks if things do not work out.</p>
<p>Such a change could involve moving to a new city, starting a new job, or ending a relationship. These new things<em> do</em> have a level of risk . Things could go wrong. On the other hand, things could go very right.</p>
<p>So, for these situations, we introduce two expressions that <strong>encourage</strong> you to take a chance.</p>
<p><strong>Nothing ventured, nothing gained.</strong></p>
<p>The first expression is <u>nothing <strong>ventured</strong>, nothing gained.</u></p>
<p>This means that without doing something risky or difficult, a bad situation will not improve. You could also sum it up this way: If you try something risky, you could fail. But if you do not try at all ... you will surely fail.</p>
<p>The word “venture” can be both a noun and a verb. As a verb, it means to proceed in a dangerous or risky plan. As a noun, it means an action that involves chance, risk, or danger.</p>
<p>For example, starting a new restaurant is a risky business venture these days. And venturing into an unknown area could be dangerous.</p>
<p>A friend of mine wanted to learn how to drive a stunt car and then move to Los Angeles to become a stunt car driver. A stunt car is a vehicle used in the movies to perform crashes and wild driving. There are not many women in this profession. So, I told her that her decision involved lots of risk. She said to me: “Well, <u>nothing ventured, nothing gained</u>.”</p>
<p><strong>Fortune favors the bold.</strong></p>
<p>Our second expression is <strong><u>fortune favors</u></strong><u> the <strong>bold</strong>.</u></p>
<p>“Fortune” usually means wealth or fame. But it can also mean being in a good situation. And, if you are bold, you are brave.</p>
<p>So, this expression means that people who are brave and take chances help themselves. Their bold, brave actions put them in a good place.</p>
<p>When using this expression, keep this in mind. The person who finds a fortune has done something to get it. It just doesn't happen to them by chance. So, if someone happens to win a lot of money in a lottery, you wouldn't use the expression <u>fortune favors the bold</u>.</p>
<p>However, let's say you quit your job and moved to a new city. That is a bold decision. But you are sure that it will be good for you. In the new city, you find your dream job. It might even pay more money than your old job. Here, you could definitely say, “<u>Fortune favors the bold</u>!”</p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>. For the start of 2023, I wish you and yours health and wealth.</p>
<p>Until next time ... I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>resolution </strong>–n. a promise to yourself to do something you believe you should do</p>
<p><strong>consequence </strong>–n. the result of an action usually that is meaningful or serious</p>
<p><strong>encourage </strong>–v. to make someone likely to take some action</p>
<p><strong>shake up </strong><em>–v. (phrasal</em>) to make a lot of changes or to make a big change</p>
<p><strong>venture </strong>–v. to do something that involves risk and reward</p>
<p><strong>fortune </strong>–n. wealth, fame or good conditions (often because of influences beyond direct control of an individual)</p>
<p><strong>favor</strong> –v. to approve of or to support</p>
<p><strong>bold </strong>–adj. not afraid of danger of difficult situations</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
