<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>VOA Special English</title>
        <link>https://www.21voa.com/special_english/</link>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <itunes:category>ESL</itunes:category>
        <itunes:author>VOA</itunes:author>
        <description>美国之音（以下称VOA）的英语节目，按播音速度可分为两种：Standard English （标准英语）和 Special English（特别英语）。

Special English 又叫“慢速英语”，是VOA 专为全世界非英语国家初学英语的听众安排的一种简易、规范的英语广播节目。该节目创始于50年代末期，是VOA 的专家们研究如何与世界各地的英语学习者进行交际的产物。它正式开播于1959年10月。当时只面向欧洲和中东，但由于这个节目适合许多国家英语学习者的需要，所以它的广播对象不久就扩大到世界其他地区，并很快在全世界范围内产生了广泛的影响。现在这个节目对欧洲、非洲和拉丁美洲每晚广播一次，对加勒比地区每晚广播一次（星期天除外），对东南亚广播次数最多，每天上午两次，晚上三次。

30多年来，VOA 为了办好Special English节目，进行了大量的调查研究工作，对播音速度、内容及用词范围都作了具体规定，基本上达到了既能为英语学习者提供信息，又不损害英语本身风格的目的，使之成为VOA 独具特色，拥有最大量听众的节目。

美国著名词汇学家S. B. Flexmer 指明了Special English的三条标准，也就是它所“特别”的地方：

1、它是一种由美国人最常用的1500个基本单词为主体构成的美国英语；

2、它用简短、明晰的句子写作和广播；

3、它以每分钟90个单词的速度，即2/3的Standard English（标准英语）速度进行广播。

Special English的节目可分为两大类：一类是新闻节目；一类是专题节目。

1．新闻节目

VOA Special English 的新闻广播向听众提供世界范围内的政治、经济、军事、外交、国际关系、宗教、天气以及各种重大事件和珍闻奇事等各个方面的信息，每天向东南亚地区广播五次，早上两次，晚上三次，每逢半点播出。

Special English新闻节目每次长约十分钟，大都播出十条左右新闻，近一千个单词，每条新闻多为一分钟，但偶尔也有长达两分钟的要闻。除头条新闻外，每条新闻都由一个电头引导，这样显得结构分明，条理清晰，适宜初学英语的人收听。在节目结束之前，播音员常常用三四句话重播其中三条新闻的提要以加深听众对要闻的印象。

Special English新闻中70%左右的内容与同时整点播出的Standard English新闻相同，但相同新闻的先后次序有所变动。每次节目的开头和结尾大同小异，格式比较固定。

2．专题节目（一）

Special English的专题节目（Feature Programs）,从时间上看，可分为两大类：一是每五分钟一次的专题，二是每十五分钟一次的专题。本节先介绍每项五分钟一次的专题材节目。

Special English五分钟一次的专题材节目安排在Special English新闻节目之后和（或）每十五分钟一次的专题材节目之前播出，每星期播七次。根据内容，可分为三个小类，即：Science Report（科学报道），逢星期一、三、五播出，每天播六遍；Agriculture Report（农业报道），逢星期二、四播出，每天播六遍；Words And Their Stories（词语掌故），逢星期六和星期天播出，每天播五遍。这三个专题材各具特色，具有相对的独立性，听众每听完一个节目，都会获得一个完整的印象。

Science Report（科学报道）这一专题材节目每周向听众介绍三篇有关现代科学技术最新发展情况的报道，涉及物理、化学、天文至高无上理、生物、环卫、心理、教育、医学和计算机等方面。适宜理工科大学生和科技工作者收集信息，积累资料，学习科技英语。

Agriculture Report（农业报道） Agriculture Report是为农业科技工作者和生产者安排的一个专题。它专门报道世界各国，特别是美国现代农业生产的最新成文汇报总务科 学家对农业生产某一方面的研究进展，以及他们对影响农业生产的某一自然现象进行分析和研究的近况。此外，它还经常向听众介绍发展中国家家业生产的一些有益经验等内容。

Words And Their Stories（词语掌故）这一专题节目，旨在向学习英语的听众介绍美国英语中生动有趣的词语和惯用法，并从科学研究和通俗词源学的角度来解释它们的含意、产生的背景及其在使用过程中的演变情况等。它通过讲故事的形式讲解每一个词语。这是VOA Special English中的优秀节目之一，是学习美国英语的极好材料。通过收听这一节目，听众不仅能学到娓娓动听的掌故和地道的美国英语，而且能增加美国的社会文化背景知识，历史传统与现状的了解。

VOA 为了更好地办好这个节目，便于听众收听学习，于1978年编辑出版了一本名为Words And Their Stories的书，共收集一百篇故事，作者是Herbert Sutcliffe, Harold Bermen 及VOA 该节目的部分编辑人员。在每次的实际广播中，播音员都以此书为蓝本，再根据需要对原稿进行适当增删。按每周两个故事计算，此书的一百个故事还不能满足一年的播音需要。于是编辑们就是重播部分词语掌故的同时，不断增加许多新的词语掌故，及时将词源学家的最新研究成果和不断增加的新词汇介绍给听众。收听实践证明，初学者在收听过程中必然会遇到许多人名、地名和一些较难的句子，有时甚至在听完之后还很难理解所播词语的确切含义及其汉语意思，为此，听众可参看1983年由中国对外翻译出版公司出版的该书英汉对照本中的有关部分。

3．专题节目（二）

VOA Special English的专题节目，除上节谈的五分钟一次的以外，还有本节要介绍的每十五分钟一次的节目。这类节目共有七个不同的小专题，以星期为单位循环，每天分四次复播出一个专题，但星期日和星期六的两个专题材每晚只播三遍，每次节目约十分钟，继每次五分钟的专题节目之后播出。

这类专题节目的基本结构是，在特定的伴声中先报告当次节目的名称，并扼要介绍其主要内容，然后播送节目正文。最后，在伴乐声中报告节目主持人和撰稿人的姓名，以邀请听众在下周的这个时间继续收听该节目而结束。

People in America（美国人物志） 这是有关美国历史名人的一个专题节目，每逢星期天晚上播出。它向听众介绍在美国历史上产生过重大影响、起过重要作用、作出了突出贡献的科学、文学、政治、或其他各方面的历史人物。节目一般都对他们的生平事迹进行简要的叙述，对其贡献作出评介，类似人物小传。有的重要人物事迹很多，必须用两次或几次的节目时间进行联播。对这样的节目要坚持收听，才会获得完整的印象。

TThis is America（今日美国） This Is America向听众介绍美国人民的生活、学习、工作和娱乐情况，是英语学习者解美国社会的一条渠道。该专题大都一个节目一个整体，每逢星期一晚播出。

Science in the News（科学新闻） 这一专题材主要对新近的科学技术新闻进行综述或摘要广播。向听众介绍世界各国在自然、医学、疾病、原子能、航天等方面的科研动态、成果、突破性进展及存在的困难。涉及当今世界人们普遍关心的重大问题，如核事故、航天飞机爆炸、自然灾害、环境污染和爱滋病等等。每逢星期二播出，每次播一到五条新闻摘要。

Explorations（自然探索） 每逢星期三晚上，听众可以收听到Explorations这一专题节目。该专题既涉及人类遨游太空、探索原子、研究自身、改造自然的现代技术，也报道发展中国家开发新资源，利用新工艺改善人民生活等方面的成就，其侧重点在各种科技实验和简易实用技术方面。该节目一般安排一段时间播一个系列，每次播出一个主题，以便能将某项新技术的研究和应用的全过程介绍给听众，电台还乐意为感兴趣的听众提供所需的文字材料。

The Making of a Nation（建国史话） 这一专题节目向听众介绍美利坚合众国从十三个殖民地区域到现代工业国的孕育、诞生以及形成超级大国的历史过程，并以历史为线索，特定的历史时期为单位，以重大的历史事件为主题材来叙述各个党派、各届总统和政府的历史作用与贡献。这是每个英语学习者都应了解的基本知识。The Making of a Nation每逢星期四播出。这是个系列节目，坚持收听，则有助于系统了解美国的历史概况。

American Mosaic（美国万花筒） American Mosaic是一个radio magazine（广播杂志）节目。该节目题材广泛、内容丰，展示着美国社会文化生活中比较轻松愉快的生活画面；听众收听该节目就如同在阅读一本图文并茂的杂志。它每次有三到五个小节目，涉及音乐、图书、技术和教育等方面的内容。我们既可以从中欣赏到著名歌唱的优秀歌曲，对美国音乐有所了解，又可以获取一些生动有趣的现代美国社会生活知识，随着播音员那亲切悦耳的声音步入美国风景如画的大好河山；同时还能听到世界各地的听众提出的有关英语语方文学等方面的问题和电台的解答。

American Stories（美国故事） 这一专题材节目安排在每星期六晚上播出。这样能使听众在学习和工作之余，得以轻松一下头脑。我们可以通过这一美国文学的“窗口”，接触各种流派、各类名家的文学作品。了解美国英语的时代特色，欣赏、学习美国人民运用语方的技巧，并从那些佳作名篇中获得艺术享受。该节目对短篇故事采取一次播一篇的方式，对中、长篇小说则先进行简写加工，再分几次播出全文。在播出故事正文之前，播音员常常先介绍故事的主要情节。对需要分几次节目时间播出的中长篇，在播第二或以后各部分之前，主持人还先重述已播部分的故事梗概，以唤起听众的回忆，使故事听起来更加连贯。</description>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          <item>
            <title>American Culture: Bald Eagle Officially Named National Bird of U.S.  (2025/3/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202503/american-culture-bald-eagle-officially-named-national-bird-of-u-s.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 March, 2025</span><br/>
<p>The bald eagle is a <strong>symbol</strong> of the United States. An image of the bird is on the flag and <strong>seal</strong> of the U.S. president, the seal of the U.S. Supreme Court, military <strong>insignia,</strong> as well as the dollar bill.</p>
<p>Even so, the bird has had its ups and downs.</p>
<p>At one time, the bald eagle was at risk of permanent disappearance, or extinction. Later, however, its numbers recovered. In the early 2000s, the federal government removed the bird from its endangered<strong> species</strong> list.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This Jan. 5, 2020, file photo shows a bald eagle in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. (AP Photo/Chris Szagola)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/cb0c1cae-fd7c-4d1f-a392-4ce116fa3fe8_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This Jan. 5, 2020, file photo shows a bald eagle in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. (AP Photo/Chris Szagola)</span></div>
<p>Culturally, too, the <strong>raptors </strong>are doing well again. In December 2024 before leaving office, Joe Biden signed legislation officially making the<strong> </strong>bald eagle<strong> </strong>the national bird of the United States.</p>
<p><strong>Their well-being was connected a bug poison</strong></p>
<p>The bald eagle has a long complex story of species weakness and recovery. An insect-killing chemical called DDT played a major part in that story.</p>
<p>DDT is a chemical used to kill insects. The substance also proved harmful to eagle eggs. American officials banned DDT in 1972. But the use of the chemical had already caused severe damage to eagle populations. For example, in the 1980s there was only one <strong>nesting</strong> <strong>pair</strong> of eagles in the state of New Jersey. Now, there are about 300 pairs.</p>
<p><strong>Efforts to save bald eagles</strong></p>
<p>To rebuild the number of eagles across the U.S., researchers wanting to save them imported the birds from places where their population numbers were secure, including Canada.</p>
<p>Early on, they also removed eggs from their nests so they could safely <strong>hatch</strong> with scientists before being returned to their parents to raise, explained Kathy Clark. She is the head of New Jersey's Endangered and Nongame Species Program.</p>
<p>Clark has worked with the birds for many years. This includes the time when New Jersey had very few bald eagles, and they only lived in areas far from people.</p>
<p>Clark said that she will always remember that feeling of not knowing if the species will survive.</p>
<p>Maia Edwards is the science director at the American Bald Eagle Foundation in Alaska. She says the species represents “one of the few conservation success stories of animals” that came close to disappearing permanently from America.</p>
<p>“...I think now it's really important to make sure people know that story and learn from it,” she said.</p>
<p>Clark said the eagles have taught officials some lessons. One is that the raptors are good at changing to fit their environment. The birds now live in parts of New Jersey that are dense with people.</p>
<p>But, the birds still face dangers in such areas.</p>
<p>Jilian Fazio is director of the Essex County Turtle Back Zoo in northern New Jersey. She said the zoo rescues a number of birds hit by cars. The zoo also is home to Freedom, a bald eagle named by the caretakers. Freedom was rescued hanging from a tree in Minnesota after he got caught in some rope. He was injured so badly that he cannot be returned to the wild, Fazio said.</p>
<p>A lack of eagle <strong>habitat</strong> and <strong>prey</strong> also threatens the species. Bald eagles feed heavily on fish, so they require clean, open water in which to hunt.</p>
<p>Disease outbreaks, such as avian influenza or bird flu, are another serious threat to the birds.</p>
<p><strong>Native American symbolism</strong></p>
<p>The birds are highly respected by several Native American cultures as symbols of strength, especially in the Pacific Northwest, says Paul Apodaca. He is a retired university professor who specializes in stories and storytelling from different cultures.</p>
<p>The position<strong> </strong>of eagles as symbols of the U.S. adds to their protection.</p>
<p>“Americans are always going to have that sort of personal relationship with bald eagles," said Clark, the New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection official.</p>
<p>Dan Day is a birder. He has seen bald eagles about 50 times in recent years both on nature walks and while driving around.</p>
<p>He said, “It really <strong>elevates</strong> your day to see a bald eagle."</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Mike Catalini reported this story for the Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>__________________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>symbol</strong> <em>-n. </em>something that stands for something else, especially:<strong> </strong>something real that stands for or suggests another thing that cannot in itself be pictured or shown</p>
<p><strong>seal </strong><em>-n. </em>a device (as an emblem, symbol, or word) used to identify or replace a signature and to authenticate (as at common law) written matter</p>
<p><strong>insignia </strong><em>-n. </em>a badge of authority or honor</p>
<p><strong>species</strong> <em>-n. </em>a class of individuals having common attributes and designated by a common name</p>
<p><strong>raptor </strong><em>-n. </em>a carnivorous medium- to large-sized bird (such as a hawk, eagle, owl, or vulture) that has a hooked beak and large sharp talons and that feeds wholly or chiefly on meat taken by hunting or on carrion</p>
<p><strong>nest</strong> <em>-n. </em>a place or structure where eggs are laid and hatched or young are raised : <strong>nesting </strong><em>-adj.</em></p>
<p><strong>pair</strong> <em>-n. </em>two things that match or are meant to be used together</p>
<p><strong>habitat </strong><em>-n. </em>the place or environment where a plant or animal naturally or normally lives and grows</p>
<p><strong>prey</strong> <em>-n. </em>an animal hunted or killed by another animal for food</p>
<p><strong>elevate </strong><em>-v. </em>to improve the mind or spirits of</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How to 'Dish Up' Something Good  (2025/3/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202503/how-to-dish-up-something-good.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 March, 2025</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Food is a popular subject with many people around the world. It is fun to talk about our favorite dishes. It is even more fun to share a favorite dish with others.</p>
<p>Today we talk about the word “dish.” A dish can be the object on which you serve food. But, a dish can also mean a specially prepared food.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A dish of salmon, avocados, grapefruit, watermelon, radish and cucumber is shown during a media event ahead of the State Dinner for Japan's Prime Minister Fumio Kishida and his spouse Yuko Kishida, at the White House in Washington, DC, on April 9, 2024. (Photo, Drew ANGERER/AFP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-cced-08dc59904b1e_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A dish of salmon, avocados, grapefruit, watermelon, radish and cucumber is shown during a media event ahead of the State Dinner for Japan's Prime Minister Fumio Kishida and his spouse Yuko Kishida, at the White House in Washington, DC, on April 9, 2024. (Photo, Drew ANGERER/AFP)</span></div>
<p>Do you have a <strong><u>signature</u></strong><u> dish</u>? Our signature is how we sign our names. So, a signature dish is a dish we are known for making well. In a way, it identifies us.</p>
<p>My signature dish is sweet potato rosemary dinner rolls. I am often asked to make them, especially for holiday parties. In my circle of friends, I am known for this dish. When the rolls are on the table, people know that I made them.</p>
<p>A tasty dish is something that makes a table look good and inviting. Sometimes the same can be said about a person. Someone who is good-looking can be called a dish. While this usage might be a bit dated, it is still used.</p>
<p>Now, let's talk about the verb “dish.”</p>
<p>“To dish” can mean to talk about private or personal information. It might be <strong>gossip</strong>. But I can also dish about myself. For example, a friend may ask me to dish about my new job.</p>
<p>I could also use a phrasal verb form and say my friend want me to <u>dish out</u> all the interesting details.</p>
<p>Now, to <u>dish up something</u> means to put food on a dish for someone to eat. However, it can also mean sharing personal details, our own and others.</p>
<p>We can also <u>dish out</u> things, like jokes or even insults.</p>
<p>Some people like to <strong>tease</strong> or insult. They can <u>dish out</u> jokes and insults all day long. But sometimes these same people do not like it if you do the same to them.</p>
<p>We have a saying for just such people. We say, “<u>They can dish it out, but they can't take it.</u>” They are able and willing to share <strong>harsh </strong>thoughts, criticisms, or insults about others, but they do not think they, themselves, deserve such treatment.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Words and Their Stories</em>.</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>signature </strong><em>– n.</em><strong> </strong>the name of a person written with his or her own hand</p>
<p><strong>gossip </strong><em>– n. </em>rumor or report of a personal nature</p>
<p><strong>tease</strong> <em>– v. </em>to make fun of</p>
<p><strong>harsh </strong><em>– adj. </em>excessively critical or negative</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Appeal  (2025/3/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/appeal.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer the following question from a listener.</p>
<p><em>Dear teacher, </em></p>
<p><em>Could you please say more about the meaning of “appeal?” </em></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Ask a Teacher: Appeal" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/171029ba-3a40-498f-e7e8-08dd4a81f35f_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Ask a Teacher: Appeal</span></div>
<p><em>Thank you.</em></p>
<p>Like many words in English, “appeal” has more than one meaning. It can also be more than one part of speech. A part of speech means the grammatical <strong>function</strong> a word has, such as a noun, verb, adverb or adjective. Let's look at the many ways we can use the word “appeal.”</p>
<p>As a verb, “appeal” means to make a request, often in official situations or involving important things. Generally, we do not use “appeal” for normal, everyday requests. For example, we would not say:</p>
<p><em>I appeal for you to get some milk at the store.</em></p>
<p>But we would say something like:</p>
<p><em>The earthquake victims appealed to the government for more aid.</em></p>
<p><strong>Appealing</strong></p>
<p>We can change the meaning of “appeal” by making it an adjective. One way to do this is to use the -ing ending. This forms the word “appealing,” which describes something that has a pleasing quality. Consider the following examples:</p>
<p><em>That job is really appealing to me. </em></p>
<p><em>Her dress looks really appealing.</em></p>
<p><em>The nice weather makes that city so appealing. </em></p>
<p><em>That argument is appealing to many voters. </em></p>
<p>As shown in these examples, we can use the adjective “appealing” to describe many different things.</p>
<p>The word “appeal” can also be used as a noun. One meaning as a noun describes a formal or urgent request, as shown in the following examples:</p>
<p><em>Their appeal for help was not answered.</em></p>
<p><em>The employees made an appeal to reduce the number of hours of work. </em></p>
<p>The second example above shows that we often use the verb “make” before the noun “appeal.”</p>
<p>The word “appeal” can also be used as a noun to describe a quality that creates interest, sympathy, or <strong>attraction</strong>. Here are some examples of that usage:</p>
<p><em>The museum's design has a lot of appeal.</em></p>
<p><em>The appeal of that music is its simplicity.</em></p>
<p><strong>Using “appeal” in the law</strong></p>
<p>“Appeal” is also often used in legal matters – both as a noun or a verb. As a noun, it means a formal request to a court to review a decision by another court. If one court accepts the other's request, we can say the court “<strong>granted</strong>” the appeal. If the court rejects the appeal, we can say the court “denied” it.</p>
<p>The following example shows “appeal” being used as a verb in legal English:</p>
<p><em>The defense team will likely appeal the decision. </em></p>
<p>An adjective form of “appeal” is also used in the legal system. The adjective “appellate” describes a kind of court that deals with cases that have been appealed.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? Was this lesson appealing to you? We want to hear your thoughts! Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please let us know where you are from, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>________________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>function </strong><em>–n. </em>the special action something or someone does to do a task or job</p>
<p><strong>attraction </strong><em>–n. </em>a positive feeling toward something that makes you interested in it or like it</p>
<p><strong>grant </strong><em>–v. </em>give permission</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Reviewing Your Birthday Message  (2025/2/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/reviewing-your-birthday-message.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Faith Pirlo</span><br/><span class="datetime">27 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Recently, our readers and listeners wrote many lovely messages about their birthdays. We have been reading all of them. Most messages are happy. You wrote about gifts you received, the people who celebrated with you, or where and how you celebrated.</p>
<p>Some messages seemed sad. Some of you do not get to celebrate your birthdays. Other messages were a mix of sad and happy.</p>
<p>In this week's Everyday Grammar, we are looking at Farhana's message about her birthday. She wrote:</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01630000-0aff-0242-c3e6-08da86b6dc3c_w100_r1.png"/></div>
<p><strong>A message from Farhana</strong></p>
<p>My birthday was on last 23 march. This was my 27th birthday. In my birthday no one wished me except my younger sister. And actually there was no devise for this day. I spent my whole day as like it is a normal day. Sometimes i felt sad and sometimes i wasn't.</p>
<p><strong>Review of Farhana's message </strong></p>
<p>Let us start at the beginning. Farhana writes:</p>
<p>My birthday was on last 23 march.</p>
<p>We suggest changing this sentence to the present tense to say when your birthday is.</p>
<p>My birthday is March 23.</p>
<p>In American English, the usual order for dates is month, day, year. So instead of “23 March,” Americans usually say “March 23.”</p>
<p>You used the past tense in this sentence:</p>
<p>This was my 27th birthday.</p>
<p>Another way we can say how old we are, is to use the past tense of the verb “turn.”</p>
<p>I turned 27 this year.</p>
<p>Here, “turn” means to reach or pass into a new age.</p>
<p>Next Farhana wrote this:</p>
<p>In my birthday no one wished me except my younger sister.</p>
<p>We can change the word order of this sentence to make it clearer.</p>
<p>No one wished me happy birthday, except my younger sister.</p>
<p>Instead of a prepositional phrase, “In my birthday,” we can just start the sentence with “No one.” “No one” is an <strong>indefinite </strong>pronoun meaning "no person." You could also use the pronoun “nobody.”</p>
<p>Onto the next sentence:</p>
<p>And<strong> </strong>actually there was no devise for this day.</p>
<p>“To devise” is a verb meaning to plan or think up something. You were close! But in this sentence we need a noun. And we find it in the definition of devise: plan.</p>
<p>Actually, there was no plan for the day.</p>
<p>If you wanted to use the word devise, however, you could! It would come right after “plan” in the sentence.</p>
<p>Actually, there was no plan devised for the day.</p>
<p>Farhana's next sentence is:</p>
<p>I spent my whole day as like it is a normal day.</p>
<p>We should make a few changes to this sentence.</p>
<p>“As” and “like” are both used to make<strong> </strong>comparisons between nouns.</p>
<p>“As” is an adverb, and “like” is a preposition. We only need one of these to make the comparison.</p>
<p>We can say:</p>
<p>I spent my whole day like it was a normal day.</p>
<p>Let us look now at Farhana's last sentence:</p>
<p>Sometimes i felt sad and sometimes i wasn't.</p>
<p>We suggest changing this sentence to:</p>
<p>Sometimes I felt sad, but other times I didn't.</p>
<p>Now the two parts of the sentence agree in verb use.</p>
<p>Also, We always <strong>capitalize</strong> the pronoun “I” in sentences. We used the conjunction “but” with “other times” only to create more <strong>contrast</strong>. It is also correct to write:</p>
<p>Sometimes I felt sad and sometimes I didn't.</p>
<p><strong>Closing thoughts</strong></p>
<p>Now, let's hear the revised message about Farhana's birthday:</p>
<p>My birthday is March 23. I turned 27 this year. No one wished me happy birthday except my younger sister. Actually, there was no plan for the day. I spent my whole day like it was a normal day. Sometimes I felt sad, but other times, I didn't.</p>
<p>Thank you Farhana for your message. We would like to wish you a happy birthday, early, for next year.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Faith Pirlo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>indefinite</strong><em> – adj.</em> unclear in meaning or detail</p>
<p><strong>devise </strong><em>– v.</em> to think of; to come up with, to invent or plan</p>
<p><strong>capitalize </strong><em>– v. </em>to begin (a word or name) with a capital letter</p>
<p><strong>contrast</strong> – <em>n</em>. a difference between things or people that are being compared</p>
<p><strong>character</strong> <em>–</em> <em>n</em>. a person who appears in a movie, book, film...</p>
<p><strong>feedback</strong> <em>– n.</em> the transmission of corrective information</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What Is a Polar Vortex Weather System?  (2025/2/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/what-is-the-polar-vortex-weather-system.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">23 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Weather experts say extreme cold in many parts of the United States this winter has been driven by a polar vortex. But what is this weather system and how does it work?</p>
<p>The National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.climate.gov/news-features/understanding-climate/understanding-arctic-polar-vortex#:~:text=The%20Arctic%20polar%20vortex%20is,pool%20of%20extremely%20cold%20air.">describes</a> a polar vortex as strong westerly winds that form each winter in the atmosphere above the North Pole.</p>
<p>These cold winds move about 16 to 48 kilometers above the surface in the Arctic area in the part of the atmosphere called the stratosphere.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this photo, heavy snow falls as a person walks along U.S. Route 42 in Florence, Ky., Monday, Jan. 6, 2025. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/be8458d8-9415-45a5-88de-08dd4a843460_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this photo, heavy snow falls as a person walks along U.S. Route 42 in Florence, Ky., Monday, Jan. 6, 2025. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster, File)</span></div>
<p>At times, the polar vortex can weaken, causing masses of cold air to break off and move south. A polar vortex can also push warmer air in <strong>northerly</strong> directions.</p>
<p>The Associated Press (AP) reports that several vortex events have affected parts of the U.S. this winter. Experts say weather forces in the Arctic have combined to push colder air to the U.S. and Europe.</p>
<p>Temperature readings that take into account the effects of wind, called <strong>windchill</strong> readings, fell to minus 51 degrees Celsius in parts of the U.S. Midwest. Meteorologists say windchill readings are colder than air temperature readings.</p>
<p>The U.S. National Weather Service (NWS) warned people in affected areas that such low temperatures can cause <strong>frostbite</strong> and <strong>hypothermia</strong> if skin is not protected from the cold. Weather officials also warned that long-term cold temperatures can cause water pipes in or around homes to freeze and burst.</p>
<p>The NWS noted that almost every U.S. state – except for Hawaii, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_SW7UHNid">California</a> and Florida – is expected to report low <strong>windchill </strong>temperatures. The coldest temperatures were expected in the midwestern states of Kansas, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_3epPopfI">Nebraska</a> and Missouri.</p>
<p>In an explanation on its website, NOAA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.climate.gov/media/11999">states</a> that the polar vortex always surrounds both of Earth's poles. The systems strengthen in the winter and weaken in the summer.</p>
<p>Every year or so, the polar vortex becomes weaker. This can cause the system to be “pushed off the pole or split into two.” This can lead to cold air at the surface being pushed southward and warm air being pushed to the north.</p>
<p>NOAA says its weather models are predicting low temperatures for states including Oklahoma, Colorado, Nebraska, Missouri, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_PKeKlPjx">Illinois</a> and Iowa. Other states likely to have very low temperatures are Wyoming, Montana, North Dakota, South Dakota, Minnesota, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_kSbcbX6A">Wisconsin</a> and Michigan.</p>
<p>The agency said some storms could bring heavy snow or flooding during that time.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters, Agence France-Presse, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_KsekuT7Q">NOAA</a> and NASA.</em></p>
<p><strong>______________________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>northerly </strong><em>–adj.</em> in, to or from the north</p>
<p><strong>frostbite </strong><em>– n. </em>a condition that results in extreme cold causing injuries to body parts such as fingers and toes</p>
<p><strong>hypothermia </strong><em>– n. </em>a serious sickness caused when a person's body becomes too cold</p>
<p><strong>windchill </strong><em>– n. </em>a temperature reading that takes into account<em> </em>the cooling effect that wind has on the human body and that is lower than the actual air temperature</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>The Statue of Liberty: ‘Enlightening the World’ for Nearly 150 Years  (2025/2/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/a-century-later-statue-of-liberty-still-attracts-millions.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">23 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>The Statue of Liberty has served as the guardian of New York Harbor for nearly 150 years.</p>
<p>The statue might be one of the most photographed works of art in the world. A French sculptor, Frederic Auguste Bartholdi, designed it in the late 1800s. Today the monument remains a beautiful sight on the New York <strong>skyline</strong>.</p>
<p>The materials required for building the Statue of Liberty were almost lost at sea. In 1885, the ship carrying those materials nearly sank in stormy seas. Luckily, the ship survived. It arrived in June of that year.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this March 9, 2020, file photo, the full moon rises behind the Statue of Liberty in New York. (AP Photo/J. David Ake, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/106ce573-e4b3-4d1f-9e95-12743e001921_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">In this March 9, 2020, file photo, the full moon rises behind the Statue of Liberty in New York. (AP Photo/J. David Ake, File)</span></div>
<p>By 1886, the Statue of Liberty was <strong>erected </strong>on what was then called Bedloe's Island. The statue was officially opened that year. Many years later, the island was given a new name: Liberty Island.</p>
<p>“Lady Liberty,” as many people call the statue, was a gift from the people of France. Its full name is “Liberty Enlightening the World.” The United States and France have been friends and allies since the American Revolution. France helped the American colonial armies defeat British forces. The war officially ended in 1783. A few years later, the French rebelled against their king.</p>
<p><strong>The Statue of Liberty from the air</strong></p>
<p>France had wanted to give the statue to the United States on the 100th anniversary of the Declaration of Independence -- July 4th, 1876. But technical problems and lack of money delayed the project. France finally officially presented the statue to the United States in Paris in 1884.</p>
<p>A <strong>pedestal</strong> to hold the 200 tons of weight was finished later.</p>
<p>The statue also needed a structure that could hold its weight of more than 200 tons. French engineer Alexandre Gustave Eiffel created the necessary technology. Later, he designed the Eiffel Tower in Paris.</p>
<p>Eiffel and others worked in Paris to produce a strong support system for the statue. The design also had to have the ability to move a little in strong winds.</p>
<p>In France, workers separated the statue into 350 pieces, put them on a ship and sent them across the ocean. After surviving the rough seas, the statue arrived in New York in more than 200 wooden boxes.</p>
<p>It took workers four months to build the statue on the pedestal.</p>
<p>On October 28th, 1886, President Grover Cleveland accepted the statue in a ceremony. He said: “We will not forget that Liberty has here made her home; nor shall her chosen <strong>altar</strong> be <strong>neglected</strong>.”</p>
<p><strong>She's a survivor</strong></p>
<p>Throughout history, the idea of liberty has often been represented by images of a woman. Historians say the statue's face was created to look like Bartholdi's mother. Her right arm holds a <strong>torch</strong> high in the air. Her left arm holds a tablet with the date of America's Declaration of Independence -- July 4th, 1776.</p>
<p>On her head, the Statue of Liberty wears a crown with seven points. Each point is meant to represent the light of freedom as it shines on the seven seas and seven <strong>continents</strong> of the world. The 25 windows in the crown represent gemstones found on Earth. A chain that represents oppression lies broken at her feet.</p>
<p>Lady Liberty was officially named a National Monument in 1924. Liberty Island and Fort Wood have been overseen by the U.S. National Park Service since 1933.</p>
<p>The Statue of Liberty has survived damage caused by time, visits by millions of people and the weather. It stood firm during a destructive storm, Hurricane Sandy, which struck the East Coast in October of 2012. But Liberty Island suffered damage, requiring major repairs.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Jerry Watson wrote this story, and Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>skyline</strong> <em>–n.</em> the outline that a large city's buildings make on the sky</p>
<p><strong>erect </strong><em>–v. </em>to put up a building or large structure</p>
<p><strong>pedestal </strong><em>–n.</em> a base that provides support</p>
<p><strong>altar</strong> <em>–n.</em> a raised structure or platform</p>
<p><strong>neglected </strong><em>–adj.</em> not taken care of, or in need of repair or care</p>
<p><strong>torch </strong><em>–n.</em> a light</p>
<p><strong>continent </strong><em>–n.</em> one of the great landmasses of the Earth such as North America, South America or Asia</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Space Agencies Report Increased Risk of Space Rock Striking Earth in 2032  (2025/2/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/space-agencies-report-increased-risk-of-space-rock-striking-earth-in-2032.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Scientists say the threat of a large space rock striking the Earth in 2032 has increased.</p>
<p>Recent calculations suggest there is a small chance - perhaps around 1 to 3 percent - the space rock 2024 YR4 will hit Earth in 2032. This also means there is around a 97 to 99 percent chance it will safely pass our planet in that year. The <strong>odds </strong>of a strike will likely continue to go up and down as the asteroid's path around the sun is better understood.</p>
<p>And scientists say there is a good chance the risk will drop to zero.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image made available by University of Hawaii's asteroid impact alert system shows the motion of asteroid 2024 YR4 over about one hour, Dec. 27, 2024. (ATLAS / University of Hawaii / NASA via AP" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/522575fc-8f82-4147-9df5-09d0a44ce867_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image made available by University of Hawaii's asteroid impact alert system shows the motion of asteroid 2024 YR4 over about one hour, Dec. 27, 2024. (ATLAS / University of Hawaii / NASA via AP</span></div>
<p>NASA and the European Space Agency's Webb Space Telescope will observe this near-Earth asteroid in March before the object becomes impossible to see. Once that happens, scientists will have to wait until 2028 when it passes our way again.</p>
<p><strong>What is an asteroid? </strong></p>
<p>Asteroids are space rocks orbiting the sun.</p>
<p>Asteroids are much smaller than planets. Scientists believe they are the leftovers from the solar system's formation 4.6 billion years ago.</p>
<p>There are millions of asteroids orbiting the sun between Mars and Jupiter. That area is known as the main asteroid belt. The asteroids sometimes get pushed out of the belt and can end up elsewhere.</p>
<p><strong>How do scientists follow worrisome asteroids? </strong></p>
<p>A telescope in Chile discovered the asteroid 2024 YR4 in late December. It is estimated to measure between 40 and 90 meters across. NASA said observations by the Webb space telescope should provide a more exact measurement.</p>
<p>At first, NASA and the European Space Agency put the odds of a strike at just over one percent. But later calculations suggested the odds had risen to 2 or even 3 percent. NASA described the likelihood of a strike as “extremely low.”</p>
<p>Until scientists have a better understanding of the asteroid's path around the sun, they warned that the odds will continue to change — and quite possibly fall to zero.</p>
<p>“You don't have to be worried about anything. It's a <strong>curiosity</strong>,” said Larry Denneau. He is a software engineer at the University of Hawaii working with ATLAS, a program to identify asteroids that might endanger Earth. That effort first spotted the asteroid. Denneau said, “Don't <strong>panic</strong>. Let the process play out, and we'll have a for-sure answer.”</p>
<p>In 2021, NASA said another possibly worrisome asteroid, Apophis, did not present a risk to Earth. NASA made the announcement after additional telescope observations ruled out any chance of it hitting Earth in 2068.</p>
<p><strong>Should we worry about asteroid 2024 YR4? </strong></p>
<p>Experts say it is too soon to worry about 2024 YR4.</p>
<p>Paul Chodas is director of NASA's Center for Near-Earth Object Studies. Chodas said in an email to the Associated Press, “No one should be concerned that the impact <strong>probability</strong> is rising. This is the behavior our team expected.”</p>
<p>Chodas added, “To be clear, we expect the <strong>impact</strong> probability to drop to zero at some point.”</p>
<p>Since the asteroid's size and orbit are uncertain, it is unclear where it might hit and what the possible effects would be should it strike Earth. ESA said, if the asteroid is smaller, the effect might be similar to the Tunguska event that flattened thousands of square kilometers of forest in Siberia in 1908. But if the asteroid is larger, close to 100 meters, the effects “would be <strong>significantly</strong> worse.”</p>
<p>Chodas said once the Webb telescope measures the asteroid's size, NASA can predict “how serious an impact this asteroid could produce and how difficult a task it might be to <strong>deflect</strong> this asteroid.”</p>
<p>NASA already has some experience moving an asteroid. The space agency's Dart spacecraft hit a harmless asteroid in 2022. This was the first planetary defense test of its kind, changing the asteroid's orbit around its larger <strong>companion </strong>asteroid.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Marcia Dunn reported this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English</em>.</p>
<p>______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>odds</strong> <em>–n. (pl.)</em> the likelihood that something will happen</p>
<p><strong>curiosity</strong><em> –n.</em> a strong desire to learn more about something</p>
<p><strong>panic </strong><em>– v.</em> to be overcome with a powerful fear</p>
<p><strong>probability</strong><em>—n.</em> the chance that an event will occur</p>
<p><strong>impact </strong><em>–n.</em> an event in which one object strikes or crashes into another</p>
<p><strong>significantly </strong><em>– adv.</em> in a major way</p>
<p><strong>deflect</strong><em> –v. </em>to cause an object to move in another direction possibly by striking it and changing its path a little</p>
<p><strong>companion</strong><em>—n.</em> an object that is closely connected to another, usually by gravity</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>The Importance of Being ‘Dialed In’  (2025/2/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/the-importance-of-being-dialed-in.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Technology is always progressing. Today, many modern devices can be controlled by touch or voice. This has led to some traditional electronic controls – such as <strong>dials</strong> and <strong>switches</strong> – being <strong>replaced</strong> with new technologies.</p>
<p><strong>Digital displays</strong> have also become increasingly common. For example, digital number readouts have long replaced the hands on many clocks.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="As coins slide down before her eyes, a German woman uses a new long distance dial telephone for public booths, July 17, 1957. (AP Photo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1B6DC79F-A7FA-4E5D-9036-FAAAE7E5BEF1_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">As coins slide down before her eyes, a German woman uses a new long distance dial telephone for public booths, July 17, 1957. (AP Photo)</span></div>
<p>Many other devices also now operate purely with digital tools instead of mechanical systems.</p>
<p>But some expressions and idioms used by English speakers still describe older technologies.</p>
<p>First, let's talk about dials. These controls are used for changing settings on a piece of equipment, like a radio or old television. We use the dial to <strong>tune in</strong> to a specific channel.</p>
<p>That's where the expressions <u>dialed in</u> and <u>tuned in</u> come from. If we are dialed in or tuned in to a radio or television program, we can hear it clearly. There is no noise or <strong>static</strong>.</p>
<p>The same can be said when using these terms in personal <strong>conversations</strong>. For example, if you are <u>dialed in</u> to a project or problem, you know exactly what needs to be done. You are thinking clearly about it and remain very <strong>focused</strong>.</p>
<p>And when you are <u>tuned in</u>, you understand clearly what is going on around you.</p>
<p>“Don't touch that dial” and “stay tuned” are two ways to tell someone to keep watching or listening to a program.</p>
<p>Now, let's talk about switches.</p>
<p>These are built to either be off or on. There are no in-between settings like with a dial. So, when we <strong><u>flip</u></strong><u> the switch</u>, we make something happen quickly and easily. It can also mean that we suddenly change something.</p>
<p>Let's listen to an example.</p>
<p><em>The restaurant's change to all organic food happened slowly over time. It wasn't a matter of flipping a switch. </em></p>
<p>Now, for our last expression -- <u>to move the <strong>needle</strong>.</u></p>
<p>Needles on measuring devices like a <strong>scale </strong>move to show a desired level has been reached. So, when something <u>moves the needle</u>, it causes a noticeable change in something, usually for the good.</p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>. Don't forget to tune in again for another story about American English expressions.</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>dial </strong><em>– n. </em>a device that may be operated to make electrical connections or to regulate the operation of a machine</p>
<p><strong>switch </strong><em>– n. </em>a device for making, breaking, or changing the connections in an electrical circuit</p>
<p><strong>replace </strong><em>– v. </em>to take the place of, especially as a substitute</p>
<p><strong>digital </strong><em>– adj. </em>of, relating to, or using calculation directly with digits rather than through measurable physical quantities</p>
<p><strong>display </strong><em>– n. </em>an electronic device that gives information in visual form</p>
<p><strong>tune in</strong> <em>– phrasal verb </em>to listen to or view a broadcast of</p>
<p><strong>static </strong><em>– n. </em>noise produced in a radio or television receiver by atmospheric or electrical disturbances</p>
<p><strong>conversation </strong><em>– n. </em>talking or a talk between two or more people</p>
<p><strong>focus </strong><em>– v. </em>to cause to be concentrated</p>
<p><strong>flip </strong><em>– v. </em>to move with a small quick motion</p>
<p><strong>needle </strong><em>– n. </em>a slender pointer on a dial : a slender bar of magnetized steel that is free to turn (as in a compass) to show the direction of a magnetic field</p>
<p><strong>scale </strong><em>– n. </em>a device for weighing</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers Use Chemical Examinations and Human Smell to Study Ancient Remains  (2025/2/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/researchers-use-chemical-examinations-and-human-smell-to-study-ancient-remains.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>A recent study about the smell of Egyptian<strong> mummies</strong> reached some surprising findings. The ancient bodies did not smell bad, the researchers found. Instead, they say, the remains mostly smelled good.</p>
<p>Cecilia Bembibre is director of research at University College London's Institute for Sustainable Heritage. “In films and books, terrible things happen to those who smell mummified bodies,” she said. “We were surprised at the pleasantness of them."</p>
<p>The researchers reported the leading descriptions of the smells as “woody,” “spicy” and “sweet.” They also reported a floral or flowery smell. That smell could be from pine and juniper <strong>resins</strong> used in mummification; a process designed to protect the body from <strong>decay.</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this undated photo, Emma Paolin, PhD researcher at University of Ljubljana, background and Dr. Cecilia Bembibre, lecturer at the University College London take swab samples for the purpose of analysis at the Krakow University of Economics. (Abdelrazek Elnaggar via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a41f6102-703b-4e88-b224-a355cdfc6a99_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this undated photo, Emma Paolin, PhD researcher at University of Ljubljana, background and Dr. Cecilia Bembibre, lecturer at the University College London take swab samples for the purpose of analysis at the Krakow University of Economics. (Abdelrazek Elnaggar via AP)</span></div>
<p>The study appeared recently in the Journal of the American Chemical Society. It used both chemical examinations and several human smellers to study nine mummies. The mummies, some around 5,000 years old, had been housed at the Egyptian <strong>Museum</strong> in Cairo.</p>
<p>Bembibre, one of the report's writers, said the researchers wanted to study the smell of mummies because it has long been a subject of interest for the public and researchers alike.</p>
<p>She added that even<strong> fiction</strong> writers have written pages of work on the subject — for good reason.</p>
<p>Scent, or smell, was an important consideration in the mummification process. This process used oils and plant-based materials to protect the body and its spirit for the afterlife. Mummification was largely used for powerful people such as pharaohs and other leaders.</p>
<p>Pleasant smells were linked with purity and gods. Bad smells were signs of corruption and decay.</p>
<p>Researchers did not want to directly measure the mummies, because doing so might be damaging. Instead, researchers were able to take measurements that did not involve touching the mummies. Researchers from UCL and the University of Ljubljana in Slovenia were able to measure smells, pesticides, and other effects due to mold, bacteria or microorganisms.</p>
<p>Using technical instruments to measure air molecules released from <strong>sarcophagi</strong> was very important, said Matija Strli<i></i>269;, a chemistry professor at the University of Ljubljana.</p>
<p>"It tells us <strong>potentially</strong> what social class a mummy was from and therefore <strong>reveals</strong> a lot of information about the mummified body...." he said. “We believe that this <strong>approach</strong> is potentially of huge interest to other types of<strong> </strong>museum collections.”</p>
<p>Barbara Huber of the Max Planck Institute of Geoanthropology in Germany was not involved in the study. Huber said the findings provide important data on compounds that could<strong> preserve</strong> or damage mummified remains. The information could be used to better protect the ancient bodies for future generations.</p>
<p>Huber said that over thousands of years, differing conditions have changed the scents of the mummies in a major way.</p>
<p>Huber wrote a study two years ago that examined a jar that had contained mummified organs of a woman. The goal was to identify the material used to preserve the organs and what that would show about ancient trade paths.</p>
<p>Researchers of the current study hope to do something similar. They want to use their findings to develop “smellscapes” to recreate the scents they discovered. They also want to change the experience for future museumgoers.</p>
<p>Bembibre said museums generally ask visitors to experience everything with their eyes. She added that seeing mummies through “a glass case reduces the experience because we don't get to smell them.”</p>
<p>Smelling the scents of mummification would improve the museum visitors' experiences, she suggested, as smell is one of the ways that people understand the world.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Brian Melley reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>mummy </strong><em>– n.</em> an ancient body treated for burial with preservatives</p>
<p><strong>resin </strong><em>– n.</em> natural organic substances that are usually transparent or translucent and yellowish to brown in color and are often made from plant materials; they are also soluble in organic solvents but not in water, are electrical nonconductors, and are used to cover and protect surfaces</p>
<p><strong>decay </strong>–<em> n.</em> to go through or cause to go through decomposition</p>
<p><strong>fiction</strong><em> – n.</em> something invented by the imagination</p>
<p><strong>museum</strong> <em>– n.</em> a place devoted to the care, study, and display of objects of interest, importance or value</p>
<p><strong>sarcophagus</strong> <em>– n.</em> an ancient container used for holding human remains</p>
<p><strong>potentially</strong><em> – adv.</em> possibly</p>
<p><strong>reveal </strong><em>– v.</em> to show plainly</p>
<p><strong>approach </strong><em>– n. </em>a way of dealing with something</p>
<p><strong>preserve </strong><em>– v.</em> to keep in a good state or condition</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Extend, Expand, etc.  (2025/2/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/extend-expand-etc.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Ann in China. Here is part of Ann's question:</p>
<p><em>Hello Teachers,<br/>
Could you please help me understand the difference between "extend," "expand," "stretch," [and] "enlarge" when I describe an activity that makes something larger than its current state?</em></p>
<p><em>Thank you, Ann.</em></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Extend, Expand, etc." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/ac83c6f0-1f39-4a4d-e43d-08dd4a81f35f_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Extend, Expand, etc.</span></div>
<p>We can use the four verbs Ann asked about to express an increase in physical size or amount. We can also use them to express increasing the time an activity takes.</p>
<p><strong>Extend</strong></p>
<p>We often use the verb “extend” to talk about increasing the amount of time for an activity or program. For example:</p>
<p><em>Officials want to extend the school year by six weeks. </em></p>
<p>We can use the verb “extend” to express an increase in people, things, or ideas. Consider the following examples:</p>
<p><em>The new rule extends to all employees in the company.</em></p>
<p><em>They want to extend the <strong>benefits</strong> of freedom to people around the world. </em></p>
<p><em>This research will extend our knowledge.</em></p>
<p>We can also use “extend” to express the distance or the area something reaches. For example:</p>
<p><em>The Rocky Mountains extend from the United States into Canada. </em></p>
<p><strong>Expand</strong></p>
<p>We use “expand” to express an increase in the size of a project or program. And, like “extend,” we can use “expand” to talk about including more people. Consider the following example:</p>
<p><em>Officials want to expand the program to include people from developing countries. </em></p>
<p>We commonly use “expand” in connection with business or industry:</p>
<p><em>We want to expand our business to reach more customers. </em></p>
<p><strong>Stretch</strong></p>
<p>We can use the phrasal verb “stretch out” to express increasing the time to continue an activity:</p>
<p><em>I wanted to stretch out my vacation for an extra two or </em><em>three days. </em></p>
<p>We can use the verb “stretch” to express improving our ability to do something:</p>
<p><em>Learning a new language will stretch your mind and improve your problem-solving abilities.</em></p>
<p>Note that when we use the verb “stretch” in this way, we communicate the idea that the improvement might be a little difficult or take a lot of effort.</p>
<p><strong>Enlarge</strong></p>
<p>Unlike the verb “extend,” we do not use “enlarge” to talk about an increase in time. Instead, it simply means to increase in size or scope. Scope means all of the things connected to an activity or project. Consider the following example:</p>
<p><em>They have enlarged their research team to examine the effects of pollution on animals. </em></p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? How are you trying to expand your knowledge? We want to hear from you! Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please let us know where you are from, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.<em> </em></p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>benefits</strong><em> </em><em>–n. </em>the good things that result from an action or situation</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Electrical Medical Device Helps Improve Muscle Strength  (2025/2/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/study-electrical-medical-device-helps-improve-muscle-strength.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By ill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">20 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Researchers recently reported new evidence from a study of a medical device placed inside the body, a spine-<strong>stimulating</strong> <strong>implant</strong>.</p>
<p>Three people with a muscle-destroying disease got a little stronger after using the implant. They were able to stand and walk more easily because of electrical stimulation to their spinal cord.</p>
<p>Marco Capogrosso is an assistant professor at the University of Pittsburg, or Pitt, who led the research. "These people were definitely not expecting an improvement," he said. Capogrosso said, "They were getting better and better," over the study that lasted one month.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image from video provided by UPMC and University of Pittsburgh Health Sciences shows Doug McCullough, who has spinal muscular atrophy, during tests of experimental spinal cord stimulation to improve muscle function in Pittsburgh, on March 14, 2023. " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/19e8c5de-d3b7-40d4-ddb8-08dd4a81f35f_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image from video provided by UPMC and University of Pittsburgh Health Sciences shows Doug McCullough, who has spinal muscular atrophy, during tests of experimental spinal cord stimulation to improve muscle function in Pittsburgh, on March 14, 2023. </span></div>
<p><strong>Returning muscle function</strong></p>
<p>The implant was able to return some muscle <strong>function</strong>, at least temporarily. The implant was already being tested to treat <strong>paralysis</strong> in other patients. This new evidence suggests it might also aid diseases of the nervous system like spinal muscle atrophy, or SMA.</p>
<p>SMA is a genetic disease that slowly destroys motor <strong>neurons</strong>, nerve cells in the spinal cord that control muscles. That leads muscles to waste away, especially in the legs, hips, and shoulders and sometimes those involved with breathing and swallowing. There is no cure. A gene therapy can save the lives of very young children with a severe form of the disease, and there are some medicines to slow the disease in older patients.</p>
<p>Stimulating the spinal cord with low levels of electricity has long been used to treat chronic, or long-term, pain. Capogrosso's team also has tested it to help people paralyzed by <strong>strokes</strong> or spinal cord injury move their arms and legs with assistance. The system sends electrical signals to nerves that have stopped reacting. This has the effect of activating the muscles.</p>
<p>Capogrosso wondered if that same technology might help patients with SMA by stimulating sensory nerves to signal damaged muscle cells causing them to move. The researchers at the University of Pittsburgh published their study in <em>Nature Medicine</em>.</p>
<p>They implanted electrodes over the lower spinal cord of the three adults with SMA. Using the device did not return normal movement but with a few hours of spinal stimulation a week, all soon experienced improvements in muscle strength and function, the researchers wrote.</p>
<p><strong>"You never get better"</strong></p>
<p>Fifty-seven-year-old Doug McCullough took part in the study. "With a progressive disease you never get any better," he said, adding, “So having any improvement is just a really <strong>surreal</strong> and very exciting <strong>benefit</strong>."</p>
<p>All three subjects increased how far they could walk in six minutes by the study's end.</p>
<p>Capogrosso said they could walk farther because they got less tired and “even a person this many years into the disease can improve."</p>
<p>Researchers found the improvements did not disappear as soon as the stimulator was turned off. But they did decrease a few months after the study ended.</p>
<p>Neuroscientist Susan Harkema led similar studies of stimulation for spinal cord injuries while at the University of Louisville. She warned that the new study is small and did not last very long but said it was an important test of the device. She said it should be tested next with other muscle-<strong>degenerating</strong> diseases.</p>
<p>Capogrosso said some small but longer studies are beginning.</p>
<p>I'm Dorothy Gundy.</p>
<p><em>Lauran Neergaard reported this story for the Associated Press. J</em><em>ill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>stimulate</strong> – <em>v. </em>to make (something) more active</p>
<p><strong>implant </strong><em>– n.</em> something placed in a person's body through a medical operation</p>
<p><strong>function </strong><em>–n.</em> the work that something is designed to do</p>
<p><strong>paralysis </strong><em>–n.</em> the condition of not being able to move muscles, especially those in the arms and legs</p>
<p><strong>neuron </strong> - <em>n</em>. a cell that carries messages between the brain and other parts of the body and that is the basic unit of the nervous system</p>
<p><strong>stroke </strong><em>–n.</em> a serious medical condition caused by a loss of oxygen or blood flow to the brain when a blood vessel is blocked or bursts</p>
<p><strong>surreal </strong>– <em>adj</em>. very strange or unusual; having the quality of a dream</p>
<p><strong>degenerate</strong> – <em>v. </em>to change to a worse state or condition; to become worse, weaker, or less useful</p>
<p><strong>benefit </strong>–n. a good result from doing something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Describing Your Birthday  (2025/2/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/describing-your-birthday.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Faith Pirlo</span><br/><span class="datetime">20 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Today, on Everyday Grammar, we will learn to describe our birthdays.</p>
<p><strong>When is your birthday?</strong></p>
<p>When people ask us the question “When is your birthday?” we can answer a few different ways.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Everyday Grammar: Describing Your Birthday" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/019e0000-0aff-0242-f2de-08da80763c93_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Everyday Grammar: Describing Your Birthday</span></div>
<p>We can use the season (spring, summer, autumn/fall, or winter), the month, or the day.</p>
<p>My birthday is in the summer.</p>
<p>Her father's birthday is in March.</p>
<p>Last Sunday was her birthday.</p>
<p>His birthday is the 4th of May.</p>
<p>Remember that word “birthday” is different from “birthdate.” “Birthdate” is the exact date, like December, 7th, 1997. The word “birthday” can be the date, or you can answer more generally.</p>
<p>For example,</p>
<p>My niece's birthday is in August.</p>
<p>Her birthdate is August 3rd.</p>
<p><strong>How old are you? What age are you turning? </strong></p>
<p>When we want to say how old we are, we can use the present or future verb tenses depending on when our birthdays are. We can use the past tense with the verb “turn.”</p>
<p>If we are talking about a future birthday, say next year or in a few months, we can answer the question of “How old will you be?” with:</p>
<p>I will be + (age). Or...</p>
<p>I'll be + (number) years old.</p>
<p>In 2023, I will be 36 years old.</p>
<p>On your birthday, you can use the present tense.</p>
<p>Deborah is 55 today.</p>
<p>For the past tense, we can use the structure of the verb “be” + age (years old), but we generally use it to talk about past ages in <strong>reference</strong> to something else.</p>
<p>We can also use the verb “turn” to talk about how old we are. In this way “turn” means to reach or pass a certain age. Therefore, we can use the past tense with “turn” for talking about birthdays. For example:</p>
<p>I turned 35 this year.</p>
<p>This means that my birthday was in the past. I am still considered to be 35 years old after my birthday.</p>
<p>In the present tense, we can use “turn” to say that a birthday is “today.” As in,</p>
<p>Brad turns 60 today.</p>
<p>And to express a future birthday, we can use the same form, the present tense.</p>
<p>Kristen turns 41 this year.</p>
<p>This means that sometime this year (the near future), Kristen will be 41 years old.</p>
<p>We can use the <strong>modal verb</strong> of “will” with “turn” to express a future birthday.</p>
<p>I will turn 36 next year.</p>
<p><strong>What do you want to do for your birthday?</strong></p>
<p>When talking about making plans for a birthday, someone may ask you: “What do you want to do for your birthday?”</p>
<p>You can answer with ideas of plans that you would like to do.</p>
<p>You can use the expressions:</p>
<p>“I want to...” or “I would like to...” to be more polite.</p>
<p>You can even use the expression “I + be going to” if you have already made the plans, yourself.</p>
<p>She wants to go to a French restaurant for her birthday.</p>
<p>I'm going to celebrate with my friends later.</p>
<p>If your birthday has already past, someone may ask you,</p>
<p>“How was your birthday?”</p>
<p>You can answer by describing your birthday with an adjective.</p>
<p>My birthday party was wonderful.</p>
<p>Then they may ask you:</p>
<p>“What did you do for your birthday?”</p>
<p>You can answer in the past tense:</p>
<p>For my birthday this year, we went to an <strong>amusement park</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>What do you want for/on your birthday? </strong></p>
<p>If someone wants to get you a gift for your birthday they may ask you:</p>
<p>“What do you want for your birthday?”</p>
<p>“What do you want on your birthday?”</p>
<p>If you want something <em>for</em> your birthday that means a gift, generally.</p>
<p>If you want something <em>on</em> your birthday that could be a party or to make some type of plans to celebrate on the actual date.</p>
<p>On my birthday next year, I would like to go to the countryside.</p>
<p>Please don't buy me anything for my birthday.</p>
<p><strong>What did you get for/on your birthday? </strong></p>
<p>After your birthday, people may ask what you received as a gift for your birthday:</p>
<p>“What did you get for your birthday?”</p>
<p>“What do you get on your birthday?”</p>
<p>You could say that you got or received something.</p>
<p>I got a cat for my birthday.</p>
<p>Or you could say what you got and who gave it to you.</p>
<p>My mom sent me a lovely birthday card in the mail.</p>
<p>Here is how you might tell about another's birthday:</p>
<p>Her husband gave her jewelry for her birthday.</p>
<p><strong>Homework</strong></p>
<p>Let's end this report with a homework assignment. In 5-8 sentences, write about your birthday this year. Try to use ideas that you have learned about in today's report. You can use the question headings as your guide! Remember to use the correct verb tense depending on when your birthday is.</p>
<p>Send your writing to our email address: 21voa.com</p>
<p>We will select one piece of writing and provide feedback and suggestions in a future report!</p>
<p>I'm Faith Pirlo</p>
<p>And I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Faith Pirlo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>Describe your birthday. Tell us about your birthday in the comments below or write to us at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>.</p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>niece </strong><em>–n. </em>the daughter of your brother or sister<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>reference </strong><em>–n. </em>the act of mentioning something in speech or in writing</p>
<p><strong>modal verbs</strong> <em>– n. (grammar)</em> verbs that are used to express possibility, ability, or necessity.</p>
<p><strong>amusement park</strong> - n. a place that has many games and rides (such as roller coasters and merry-go-rounds) for entertainment</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Tech Tip: How to Block Location Tracking on your Phone  (2025/2/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/tech-tip-how-to-block-location-tracking-on-your-phone.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Smartphones have become valuable tools for helping to organize our lives. However, the devices can also capture personal data and <strong>location</strong> information that users might want to keep private.</p>
<p>Here are some tips, suggested by the Associated Press (AP), to help smartphone users limit the collection of private data on personal devices.</p>
<p><strong>How does a smartphone track your location?</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file photo, a person holds an iPhone 15 Pro at the Apple campus, Sept. 12, 2023, in Cupertino, Calif. (AP Photo/Jeff Chiu, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/879b0752-afd3-4b32-fbbe-08dd4a817620_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this file photo, a person holds an iPhone 15 Pro at the Apple campus, Sept. 12, 2023, in Cupertino, Calif. (AP Photo/Jeff Chiu, File)</span></div>
<p>All a user has to do is open a phone's map tool to search for a restaurant or other business to activate data <strong>tracking</strong>. Similarly, someone choosing to look up the price of a product online can unknowingly permit the smartphone to track the user's location and share data with others.</p>
<p>Darren Guccione is the chief executive of U.S.-based internet security company Keeper Security. He told the AP that many apps, “from fitness tracking to <strong>navigation</strong>,”<strong> </strong>can record data signals that show a user's movements, both physical and <strong>digital</strong>.</p>
<p>Guccione's advice to users is to “turn on location tracking only when necessary, such as during navigation, emergencies or sharing updates with trusted contacts...” He adds that after this kind of necessary tracking is complete, users should immediately turn off location tracking.</p>
<p><strong>Identify your app permissions</strong></p>
<p>One step to limit smartphone tracking is to identify and change app permission settings. To do this, iPhone users can first go to the device's Privacy &amp; Security settings. Then go to Location Services to check settings for individual apps.</p>
<p>Internet security experts say it is not a good idea to let apps always use your location in the background. Instead, get the app to either ask first before using your location, or use it only when the app is open. A user can also choose the setting that never lets an app track location.</p>
<p>The process works a little differently for Android phones because manufacturers have different versions. In general, Android users should go to settings. Then go to Location to turn the setting on or off for all apps.</p>
<p><strong>Ad trackers</strong></p>
<p>To avoid being tracked by advertising systems, privacy experts suggest that users block advertising identifiers on Android or Apple devices. This can stop third parties from tracking ads to target users.</p>
<p>To do this, iPhone users can go to the Privacy setting, then find Apple Advertising. Then turn off Personalized Ads. On newer Android phones, users should go to the Privacy setting, then to Ads, and choose Delete Advertising ID.</p>
<p><strong>Check your Google account</strong></p>
<p>Along with app permissions for your device, security experts say it is a good idea to look closely at your Google account to make sure it is not tracking you.</p>
<p>To find this out, go to myaccount.google.com and find Data &amp; Privacy. Users can find Location History controls there. Under recent changes, the history will be removed after three months although users can change that setting as well.</p>
<p><strong>How to use web browsers</strong></p>
<p>Popular web browsers for smartphones – like Safari or Chrome – could also give away location information. Try using one that does not store your data. Such browsers include DuckDuckGo, Firefox Focus or Ecosia.</p>
<p>If a privacy-protected browser needs to identify your location through an IP address, it will ask first before doing so. These kinds of browsers will also let users easily remove internet <strong>cookies</strong> and other web browsing data.</p>
<p><strong>Find my device</strong></p>
<p>Phones or <strong>tablets</strong> can also be tracked with Apple's Find My or Google's Find My Device services designed to recover lost devices. Users can turn this tool off if they think someone was able to take control of their Apple or Google account and is using it for tracking.</p>
<p><strong>Block the signal</strong></p>
<p>Some cybersecurity websites advise using a smartphone's Airplane Mode to block tracking operations. But some experts say this does not always turn off all tracking signals. Users should not depend on this setting alone to block data collection.</p>
<p>A better tool in many situations would be a signal-blocking Faraday <strong>bag</strong>. These block all wireless signals to the smartphone. Experts suggest testing the bag to make sure data is actually being blocked. While such bags can be helpful, devices kept inside the containers cannot be used.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>location </strong><em>– n. </em>a place where someone goes or something happens</p>
<p><strong>track </strong><em>– v. </em>to follow the movements of something</p>
<p><strong>navigation</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a method to find the right direction to travel in by using maps or other equipment</p>
<p><strong>digital </strong>– <em>adj.</em> any kind of information that is changed from electrical or physical to a form that is used by computers</p>
<p><strong>cookie </strong><em>– n. </em>small data files that are stored on an internet user's computer as they browse different websites.</p>
<p><strong>tablet </strong><em>– n. </em>a small computer that uses a touch screen</p>
<p><strong>bag</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n. </em>a container made of paper, plastic, etc. that is used for carrying things</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>The Westminster Kennel Club Dog Show, the ‘Super Bowl’ of Dog Shows  (2025/2/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/top-dog-takes-westminster-the-super-bowl-of-dog-shows.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>At America's 149<sup>th</sup> Westminster Kennel Club dog show, Monty the <strong>giant </strong>schnauzer won the top prize.</p>
<p>The lively schnauzer beat six other <strong>finalists</strong> in New York City to become the first of his <strong>breed</strong> to win Westminster's “best in show.” The prize is the most important and respected in the U.S. dog show world.</p>
<p>While Monty came close to winning Westminster the past two years, he <strong>fell short</strong> of the big prize. In December 2024, the dog won another big prize, the huge American Kennel Club championship.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Handler and co-owner Katie Bernardin poses with Monty, a giant schnauzer, after winning best in show at the 149th Westminster Kennel Club dog show, in New York, February 12, 2025. (AP Photo/Richard Drew)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/cb3140da-2c53-4ba6-8343-08dd4a843460_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Handler and co-owner Katie Bernardin poses with Monty, a giant schnauzer, after winning best in show at the 149th Westminster Kennel Club dog show, in New York, February 12, 2025. (AP Photo/Richard Drew)</span></div>
<p>But for dog show lovers, Westminster is considered the Super Bowl of all shows. This year the comparison is especially fitting. That is because the most respected U.S. dog competition opened on the same weekend as the Super Bowl -- the most important game in American professional football. This rare happening came after the dates of both competitions changed in recent years.</p>
<p>At Westminster, dogs first compete against other members of their breed. Then, the winner of each breed goes up against other dogs within different competition “groups.” Among the groups are sporting, working, toy, and <strong>herding</strong>. Group winners then compete in the final round.</p>
<p>The best in show winner gets an award – a large, shiny cup called a trophy – and a place in dog-world history. The top prize, however, does not include money.</p>
<p>In her <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/miniature-poodle-wins-westminster-dog-show-/7613398.html">report on the dog show</a>, Learning English's Caty Weaver explains that the Westminster show dates back to 1877. It centers on the traditional purebred judging that leads to the best in show prize. But over the last few years, the organization has added <strong>agility</strong> and <strong>obedience</strong> events open to mixed-breed dogs.</p>
<p>In 2024, Sage, a <strong>miniature</strong> poodle, won best in show at the 148th Westminster Kennel Club dog show.</p>
<p>And in 2023, a petit basset griffon Vendéen, named Buddy Holly, won best in show at Westminster. The breed he represents is known for its rabbit-hunting abilities.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Writers for the Associated Press reported this story from New York. Anna Matteo adapted the reports for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>giant </strong>–<em>adj. </em>something unusually large or powerful<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>finalist </strong>–<em>n. </em>a contestant in a competition finals<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>breed </strong>–<em>n. </em>a particular kind of dog, cat, horse, etc.<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>fall short (of something) </strong>–<em>phrase</em> fail to meet an expectation or standard for something</p>
<p><strong>herd </strong>–<em>v. </em>to move animals or people in a group<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>agility </strong>–<em>n. </em>the quality or state of being ability to move with quick easy grace<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>obedience </strong>–<em>n. </em>an act or instance of taking commands</p>
<p><strong>miniature </strong>–<em>adj. </em>something small of its kind<strong> </strong></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Senegal Starts Introducing English in Preschools  (2025/2/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/senegal-starts-introducing-english-in-preschools.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>In Senegal, educators are starting to teach English to younger children in an effort to better prepare them to succeed in future educational and professional activities.</p>
<p>The preschool students also learn French – the country's official language – as well as Arabic and the nation's national languages, the French news agency AFP reports.</p>
<p>Senegalese children who attend preschool – also known as nursery school, are generally under five. Since mid-January, the education ministry has been testing a program that teaches English in more than 600 nursery and <strong>primary school</strong> classes. It is part of a plan to better connect Senegal with the rest of the world.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Second-graders in Alieu Samb primary school hold up chalk boards with French conjugations. Dakar, Senegal, Dec. 7 2017. (Photo: Sofia Christensen for VOA) " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/5B2EE9AB-5F97-47B8-89F0-8CAC927954E1_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Second-graders in Alieu Samb primary school hold up chalk boards with French conjugations. Dakar, Senegal, Dec. 7 2017. (Photo: Sofia Christensen for VOA) </span></div>
<p>At one nursery school visited by AFP reporters near central Dakar, five-year-old students were heard singing, "Good morning, teacher!" The teacher, Absa Ndiaye, said, "They're interested in the lesson, and they start a <strong>conversation </strong>with 'How are you?'"</p>
<p>Senegal recently became an oil and gas producer and has seen large population growth. However, many young people have been leaving the country searching for <strong>opportunities</strong> elsewhere.</p>
<p>In Senegal, French is used in public schools and in government administration. Until recently, English was only taught in public high schools and universities, and sometimes in private nursery schools.</p>
<p>Aissatou Sarr Cisse is in charge of the education ministry's English program. She told AFP that even after some students had studied English for up to seven years, they “can barely communicate properly in English."</p>
<p>"We're starting from a younger age so that they can improve their language skills. The aim is to shape people who are open to the world,” Cisse said. She added that improving their English will give them <strong>access</strong> to more opportunities to cooperate “with Senegal's partners.”</p>
<p>In March, President Bassirou Diomaye Faye was elected after running a nationalist campaign. After many years of strong ties with the former colonial power, he is trying to reset Senegal's relationship with France, without breaking away completely.</p>
<p><strong>A desire to learn</strong></p>
<p>In the schools testing the program, English is taught every Tuesday and Thursday. On both days, two 25-minute lessons are taught in nursery schools and two 30-minute lessons in primary schools. The subjects taught center on family, colors, everyday greetings, the environment and the weather.</p>
<p>In Dakar's working-class Medina neighborhood, teacher Mamadou Kama listens to a conversation in English between two 13-year-olds in his primary school class of around 60 students.</p>
<p>"I can see that the students are <strong>motivated</strong>. Some of them are asking for English lessons to be (taught) every day," said Kama, who has a degree in English.</p>
<p>The ministry has invested in teachers who have high English levels. However, most of them have not yet received the teaching materials the ministry aims to provide.</p>
<p>"We haven't had the time to create handbooks,” said the education ministry's Cisse. “Computers have been ordered, and in the meantime, we have provided students with printed documents with fun pictures."</p>
<p><strong>Change or be left behind </strong></p>
<p>The project has been praised by Ousmane Sene, director of the Dakar-based West African Research Centre (WARC). WARC handles educational exchanges between the United States and west African universities.</p>
<p>"English is the most common language at an international level. And it's the most used language in diplomacy and international cooperation, so it's an additional <strong>asset</strong>," Sene told AFP.</p>
<p>Additionally, most scientific material worldwide is written in English, said Mathiam Thiam. He helped create the English program. Thiam added that if people in Senegal do not <strong>adapt</strong> and improve their English, they will run into many barriers.</p>
<p>But Sene noted that something needs to happen first: The project needs “... to train and equip the teachers well.”</p>
<p><strong>Criticism of the program</strong></p>
<p>Some critics of the program point to a lack of teachers. Samba Dioulde Thiam is a former member of parliament and retired teacher. In an opinion article, he wrote, "On these grounds alone, introducing English at nursery and primary school levels is a <strong>pipe dream</strong>. It's impossible."</p>
<p>He noted that <strong>intellectuals</strong> have been demanding the introduction of Senegal's national languages in education for many years. The program involving English could further delay that goal.</p>
<p>But one 13-year-old student, Aissatou Barry, seems far removed from such debates. She told AFP that she "can't wait to study English in sixth grade."</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Malick Rokhy Ba reported this story for Agence France-Presse. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>conversation </strong><em>– n. </em>oral exchange of sentiments, observations, opinions, or ideas</p>
<p><strong>primary school </strong><em>– adj. </em>a school usually including the first three grades of elementary school but sometimes also including kindergarten</p>
<p><strong>opportunity </strong><em>– n.</em> a good chance for advancement or progress</p>
<p><strong>access </strong><em>– n. </em>permission or power to enter, approach, or make use of</p>
<p><strong>motivated </strong><em>– adj. </em>having an incentive or a strong desire to do well or succeed in some pursuit</p>
<p><strong>asset </strong><em>– n. </em>a quality or thing that can be used to advantage</p>
<p><strong>adapt </strong><em>– v. </em>to make or become suitable, especially to change so as to fit a new or specific use or situation</p>
<p><strong>pipe dream </strong><em>– n. </em>an illusory or fantastic plan, hope, or story</p>
<p><strong>intellectual </strong><em>– adj. </em>engaged in or given to learning and thinking</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Airbus Delays Development of Hydrogen-Powered Aircraft  (2025/2/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/airbus-delays-development-of-hydrogen-powered-aircraft.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>European manufacturer Airbus has announced a delay in its development efforts of a hydrogen-powered aircraft. The company explained that progress on the project has been slower and more complex than expected.</p>
<p>Airbus had set a goal to make a zero-<strong>emission</strong> airplane by 2035. The company has not announced a new target date for the plane's production. But the French union Force Ouvrière said some of its aircraft workers were recently told the technology was running five to 10 years behind, Reuters news agency reported.</p>
<p>The French news agency AFP reported Airbus also said it had reduced the program's budget by 25 percent, but was still examining ways to reduce emissions.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="The logo of Airbus is pictured outside the Airbus facility in Saint-Nazaire, France, November 7, 2023. REUTERS/Stephane Mahe
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/96ec70d1-b4d2-4442-f5ea-08dd4a817620_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">The logo of Airbus is pictured outside the Airbus facility in Saint-Nazaire, France, November 7, 2023. REUTERS/Stephane Mahe
</span></div>
<p>"Our <strong>ambition</strong> and <strong>roadmap</strong> towards decarbonizing. . .remain unchanged," an Airbus spokesman told AFP.</p>
<p>In September 2020, Airbus presented three hydrogen-fueled airplane designs, called ZEROe, as part of its efforts to decarbonize.</p>
<p>Other airplane manufacturers, however, have centered more on <strong>renewable</strong> fuels or developing electric-powered planes for short-distance flights.</p>
<p>Airbus noted it has no plans to completely stop developing hydrogen-powered aircraft technology. The company said it sees hydrogen as “a revolutionary energy source for aviation."</p>
<p>However, Airbus said in a statement to Reuters it recognizes that developing systems to produce, transport, and store hydrogen represent “a huge <strong>challenge</strong> requiring global <strong>collaboration</strong> and investment."</p>
<p><strong>Difficulties with hydrogen</strong></p>
<p>Hydrogen motors do not release gases that can warm the earth's atmosphere. Instead, they release water.</p>
<p>However, much of the hydrogen used for fuel is produced using natural gas or coal. Both of these production methods often release carbon dioxide gas, which can warm the atmosphere.</p>
<p>Running renewable electricity through water can produce hydrogen without adding to carbon emissions. However, this process is generally more costly. Transporting and storing hydrogen also present problems.</p>
<p>As a gas at room temperature, hydrogen takes up a very large space. This makes it impossible to use as fuel. It first needs to be turned into a liquid to be transported or stored. And it needs to be cooled to -253° Celsius to be liquefied. This cooling process requires its own source of energy. Liquified hydrogen still takes up four times the space of jet fuel.</p>
<p>The airline industry trade association IATA believes aviation will reach most of its reduction in emissions by using <strong>sustainable</strong> aviation fuel (SAF). It believes other technologies, like hydrogen, will take longer to develop.</p>
<p>SAF uses food and plant waste from cities, agricultural and forest wastes, and other non-<strong>petroleum</strong> sources. This fuel is then added to jet fuel in mixtures of 10 to 50 percent to become SAF.</p>
<p>Airbus says it agrees that SAF can also play an important part in reducing emissions, particularly for medium and long-distance flights.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith adapted this story for VOA Learning English based on reporting from Agence France-Presse and Reuters</em>.</p>
<p>______________________________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>emission </strong><em>-n. </em>a release of gas</p>
<p><strong>ambition </strong><em>-n. </em>a strong desire to achieve a goal</p>
<p><strong>roadmap </strong><em>-n. </em>a plan of action to achieve a goal</p>
<p><strong>renewable </strong><em>-adj. </em>describing resources such as wind, water, and sunlight which are always available</p>
<p><strong>challenge </strong><em>-n. </em>a difficult thing to do or difficult goal to reach</p>
<p><strong>collaboration </strong><em>-n. </em>working well with other people</p>
<p><strong>sustainable </strong><em>-adj. </em>describing resources that can be used again without increasing pollution</p>
<p><strong>petroleum </strong><em>-n. </em>oil found under the surface of the earth or sea.</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Mary Kay: A Leader in the Beauty Product Industry  (2025/2/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/mary-kay-a-leader-in-the-beauty-product-industry.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Mary Kay Cosmetics is an international company that sells beauty products.</p>
<p>One woman started the business in the 1960s with an investment of $5,000.</p>
<p>Mary Kathlyn Wagner was born in the state of Texas in 1918. For much of her childhood, she cared for her sick father while her mother worked long hours at a restaurant.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Mary Kay Ash, president of Mary Kay Cosmetics, is seen in her Dallas, Texas, office in January 1982. (AP File Photo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/9281acf5-e66e-4341-de0f-08dd4a81f35f_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Mary Kay Ash, president of Mary Kay Cosmetics, is seen in her Dallas, Texas, office in January 1982. (AP File Photo)</span></div>
<p>Mary Kay married Ben Rogers when she was 17 years old. They had three children before he left home to serve in World War Two. When he returned, their marriage ended. Mary Kay looked for a job so she could support her children.</p>
<p>She began selling different kinds of products. One night, Mary Kay was showing products at the home of Ova Heath Spoonemore. Ms. Spoonemore began giving her guests some homemade skin care products. The products were developed by her father, J.W. Heath, in Arkansas. Mary Kay tried the skin care products and liked them.</p>
<p>She bought the rights to Heath's skin care products and started her own company. She paid $500 for the legal rights to the products. And in 1963, The Mary Kay Cosmetics company began operating in Dallas, Texas.</p>
<p>The idea was to sell skin care products through demonstrations in homes and offices. Independent sales representatives bought beauty products from the company and sold them at higher prices.</p>
<p>Mary Kay decided that each representative who brought other saleswomen into the company would receive part of the new person's earnings. That way, experienced sales representatives would be willing to train new ones.</p>
<p>By 1965, the company was selling almost one million dollars in products.</p>
<p>Mary Kay Cosmetics became one of the most successful direct sellers of skin care products in America. It continues to have sales offices and representatives in many different countries.</p>
<p>Mary Kay aimed to grow sales based on the idea that it is best to compete against yourself. That means every individual is trying to beat their own sales records. Prizes for high sales marks included special paid holidays and jewelry. Until a few years ago, a pink Cadillac was a top prize.</p>
<p>After her third husband, Mel Ash, died of cancer in 1980, she wanted to help find a cure for the disease. At first, she helped organizations raise money for research.</p>
<p>Later, she started the Mary Kay Ash Charitable Foundation, a nonprofit group that provides money to support research on cancers affecting women. In 2001, the company and foundation expanded their goals to help prevent violence against women.</p>
<p>Mary Kay Ash also wrote three books. She worked in her business until she suffered a <strong>stroke</strong> in 1996. She died in 2001.</p>
<p>Sales representatives say Mary Kay developed a way for women to earn money and still spend time with their families.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Nancy Steinbach</em><em> wrote this story for VOA Special English. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>stroke –</strong>n. A problem with one or more blood vessels that prevents the brain from getting enough blood</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Saying ‘No’ at Work Can Be Good for Your Health  (2025/2/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/saying-no-at-work-can-be-good-for-your-health.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>People might find it hard to set work limits or say “no” before taking on too many responsibilities. But experts say it is important for workers to learn to set such limits, or boundaries.</p>
<p>These limits can be important in helping workers protect their physical and mental health. And as with any new skill, setting boundaries gets easier with practice.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="People work at the Yelp office in San Francisco on February, 14, 2023. (AP Photo/Jeff Chiu, File)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/09b90e24-5d9f-49ae-a486-3ea2d175a00c_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">People work at the Yelp office in San Francisco on February, 14, 2023. (AP Photo/Jeff Chiu, File)
</span></div>
<p>Justin Stewart is a 36-year-old who works as a news show production assistant. He told The Associated Press that in the past, he had problems setting clear limits in his work life.</p>
<p>Stewart explained that when starting his career, he held several jobs. In addition to his full-time position, he also rented cars at the airport and did sales at a store. He said his life was so busy that he said he would sometimes sleep in his car between jobs. After a time, he had to be hospitalized for extreme tiredness and an infection.</p>
<p>Stewart said that over time, his busy work life finally caught up with him. “While people around me praised my <strong>hustle</strong>, I eventually <strong>paid the price</strong>.” He added, “The doctor looked at me and said, ‘I don't know what lifestyle you're living, but you're too young to be this <strong>stressed</strong>. You're going to have to quit something.'”</p>
<p>As a result, Stewart began trying to set boundaries. He gave up his side jobs after deciding he could live without the extra money. If people from the news show contacted him to work after-hours, he told them he was not available and suggested other people who might be able to help.</p>
<p>However, experts say making such changes can be difficult. Many people already have a hard time turning down work requests –from both co-workers and <strong>managers</strong>. For example, it might make some people feel good to be needed or to please others. But as with any new skill, setting boundaries can get easier over time.</p>
<p>Here are some suggestions from employment experts and workers for effectively setting meaningful work limits.</p>
<p><strong>Take control of your time</strong></p>
<p>If your goal is to do less, adding things to your daily plans may seem like a bad idea. But it can actually provide more control over your time.</p>
<p>Bobby Dutton is the founder of event production company GBM6.</p>
<p>Every Monday at 2 p.m., he plans the task he is most likely to delay finishing. And to keep from becoming too busy, he even sets his daily activities, like walking his dog and eating lunch.</p>
<p><strong>Practice “no” responses</strong></p>
<p>If workers have a hard time saying no, they can write down what to say beforehand. And it can also help to say it out loud.</p>
<p>Cara Houser is a workplace <strong>engagement</strong> coach. She says workers do not always have to explain themselves when turning down a request. They can simply explain they are not available, thank the person for asking, and suggest when they might be available.</p>
<p>Amber Krasinski grew up in a working-class environment where saying "no" to a manager could mean losing pay. As the founder of marketing company IvyHill Strategies, Krasinski worries that she will lose business<strong> </strong>if she turns down a project.</p>
<p>So, she often says “not yet” when one more project is too much. “That phrase has helped me through a lot of situations,” she said.</p>
<p><strong>Know yourself</strong></p>
<p>When asked for help, workers may want to agree immediately. However, when faced with a new work request, it can be better to take time before answering. Use the time to consider such things as workload, energy level, and interest.</p>
<p>Israa Nasir is a <strong>psychotherapist</strong> in New York. She suggests that workers pay attention to the activities and interactions that leave them feeling tired or stressed. Those kinds of events can be put on a “No List” to be dealt with later.</p>
<p><strong>Technology can help</strong></p>
<p>Experts say that just because mobile devices can keep people connected to work all the time, they do not have to interfere with a person's non-working life.</p>
<p>For example, Nasir said she found herself checking email far too often on weekends. So, during weekends, she moved the Gmail app from her iPhone's homepage to the second page. This extra step helped her avoid checking her email.</p>
<p>Experts also suggest using an <strong>email signature</strong> as another tool to manage expectations. This tool can include more than just your name and contact information. You can also use it to let others know your working hours or upcoming vacation plans.</p>
<p>And that's the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p>And I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Cathy Bussewitz reported this story for The Associated Press from New York City. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>hustle </strong><em>– n.<strong> </strong></em>to move or work rapidly and tirelessly</p>
<p><strong>pay the price </strong><em>– idiom </em>to experience the bad result of something you have done</p>
<p><strong>stressed </strong><em>– adj.<strong> </strong></em>effected by a physical, chemical, or emotional factor that causes bodily or mental tension and may be a factor in disease causation</p>
<p><strong>manager </strong><em>– n. </em>a person who manages especially a business or household affairs</p>
<p><strong>engagement </strong><em>– n. </em>the state of being meshed into a working arrangement in which one part drives another</p>
<p><strong>psychotherapist </strong><em>– n. </em>person who treats mental or emotional disorders by psychological means</p>
<p><strong>email signature </strong><em>– n. </em>a block of text or image that appears at the end of an email message</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>WHO Launches New Cancer Drug Plan for Children  (2025/2/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/who-launches-new-cancer-drug-plan-for-children.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>The World Health Organization (WHO) has launched a new service, or platform, to provide free cancer medicines to thousands of children in less wealthy nations.</p>
<p>The WHO defines these as low- and middle-income countries. The first medicines were to be provided to Mongolia and Uzbekistan. The next shipments would go to Ecuador, Jordan, Nepal and Zambia, as part of the project's testing, or pilot period, the WHO said.</p>
<p>The drug treatments are expected to reach around 5,000 children with cancer this year across at least 30 hospitals in the six countries.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Director-General of the World Health Organisation (WHO) Dr. Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus attends the World Health Assembly at the United Nations in Geneva, Switzerland, May 27, 2024. REUTERS/Denis Balibouse" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/8203a69b-b2a2-40c5-b0ce-7a4bf175a9c4_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Director-General of the World Health Organisation (WHO) Dr. Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus attends the World Health Assembly at the United Nations in Geneva, Switzerland, May 27, 2024. REUTERS/Denis Balibouse</span></div>
<p>"Countries in the pilot phase will receive an<strong> uninterrupted</strong> supply of quality-<strong>assured</strong> childhood cancer medicines at no cost," the U.N. health agency said in a statement.</p>
<p>The WHO said childhood cancer survival rates in low- and middle-income countries were often below 30 percent. That compares to survival rates of around 80 percent in wealthy nations.</p>
<p>The agency's Director-General, Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.who.int/news/item/11-02-2025-who-st.-jude-launch-groundbreaking-international-delivery-of--childhood-cancer-medicines" target="_blank">said</a> in a statement, "For too long, children with cancer have lacked <strong>access</strong> to life-saving medicines." He added that the new platform aims to bring "health and hope to children around the world."</p>
<p>El Salvador, Moldova, Senegal, Ghana, Pakistan and Sri Lanka are expected to join the program very soon. The platform hopes to reach 50 countries in the next five to seven years, providing medicines for up to 120,000 children.</p>
<p>The WHO estimates about 400,000 children worldwide develop cancer every year. Most of the children live in places with limited resources.</p>
<p>The agency says about 70 percent of children in those settings die for several reasons. These include the use of low-quality medicines, an inability to get correct treatments, or problems with the supply of treatments.</p>
<p>The plan to establish the platform was first announced in December 2021. It is a cooperative deal between the WHO and St. Jude Children's Research Hospital in Memphis, Tennessee in the United States. The U.S. non-profit treatment and research organization provided $200 million for its launch, the WHO said.</p>
<p>The WHO called the financial commitment the largest ever made for childhood cancer medicines worldwide. It added that the cost-free service would continue beyond the pilot phase. The platform is working on developing its sustainability – or ability to continue to provide the service - over the longer term.</p>
<p>Andre Ilbawi is with the WHO's cancer control program. He told reporters the program seeks to widen the platform and bring additional partners on board. "This marks the beginning of a global movement to provide children with cancer the medicines that they need, regardless of where they live, or their ability to pay," Ilbawi said.</p>
<p>He added that the issue of children with cancer was getting more attention in wealthier countries. "Childhood cancer is increasingly a leading cause of death for middle- and high-income countries...so governments are increasingly paying attention," Ilbawi said.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Robin Millard reported on this story for Agence France-Presse. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>_______________________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>uninterrupted </strong><em>– adj. </em>not stopped or blocked</p>
<p><strong>assured</strong> <em>– adj. </em>sure that something is true; guaranteed</p>
<p><strong>access </strong><em>– n.</em> the ability to use or see something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Thomas Edison: Inventor and Busy Team Leader  (2025/2/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/thomas-edison-inventor-and-busy-team-leader.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>The inventor Thomas Alva Edison had a major effect on the lives of people around the world. Thomas Edison is remembered most for the electric light, his <strong>phonograph</strong>, and his work with motion pictures.</p>
<p>Edison was born on February 11, 1847, in Milan, Ohio. He was mostly self-taught. His mother taught him reading, writing, and mathematics. He learned from books, and he experimented.</p>
<p>At the age of 10, he experimented with chemicals and electricity. He built a <strong>telegraph</strong> machine and, at the age of 16, he went to work as a telegraph operator.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="File - Thomas Edison presses a button in West Orange, N.J., in 1928. The button turns on street lights in Seattle. (AP Photo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/2bae181d-78a9-4007-bdfb-8a9aeaa5cb8a_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">File - Thomas Edison presses a button in West Orange, N.J., in 1928. The button turns on street lights in Seattle. (AP Photo)</span></div>
<p>He continued his work with electricity, making improved telegraph machines, and he invented an electrical voting machine.</p>
<p>Edison earned enough money from his early inventions to start his own company in 1871. Instead of working alone, he worked with a group of employees on many different projects at one time. They asked the United States government for <strong>patents</strong> to protect more than one hundred devices or inventions each year. He was an extremely busy man.</p>
<p>In 1913, a popular magazine at the time called Thomas Edison the most useful man in America.</p>
<p>He almost never slept more than four or five hours a night. He usually worked 18 hours each day because he enjoyed what he was doing.</p>
<p>A reporter asked Edison in 1917 which of his many inventions he enjoyed the most. He answered, the phonograph was really the most interesting. The hardest invention to develop, he said, was the electric light. He said that it was the most difficult and the most important. He also invented the modern motion picture film.</p>
<p>In 1928, he received a special medal of honor from the Congress of the United States. Thomas Edison died on January 6, 1931. People worldwide have had easier and more enjoyable lives because of his inventions.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Paul Thompson reported this story for VOA's People in America program. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>phonograph</strong> <em>– n. </em>device to play records</p>
<p><strong>telegraph</strong> <em>– n.</em> an old-fashioned system of sending messages over long distances by using wires and electrical signals</p>
<p><strong>patent</strong> <em>– n.</em> an official document that gives a person or company the right to be the only one that makes or sells a product for a certain period of time</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>European Telescope Discovers ‘Einstein Ring’ in Nearby Galaxy  (2025/2/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/european-telescope-discovers-einstein-ring-in-nearby-galaxy.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Scientists say Europe's Euclid space telescope has discovered a bright ring of light circling a nearby <strong>galaxy</strong>. The observed light is known as an Einstein ring.</p>
<p>Researchers have estimated the ring encircles a galaxy 590 million light years away from Earth. A light year is the distance light travels in a year – about 9.5 trillion kilometers.</p>
<p>Astronomers have long known about the galaxy where the ring was discovered. So, they were surprised that the bright ring had not been identified before.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This photo provided by the European Space Agency shows a ring of light surrounding the center of the galaxy NGC 6505, captured by European Space Agency's Euclid telescope, an example of an Einstein ring. (European Space Agency via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a618e8da-a212-4c07-f5ed-08dd4a817620_cx0_cy28_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This photo provided by the European Space Agency shows a ring of light surrounding the center of the galaxy NGC 6505, captured by European Space Agency's Euclid telescope, an example of an Einstein ring. (European Space Agency via AP)</span></div>
<p>It was discovered in a well-studied galaxy called NGC 6505. It is in the constellation – a group of stars – named Draco.</p>
<p>Einstein rings are rare. They form when light from a more distant galaxy <strong>bends</strong> around a closer galaxy. The nearer galaxy appears to have a circle of light, or a halo, around it.</p>
<p>The Einstein ring gets its name from physicist Albert Einstein. Einstein predicted that light would bend around extremely massive objects in space. This is called “gravitational lensing.”</p>
<p>The American space agency NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/hubble/science/science-highlights/focusing-in-on-gravitational-lenses/#:~:text=Gravitational%20lenses%20are%20'Nature's%20Boost,in%20eyeglasses%20or%20contact%20lenses.">explains</a> that as light passes through a gravitational <strong>lens</strong>, “it may take different paths, producing multiple images of the same object.” In this way, gravity itself acts as a lens, <strong>magnifying</strong> and distorting space and time in a way that is similar to an optical lens like those in eyeglasses or contact lenses.</p>
<p>Gravitational lenses permit telescopes like Euclid to observe more distant and less-bright objects. In the latest project, researchers from Germany's Max Planck Institute for Astrophysics used data from Euclid to create a computer model to discover the Einstein ring.</p>
<p>The Euclid space telescope is operated by the European Space Agency (ESA). In 2023, it <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/europe-prepares-to-launch-spacecraft-to-observe-dark-side-of-universe/7148712.html">launched</a> on a six-year mission that ESA officials have said aims to study the mysteries of dark matter and dark energy across the universe.</p>
<p>Astronomers at the Max Planck Institute are leading the research. In a statement, the organization said the first sign that the Einstein ring existed came during testing right after Euclid was deployed. A team member, Bruno Altieri, was looking over early data collected by Euclid.</p>
<p>“Even from that first observation, I could see it,” Altieri said in a statement. “But after Euclid made more observations of the area, we could see a <strong>perfect</strong> Einstein ring. For me, with a lifelong interest in gravitational lensing, that was amazing.”</p>
<p>The scientists said the more distant galaxy involved in the method is about 4.4 billion light years away from Earth. They noted that the more distant galaxy had never been observed before and does not have a name.</p>
<p>Altieri's team recently reported the findings <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.aanda.org/articles/aa/full_html/2025/02/aa53014-24/aa53014-24.html">in a study</a> in the publication <em>Astronomy and Astrophysics</em>.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p>Conor O'Riordan is another team member from the Max Planck Institute and was the lead writer of the study. He said, “All strong lenses are <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_l2kTlzAg">special, because</a> they're so rare, and they're incredibly useful scientifically. This one is particularly special, because it's so close to Earth and the <strong>alignment</strong> makes it very beautiful.”</p>
<p>O'Riordan added that the researchers used the latest gravitational lensing methods developed at the institute. This permitted them to model the light of the ring. “We even had to look at some of the <strong>raw </strong>data to better understand how the <strong>detector</strong> works.”</p>
<p>O'Riordan said the team's modeling operations were just the first step in studying the newly discovered Einstein ring. He said the group plans to use the ring to also study “dark matter substructures” within the lensing galaxy.</p>
<p>O'Riordan predicted, “Euclid is going to revolutionize the field, with all this data we've never had before.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, the Max Planck Institute, the European Space <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_C1ZJT1vu">Agency</a> and NASA.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>galaxy </strong><em>– n. </em>a very large group of stars held together in the universe</p>
<p><strong>bend</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to make something become curved</p>
<p><strong>distort </strong><em>– v. </em>to change the shape, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_wbyJPVIx">sound</a> or appearance of something<em> </em></p>
<p><strong>lens </strong><em>– n. </em>a curved piece of glass in cameras, glasses and scientific equipment used or looking at things</p>
<p><strong>magnify</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v. </em>to make an object look larger than it is by looking through special equipment</p>
<p><strong>perfect </strong>–adj. complete; having no mistakes; completely correct</p>
<p><strong>align </strong><em>– v. </em>to put things in an exact line or make them parallel</p>
<p><strong>raw </strong><em>– n. </em>unprepared or imperfectly prepared for use</p>
<p><strong>detect</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v. </em>to identify something, especially something that is difficult to see, hear, smell, etc.</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Yellowstone: The World’s First National Park  (2025/2/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/yellowstone-the-world-s-first-national-park.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Yellowstone National Park in the western United States was the world's first national park.</p>
<p>Established in 1872, it is famous for its <strong>geothermal</strong> activity and wild animals. It includes beautiful mountains, deep canyons, lakes and rivers.</p>
<p>Yellowstone is still one of the largest national parks in the U.S. It takes up almost 9,000 square kilometers. Most of the park lies within the western state of Wyoming.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE --Old Faithful geyser erupts in Yellowstone National Park, January, 2011. (Photo:National Park Service, Diane Renkin)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e487777c-e7e7-43ea-def4-08dd4a81f35f_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE --Old Faithful geyser erupts in Yellowstone National Park, January, 2011. (Photo:National Park Service, Diane Renkin)</span></div>
<p>The park is unusual because of what lies underneath it. It sits on top of an ancient super volcano, known as the Yellowstone Caldera. The caldera remains an active volcano.</p>
<p>A lake of hot liquid rock is about six kilometers under the park. Experts say this lake is under huge amounts of pressure. The pressure and heat cause <strong>geysers</strong> to shoot hot water out of the ground and mud to boil at Yellowstone.</p>
<p>The park is home to more than 300 geysers. There are more geysers and hot springs in Yellowstone than any other place on Earth. “Old Faithful” is the name of the park's most famous geyser because it erupts about every 90 minutes.</p>
<p>Yellowstone is on a high <strong>plateau</strong> with an average height of 2,400 meters above sea level. This makes the weather very cold in winter, with January temperatures averaging between -18 degrees and -7 degrees Celsius. However, some areas of the park remain open to visitors throughout the year.</p>
<p>Yellowstone Canyon is about 365 meters deep. The Yellowstone River runs through it and drops 93 meters in the Lower Falls. Visitors can walk on a path that brings them very close to the top of the falls. There, they can see and hear the powerful falls.</p>
<p>In summer of 1988, forest fires burned large areas of the park. Most of those areas are now covered with plants and young trees.</p>
<p><strong>Home to wildlife</strong></p>
<p>Yellowstone is home to the largest group of wild animals in the lower 48 United States. These include bison, grizzly bear, elk, deer, moose, fox, beaver, coyote and wolves. In 2024, park officials estimated the bison population to be about 4,500 animals. That makes it the largest group of wild bison in the world.</p>
<p>There is still a wild west in America...and its name is Yellowstone.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this story.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>geothermal </strong>–adj. describing geological or volcanic activity that is the result of underground heat</p>
<p><strong>geyser </strong>–n. a hot spring that periodically shoots boiling water high into the air as underground steam pressure builds up and is released</p>
<p><strong>plateau</strong> –n. an area of land that is flat at the top and higher than surrounding land</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Don't Miss a Thing With 'Eagle Eyes'  (2025/2/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/don-t-miss-a-thing-with-eagle-eyes.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>From above, birds must have a wonderful <strong>view</strong> of the world below. Flying over everything at such a height gives them a rare ability to see many things.</p>
<p>In English, we use the term “bird's eye view” to describe a view from above as if seen by a bird in flight. It is also described as an “overall view” or “big picture view.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Uncle Sam, a 25-year-old bald eagle, sits in front of a U.S. flag before the Extreme Raptors Show at the Permian Basin Fair in the Ector County Coliseum fairgrounds in Odessa, Texas, on September 11, 2013. (Edyta Blaszczyk/Odessa American via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/6c220688-1e51-48fa-b836-ec3b32f66138_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Uncle Sam, a 25-year-old bald eagle, sits in front of a U.S. flag before the Extreme Raptors Show at the Permian Basin Fair in the Ector County Coliseum fairgrounds in Odessa, Texas, on September 11, 2013. (Edyta Blaszczyk/Odessa American via AP)</span></div>
<p>For example, when I start a project, I first like to get a bird's eye view. I ask myself several important questions: What is the overall goal? Who is the main <strong>focus</strong>? What resources do I have available to me? Answers to these “big picture” questions can help me understand the <strong>scope</strong> of the project.</p>
<p>Now, let's talk about <strong>noticing </strong>the smaller details.</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" name="_Hlk81395775">Some birds, called raptors, are known for their extremely sharp vision. Eagles, hawks, and owls can see their <strong>prey</strong> from very far away.</a></p>
<p>The Raptor Center is part of the University of Minnesota's College of Veterinary Medicine. Its website explains why eagles, hawks, and owls see so well: “Raptors have powerful <strong>binocular</strong> vision, where both their left and right eyes can see and focus on a single object.”</p>
<p>Eagles and hawks also have a special bone structure around their eyes that protects them from bright sunlight. Their ability to focus on faraway details in addition to other <strong>factors</strong> make them extremely effective hunters.</p>
<p>In English, the <strong>keen </strong>vision of eagles and hawks describes a certain type of person.</p>
<p>If you have an <u>eagle eye</u>, you have the ability to see or notice distant objects. Also, you observe<strong> </strong>everything, even very small details which others might miss. On the same note, someone who is <u>hawk-eyed </u>watches and notices everything that happens.</p>
<p>These types of people may even <strong>perceive</strong> things that are not clear to others. Both eagle-eyed and hawk-eyed people are observant or perceptive.</p>
<p>A person does not have to have this ability all the time. They might use their keen vision and powers of observation only at certain times, especially times when they need to keep a close watch.</p>
<p>For example, during Christmastime, hawk-eyed children might search the sky looking for Santa Claus. These children may not be very observant during the rest of the year, but during Christmastime, they are looking for gifts.</p>
<p>Let's hear these terms used between two friends.</p>
<p><em>A: This is a great party. Thanks for inviting me. </em></p>
<p><em>B: The more the merrier! This yearly neighborhood party always</em> <em>draws a huge number of people.</em></p>
<p><em>A: I'd say so! There must be over a hundred people here! Hey, wait a minute. I think I see our old co-worker. Isn't that Samantha way over there <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_bsfxpB2E">by</a> the food and drinks?</em></p>
<p><em>B: I don't know. I can't see that far.</em></p>
<p><em>A: It's her. My eagle eyes don't miss a thing. I'm going to go say hi and grab the last hamburger while I'm there. Oh, and you should let the hosts know that they're low on drinks. </em></p>
<p><em>B: Wow! You're right. I didn't realize you were so hawk-eyed.</em></p>
<p><em>A: Only at parties. I start off with a bird's eye view and then <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_dcszQGDq">focus in</a> on the food, drinks, and people I want to see more closely. See you in a few... </em></p>
<p>The term “eagle eye” has been used for hundreds of years. Word experts say it was first used in writing in the mid-1500s. The Oxford English Dictionary website says the “earliest evidence for ‘eagle eye' is from 1567, in the writing of Thomas Stapleton, a Roman Catholic theologian.”</p>
<p>A theologian is an expert in religious thought.</p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_9P0us6wD">this</a> <em>Words and Their Stories</em>. Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>___________________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>view </strong><em>–n.</em> things that can be seen from a certain position or place</p>
<p><strong>focus </strong><em>–n.</em> the thing that takes up most of one's attention : <strong>focus</strong> <em>–v.</em> to make an image seen by the eyes as sharp as possible</p>
<p><strong>notice </strong><em>–v. </em>to see and pay attention to something</p>
<p><strong>prey </strong><em>–n.</em> an animal that is being hunted</p>
<p><strong>binocular </strong><em>–adj.</em> involving two eyes</p>
<p><strong>factor </strong><em>–n.</em> one thing that is involved in a process aimed at producing a result</p>
<p><strong>keen </strong><em>–adj. </em>very sharp</p>
<p><strong>perceive </strong><em>–v. </em>to understand</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Monarch Butterfly Count Nears 30-Year Low  (2025/2/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/monarch-butterfly-count-nears-30-year-low.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>An American nonprofit group says the number of monarch butterflies spending the winter in the western United States has dropped to its second-lowest mark in nearly 30 years.</p>
<p>The Xerces Society for Invertebrate Conservation, based in Oregon, said the causes for this include the use of chemicals to kill insects, known as <strong>pesticides</strong>. The group also blames reductions in <strong>habitat</strong> and climate change.</p>
<p><strong>The survey began in 1997</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Monarch butterflies from Canada stop to rest in Wendy Park on their way to Mexico, Sept. 12, 2023, in Cleveland, OH." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/b08a8f60-4c55-4ddc-93d9-89688273204a_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Monarch butterflies from Canada stop to rest in Wendy Park on their way to Mexico, Sept. 12, 2023, in Cleveland, OH.</span></div>
<p>Monarch butterflies are known for their clear orange-and-black markings. They live across North America. Monarchs in the eastern United States spend the winter in Mexico. The World Wildlife Fund, a non-profit based in Switzerland, counts them there but has not yet released data for this year. Monarchs west of the Rocky Mountains usually spend the winter along the California coast.</p>
<p>The Xerces Society for Invertebrate Conservation has been counting western overwinter populations in California and Arizona for the last 28 years. The highest number recorded was 1.2 million in 1997. The organization announced Friday that it counted just 9,119 monarchs in 2024, a decrease of 96 percent from 233,394 in 2023. The total was the second lowest since the survey began in 1997. The record-low count was 1,901 monarchs in 2020.</p>
<p>The <strong>survey</strong> noted that a place in Santa Barbara that saw 33,200 monarchs last winter had only 198 butterflies this year.</p>
<p><strong>Heat might have hurt western monarchs</strong></p>
<p>Monarchs across North America face increasing threats. One is the supply of a plant, milkweed, which they feed on as <strong>caterpillars</strong>. Monarch Joint Venture is a nonprofit group based in Minnesota that aims to protect monarchs. The group said milkweed has been disappearing because of dry weather, wildfires, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_rfBYIGT0">agriculture</a> and urban development. The Xerces Society said pesticides might be on the remaining plants.</p>
<p>Emma Pelton is a biologist with the Xerces Society. She said it is unclear what caused such a sharp decrease in the western population in just one year. The monarch population is already small, she said, and heat above 37.7 degrees Celsius in the western states last year might have slowed <strong>breeding</strong>.</p>
<p>Monarchs suffer when the temperature gets up to 37.7 degrees Celsius and any temperatures above 42.2 degrees Celsius will kill the insects, Pelton said.</p>
<p>The western states saw a heat wave in July with temperatures in some areas well past 37.7 degrees. Palm Springs, for example, reportedly reached a record 51.1 degrees Celsius on July 5. Another heat wave hit northern California in early October, with several cities breaking heat records.</p>
<p><strong>Western monarchs' future unclear</strong></p>
<p>Pelton said that it is too early to tell what long-term effect the sharp drop might have on the overall western monarch population. Insects can reproduce very quickly, Pelton said. After a low point of 1,901 butterflies in 2020, the population recovered to 247,246 insects the following year, an increase of nearly 13,000 percent. The year after that the survey recorded 335,479 monarchs.</p>
<p>"This is bad news," Pelton said of the 2024 population drop. "But we have seen <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_jDuC50In">incredible</a> recovery. This doesn't mean we're not going to have western monarchs.”</p>
<p><strong>Federal officials working on protections</strong></p>
<p>The U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service announced in December 2024 that it wanted to list monarchs as threatened. Such a move would ban people from killing or transporting them. The proposed change would also ban property owners from making changes to their property that would make it unusable to the butterflies. For example, removing all milkweed from a property would by banned by law.</p>
<p>Earthjustice is an environmental nonprofit legal group based in San Francisco. It asked the Environmental Protection Agency in December 2024 to require testing of pesticides' effects on insects such as bees, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_Ud7REN2f">moths</a> and butterflies.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Todd Richmond reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>pesticide </strong>– <em>n</em>. a chemical that is used to kill animals or insects that damage plants or crops</p>
<p><strong>habitat </strong>–n. the place or environment where a living thing lives</p>
<p><strong>survey </strong>–n. a study of a subject aimed at finding something out</p>
<p><strong>caterpillar </strong>–n. an early stage in the life of certain insects</p>
<p><strong>breed</strong> – <em>v</em>. to produce young animals, birds, or the like</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Visitors Laugh Away Troubles at the HaHaHouse Museum  (2025/2/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/visitors-laugh-away-troubles-at-the-hahahouse-museum.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">14 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>A new <strong>museum</strong> of laughter in Croatia is offering to help people deal with the <strong>negativity</strong> of modern life.</p>
<p>Visitors to the HaHaHouse in the Croatian capital Zagreb walk into a little cloud of white smoke when they step inside. Its purpose is to blow away their worries before they climb into a "giant washing machine".</p>
<p>Then they move down a <strong>twisting </strong>slide into a space filled with little white balls where their trip to a happier place starts.</p><div class="contentImage"><img afp="" alt="Visitors, wearing stuffed costumes, fight in the " arena="" at="" by="" central="" damir="" hahahouse="" in="" january="" laughter="" museum="" of="" on="" sencar="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/8ec18af2-fbb0-4f45-9234-d991c991aaa3_w268_r1.jpg" sumo="" the="" zagreb=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Visitors, wearing stuffed costumes, fight in the "sumo arena" at the HaHaHouse museum of laughter in central Zagreb, on January 21, 2025. (Photo by Damir SENCAR / AFP)</span></div>
<p>Forty-three-year-old Andrea Golubic is the museum's creator. Golubic said she got the idea during the COVID-19 pandemic. At that time, many people were feeling down, depressed and alone: "I realized that I had a mission -- to heal people with laughter."</p>
<p>The idea "came straight from the heart", Golubic told the French News Agency (AFP). She had ideas for many of the museum elements in one day: “that's how the HaHaHouse began."</p>
<p>Golubic said a picture of her when she was seven-year-old <strong>inspired</strong> her. “I was constantly joking as a kid," she added.</p>
<p>Visitors press a button to be "disinfected from negativity" as soon as they step inside the museum, which has eight<strong> interactive</strong> zones, or areas.</p>
<p>One has rubber chickens singing cheerfully. They sing songs like ABBA's "Dancing Queen." There is a <strong>karaoke</strong> room with distorted voices and a "Sumo Arena" for wrestling in puffed up clothes.</p>
<p>There is also some serious history of humor from ancient to modern times told through theatre, film or the internet.</p>
<p>The museum also explains different kinds of humor. These include word play, <strong>slapstick</strong>, dark humor and <strong>satire</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Inner child </strong></p>
<p>Golubic said the HaHaHouse is popular with everyone from small children to older people. Adults say it is a good excuse to act like a child.</p>
<p>"All those who still feel a bit of childish joy and <strong>embrace</strong> their inner child, will <strong>recharge</strong> themselves," she said.</p>
<p>Retiree Bruno Dadic told AFP he was pleased by his visit "as there is never enough humor in life.</p>
<p>"Laughter is a medicine for the soul," he said.</p>
<p>Aleksandar Suka celebrated his fifth birthday with a visit. Visiting with his mother, the little boy said he liked lying on the "Bed of Nails" since they<strong> tickled</strong> him.</p>
<p>Singer Zorica Bucic, from the coastal town of Split, said the museum was just right for our times.</p>
<p>"Entering here is like entering childhood, being relieved of all problems,” she said. Bucic added that if you could come to museum often, you would not need to visit a <strong>psychologist</strong>.</p>
<p>Psychologist Petar Kraljevic told AFP that laughter is a kind of weapon which gives people strength to face their problems. He said that if doctors could advise their patients to have "three hours of laughter” a day, people would feel much better.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Lajla Veselica reported this story for Agence-France Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>museum</strong><em> –n.</em> a building that holds many exhibits showing things related to a subject such as history, art or any other subject people are interested in</p>
<p><strong>negativity</strong> <em>– n.</em> an attitude in which someone considers only the bad qualities of someone or something</p>
<p><strong>twist</strong> <em>– v.</em> to curve or change direction suddenly</p>
<p><strong>inspire</strong> <em>– v.</em> to make (someone) want to do something; to give (someone) an idea about what to do or create</p>
<p><strong>interactive</strong> –<em> adj.</em> designed to respond to the actions or commands of a user</p>
<p><strong>karaoke</strong><em> –n.</em> a pastime in which people sing along with music of popular songs</p>
<p><strong>slapstick</strong> <em>– n.</em> comedy that involves physical action (such as falling down or hitting people</p>
<p><strong>satire </strong><em>– n.</em> a way of using humor to show that someone or something is foolish, weak, or bad; humor that shows the weaknesses or bad qualities of a person, government, society, etc.</p>
<p><strong>embrace</strong> –<em> v.</em> to accept (something or someone) readily or gladly</p>
<p><strong>recharge</strong> <em>– v. </em>to rest and relax in order to regain your energy and strength</p>
<p><strong>tickle</strong> <em>– v.</em> to make (someone) laugh by lightly touching a very sensitive part of the body with fingers, a feather, or the like</p>
<p><strong>psychologist</strong> <em>–n.</em> a health specialist who is not usually a doctor but aims to treat people with mental or behavioral problems</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Nepal Increases Cost of Permits to Climb Everest  (2025/2/14)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/nepal-increases-cost-of-permits-to-climb-everest.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">13 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>The government of Nepal has increased the cost of a permit to climb Mount Everest by about one-third. Officials say the price increase aims to help reduce pollution and increase safety on the world's highest mountain.</p>
<p>The director of Nepal's tourism department is Narayan Prasad Regmi. He told the French news agency AFP the cost for a permit in the popular spring climbing season will increase from $11,000 to $15,000. Regmi noted the price had remained the same for about 10 years, so the government decided it was time to make a change.</p>
<p>The costs, or fees, for climbing during less popular and more difficult times of year -- such as during winter or the summer monsoon rains -- have also increased. This includes an increase from $5,500 to $7,500 during the autumn climbing season.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A golden glow is cast as the sun sets on the worlds highest mountain, center, seen from Kalapathar, on the trail to Everest, Nepal, Tuesday Nov. 15, 1983. (AP Photo/Bikas Das)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/47e066c0-fc14-42d0-a826-ac1cd036b2a0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A golden glow is cast as the sun sets on the worlds highest mountain, center, seen from Kalapathar, on the trail to Everest, Nepal, Tuesday Nov. 15, 1983. (AP Photo/Bikas Das)</span></div>
<p>Thousands of climbers come to Nepal each year. The country is home to eight of 14 of the world's tallest mountains over 8,000 meters. Everest is 8,849-meters tall and sits on the border between Nepal and China.</p>
<p>Foreign climbers spend tens of thousands of dollars on their efforts to climb Everest. More than 400 people bought climbing permits for Everest last year. This brought in around $4 million to the government.</p>
<p>Nepal uses the money to remove waste from the mountain and to finance search and rescue operations.</p>
<p>Some mountain climbing companies worry the higher price could lower the number of climbers wanting to climb Everest from the Nepalese side. The companies warn that some climbers might decide to climb Everest through China.</p>
<p>"Some climbers might <strong>shift</strong> to Tibet where the <strong>facilities</strong> are much better," said Mingma G Sherpa. He runs the Imagine Nepal mountaineering company and says Nepal must use the money to improve conditions.</p>
<p>"Our government just increases the <strong>royalty</strong>, but doesn't do much. It needs to also provide support to the climbers and guides," he added.</p>
<p>Some groups have criticized Nepal for permitting too many climbers on Everest while not doing enough to keep the mountain clean.</p>
<p>Last year, Nepal's government ordered all Everest climbers to carry <strong>trackers</strong> and bags to remove their human waste. The government approved the fee increase in January, but it was first published on February 3.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith adapted this story for VOA Learning English based on reporting from Agence France-Presse. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>shift</strong> <em>– v. </em>to change to something different</p>
<p><strong>facilities </strong><em>– n. (plural) </em>buildings or other structures that provide basic services such as shelter, water, and electricity</p>
<p><strong>royalty </strong><em>– n. </em>payments made for the use of something</p>
<p><strong>tracker </strong><em>– n. </em>a small device on a person or object that lets others know their exact location and movements</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Important Terms and Ideas for Describing Artificial Intelligence  (2025/2/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/important-terms-and-ideas-involved-in-describing-artificial-intelligence.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>There are several terms experts use to describe computer systems in the field of artificial intelligence.</p>
<p>Recently, the French News Agency (AFP) defined some of the common terms and ideas used in that field.</p>
<p>Here is a version for English learners:</p><div class="contentImage"><img act="" ai="" alt="FILE - A copy of " artificial="" at="" big="" britain="" data="" display="" during="" european="" expo="" february="" in="" infantes="" intelligence="" isabel="" london="" olympia="" on="" reuters="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/aeda1905-020d-4606-b3e9-ae4b0ccd1d81_w268_r1.jpg" the="" union=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A copy of "The European Union Artificial Intelligence (AI) Act" on display during the AI &amp; Big Data Expo 2025 at the Olympia, in London, Britain, February 5, 2025. REUTERS/Isabel Infantes</span></div>
<p><strong>Artificial intelligence </strong></p>
<p>The first term is “artificial intelligence.”</p>
<p>When asked what artificial intelligence is, the AI-powered ChatGPT system says that the term means “the<strong> simulation</strong> of human intelligence in machines that are programmed to think, learn and make decisions".</p>
<p>AI's main quality or characteristic is taking in large amounts of data and then processing it using methods from <strong>statistics</strong>.</p>
<p>AI involves using ideas from many fields including computing, mathematics, languages, psychology, and others.</p>
<p>Currently, the technology is being used heavily for investigating health issues, translating human languages, and predicting problems in machine tools and self-driving cars. But AI is affecting many fields of business and industry.</p>
<p><strong>Algorithm </strong></p>
<p>A second important term is “algorithm.”</p>
<p>An algorithm is important to all computer operations. It is a series of steps or instructions followed by a computer program to get a result.</p>
<p>Algorithms can give rules for an AI's behavior, helping it to realize the objectives of computer program developers.</p>
<p>Unlike a simple computer program, AI algorithms permit a computer system to “learn” for itself.</p>
<p><strong>Machine learning </strong></p>
<p>A third important term is “machine learning.”</p>
<p>Machine learning is one method that researchers have used in their efforts to produce artificial intelligence.</p>
<p>Machine learning lets computers learn from data without being directly programmed on what results to produce.</p>
<p>In recent years, the field of <strong>neural</strong> networks has given important results.</p>
<p>In a neural network, connections between some <strong>nodes </strong>are strengthened and others weakened as the system learns and makes changes.</p>
<p>Learning can be "supervised." This means the system learns to put new data into specific groups based on a model. For example, the system could learn to identify <strong>spam</strong> in an email or other messaging programs.</p>
<p>"Unsupervised" learning permits the system to independently discover new areas or ways of doing things. These discoveries in the available data might not have been immediately clear.</p>
<p>An example would be letting an online store identify buying<strong> trends </strong>in sales data.</p>
<p>"Reinforcement" learning adds a process of repeated trial-and-error. In this process, the system is rewarded based on its outcomes, causing it to learn and improve.</p>
<p>One example might be a self-driving vehicle whose objective is to reach its destination as quickly as possible but also safely. That requirement would lead it to learn to stop at red lights although it requires additional time.</p>
<p><strong>Deep learning </strong></p>
<p>Deep learning owes its name to its use of many layers of neural networks.</p>
<p>Raw data is examined by each layer in turn at growing levels of <strong>abstraction</strong>.</p>
<p>Geoffrey Hinton received the 2024 Nobel Prize in Physics. Hinton is credited with developing deep learning. Hinton received the prize along with 1980s neural-network developer John Hopfield.</p>
<p>Francis Bach, head of France's SIERRA statistical learning laboratory, said this about deep learning: "The more layers you have, the more complex behavior can become, and the more complex the behavior can be, the easier it is to learn a desired behavior <strong>efficiently</strong>."</p>
<p>The method might help lead to scientific discoveries.</p>
<p><strong>Language models </strong></p>
<p>We now turn to large language models (LLMs).</p>
<p>These might be the most popular example of generative AI. Large language models power tools like OpenAI's ChatGPT or Google's Gemini.</p>
<p>Such systems are able to write long papers, answer legal questions or even produce a cake recipe based on their statistical models.</p>
<p>But the technology is still new. LLM's can suffer from "hallucinations"- the creation of content that is false or incorrect.</p>
<p><strong>Artificial general intelligence </strong></p>
<p>A final important term is artificial general intelligence (AGI) - one the big goals of the whole AI field.</p>
<p>AGI suggests the unrealized dream of a machine able to reproduce all human processes of human thinking.</p>
<p>People who push the idea include OpenAI chief Sam Altman and his competitors at Anthropic. They consider such a system to be within reach.</p>
<p>The goal is to use large amounts of data and processing power to train LLMs that are increasingly powerful.</p>
<p>But critics say that LLM technology has important limits, including its ability to reason.</p>
<p>Maxime Amblard, computing professor at France's University of Lorraine, told AFP last year, "LLMs do not work like human beings."</p>
<p>Amblard added that humans, as flesh-and-blood -intelligent beings, are "sense-making machines" with different abilities from today's computer systems.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo. And I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Pierre Celerier reported on this story for Agence France-Presse. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>simulation</strong> <em>– n. </em>the representation of the functioning of one system or process by means of the functioning of another system</p>
<p><strong>statistics</strong> <em>–n. pl. (science)</em> the field of processing numerical information to describe processes and things</p>
<p><strong>neural </strong><em>–adj.</em> related to the brain or nerves</p>
<p><strong>node </strong><em>– n. </em>a point at which smaller parts begin or center</p>
<p><strong>spam<em> </em></strong><em>– n.</em> unsolicited messages (such as an email) that often have a commercial purpose</p>
<p><strong>trend </strong><em>– n.</em> a line or direction of movement or change</p>
<p><strong>abstraction </strong>–<em>n.</em> the formation of ideas</p>
<p><strong>efficiently </strong><em>– adv.</em> with success, competence, or a suitable effect</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Cambodia Warns of ‘Aggressive’ Monkeys around Angkor Wat  (2025/2/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/cambodia-warns-of-aggressive-monkeys-around-angkor-wat.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Cambodian officials are warning visitors to the nation's famous Angkor Wat complex of buildings to stay away from wild m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s. They say the animals have become aggressive and destructive.</p>
<p>The officials blamed the behavior of the macaque m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s on visitors to the area who feed the animals or interact with them.</p>
<p>Social media influencers – many of them on YouTube – use video of the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s to grow their online followings, the officials added.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="YouTuber Phut Phu takes videos of m&lt;I&gt;&lt;I&gt;onkey&lt;/I&gt;&lt;/I&gt;s near the Bayon temple of an Angkor Wat temple complex in Siem Reap province, Cambodia, Tuesday, April 2, 2024. (AP Photo/Heng Sinith)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/7e6de401-8042-465a-92c3-df1fce4c62c7_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">YouTuber Phut Phu takes videos of m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s near the Bayon temple of an Angkor Wat temple complex in Siem Reap province, Cambodia, Tuesday, April 2, 2024. (AP Photo/Heng Sinith)</span></div>
<p>The macaques are native to forest areas surrounding Angkor Wat, a UNESCO World Heritage Site in northwestern Cambodia. The m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s have become more destructive of property around the popular <strong>tourist</strong> area.</p>
<p>Officials watching the animals told the French News Agency, AFP, that too much human interaction – especially by people filming material to publish online – had changed the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s' behavior.</p>
<p>The agency that operates Angkor Wat is the APSARA National Authority. It said in a statement that a small number of YouTubers repeatedly feed the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s to create videos. This "changed the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s' natural behavior from being wild animals to <strong>domestic</strong> ones that are aggressive, steal food, and cause injuries among people."</p>
<p>Agency spokesman Long Kosal told AFP that officials also worry about the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s causing damage to stonework that dates back centuries. "On top of biting visitors, they have been climbing up and pushing stones down, damaging temples," he said. Some macaques had also damaged information signs.</p>
<p>Local officials have urged tourists to leave the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s alone while visiting Angkor Wat. They added that they are currently looking for "an <strong>appropriate</strong> solution" to solve the problem.</p>
<p>Angkor Wat was the capital of the Khmer Empire. Building work began on the complex about 900 years ago. It remains Cambodia's top tourist site and earns a lot of money for the developing nation. More than one million foreign tourists visited the area last year.</p>
<p>Since becoming a world heritage site in 1992, Angkor Wat and the surrounding forest have received increased legal protection and security.</p>
<p>Officials have expressed hope that wildlife sightings around Angkor Wat will increase visitor interest and support <strong>conservation</strong> education efforts.</p>
<p>Last year, Cambodian officials announced a plan to carry out a <strong>census</strong> of m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s in public areas to identify and take away those presenting a danger to humans.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Agence France-Presse reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong>________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>tourist </strong><em>– n. </em>someone who visits a place for pleasure and does not live there</p>
<p><strong>domestic</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj.</em> inside one country and not international</p>
<p><strong>appropriate </strong><em>– adj. </em>suitable or right for a particular situation</p>
<p><strong>conservation </strong><em>– n. </em>an organized effort that aims to protect animals and natural resources</p>
<p><strong>census</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n. </em>an effort to officially count the number of people living in a certain area</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>George Washington – the First President  (2025/2/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/george-washington-first-president.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>George Washington was the first president of the United States. He served from 1789 to 1797. He was a famous general who led the American colonists to freedom from British rule and he <strong>presided</strong> over the convention that created the U.S. Constitution.</p>
<p>He wanted to retire from public service and return home. But the country's founders wanted him to move to New York and serve as the American president. Washington accepted the job as his duty.</p>
<p>Washington was sworn in as president in 1789. He had to invent the job of being president for all future presidents. He established a group of advisors — called the cabinet—as well as the nation's official money. He appointed a six-member Supreme Court. And he created the Department of Foreign Affairs, now called the State Department. He hoped to act in such a way that future presidents could continue to build on what he began.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Martha and George Washington with their grandchildren. Courtesy George Washington's Mount Vernon." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/900EEF71-D49B-418C-A213-4BA10138FAF7_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Martha and George Washington with their grandchildren. Courtesy George Washington's Mount Vernon.</span></div>
<p>From the beginning, George Washington was careful to establish a good working relationship with Congress. By his actions, he confirmed the separation of powers of the three <strong>branches</strong> of the government, as described in the Constitution.</p>
<p>Historian Joseph Ellis says one of the best things about George Washington was his ability to give up power. At the end of the Revolutionary War, General Washington returned his sword. And at the end of his second term, President Washington simply returned home.</p>
<p>Like many plantation owners, Washington was a slave holder. By the end of his life, Washington opposed slavery. He left a <strong>will</strong> ordering his survivors to free his slaves after his wife's death.</p>
<p>Three years after he finished his second term as president, Washington fell ill. On December 14, 1799, he died in his bed, surrounded by his wife, enslaved maids, and friends. He was 67.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Kelly Jean Kelly and Steve Ember reported this story for VOA Learning English. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>preside</strong><strong> </strong>– <em>v</em>. to formally oversee a meeting or office</p>
<p><strong>branch</strong> <em>–n.</em> a major part of a government with powers and responsibilities that are different from other parts</p>
<p><strong>will </strong>– <em>n</em>. a legal document in which a person states who should receive his or her possessions after he or she dies</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>American Inventions: The Television  (2025/2/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/american-inventions-the-television.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Television has made it possible for people around the world to share in many different experiences – sports, music shows, films, and more.</p>
<p>Yet many people would find it difficult to name the inventor of the television. They might also be surprised to learn that the inventor came up with the idea when he was just fourteen years old.</p>
<p>Today, we explore the life of one of the great inventors of 20th century America: Philo Taylor Farnsworth.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A shopper passes by a line of large-screen televisions on display in a Costco warehouse, Feb. 3, 2025, in east Denver. Flat screen TVs are the ancestor of the first televisions developed by Farnsworth. (AP Photo/David Zalubowski)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a44ea134-5f72-4b71-817c-2849a43d01cc_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A shopper passes by a line of large-screen televisions on display in a Costco warehouse, Feb. 3, 2025, in east Denver. Flat screen TVs are the ancestor of the first televisions developed by Farnsworth. (AP Photo/David Zalubowski)</span></div>
<p><strong>A young boy </strong></p>
<p>Philo Farnsworth was born in August 1906, near Indian Creek in the western state of Utah. The house he lived in for the first few years of his life had no electricity. But Philo read about electricity and quickly began to experiment with it.</p>
<p>One night, Philo read a magazine story about the idea of sending pictures and sound through the air. The story said some of the world's best scientists were working on the idea. It said these scientists were using special machines to try to make a kind of device to send pictures.</p>
<p>Fourteen-year-old Philo decided these famous scientists were wrong. He decided that mechanical devices would never work.</p>
<p>Philo believed such a device would have to be electronic. Philo knew electrons could be made to move very fast. All he would have to do was find a way to make electrons do the work.</p>
<p>Soon, Philo had an idea for such a receiver. It would trap light in a container and send the light on a line of electrons. Philo called it “light in a bottle.”</p>
<p>Several days later, Philo told his teacher about a device that could capture pictures. He drew a plan for it and gave it to his teacher.</p>
<p>Philo's drawing seemed very simple. But it still clearly showed the information needed to build a television.</p>
<p>Philo's teacher was Justin Tolman. Many years later, Philo would credit Mr. Tolman with guiding his imagination and helping him open the doors of science.</p>
<p><strong>Inventor </strong></p>
<p>In September 1927, Philo turned on a device that was the first working television receiver. In another room was the first television camera. Philo had invented the special camera tube earlier that year.</p>
<p>While the image produced on the receiver was not very clear, the device worked. Within a few months, Philo had found several people who wanted to invest money in his invention.</p>
<p>In August 1930, the United States government gave Philo patent documents. These documents aimed to protect his invention from being copied by others.</p>
<p>Still, he became involved in legal disputes with a powerful company at the time known as RCA. Philo won the disputes but faced many business and financial difficulties in his life.</p>
<p>He developed more than 100 devices that helped make modern television possible. He also developed early radar, invented the first electronic microscope, and worked on developing peaceful uses of atomic energy.</p>
<p>Philo Farnsworth died in March of 1971. He is considered one of the most important inventors of the 20th century.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Paul Thompson wrote this story for VOA Learning English. John Russell adapted it. </em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What Is the healthiest way to prepare vegetables?  (2025/2/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/what-is-the-healthiest-way-to-prepare-vegetables.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Carlene Thomas is a dietitian, a person who gives advice about healthy foods to eat.</p>
<p>When it comes to eating healthy vegetables, Thomas says there are two kinds of people who ask her for advice.</p>
<p>The first kind wants to know how different cooking methods affect the nutrition in vegetables. The other kind of person wants to know how to eat more vegetables. Thomas' simple answer to both groups is this: The best vegetables are the ones you actually want to eat.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this April 24, 2014 file photo, a variety of healthy fruits and vegetables are displayed for sale at a market in Washington. (AP Photo/J. Scott Applewhite, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/3cfac617-78de-4660-9dc6-f89b4e910992_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this April 24, 2014 file photo, a variety of healthy fruits and vegetables are displayed for sale at a market in Washington. (AP Photo/J. Scott Applewhite, File)</span></div>
<p>Thomas told the Associated Press that many people buy vegetables that they <em>think </em>they will eat. Maybe the <strong>produce</strong> is popular or someone is bringing attention to it on social media. But then they end up not using it. That means the vegetable gets thrown away after it goes bad.</p>
<p>In that case, Thomas said, “It doesn't matter how you cook them, because if they're going in the trash, they're not in your body.”</p>
<p>However, Thomas said research shows cooking methods do affect nutrition. But it is not as simple as comparing raw, or uncooked, vegetables to cooked ones. Cooking methods can include steaming, <strong>roasting</strong>, boiling, or <strong>sauteing</strong>.</p>
<p>So, are raw vegetables healthier than cooked? Not always.</p>
<p>When vegetables are cooked with high heat for a long period of time many nutrients break down. However, cooking softens the cell walls in vegetables, making them easier for the body to <strong>digest</strong>.</p>
<p>Cooking changes the structure of vegetables which increases what dietitians call bioavailability. This is the body's ability to use the nutrients in vegetables, Thomas said.</p>
<p>Cooked food is often more nutritious than raw food. For example, cooked tomatoes release more of the <strong>antioxidant</strong> lycopene than raw tomatoes, she said. Lycopene is believed to have qualities that prevent cancer.</p>
<p>Also, cooked carrots have more beta-carotene that can be <strong>absorbed</strong> by the body. Roasting pumpkins, carrots and sweet potatoes increases available carotenoids. These antioxidants are thought to prevent <strong>inflammation</strong> in the body.</p>
<p><strong>Which cooking methods are the healthiest?</strong></p>
<p>However, the shorter the cooking time, the more nutrients are kept in the food. That advice comes from Amber Pankonin, a dietitian in the U.S. state of Nebraska.</p>
<p>Cooking over boiling water, or steaming, and in a microwave are considered the most nutritious methods. These two methods use little time and require no fat.</p>
<p>Another healthy method is <strong>blanching</strong>. This is when you boil vegetables in water for a minute or two. But not too long. Boiling vegetables runs the risk of losing <strong>water-soluble</strong> nutrients including vitamin C, B1 and folate.</p>
<p>Thomas explained the reason boiling is not good for vegetables: The nutrients are "... <strong>leaching </strong>into the water, and you're <strong>tossing out</strong> the water.”</p>
<p>However, you could save the water from boiled vegetables and use it for other purposes, such as soups, or just drink it.</p>
<p><strong>What about taste?</strong></p>
<p>Dietitians say there is no problem using a small amount of fat. Besides making vegetables taste better, a little cooking oil helps the body to absorb fat-soluble vitamins, said Pankonin.</p>
<p>That means more vitamin A from squash, carrots, and sweet potatoes; more vitamin D from mushrooms; more vitamin E from bell peppers, leafy greens and asparagus; and more vitamin K from greens, broccoli and onions.</p>
<p>For <strong>pan</strong> frying or sauteing, Pankonin suggests cooking with enough oil so the vegetables do not stick to the pan. The amount of oil will depend on the quantity of vegetables and the size of the pan.</p>
<p>For roasting, you will likely need more oil. Despite the longer cooking time, roasting will still keep some nutrients and will increase the <strong>flavor</strong> with the heating of natural sugars.</p>
<p>“Flavor is king,” Pankonin said. “I would much rather see people roasting their vegetables and enjoying them.”</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Albert Stumm reported this story for The Associated Press from New York City. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>produce </strong><em>–n.</em> fresh fruits and vegetables</p>
<p><strong>roast </strong><em>–v.</em> to cook with dry heat in an oven</p>
<p><strong>sauté </strong><em>–v.</em> to cook using fat in a flat pan on a stovetop</p>
<p><strong>digest </strong><em>–v. </em>to biologically change food in the digestive system to forms that can be directly used by organs and tissue in the body</p>
<p><strong>antioxidant</strong> <em>–n.</em> a substance that prevents oxygen from chemically changing food</p>
<p><strong>absorb </strong><em>–v.</em> to take into and biologically use in the body</p>
<p><strong>inflammation</strong> <em>–n.</em> swelling and reddening of tissue in the body</p>
<p><strong>blanch </strong><em>–v.</em> to cook something in hot water for a brief time</p>
<p><strong>water-soluble</strong> –<em>adj.</em> able to dissolve in water</p>
<p><strong>leach </strong><em>–v. </em>to remove a substance from a material by having it dissolve in water</p>
<p><strong>toss out </strong><em>–v. (phrasal)</em> to throw away</p>
<p><strong>pan </strong><em>–n.</em> a relatively flat metal cooking tool usually used for frying</p>
<p><strong>flavor</strong> <em>–n.</em> the taste of something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Teachers Use Games for More Enjoyable Learning  (2025/2/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/teachers-use-games-for-more-enjoyable-learning.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/6425558.html">Wordle</a> has become one of the most popular online games in the United States since it came out last October.</p>
<p>Players get six chances to <strong>guess</strong> and learn a five-letter word for the day. Many are sharing their game results on social media, adding more interest in the game.</p>
<p><strong>Gamifying the classroom</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Teachers Use Games for More Enjoyable Learning" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/02280000-0aff-0242-d93c-08da010b9608_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Teachers Use Games for More Enjoyable Learning</span></div>
<p>Creative teachers have long found games could make their classes more enjoyable for students. During the pandemic, many have looked for new ways or games to help their students learn. It is part of a learning theory called “<strong>gamification</strong>” to keep students' interest.</p>
<p>Beyond Wordle, here are other games that help learners with different subjects.</p>
<p><strong>Mathematics</strong></p>
<p>British data scientist Richard Mann of London was talking with his daughter about the popularity of Wordle. He thought there should be a game for people who like mathematics and developed <a class="wsw__a" href="https://nerdlegame.com/">Nerdle</a>. It is a daily game in which a player has six tries to guess a math solution.</p>
<p>Does it sound familiar? Math teachers note that a Nerdle player uses logic, a careful way of thinking about something, to solve a math problem. It is similar to how a Wordle player applies logic to guess a word.</p>
<p><strong>Geography</strong></p>
<p>Do not <strong>confuse</strong> Wordle with <a class="wsw__a" href="https://worldle.teuteuf.fr/">Worldle</a>. There is an extra letter ‘l” in Worldle. French video game developer Antoine Teuf said he invented Worldle in honor of that word game, Wordle.</p>
<p>Players guess a country based on its shape. They get six tries to guess a country based on information about the country. Teuf first shared the game on January 22. He said there are two million visits a day to the game's page a month later.</p>
<p><strong>Other games, online services</strong></p>
<p>Teachers of English see word games as a way for students to learn new words. Other word games include Blooket and Flippity.</p>
<p>Teachers create quizzes in <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.blooket.com/">Blooket</a> similar to the kinds of games students play on mobile devices. They can look at results and see areas that students can improve.</p>
<p>In <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.flippity.net/">Flippity</a>, teachers can create flash cards, <strong>rewards</strong>, spelling <strong>quizzes</strong>, memory games and word searches from a simple Google <strong>spreadsheet. </strong>It is also a good tool for students to create their own projects.</p>
<p>There are several online services that teachers could use to “gamify” learning. They include <a class="wsw__a" href="https://kahoot.com/">Kahoot!,</a> <a class="wsw__a" href="https://quizlet.com/">Quizlet</a>, <u><a class="wsw__a" href="https://quizizz.com/">Quizziz</a></u> and <a class="wsw__a" href="https://nearpod.com/">Nearpod</a>. All of them “gamify” learning by creating competition among learners while reviewing the content presented by teachers.</p>
<p><strong>Teaching without a computer?</strong></p>
<p>In many places, teachers and students do not have a computer. So, English language teacher Larry Ferlazzo asked them to share their language-learning games. Ferlazzo wrote about them in his <a class="wsw__a" href="https://larryferlazzo.edublogs.org/2011/06/05/the-best-language-learning-games-that-are-not-online/">blog</a>. Here are two of the games that teachers suggested:</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" href="https://kelaskubermain.blogspot.com/">Danielle Horne</a> teaches at Helena College in Glen Forrest, Western Australia. She said one of the games that her students love playing is “hot or cold.”</p>
<p>In “hot or cold,” students hide something in the classroom while a student, or searcher, is waiting outside. The students then say a word, phrase, or sentence. They get louder when the searcher gets nearer to the object and softer when the searcher is more distant. Horne said to be prepared for quite a bit of noise though!</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.111variation.dk/">Eva Pors</a> is a Danish high school teacher. Her students play “questions and answers” to learn new words or vocabulary.</p>
<p>Pors write words or phrases on small pieces of paper and divides students into groups of four. Within a group, student A picks a piece of paper with a word or phrase on it and asks questions that will make student B say the exact word or phrase on the paper.</p>
<p>For example, with the word “milk,” Student A would ask, “What do you put on your <strong>cereal</strong> in the morning?” Student B has one minute to try to answer as many words or phrases as possible. The other two students in the group will then take over for one minute. And the team with the most correct guesses wins the game.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jill Robbins wrote this lesson for Learning English.</em></p>
<p><em>_________________________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>guess</strong> – <em>v. </em>to give an answer or opinion about something without having all the facts</p>
<p><strong>gamification</strong>– <em>n.</em> the practice of making activities more like games in order to make them more interesting or enjoyable:</p>
<p><strong>confuse</strong> – <em>v.</em>to mix up someone's mind or ideas, or to make something difficult to understand</p>
<p><strong>reward</strong> – <em>n. </em>something given in exchange for good behavior or good work</p>
<p><strong>quiz</strong> – <em>n. </em>a game or competition in which you answer questions</p>
<p><strong>spreadsheet</strong> – <em>n</em>. a computer program that helps make calculations and store information</p>
<p><strong>cereal</strong> – <em>n. </em>a food that is made from grain and eaten with milk, especially in the morning</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>The Paradox Museum Miami Aims to Trick the Eye  (2025/2/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/the-paradox-museum-miami-aims-to-trick-the-eye.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p><a class="wsw__a" href="https://paradoxmuseummiami.com/" target="_blank">Paradox Museum Miami</a> is a mixture of art, science, and fun.</p>
<p>The 1,000-square-meter <strong>museum</strong> is housed in Miami's Wynwood arts and <strong>entertainment</strong> area. It has more than 70 public displays known as exhibits. Executive director Samantha Impellizeri says these exhibits <strong>challenge</strong> the imagination.</p>
<p>She added that visitors can walk away from the experience with some really fun and interesting material for social media.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A group of friends pose for a picture that will be rotated upside down to create an optical illusion, at Paradox Museum Miami, Tuesday, Jan. 28, 2025, in Miami. (AP Photo/Rebecca Blackwell)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/6089c788-f5f8-452a-8e5b-dc984ca18a7e_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A group of friends pose for a picture that will be rotated upside down to create an optical illusion, at Paradox Museum Miami, Tuesday, Jan. 28, 2025, in Miami. (AP Photo/Rebecca Blackwell)</span></div>
<p>Paradox Museum has more than ten <strong>locations</strong> throughout North America, Europe and Asia. The Miami location, which opened in 2022, was the first in North America.</p>
<p>The term paradox is central to the museum and what visitors experience. A paradox is a situation or thing that has seemingly opposite or contradictory qualities.</p>
<p>“Each paradox is uniquely tied to its community,” Impellizeri said. “So as you walk throughout the experience, you'll notice different <strong>themes</strong> and art <strong>installations </strong>that directly reflect not only Miami but the Wynwood community specifically."</p>
<p>Many of the displays at Paradox Museum suggest old carnival funhouses – buildings that had devices and rooms designed to surprise or amaze visitors.</p>
<p>Examples include the mirror maze, the spinning tunnel, and the upside-down room. The difference is that Paradox Museum explains the math and science behind each<strong> illusion</strong>.</p>
<p>“We're a top field trip destination for <strong>pre-K</strong> all the way up through college students,” Impellizeri said. She added that the museum has a large number of educational activities that students can do before, during, and after the visit.</p>
<p>Like any museum, Paradox Museum plans to change its exhibits to keep visitors coming back.</p>
<p>“We're not going to be the same space in a year to three years from now," Impellizeri said.</p>
<p>Paradox Museum Miami introduced a new Zero Gravity Room last fall. Visitors can turn their smart phone cameras on and attach their phones to a spinning holder. Then they step into a large, slowly moving room designed to look like the inside of a space station. The resulting video makes it look as though they are walking up the wall and ceiling inside a room unaffected by gravity.</p>
<p>Paradox Museum is part of a movement towards so-called “<strong>immersive</strong> art experiences.” These kinds of art experiences often use technology to make the visitors feel like they are taking part in art rather than just looking at it.</p>
<p>“Immersive experiences around the world are increasing in popularity,” Impellizeri noted.</p>
<p>Immersive art experiences have opened all over the world during the past 10 years or so. Examples include a company called <a class="wsw__a" href="https://meowwolf.com/" target="_blank">Meow Wolf</a> with several locations in the western United States, as well as a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://vangoghexpo.com/" target="_blank">Van Gogh exhibit</a> that has been traveling through North America, Europe and Asia since 2017. Superblue Miami, which opened in 2021, is another example.</p>
<p>Visitors generally take 60 to 90 minutes to make their way through Paradox Museum. Tickets normally cost $26 for adults and teenagers and $20 for children.</p>
<p>Seventeen-year-old Facundo Ildarraz and his family came to Miami from Argentina. Ildarraz said his mother found Paradox Museum online. He said it turned out to be a great chance to take fun photos with his family.</p>
<p>“I've been laughing since I went inside,” Ildarraz said. “It's really amazing.”</p>
<p>Dennis Speigel is head of a business advisory company called <a class="wsw__a" href="http://www.interthemepark.com/" target="_blank">International Theme Park Services, Inc.</a> Speigel said immersive experiences are a natural progression of location-based entertainment. Location-based entertainment includes go-cart tracks, laser tag, paint ball, indoor skydiving, escape rooms and trampoline parks. These are activities that take visitors a few hours to go through.</p>
<p>“It's a lot of little things that we've had in the industry for years, heightened by our new technology...to make the experience new and something people haven't seen,” Speigel said.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>David Fischer reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>museum </strong><em>– n.</em> a place where objects are shown or exhibited</p>
<p><strong>entertainment</strong> <em>–n. </em>watching performances and doing public activities for fun</p>
<p><strong>challenge</strong> <em>– v. </em>to interest or stimulate by presenting difficulties; to invite for a competition</p>
<p><strong>location</strong> <em>–n.</em> the place where a business is</p>
<p><strong>theme</strong> <em>– n.</em> subject of artistic representation</p>
<p><strong>installation</strong><em> – n.</em> a work of art that usually has several components and is often in mixed media</p>
<p><strong>illusion</strong><em> – n.</em> something that tricks or deceives</p>
<p><strong>pre-K (pre-kindergarten)</strong> <em>–n.</em> school for very young children</p>
<p><strong>immersive</strong> <em>– adj.</em> characterized by immersion or deep involvement in something (such as an activity or artificial environment)</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers: Oldest Evidence of Lead Pollution Found in Greece  (2025/2/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/researchers-oldest-evidence-of-lead-pollution-found-in-greece.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Ancient Greece produced the earliest records of democracy - and, scientists now say, lead pollution.</p>
<p>That is the finding of a study that recently appeared in <em>Communications Earth and Environment</em>. The researchers studied <strong>sediment cores</strong> removed from mainland Greece and below the Aegean Sea. They found in the cores the oldest known evidence of lead pollution in the environment dating back around 5,200 years.</p>
<p>That is 1,200 years older than the former oldest evidence of lead pollution. That evidence was discovered in Serbia.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A woman poses for a photo in front Caryatid statues that prop up the porch of the 5th century B.C. Erechtheion temple, as at the background is seen smoke from a fire , during a hot day at Acropolis hill, in Athens, Tuesday, July 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Petros Giannakouris)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/b1053b7d-b7ce-43cc-a000-0087f8386d6c_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A woman poses for a photo in front Caryatid statues that prop up the porch of the 5th century B.C. Erechtheion temple, as at the background is seen smoke from a fire , during a hot day at Acropolis hill, in Athens, Tuesday, July 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Petros Giannakouris)</span></div>
<p>In ancient times, lead was released into the atmosphere as a product of copper and silver production. The toxic, or poisonous, metal turned to dust over time and settled onto the soil.</p>
<p>Joseph Maran of Heidelberg University was a co-writer of the new study.</p>
<p>“Silver was used for jewelry, for special objects — but it wasn't found in a pure state,” it was mined in ore combined with lead, Maran said</p>
<p>The place with the earliest signs of lead is in northeastern Greece, near the island of Thasos. Past evidence suggests Thasos was one of the area's most important places for silver mining and metalwork, said Maran.</p>
<p>Yale historian Joseph Manning, who was not involved in the study, said “Lead released from<strong> smelting</strong> is the world's first form of toxic or industrial pollution.”</p>
<p>The researchers found that levels of lead contamination remained fairly low in ancient Greece. The levels remained low throughout the Bronze Age, the Classical period and the Hellenistic period. The Classical period is famous for Athenian democracy, and the thinkers Socrates and Plato. And the Hellenistic period saw Greek cultural influence reach its height across the Mediterranean.</p>
<p>But the new study shows that around 2,150 years ago “a very strong and<strong> abrupt</strong> increase" in lead releases caused by human activities took place across Greece, said co-writer Andreas Koutsodendris of Heidelberg University.</p>
<p>Around that time, the Roman army won control of the Greek peninsula, completely changing the area's society and economy. As Roman trade, colonies and shipping grew across the Mediterranean Sea and Black Sea, demand for silver coins also grew. As a result, more smelting was required, Koutsodendris said.</p>
<p>Later the Roman Empire used lead to make tools for eating and building, including pipes.</p>
<p>Past research – including a study of ice cores from Greenland – had detected high levels of lead across much of the Northern Hemisphere during Roman times.</p>
<p>But the new study adds a more exact “and local picture to how lead levels changed,” said Nathan Chellman. Chellman, an environmental scientist at the University of Nevada, Reno, was not involved in the research.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Christina Larson reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>_______________________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>sediment core</strong> <em>– n. </em>a sample of circular layers of the Earth's ground that gives information about surface conditions over time</p>
<p><strong>smelt</strong> <em>– v.</em> to melt or fuse a substance to separate the metals</p>
<p><strong>abrupt </strong><em>– adj.</em> sudden and unexpected</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Asteroid Hit Created Two ‘Grand Canyons’ on Moon  (2025/2/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/study-asteroid-hit-created-two-grand-canyons-on-moon.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>A new study suggests an <strong>asteroid </strong>strike on the moon billions of years ago left two huge valleys about the size of Earth's Grand Canyon.</p>
<p>Researchers from the United States and Britain said their research shows the two steep valleys, or canyons, likely formed in less than 10 minutes.</p>
<p>They noted the crash, or impact, happened near the south pole on the far side of the moon. That is the side of the moon which always faces away from Earth. The area is known as the Schr<i></i>246;dinger impact basin.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image provided by NASA shows a view from orbit looking across the surface of the moon, where an ancient asteroid strike carved out a pair of grand canyons on the moon's far side. (Ernie T. Wright/NASA via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f8084c1d-8f6f-4e18-a5b8-4ba6a4b7fad1_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image provided by NASA shows a view from orbit looking across the surface of the moon, where an ancient asteroid strike carved out a pair of grand canyons on the moon's far side. (Ernie T. Wright/NASA via AP)</span></div>
<p>The speed of the incoming object – which the team said might have been a <strong>comet</strong> – was estimated to be around 55,000 kilometers per hour. The strike likely happened about 3.8 billion years ago.</p>
<p>The researchers used data collected by a spacecraft operated by the American space agency NASA. That vehicle, the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/lro/">Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter</a>, has been capturing lunar data since entering orbit around the moon in June 2009.</p>
<p>One main goal of the orbiter's mission was to create a highly detailed, <strong>three-dimensional</strong>, or 3D, map of the moon. The data has been used by NASA to learn more about lunar resources and to plan for future missions. The agency <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/lro/science-and-data/">noted</a> that the Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter had “already collected as much data as all other planetary missions combined.”</p>
<p>The team studying the canyons used the orbiter's map data to <strong>simulate</strong> the path of the incoming object, as well as material that was displaced by the crash. The scientists recently published <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-024-55675-z">a study</a> describing their results in <em>Nature Communications</em>.</p>
<p>The group's simulations suggested the space rock passed over the south pole before hitting. It then created a huge <strong>basin</strong> and launched rocky materials at speeds up to 1 kilometer per second.</p>
<p>The <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_l2RxFLOk">researchers</a> said material was sent flying and struck the lunar surface like missiles. This resulted in the creation of the canyons.</p>
<p>The team said the canyons appear comparable in size to the Grand Canyon, in the U.S. state of Arizona.</p>
<p>The study's lead writer was David Kring of the Lunar and Planetary Institute in Houston. He told the Associated Press that findings suggest the asteroid strike was a “very violent” geologic process.</p>
<p>Kring and his team estimated the asteroid was 25 kilometers across. They estimated that the energy needed to create the two canyons would have been more than 130 times greater than the power of all the world's current nuclear weapons.</p>
<p>Kring said most of the rock and debris was thrown in a direction away from the south pole. That finding is good news for NASA which plans to land astronauts in that area in the future.</p>
<p>Kring noted it should improve the exploration possibilities of future astronauts.</p>
<p>"Because debris from the Schr<i></i>246;dinger impact was <strong>jettisoned</strong> away from the lunar south pole, ancient rocks in the polar region will be at or close to the surface...,” Kring told Reuters news agency. This should make it easier for future American astronauts to collect them.</p>
<p>NASA's future lunar exploration plans are known as the agency's Artemis program. The program aims to return astronauts to the moon for the first time since NASA's Apollo 17 mission in 1972. The agency's current plan is to send astronauts on a trip around the moon next year. That would be followed a year or so later by a landing attempt on the lunar surface.</p>
<p>The researchers said older rocks in the area can help scientists gain a better understanding of the moon's past history. They could also help answer questions about the formation of Earth.</p>
<p>Kring noted it is currently not clear whether the two huge canyons are permanently <strong>shadowed</strong> like some of the craters at the moon's south pole. “That is something that we're clearly going to be reexamining,” he said.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters, The Universities Space Research Association and Nature Communications. </em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>asteroid </strong><em>– n. </em>a rocky object that goes around the sun like a planet</p>
<p><strong>comet</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> an object in space that leaves a bright line behind it in the sky</p>
<p><strong>three-dimensional (3D) </strong><em>–adj.</em> having height, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_I4M0FVMP">width</a> and length</p>
<p><strong>simulate </strong><em>– v. </em>to do or make something that behaves or looks like something real but is not</p>
<p><strong>basin </strong><em>– n. </em>a low area of land from which water flows into another body</p>
<p><strong>jettison</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v. </em>throwing material from one place to another</p>
<p><strong>shadow </strong><em>– n. </em>a dark area made by something blocking the light</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>American Places – Gettysburg, Pennsylvania  (2025/2/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/american-places-gettysburg-pennsylvania.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>The Gettysburg National Military Park is in the small town of Gettysburg in the eastern state of Pennsylvania.</p>
<p>Much of the area around Gettysburg still looks like it did in the 1860s, during the American Civil War. The town is in the middle of good farmland.<br/>
<br/>
Roads pass through Gettysburg that lead to Baltimore, Washington, D.C., and other eastern cities. It is hard to believe that two huge armies fought there.</p>
<p>One fighting force was the United States Army of the Potomac, commanded by General George Meade. The other was the Confederate Army of Northern Virginia led by General Robert E. Lee. Lee's troops had moved north into Pennsylvania from Virginia.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - In this Friday, May 24, 2013 photo, shown is the Gettysburg National Military Park, Museum &amp; Visitor Center, in Gettysburg, Pa. " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/6cf93a63-c8a6-4f64-a4eb-8721a7320d3d_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - In this Friday, May 24, 2013 photo, shown is the Gettysburg National Military Park, Museum &amp; Visitor Center, in Gettysburg, Pa. </span></div>
<p>Lee believed that a Southern win of a battle on Northern land would force a negotiated settlement of the Civil War and mean independence for the Confederate States.</p>
<p>The battle of Gettysburg began on July 1, 1863. About 170,000 soldiers fought for three days. When it ended on July 3, more than 50,000 soldiers were dead, wounded or missing.</p>
<p>Lee's army lost the battle.</p>
<p>Many visitors start their visit to Gettysburg at the Gettysburg Museum of the Civil War. The <strong>museum</strong> has a large collection of Civil War objects. The museum has more than 1 million <strong>artifacts</strong>, from soldiers' private notebooks and clothing to maps of the battlefield.</p>
<p>The museum also houses the Gettysburg cyclorama painting. This kind of artwork completely surrounds the people looking at it.</p>
<p>The painting shows the artist's <strong>vision</strong> of the final major attack of the battle on July 3, 1863. Over time, it has come to be called Pickett's Charge. George Pickett was one of several Confederate commanders ordered to make the charge.</p>
<p>The Confederate soldiers reached a point close to the northern lines and headquarters. Today, the point is called the “High Water Mark.” Northern forces then turned the Confederates back.</p>
<p>The charge failed. Southern forces would never again reach so far north.<br/>
Soon after the battle, people began to visit Gettysburg to try to understand what happened there. One of those visitors, on November 19, 1863, was President Abraham Lincoln. He was invited to help <strong>dedicate</strong> a burial ground for Union soldiers killed in the battle.</p>
<p>Lincoln spoke for just two minutes. But his speech, known as “The Gettysburg Address,” is one of the most famous pieces of American <strong>oratory</strong>.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Nancy Steinbach and Ashley Thompson with additional material from the National Park Service for VOA Learning English. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for the VOA Learning English podcast.</em></p>
<p>____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>museum</strong> <em>– n. </em>a building in which interesting and valuable things (as works of art or historical or scientific objects) are collected and shown to the public<br/>
<strong>artifact </strong><em>– n.</em> a usually simple object (as a tool or ornament) showing human work and representing a culture or a stage in the development of a culture<br/>
<strong>vision</strong> <em>– n.</em> a thought, idea, or object formed by the imagination<br/>
<strong>dedicate </strong><em>– v.</em> to set apart for some purpose and especially a sacred or serious purpose<br/>
<strong>oratory </strong><em>– n.</em> the job of making speeches in public</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What Does It Take to Be a 'Power Couple'?  (2025/2/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/what-does-it-take-to-be-a-power-couple.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>In American English, we use many expressions to describe when two people have a lot of similarities or are very close. Here are some examples.</p>
<p>If we say two people are <u>joined at the hip,</u> they are nearly always together. If we describe individuals as <u>thick as thieves</u>, it means they are very close. People considered <u>two peas in a pod</u> have many things in common. And we use the term <u>kindred spirits</u> to describe people who often share the same opinions and interests.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Tara Davis-Woodhall and husband Hunter Woodhall kiss after she won the silver medal for the U.S. in the women's long jump final at the World Athletics Championships in Hungary, Aug. 20, 2023. They have been called track and field's power couple. (AP Photo/Matthias Schrader, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/837bc8a7-a6c0-47de-8456-b5adc25c909d_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Tara Davis-Woodhall and husband Hunter Woodhall kiss after she won the silver medal for the U.S. in the women's long jump final at the World Athletics Championships in Hungary, Aug. 20, 2023. They have been called track and field's power couple. (AP Photo/Matthias Schrader, File)</span></div>
<p>These expressions can represent people who grew closer for different reasons. Maybe they <strong>complemented</strong> each other well in certain ways. Or maybe their situations brought them together for the purpose of completing something important or meaningful.</p>
<p>But today we are going to discuss a very special kind of relationship – one that involves two people who are <strong>romantically</strong> involved and very successful.</p>
<p>People in such relationships can be described as <u>power couples</u>.</p>
<p>There are many examples of famous power couples, including successful movie stars, musicians and others in the performing arts. But power couples can exist in many other industries and communities, as well. And, the two people do not have to work in the same industry.</p>
<p>If they do, however, that can make them even more powerful. For example, a well-known <strong>architect</strong> who builds homes could be partnered with a famous designer who <strong>decorates</strong> them. Or, one person in a power couple may be a music producer, while the other is a famous singer.</p>
<p>Even though power couples involve highly successful people, one person could describe their partner as <u>their better half</u>. This is a way to <strong>compliment </strong>their “other half” in the relationship. For example, one might say during a meeting with a friend, “Hello! How are you? And more importantly, how is your better half?”</p>
<p>Now, let's hear two friends use some of these expressions.</p>
<p><em>A: Hey, I'm not used to seeing you alone. Where's your <strong>sidekick</strong>?</em></p>
<p><em>B: Huh? Who are you talking about?</em></p>
<p><em>A: Ben. You guys have been joined at the hip for weeks. Looks like you're thick as thieves. </em></p>
<p><em>B: Well, the project is pretty important for the company. So, we're putting in a lot of hours. </em></p>
<p><em>A: Are you becoming kindred spirits from working so much together?</em></p>
<p><em>B: No. It's just keeping us both very busy. </em></p>
<p><em>A: Busy trying to become the new power couple in the office?</em></p>
<p><em>B: What are you talking about?? We're not thick as thieves or kindred spirits, and we're definitely not a power couple. We are just working hard on the same project! </em></p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>. Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>complement</strong> <em>-n. </em>something that fills up, completes, or makes better or perfect : <em>-v. </em>to complete or enhance by providing something additional</p>
<p><strong>romantically </strong><em>-adv. </em>done in a way that relates or is associated with love<em> </em>: <strong>romantic </strong><em>-adv. </em>of, relating to, or associated with love</p>
<p><strong>architect</strong> <em>-n. </em>a person who designs buildings and advises in their construction</p>
<p><strong>decorate</strong> <em>-v. </em>to make more attractive by adding something that is beautiful or becoming</p>
<p><strong>compliment</strong> <em>-n</em>. an expression of respect, affection, or admiration : <em>-v. </em>to make an expression of respect, affection, or admiration</p>
<p><strong>sidekick</strong> <em>-n. </em>a person closely associated with another as a subordinate or partner</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Norway Nears Goal to Sell only Electric New Cars  (2025/2/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/norway-nears-goal-to-sell-only-electric-new-cars.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Norway is very close to meeting its goal of selling only fully electric new vehicles starting this year.</p>
<p>The Norwegian Road Federation (OFV), an automotive industry group, estimates that nearly 96 percent of new cars registered in Norway in January were all-electric. No other country has such a high rate of electric car (EV) ownership.</p>
<p>The OFV noted that of the 9,343 new cars sold last month in Norway, 8,954 of them were all-electric. Of the 50 most-sold models, only two were non-electric. The first of those came in 33rd place among the 50 models, the federation said.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE: Electric cars are charged via a charging station on a street in the Norwegian capital Oslo on September 25, 2024. " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/8a75879d-727f-4cd8-ab54-b6b3e446d6da_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE: Electric cars are charged via a charging station on a street in the Norwegian capital Oslo on September 25, 2024. </span></div>
<p>The European Automobile Manufacturers' Association (ACEA) reported the share of electric cars in Europe was just 13.6 percent during 2024. That was the first recorded decrease since 2020.</p>
<p>OFV director Oyvind Solberg Thorsen said in a statement, "We've never seen this before...If the rest of the year continues like this, we will very soon be close to the 2025 goal." He noted that reaching 100 percent of the goal means to continue to offer the “<strong>incentives</strong> that make it profitable to choose an electric car over other models.”</p>
<p>Even though it is a major oil and gas producer, Norway aims to only sell "zero <strong>emission</strong>" new vehicles starting in 2025. That goal is 10 years ahead of the target set by the European Union (EU). Norway is not a member of the EU.</p>
<p>One difference between the EU and Norway's method is that Norway has not banned the sale of cars with engines that burn fuel. Instead, Norway offers a number of tax breaks to EV manufacturers and owners. On the other hand, the country heavily taxes gas-powered vehicles.</p>
<p>For example, Norwegian EV owners do not have to pay road<strong> tolls</strong> and receive free parking in public car parks. EVs are also permitted to use parts of roads normally saved for public transportation vehicles.</p>
<p><strong>Chargers everywhere</strong></p>
<p>While some tax breaks and incentives have been reduced over the years, EVs have still kept expanding across Norwegian roads.</p>
<p>Frode Hvattum is a 50-year-old father of three who owns two EVs. He told the French News Agency AFP he started buying EVs because of his concern for the environment and for the <strong>benefits</strong> of driving them.</p>
<p>He lives in an area near Oslo where the streets are full of Teslas, Audis and Volkswagens. Some less costly Chinese EVs are increasingly appearing too.</p>
<p>Many homes have a device to charge, or supply electricity to, their EV's <strong>battery</strong>. Norway also has a large national network of superfast charging stations.</p>
<p>Having a nationwide charging network was important for Hvattum, who, like many Norwegians, often travels by car to his second home in the mountains several hours outside Oslo. He said he finds it easy to plan and make trips with numerous charging stations available.</p>
<p>"You don't have to plan your trip as much as before," Hvattum said. He added that he uses the 15-to-20-minute charging breaks his vehicle needs to make it up to the mountains to shop for food.</p>
<p><strong>Meeting its goal</strong></p>
<p>Even if EV sales fail to meet the 100 percent mark this year, experts say Norway can still be seen as having met its goal.</p>
<p>Christina Bu heads the Norwegian Electric Vehicle Association. She told AFP, "We should finish the year at between 95 and 100 percent."</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Pierre-Henry Deshayes reported this story for Agence France-Presse.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>incentive</strong> – <em>n</em>. something that urges a person to act in a particular way</p>
<p><strong>emission</strong> <em>– n.</em> harmful substances released into the air by automobiles or factories burning oil or coal</p>
<p><strong>toll</strong> – <em>n</em>. an amount of money that you are required to pay for the use of a road or bridge</p>
<p><strong>benefit</strong> – <em>n</em>. a good result or effect</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What is the Super Bowl?  (2025/2/8)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/what-is-the-super-bowl.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By VOA</span><br/><span class="datetime">07 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>This Sunday, February 9, is not a holiday in the United States, but it might seem like one to Americans.</p>
<p>Many will be attending parties to watch Super Bowl LIX. The Super Bowl is the championship game of professional American football.</p>
<p>The National Football League, or NFL, has 32 teams mainly based in large cities across the U.S.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Kansas City Chiefs place kicker Harrison Butker (7) kicks the game-winning field goal in the second half of the NFL Super Bowl 57 football game, against the Philadelphia Eagles Sunday, Feb. 12, 2023, in Glendale, Ariz. (AP Photo/David J. Phillip, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/96945554-e6ae-401d-8bbd-0b73a46cc8d0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Kansas City Chiefs place kicker Harrison Butker (7) kicks the game-winning field goal in the second half of the NFL Super Bowl 57 football game, against the Philadelphia Eagles Sunday, Feb. 12, 2023, in Glendale, Ariz. (AP Photo/David J. Phillip, File)</span></div>
<p>The first professional <strong>league</strong> was formed in 1920, when representatives of four teams met in Canton, Ohio. The group first called itself the American Professional Football Association but changed the name two years later to the National Football League.</p>
<p>In 1960, Texas businessman Lamar Hunt pushed the effort to create the American Football League, or AFL. The two leagues competed with each other to sign top football players from universities around the country.</p>
<p>In 1965, established NFL players began negotiating to play for the competing league. So, officials of the two leagues decided to work together. This agreement established a championship game between the two leagues. It was officially called the AFL-NFL World Championship Game but became known as the Super Bowl.</p>
<p>The first Super Bowl was played in 1967 in Los Angeles, California. The Green Bay Packers defeated the Kansas City Chiefs. It was not a very <strong>exciting</strong> game. Many of the seats in the sports center were empty. That changed with the Super Bowl played two years later. Experts say the public finally accepted the new league when the New York Jets defeated the Baltimore Colts.</p>
<p>After that game in 1969, officials of the two leagues decided to create a new National Football League. They divided the teams into two competing conferences, the American Conference, or AFC, and the National Conference, NFC. Each year, the conference champions play in the Super Bowl.</p>
<p>Today, the Super Bowl is a major sporting event. Tens of thousands of people will be watching the game Sunday at the Superdome in New Orleans, Louisiana.</p>
<p>Tens of millions of other people around the world will be watching Super Bowl LIX. They will be watching to see if the AFC Kansas City Chiefs or the NFC Philadelphia Eagles become the champions of American football.</p>
<p>Both teams have had success in the Big Game. The Eagles are one-time NFL champions. They defeated the New England Patriots in Super Bowl LII. This Sunday will be the team's fifth NFL championship game appearance.</p>
<p>The Kansas City Chiefs have played for the championship six times. They have won four times, including the last two Super Bowls. The Chiefs are the first team in NFL history to have a chance to win a third Super Bowl <strong>in a row</strong>.</p>
<p>I'm <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_f4j55Zlw">Caty Weaver.</a></p>
<p><em>Caty Weaver wrote this report for VOA Learning English with contributing information from the Associated Press.</em></p>
<p>____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in this Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>league </strong>–n. sports teams that play each other and are linked by a business agreement and rules</p>
<p><strong>exciting</strong> <em>–adj.</em> something that causes excitement</p>
<p><strong>in a row </strong><em>–phrase</em> one following another in a series</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Regarding and Regardless  (2025/2/8)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/regarding-and-regardless.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">07 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em> we answer a question from Ramatoulaye in Senegal. Here is Ramatoulaye's question:</p>
<p>Dear teacher,</p>
<p>Thank you and all the VOA Learning English team for their great work! My question is: what is the difference between “regarding” and “regardless?”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Ask a Teacher: Regarding and Regardless" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/2593bf3f-7416-4990-8c7b-cdbb32887111_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Ask a Teacher: Regarding and Regardless</span></div>
<p>Thank you for your comments, Ramatoulaye. And I am happy to answer your question.</p>
<p>Both words are very useful in speaking and writing. That's because the words give us a quick way to connect to other ideas.</p>
<p>“Regarding” simply means what someone is talking or writing about. Consider the following two examples:</p>
<p><em>We have all the information we need about the project.</em></p>
<p><em>We have all the information we need regarding the project.</em></p>
<p>The word “regarding” in the second example means the same thing as the preposition “about” in the first example. We generally use the word “about” more than “regarding.” However, it is more common to use “regarding” in formal speech than in informal communication.</p>
<p>Also, the expression “in regard to” means the same thing as “regarding.” Here are some examples:</p>
<p><em><u>In regard to</u></em><em> the price, I think it was too expensive.</em></p>
<p><em><u>In regard to</u></em><em> what you said, I don't think we know all the facts yet.</em></p>
<p>Note that we use a noun, noun phrase, or noun clause after the expression “in regard to.” Also, you will sometimes hear native speakers say “in regards to” instead of “in regard to.”</p>
<p>Here is something you may find interesting when we compare the expression “in regard to” and the verb “regard.” The verb “regard” is a somewhat formal way to say, “look at.” So, just as we can direct someone's attention to something by having them look at it, the expression “in regard to” directs us to something we are talking about.</p>
<p><strong>Regardless</strong></p>
<p>The word “regardless” expresses the idea that one or more things do not affect the current situation or what we want to express now. When you look at the word, you will see that it ends with the suffix <em>-less</em>. This suffix means the same thing as the word “without.” So, “regardless” means “without regard to.”</p>
<p>Consider the following examples.</p>
<p><em><u>Regardless of</u> religion, all people want happiness.</em></p>
<p><em>All people want happiness, <u>regardless of</u> religion.</em></p>
<p>Notice that you can use the word “regardless” either before or after the sentence or phrase it <strong>modifies</strong>.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? Regardless of your level of English, we want to hear from you! Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please let us know where you are from, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>________________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>modify</strong> <em>-v. </em>in grammar, to limit or specify the meaning of another word</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Millions of Europeans Could Die from Heat by 2100  (2025/2/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/study-millions-of-europeans-could-die-from-heat-by-2100.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>A new study warns that millions of Europeans could die from heat-related causes by the end of the century.</p>
<p>The study was based on computer <strong>simulations</strong> of predicted climate activity in 854 different European cities. It found that extreme temperatures, mostly heat, could kill as many as 2.3 million people in Europe by 2100.</p>
<p>The researchers said the number of predicted deaths could be reduced if nations are able to find better ways of cutting carbon pollution levels and dealing with extreme heat.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file photo, people watch a sunset sitting on a beach next to the Trafalgar Lighthouse in Los Ca&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;241;os de Meca, Spain, on, July 29, 2020. (AP Photo/Emilio Morenatti, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/435c5886-5e72-42b0-90d6-6f75aae18b43_cx6_cy17_cw86_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this file photo, people watch a sunset sitting on a beach next to the Trafalgar Lighthouse in Los Ca<i>&amp;#</i>241;os de Meca, Spain, on, July 29, 2020. (AP Photo/Emilio Morenatti, File)</span></div>
<p>Currently, cold weather kills far more people in Europe than hot weather. But the study found that as temperatures continue to rise, deaths from cold weather will lessen over time. However, heat-related deaths are predicted to rise sharply.</p>
<p>Scientists at the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine led the research. The results appeared recently <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-00239-4#:~:text=An%20extra%202.3%20million%20people,the%20effects%20of%20rising%20temperatures.">in a study</a> in the publication <em>Nature Medicine</em>.</p>
<p>The researchers urged increased efforts to reduce greenhouse gases and expand indoor air-cooling systems and cooling centers in parts of Europe. Without such efforts, places in Italy, southern Spain and Greece are likely to see large increases in heat deaths related to climate change, the study found.</p>
<p>On the other hand, much of Scandinavia and Britain are predicted to see fewer temperature-related deaths, largely because low temperatures are expected to become more moderate.</p>
<p>Pierre Masselot studies the environmental effects of human health at the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine. He helped lead the research.</p>
<p>Masselot told the Associated Press that drops in cold deaths in northern parts of Europe are happening in areas not as populated as places further south. “The Mediterranean is a so-called climate hotspot," he said. "It's a <strong>region</strong> that is warming much quicker than the rest of the world. And Malta is right in the middle of it.”</p>
<p>The study predicts Malta's temperature-related deaths will increase by 269 people for every 100,000 individuals by the end of the century. On the other hand, Ireland's rate is expected to drop slightly to 15 per 100,000 people.</p>
<p>European officials reported several heat waves have killed thousands of people in recent years across the continent. The highest number was in 2003, when about 70,000 deaths were recorded.</p>
<p>Among the areas predicted to see the most deaths from future temperature rises is Barcelona, Spain. The study found almost 250,000 people could die from temperature-related causes in that city by 2100. And the study warned that Rome and Naples could have up to 150,000 deaths.</p>
<p>The study predicted that more than 5.8 million extra heat deaths would be linked to climate change. At the same time, the study found cold-related deaths would drop by 3.5 million.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>simulate </strong><em>– v. </em>do or make something that behaves or looks like something real but is not</p>
<p><strong>region </strong><em>– n. </em>a particular area in a country or the world</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study Finds India’s Tiger Population Doubled in 12 Years  (2025/2/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/study-finds-india-s-tiger-population-doubled-in-12-years.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p class="MsoBodyText">A recent study says India has doubled its tiger population in 12 years.</p>
<p>Researchers said the gain came from efforts to protect the big cats from hunters, and to protect against the loss of tiger <strong>habitat</strong> and <strong>prey</strong>, among other things.</p>
<p>The National Tiger Conservation Authority said the number of tigers grew from an estimated 1,706 in 2010 to around 3,682 in 2022. Those numbers mean India is home to about 75 percent of the total tiger population.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Tigers interact at the Ranthambore National Park in Sawai Madhopur, India on April 12, 2015. (AP Photo/Satyajeet Singh Rathore, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/54dd38b3-b64e-42a3-9597-cfd4c8a2a9c4_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Tigers interact at the Ranthambore National Park in Sawai Madhopur, India on April 12, 2015. (AP Photo/Satyajeet Singh Rathore, File)</span></div>
<p>The research shows that a reduction in conflict between humans and wildlife also played a part in the population growth. The study credited efforts to improve economic conditions for communities near tiger habitats. The researchers said the growth in the tiger population also led to improvements in local economies through increased <strong>ecotourism</strong>.</p>
<p>The study appears in the publication <em>Science</em>. It said India's success demonstrates that wildlife protection can help both <strong>biodiversity</strong> and nearby communities.</p>
<p>“The common belief is that human densities <strong>preclude</strong> an increase in tiger populations," said Yadvendradev Jhala. Jhala is a scientist at Bengaluru-based Indian National Academy of Sciences and was the study's lead writer. “What the research shows is that it's not the human density, but the <strong>attitude</strong> of people, which matters more.”</p>
<p>Wildlife <strong>conservationists</strong> and ecologists welcomed the study. But they said making the source data available to a larger group of scientists would aid tigers and other wildlife in India. The study was based on data collected by Indian government-supported organizations.</p>
<p>Arjun Gopalaswamy is an ecologist who knows how to measure wildlife populations. He said that estimates from India's official tiger observation program have been undependable. He said some of the numbers in the study are much higher than past estimates of tiger populations from the same datasets. But he added that the study's findings seem to have corrected a data problem noted repeatedly by scientists since 2011 related to tiger population size and their <strong>range</strong>.</p>
<p>The study said tigers disappeared in some areas. These included habitats that were not near national parks or other protected areas, and areas of increased development, increased human use of forest resources and areas with armed conflict.</p>
<p>“Without community support and<strong> participation</strong> and community benefits, conservation is not possible in our country,” said Jhala.</p>
<p>That means local people need to see good results from their efforts to save tigers.</p>
<p>Tigers are spread across about 138,200 square kilometers of India. But just 25 percent of the area is rich in tiger prey and is protected. Another 45 percent of tiger habitat is shared with about 60 million people, the study said.</p>
<p>Jhala said strong wildlife protection legislation is the “backbone” of tiger conservation in India. “Habitat is not a <strong>constraint</strong>, it's the quality of the habitat which is a constraint,” he said.</p>
<p>Wildlife biologist Ravi Chellam, who did not take part in the study, praised the tiger conservation efforts as promising. But, he said, such efforts need to be extended to other wild animals to better care for the whole ecosystem in India.</p>
<p>Chellam said several kinds of Indian wildlife are “on the edge,” and need more attention.</p>
<p>I'm <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_f4j55Zlw">Caty Weaver.</a></p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>______________________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>habitat</strong> <em>–n.</em> the place or environment where a plant or animal naturally or normally exists</p>
<p><strong>prey </strong><em>–n.</em> an animal hunted or killed by another animal for food</p>
<p><strong>ecotourism </strong><em>–n.</em> people who travel to and visit a place to see its natural beauty and wildlife</p>
<p><strong>biodiversity </strong><em>–n.</em> biological variety in an environment as indicated by numbers of different species of plants and animals</p>
<p><strong>preclude </strong><em>–v.</em> to make impossible by necessary consequence</p>
<p><strong>attitude </strong><em>–n</em>. the visible behavior that shows how a person thinks or feels about something or someone</p>
<p><strong>conservationist </strong>–n. a person who works to preserve animals, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_iuIUpwMv">plants</a> and natural resources for future generations</p>
<p><strong>range </strong><em>–n.</em> the area where a plant or animal naturally lives and can be found</p>
<p><strong>constraint </strong><em>–n.</em> the state of being restricted</p>
<p><strong>participation </strong><em>– n.</em> the action or state of taking part in something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>New US Jet Breaks Sound Barrier in First Flight Test  (2025/2/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/new-us-jet-breaks-sound-barrier-in-first-flight-test.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>An experimental aircraft developed by a private American company broke the sound barrier during a recent flight test.</p>
<p>California-based company Boom Supersonic built the plane, named XB-1. The company said the aircraft reached a speed of Mach 1.05 during a test on January 28. The test flight operated from the Mojave Air &amp; Space Port in Mojave, California.</p>
<p>Any speed greater than Mach 1.0 breaks the sound barrier and is considered supersonic. The American space agency NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/learning-resources/for-kids-and-students/what-is-supersonic-flight-grades-5-8/#:~:text=Vehicles%20that%20fly%20at%20supersonic,to%20the%20speed%20of%20sound.">explains</a> that at sea level, the speed of sound is estimated to be about 1,236 kilometers per hour.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="The Boom Supersonic's XB-1 aircraft breaks the sound barrier, Mach 1, during a test flight Tuesday, Jan. 28, 2025, over the Mohave Desert, Calif. (Boom Supersonic via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/2d899815-edd8-4ed9-91dc-03ace83020b5_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">The Boom Supersonic's XB-1 aircraft breaks the sound barrier, Mach 1, during a test flight Tuesday, Jan. 28, 2025, over the Mohave Desert, Calif. (Boom Supersonic via AP)</span></div>
<p>In a statement, Boom Supersonic said the XB-1 demonstrator aircraft climbed to more than 35,000 feet before reaching Mach 1.0. It recorded the speed within 11 minutes of taking off. The company also released a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-qisIViAHwI">video feed</a> of the supersonic test flight.</p>
<p>The company said in a press release, “Historically, supersonic aircraft have been the work of nation states, developed by militaries and governments.” But the latest flight made the XB-1 “the world's first independently developed supersonic <strong>jet</strong>” to break the sound barrier, Boom Supersonic said.</p>
<p>The company's founder and chief executive officer, Blake Scholl, said, “XB-1's supersonic flight demonstrates that the technology for passenger supersonic flight has arrived.”</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" href="https://boomsupersonic.com/">Boom Supersonic</a> launched in 2014 “with the goal of making high-speed travel <strong>mainstream</strong> and <strong>enabling</strong> a new world of human connection.” With that in mind, the company has been working to develop a supersonic passenger airliner called Overture. The aircraft would carry up to 80 passengers.</p>
<p>Boom Supersonic is one of several American companies seeking to develop supersonic flight vehicles. NASA is also working on a supersonic aircraft in partnership with a U.S. contractor.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p>The last time supersonic travel was available to passengers was 2003. That is the year the Concorde – the world's first supersonic passenger jet aircraft – stopped service. Britain and France jointly operated the Concorde.</p>
<p>But the joint operation between British Airways and Air France suffered several business difficulties that led to the decision to stop flying the supersonic planes. Some of the difficulties were linked to publicity about a deadly Concorde crash in 2000. That incident involved an Air France airliner crashing shortly after taking off from Paris. The crash claimed a total of 113 lives.</p>
<p>Boom Supersonic says its planned Overture airliner will be designed to transport passengers from the U.S. East Coast across the Atlantic to Europe in about 3-and-a-half hours. The flight with normal passenger jets takes about eight hours.</p>
<p>Amy Marino Spowart is the president and chief executive officer at the National Aeronautic Association. She told The Associated Press the latest supersonic test flight suggests “the future of <strong>aviation</strong> is here and now.” Spowart added, “Not only is there hope for faster and better commercial flight, but Boom proves that it can be done <strong>sustainably</strong>.”</p>
<p>Boom Supersonic has said its planned supersonic airliner will be designed to run on up to 100 percent sustainable aircraft fuel. Such sustainable fuels are made from non-petroleum products, such as food waste or other biomass materials. Both XB-1 and Overture are made mostly from a carbon-based <strong>composite</strong> material to provide “a strong, lightweight structure,” the company said.</p>
<p>NASA's supersonic aircraft – built together with Lockheed Martin – is called X-59. It is also an experimental plane that is seeking to test the level of noise produced by supersonic travel. Currently, supersonic flights are banned over land because of the loud noise they produce.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
renderExternalContent("https://www.youtube.com/embed/eC3Fl7Bt4qQ?&amp;&amp;&amp;fs=1&amp;enablejsapi=1")



<p>NASA has <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/missions/quesst/quesst-mission/quesst-the-mission-description/">explained</a> it plans to carry out testing this year of the X-59 aircraft, which has been designed and engineered to operate at lower noise levels than other supersonic aircraft. The tests – to take place at supersonic test centers in California – are designed “to prove the quiet supersonic technology works as designed.”</p>
<p>NASA said that after that testing is done, the agency plans to begin community reaction studies, beginning in 2026. These will involve flying the X-59 over several cities and then asking people on the ground to share their thoughts on the level of noise they heard.</p>
<p>NASA has said the X-59 – which measures 30 meters long and nine meters wide – is expected to fly at 1.4 times the speed of sound. That is about 1,500 kilometers per hour.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press, Reuters and Boom Supersonic reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>_______________________________________</strong></h2>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>mainstream </strong><em>– adj. </em>the beliefs or way of living that are accepted by most people</p>
<p><strong>enable </strong><em>– v. </em>to make something possible</p>
<p><strong>sustainable </strong><em>– adj. </em>method of energy production that cause little or no damage to the environment</p>
<p><strong>composite </strong><em>– adj. </em>made up of several different materials or parts</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Japan Launches New Satellite to Improve Navigation System  (2025/2/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/japan-launches-new-satellite-to-improve-navigation-system.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Japan's space agency says it successfully launched a <strong>navigation</strong> satellite on its new H3 rocket. The latest launch on February 2 took place as the country aims to develop a more <strong>precise</strong> positioning system.</p>
<p>The H3 rocket carrying the Michibiki 6 satellite lifted off from the Tanegashima Space Center on a southwestern Japanese island.</p>
<p>Makoto Arita oversees the H3 project for the Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency known as JAXA. Arita said everything went smoothly and the satellite successfully separated from the rocket as planned about 29 minutes after liftoff.</p><div class="contentImage"><img a="" alt="The H3 Launch Vehicle No. 5, carrying the " at="" center="" feb.="" in="" japan="" launch="" lifts="" michibiki="" no.="" off="" pad="" southern="" space="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/8068b7d6-2728-49af-a20b-c23c10b60066_w268_r1.jpg" sunday="" tanegashima=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">The H3 Launch Vehicle No. 5, carrying the "Michibiki No. 6," lifts off at a launch pad in Tanegashima Space Center in Tanegashima, southern Japan, Sunday Feb. 2, 2025.</span></div>
<p>Officials said it should reach its target orbit around Earth in the middle of February.</p>
<p>Japan's current system is called the <strong>quasi</strong>-<strong>zenith</strong> satellite system, or QZSS. It started operating in 2018 and has four satellites that serve a regional <strong>navigation</strong> system. The Michibiki 6 will be the fifth satellite in the network.</p>
<p>Michibiki's signals are used to <strong>supplement</strong> the American satellite system called the Global Positioning System (GPS). It will also improve positioning data for smartphones, car navigation, navigation at sea and <strong>drones</strong>.</p>
<p>Japan plans to launch two more navigation satellites to have a seven-satellite system by March 2026. The Japan Science and Technology Agency hopes that will create a more precise global positioning ability without depending on foreign services, including GPS. By the late 2030s, Japan plans to have an 11-satellite network.</p>
<p><strong>First launch not successful</strong></p>
<p>Sunday's launch was the fourth successful flight in a row for the H3 system. The first attempt to launch last year failed and the rocket had to be destroyed with its <strong>payload</strong>.</p>
<p>Japan considers the ability to regularly put satellites into orbit as important to its space program and national security. It has been developing two new leading rockets. One is the large H3 from Mitsubishi Heavy Industries. The other is a much smaller Epsilon system with the aerospace unit of IHI corporation. Japan hopes to meet the needs of companies for space launch services and improve its position in the growing satellite launch market.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Mari Yamaguchi reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>navigation</strong> – <em>n</em>. the act, activity, or process of finding the way to get to a place when you are traveling in a ship, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_QWvmxS9e">airplane</a> or car</p>
<p><strong>precise </strong><em>–adj.</em> exactly placed; exactly where something is supposed to be</p>
<p><strong>quasi </strong><em>– prefix</em> almost, nearly</p>
<p><strong>zenith </strong><em>– n. </em>to point in the sky directly above your head</p>
<p><strong>drone</strong> - <em>n</em>. a small aircraft that flies without a pilot and is controlled from the ground</p>
<p><strong>supplement </strong><em>– v.</em> to provide additional support</p>
<p><strong>payload</strong> <em>– n.</em> anything that someone is paying to have transported by a vehicle such as an airplane or rocket</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Huge Iceberg Could Threaten Penguins in the South Atlantic Ocean  (2025/2/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/huge-iceberg-could-threaten-penguins-in-the-south-atlantic-ocean.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Scientists are worried that a large <strong>iceberg</strong> heading toward an island in the South Atlantic Ocean could threaten wildlife there.</p>
<p>Researchers say the iceberg is the largest in the world. It is moving through the South Atlantic toward the island of South Georgia. The island is a British overseas territory that is about 1,400 kilometers east of the Falkland Islands.</p>
<p>Scientists say South Georgia is a main mating ground for wildlife, especially penguins and seals.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image provided by the Ministry of Defence shows the iceberg, known as A23a, on Nov. 25, 2024, off the coast of Antarctica. (Cpl Tom Cann RAF/Crown Copyright 2024 via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/52c90d07-ee3c-49bc-abf0-3215f1af247c_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image provided by the Ministry of Defence shows the iceberg, known as A23a, on Nov. 25, 2024, off the coast of Antarctica. (Cpl Tom Cann RAF/Crown Copyright 2024 via AP)</span></div>
<p>The iceberg is officially known as A23a and it measures about 3,500 square kilometers. It has existed since 1986, when it broke off from the Antarctic <strong>shelf</strong>.</p>
<p>Andrew Meijers is an oceanographer with the British Antarctic Survey. He told the French News Agency (AFP) that scientists have been using satellite imagery to follow the iceberg's movements.</p>
<p>Meijers said observations had shown the iceberg had not broken into smaller pieces like some other so-called "megabergs" that passed through the Southern Ocean. He added that predicting the iceberg's exact path is difficult. But ocean conditions suggest it should reach South Georgia in two to four weeks.</p>
<p>Meijers said he is worried the iceberg will get caught on the underground <strong>continental shelf</strong> around South Georgia. But he said it is also possible the large ice mass could miss the shelf and continue moving into open waters beyond South Georgia.</p>
<p>If the iceberg does get caught, or stuck, on the shelf, Meijers said it could remain there for months or it could break into pieces. Meijers is concerned that this could harm efforts by penguins and seals on the island to feed and raise their young. Icebergs that have grounded there in the past led to the deaths of young penguins and seals, he said.</p>
<p>Raul Cordero is a mechanical engineer from Chile's University of Santiago. He is also a member of the National Antarctic Research Committee. Cordero told AFP he thinks the iceberg will miss South Georgia.</p>
<p>"The island acts as an <strong>obstacle</strong> for ocean currents and therefore usually <strong>diverts</strong> the water long before it reaches the island," he said. "The iceberg is moved by that water flow, so the chances of it hitting are not that high." Cordero added, however, that some iceberg pieces could affect the island.</p>
<p>Soledad Tiranti is a <strong>glacier</strong> expert who is currently on an Argentinian exploration trip in the Antarctic. She told AFP that icebergs such as A23a "are so deep that before reaching an island or mainland they generally get stuck" on the seabed.</p>
<p>It is currently summer in South Georgia and penguins and seals from the area have been looking for food in the cold Antarctic waters to bring back to their young. Meijers said the animals might have to go around the iceberg if it gets stuck.</p>
<p>He added that if they had to move around it, this would take a lot of their energy, possibly leading to animal deaths. The seal and penguin populations on South Georgia have already been having a "bad season" with cases of bird flu, Meijers said.</p>
<p>Iceberg A23a remained stuck for 30 years before finally breaking free from the Antarctic shelf in 2020. Scientists watching its movements say the iceberg has followed nearly the same path as other large ice masses in the past.</p>
<p>The icebergs generally pass the east side of the Antarctic Peninsula through the Weddell Sea along a path known as "iceberg <strong>alley</strong>." They are pushed by the world's most powerful ocean current system, the Antarctic Circumpolar Current.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Agence France-Presse reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>______________________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>iceberg </strong><em>– n. </em>a huge piece of ice that floats freely in the sea</p>
<p><strong>shelf</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> an area of relatively shallow water that surrounds a land mass</p>
<p><strong>continental shelf </strong><em>–n.</em> an area of relatively shallow water that extends from the world's great land masses and beyond which is the deep ocean</p>
<p><strong>obstacle </strong><em>– n. </em>something that makes it difficult or gets in the way of doing something; a barrier</p>
<p><strong>divert </strong><em>– v. </em>to<em> </em>send someone or something to a place other than where they had expected to go</p>
<p><strong>glacier</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n. </em>a large mass of ice that moves very slowly, usually down a hill or valley</p>
<p><strong>alley </strong><em>– n. </em>a narrow street or place where things are likely to pass</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How to Write a Good Email  (2025/2/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/how-to-write-a-good-email.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Gregory Stachel</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>
Email is one of the most important ways through which we communicate. It has become part of most everyone's day-to-day life.</p>
<p>Writing a good email can mean the difference between someone reading it and writing back, and someone ignoring it all together. Do you have questions on how to make your message more effective?</p>
<p>Today on <em>Education Tips, </em>we will answer the question, “How can I make my emails better?”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Education Tips: How to Write a Good Email" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/5663032C-AEBD-4C48-BFC2-1BFC5947DC1C_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Education Tips: How to Write a Good Email</span></div>
<p>Emails are made up of four different parts:</p>
<ul style="margin-left:40px">
<li>the subject line,</li>
<li>the opening,</li>
<li>the body, and</li>
<li>the closing.</li>
</ul>
<p>Let us explore how to make each of these parts better.</p>
<p><strong>Subject line</strong></p>
<p>The subject line is what the other person, or receiver, will read first. The subject line is usually the most important part of an email. It should be short but contain enough details that the receiver recognizes the subject of the email. A good subject line sets the expectations for the email. A bad subject line can mean the receiver will not read the email.</p>
<p>Some people will add the word “important” to the subject line, but this does not provide enough information. Instead of writing “important,” two better choices for subject lines are:</p>
<p><em>Meeting Tomorrow at 10am to Discuss New Changes<br/>
Question About Future Classes</em></p>
<p><strong>Opening an email</strong></p>
<p>As in any form of writing, you should know your <strong>audience</strong>. The opening of an email depends on things like how <strong>formal </strong>the relationship is.</p>
<p>If you are sending an email to a friend or someone you work with, two good openings or greetings are:</p>
<p><em>Good Morning/Afternoon,<br/>
Hello, or Hello [name], </em></p>
<p>If you are sending the email to someone you do not know and it is a formal situation, some possible openings are:</p>
<p><em>Dear [name of department],<br/>
To Whom it May Concern,</em></p>
<p>In a formal situation, when you know the name of the person, a good opening is simply:</p>
<p><em>Dear [title] [family name],</em><br/>
As in, <em>Dear Mister Brown, </em></p>
<p><strong>Body</strong></p>
<p>The body of the email is where you ask for what you need or make clear your reason for writing the email. This could be asking them a question or keeping them informed. The body of the email should <strong>prioritize</strong> the most important information. It should be direct, and it is wise to keep it short.</p>
<p>If the person you are emailing does not know you, you should <strong>introduce</strong> yourself in the first few lines. You might write:</p>
<p><em>My name is Patricia Jones. I am sending this email to get some more information about the job you advertised.</em></p>
<p>After you have introduced yourself and given your reason for writing, you can follow this with the body of your email. The most important information should come first. This makes your email clear to your receiver and saves them time. Here is an example.</p>
<p><em>I wanted to know if you are currently accepting <strong>applications</strong>. If so, where can I send my information? Additionally, will you be meeting people in-person or online?</em></p>
<p>It is important to clearly explain yourself in as few words as possible. Try to keep your email short, but <strong>polite</strong>. This is important because you want to make yourself clear to your receiver.</p>
<p><strong>Closings</strong></p>
<p>The last part to a good email is the closing. It is usually one or two words that let the receiver know that this is the end of the email. The ending should include your name and tell the receiver where you work and what you do. A few different closings are:</p>
<p><em>Kind regards,<br/>
Best,<br/>
Thank you,</em></p>
<p>Some applications create an <strong>automatic signature</strong> for the sender. This is useful because it saves time when you are writing.</p>
<p><strong>Example email</strong></p>
<p>So, what does a completed email look like? Here is an example email:</p>
<p>If you follow these suggestions, you will find that you receive more <strong>responses</strong> to your emails. Effective email writing is important especially now when so much of what we do is online.</p>
<p>I'm Gregory Stachel.</p>
<p>And I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Gregory Stachel wrote this story for VOA Learning English. George Grow was the editor.</em></p><div id="bottom"><!-- 51-content-bottom -->
<ins class="adsbygoogle" data-ad-client="ca-pub-3585518775245612" data-ad-format="auto" data-ad-slot="9284795419" data-full-width-responsive="true" style="display:block; text-align:center;"></ins>
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></div>
<p>______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>audience </strong>– <em>n.</em> the people who watch, read, or listen to something</p>
<p><strong>formal</strong> – <em>adj.</em> <em>of language:</em> suitable for serious or official speech and writing</p>
<p><strong>prioritize</strong> – <em>v.</em> to make (something) the most important thing in a group</p>
<p><strong>introduce</strong> – <em>v.</em> to make (someone) known to someone else by name</p>
<p><strong>application</strong> – <em>n.</em> formal and usually written request for something (such as a job, admission to a school, a loan, or such</p>
<p><strong>polite</strong> – <em>adj.</em> having or showing good manners or respect for other people</p>
<p><strong>automatic</strong> – <em>adj.</em> <em>of a machine or device</em>: having controls that allow something to work or happen without being directly controlled by a person</p>
<p><strong>signature</strong> – <em>n.</em> a person's name written in that person's handwriting or, on an electronic message, the person's name and other contact information</p>
<p><strong>response</strong> – <em>n.</em> something that is said or written as a reply to something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>New Zealand Recognizes a Mountain as a Legal Person  (2025/2/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/new-zealand-recognizes-a-mountain-as-a-legal-person.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>New Zealand's parliament recently passed a law that gives a mountain all the rights and responsibilities of a human being.</p>
<p>The <strong>indigenous</strong> Māori people of New Zealand consider the mountain their ancestor.</p>
<p>The mountain is now known by its Māori name, Taranaki Maunga. The Māori people of New Zealand represent about 15 percent of the country's population.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A man takes a picture of his wife with Mount Taranaki, also known as Mount Egmont, in the background in New Plymouth, New Zealand, Sept. 26, 2011. (AP Photo/Dita Alangkara, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/7374aa6d-0b65-47f6-a124-0eaba2737c33_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A man takes a picture of his wife with Mount Taranaki, also known as Mount Egmont, in the background in New Plymouth, New Zealand, Sept. 26, 2011. (AP Photo/Dita Alangkara, File)</span></div>
<p>Taranaki Maunga is a <strong>dormant</strong> volcano on New Zealand's North Island. Snow covers the top of the 2,516-meter-high mountain. It is a popular place for <strong>tourism</strong>, hiking and snow sports.</p>
<p>The legal recognition of the mountain is one of the steps New Zealand's government has taken to make up for harm the indigenous population suffered in the past. The new law makes it known that the Taranaki area was stolen from the Māori after New Zealand was colonized.</p>
<p>The new law gives Taranaki Maunga all the rights, powers, duties, responsibilities and <strong>liabilities</strong> of a person. The law says a newly created group will be “the face and voice” of the mountain. Four members from local Māori tribes and four members appointed by the country's conservation minister will be in the group.</p>
<p>Paul Goldsmith is the lawmaker responsible for the legal settlements between the government and Māori tribes. In a speech to Parliament, he said, “The mountain has long been an honored ancestor, a source of physical, cultural and spiritual <strong>sustenance</strong> and a final resting place."</p>
<p>Britain colonized New Zealand in the 1700s and 1800s. In 1770, the British explorer Captain James Cook named the volcano Mount Egmont.</p>
<p>In 1840, Māori tribes and representatives of the British government signed the Treaty of Waitangi. The treaty promised the Māori would keep the rights to their land and resources. However, the British government began breaking parts of the treaty after that.</p>
<p>In 1865, the government took a large area of Taranaki land, including the mountain, to punish the Māori for rebelling against British rule. Over the next one hundred years, hunting and sports groups helped oversee how the land was used, but the Māori did not.</p>
<p>Goldsmith told the Associated Press that, in the past, Māori customs connected to the mountain were banned while the government supported tourism in the area.</p>
<p>The Māori protest movement of the 1970s and 1980s led to increased recognition of the Māori language, culture and rights in New Zealand's law. This has included billions of dollars to pay for the harm caused by breaking the Treaty of Waitangi.</p>
<p>The mountain's legal rights are in place to support its health and wellbeing. The law will support traditional uses of the land and calls for conservation work to protect the native wildlife. The mountain will remain open to the public.</p>
<p><strong>Are other landforms considered people?</strong></p>
<p>New Zealand was the first country in the world to recognize landforms as people. In 2014, a law gave personhood to Te Urewera, a large forest on the North Island. Government ownership ended and the Tūhoe tribe became its guardian.</p>
<p>And in 2017, New Zealand recognized the Whanganui River as a human, as part of a settlement with the tribe connected to the river.</p>
<p>All 123 lawmakers in Parliament supported the new law for Taranaki Maunga. The unity of the vote was a change from recent disagreements in New Zealand about proposed changes to the Treaty of Waitangi itself.</p>
<p>In November, about 40,000 people marched to Parliament to protest a new law with proposed changes to the treaty. The protesters said the new law would take away Māori rights and harm the progress that has been made during the last 50 years.</p>
<p>Most officials do not expect the bill with the proposed changes to become law.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Charlotte Graham-McLay wrote this story for The Associated Press. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>indigenous </strong><em>–n.</em> someone or something that is native to a place for a relatively long period of time</p>
<p><strong>dormant </strong><em>–adj. </em>not currently active</p>
<p><strong>tourism </strong><em>–n.</em> the activity of traveling to places for enjoyment or the industry that provides food, shelter and activity to tourists</p>
<p><strong>liability </strong><em>–n.</em> something that you are responsible for such as paying back a loan</p>
<p><strong>sustenance </strong>–n. something that gives support, help and strength; food</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Find ‘Chorus Waves’ in Unexpected Part of Space  (2025/2/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/scientists-find-chorus-waves-in-unexpected-part-of-space.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p class="paragraph">International researchers recently released a study on bursts of energy in an unexpected area of space.</p>
<p>Scientists call the energetic activity “<strong>chorus</strong> waves” because they are said to move at the same <strong>frequency</strong> as sounds humans can hear. When the energy is turned into audio signals, the waves sound like birds <strong>chirping</strong>.</p>
<p>Researchers have known about chorus waves in space for many years. But the latest research has found the waves exist 100,000 kilometers from Earth. Chorus waves have never before been measured at such a big distance from a planet.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="NASA's four Magnetospheric Multiscale, or MMS, satellites at the Astrotech Space Operations facility in Titusville, Florida, March 2015. (NASA via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/84f639b0-d205-4ab1-aa8f-c1c89806bc6c_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">NASA's four Magnetospheric Multiscale, or MMS, satellites at the Astrotech Space Operations facility in Titusville, Florida, March 2015. (NASA via AP)</span></div>
<p>In an email, study writer Chengming Liu from Beihang University in Beijing wrote: “They are one of the strongest and most <strong>significant </strong>waves in space.”</p>
<p>Allison Jaynes is a space physicist at the University of Iowa who was not involved with the study. Speaking about the recent study, Jaynes said, “That opens up a lot of new questions about the physics that could be possible in this area.”</p>
<p>The newfound chorus waves were detected in an area where Earth's <strong>magnetic field</strong> is stretched out. Scientists said they did not expect to find <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_jRlu8izx">the waves</a> there. The discovery raises new questions about how the chirping waves form.</p>
<p>Jaynes added, “We definitely need to find more of these events.”</p>
<p>Scientists still are not sure how the waves develop. But they think Earth's <strong>magnetic field</strong> may have something to do with it.</p>
<p>For many years, radio <strong>antennas</strong> have picked up chorus waves. This includes receivers at an Antarctica research station in the 1960s. And NASA's two Van Allen Probes heard the chirping sounds from Earth's <strong>radiation belts</strong> at a closer distance than the newest observations.</p>
<p>The latest chorus waves were picked up by NASA's Magnetospheric Multiscale satellites. They were launched in 2015 to explore the Earth and the sun's magnetic fields.</p>
<p>Chorus waves have also been found near other planets including Jupiter and Saturn. The waves can produce high-energy electrons.<strong> </strong>That means they can threaten satellite communications.</p>
<p>The researchers said their findings suggest that chorus waves might be found everywhere in the magnetic fields of planets.</p>
<p>The study was released on January 22 in the scientific publication <em>Nature</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Adithi Ramakrishnan reported this story for the Associated Press from New York. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>chorus</strong> –n. a group of singers who sing together</p>
<p><strong>significant </strong>–adj. important, meaningful</p>
<p><strong>chirping </strong>–n. short, sharp sounds similar to the songs of certain birds</p>
<p><strong>frequency </strong>–n. the number of times a wave form repeats in a certain amount of time</p>
<p><strong>magnetic field</strong> –n. the area around a magnetized object that is influenced by its magnetism</p>
<p><strong>antenna</strong> –n. a device that carries radio waves to a receiver</p>
<p><strong>radiation belt </strong>–n. an area of charged particles around a planet that is formed largely because of its magnetic field</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
