<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>VOA Special English</title>
        <link>https://www.21voa.com/special_english/</link>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <itunes:category>ESL</itunes:category>
        <itunes:author>VOA</itunes:author>
        <description>美国之音（以下称VOA）的英语节目，按播音速度可分为两种：Standard English （标准英语）和 Special English（特别英语）。

Special English 又叫“慢速英语”，是VOA 专为全世界非英语国家初学英语的听众安排的一种简易、规范的英语广播节目。该节目创始于50年代末期，是VOA 的专家们研究如何与世界各地的英语学习者进行交际的产物。它正式开播于1959年10月。当时只面向欧洲和中东，但由于这个节目适合许多国家英语学习者的需要，所以它的广播对象不久就扩大到世界其他地区，并很快在全世界范围内产生了广泛的影响。现在这个节目对欧洲、非洲和拉丁美洲每晚广播一次，对加勒比地区每晚广播一次（星期天除外），对东南亚广播次数最多，每天上午两次，晚上三次。

30多年来，VOA 为了办好Special English节目，进行了大量的调查研究工作，对播音速度、内容及用词范围都作了具体规定，基本上达到了既能为英语学习者提供信息，又不损害英语本身风格的目的，使之成为VOA 独具特色，拥有最大量听众的节目。

美国著名词汇学家S. B. Flexmer 指明了Special English的三条标准，也就是它所“特别”的地方：

1、它是一种由美国人最常用的1500个基本单词为主体构成的美国英语；

2、它用简短、明晰的句子写作和广播；

3、它以每分钟90个单词的速度，即2/3的Standard English（标准英语）速度进行广播。

Special English的节目可分为两大类：一类是新闻节目；一类是专题节目。

1．新闻节目

VOA Special English 的新闻广播向听众提供世界范围内的政治、经济、军事、外交、国际关系、宗教、天气以及各种重大事件和珍闻奇事等各个方面的信息，每天向东南亚地区广播五次，早上两次，晚上三次，每逢半点播出。

Special English新闻节目每次长约十分钟，大都播出十条左右新闻，近一千个单词，每条新闻多为一分钟，但偶尔也有长达两分钟的要闻。除头条新闻外，每条新闻都由一个电头引导，这样显得结构分明，条理清晰，适宜初学英语的人收听。在节目结束之前，播音员常常用三四句话重播其中三条新闻的提要以加深听众对要闻的印象。

Special English新闻中70%左右的内容与同时整点播出的Standard English新闻相同，但相同新闻的先后次序有所变动。每次节目的开头和结尾大同小异，格式比较固定。

2．专题节目（一）

Special English的专题节目（Feature Programs）,从时间上看，可分为两大类：一是每五分钟一次的专题，二是每十五分钟一次的专题。本节先介绍每项五分钟一次的专题材节目。

Special English五分钟一次的专题材节目安排在Special English新闻节目之后和（或）每十五分钟一次的专题材节目之前播出，每星期播七次。根据内容，可分为三个小类，即：Science Report（科学报道），逢星期一、三、五播出，每天播六遍；Agriculture Report（农业报道），逢星期二、四播出，每天播六遍；Words And Their Stories（词语掌故），逢星期六和星期天播出，每天播五遍。这三个专题材各具特色，具有相对的独立性，听众每听完一个节目，都会获得一个完整的印象。

Science Report（科学报道）这一专题材节目每周向听众介绍三篇有关现代科学技术最新发展情况的报道，涉及物理、化学、天文至高无上理、生物、环卫、心理、教育、医学和计算机等方面。适宜理工科大学生和科技工作者收集信息，积累资料，学习科技英语。

Agriculture Report（农业报道） Agriculture Report是为农业科技工作者和生产者安排的一个专题。它专门报道世界各国，特别是美国现代农业生产的最新成文汇报总务科 学家对农业生产某一方面的研究进展，以及他们对影响农业生产的某一自然现象进行分析和研究的近况。此外，它还经常向听众介绍发展中国家家业生产的一些有益经验等内容。

Words And Their Stories（词语掌故）这一专题节目，旨在向学习英语的听众介绍美国英语中生动有趣的词语和惯用法，并从科学研究和通俗词源学的角度来解释它们的含意、产生的背景及其在使用过程中的演变情况等。它通过讲故事的形式讲解每一个词语。这是VOA Special English中的优秀节目之一，是学习美国英语的极好材料。通过收听这一节目，听众不仅能学到娓娓动听的掌故和地道的美国英语，而且能增加美国的社会文化背景知识，历史传统与现状的了解。

VOA 为了更好地办好这个节目，便于听众收听学习，于1978年编辑出版了一本名为Words And Their Stories的书，共收集一百篇故事，作者是Herbert Sutcliffe, Harold Bermen 及VOA 该节目的部分编辑人员。在每次的实际广播中，播音员都以此书为蓝本，再根据需要对原稿进行适当增删。按每周两个故事计算，此书的一百个故事还不能满足一年的播音需要。于是编辑们就是重播部分词语掌故的同时，不断增加许多新的词语掌故，及时将词源学家的最新研究成果和不断增加的新词汇介绍给听众。收听实践证明，初学者在收听过程中必然会遇到许多人名、地名和一些较难的句子，有时甚至在听完之后还很难理解所播词语的确切含义及其汉语意思，为此，听众可参看1983年由中国对外翻译出版公司出版的该书英汉对照本中的有关部分。

3．专题节目（二）

VOA Special English的专题节目，除上节谈的五分钟一次的以外，还有本节要介绍的每十五分钟一次的节目。这类节目共有七个不同的小专题，以星期为单位循环，每天分四次复播出一个专题，但星期日和星期六的两个专题材每晚只播三遍，每次节目约十分钟，继每次五分钟的专题节目之后播出。

这类专题节目的基本结构是，在特定的伴声中先报告当次节目的名称，并扼要介绍其主要内容，然后播送节目正文。最后，在伴乐声中报告节目主持人和撰稿人的姓名，以邀请听众在下周的这个时间继续收听该节目而结束。

People in America（美国人物志） 这是有关美国历史名人的一个专题节目，每逢星期天晚上播出。它向听众介绍在美国历史上产生过重大影响、起过重要作用、作出了突出贡献的科学、文学、政治、或其他各方面的历史人物。节目一般都对他们的生平事迹进行简要的叙述，对其贡献作出评介，类似人物小传。有的重要人物事迹很多，必须用两次或几次的节目时间进行联播。对这样的节目要坚持收听，才会获得完整的印象。

TThis is America（今日美国） This Is America向听众介绍美国人民的生活、学习、工作和娱乐情况，是英语学习者解美国社会的一条渠道。该专题大都一个节目一个整体，每逢星期一晚播出。

Science in the News（科学新闻） 这一专题材主要对新近的科学技术新闻进行综述或摘要广播。向听众介绍世界各国在自然、医学、疾病、原子能、航天等方面的科研动态、成果、突破性进展及存在的困难。涉及当今世界人们普遍关心的重大问题，如核事故、航天飞机爆炸、自然灾害、环境污染和爱滋病等等。每逢星期二播出，每次播一到五条新闻摘要。

Explorations（自然探索） 每逢星期三晚上，听众可以收听到Explorations这一专题节目。该专题既涉及人类遨游太空、探索原子、研究自身、改造自然的现代技术，也报道发展中国家开发新资源，利用新工艺改善人民生活等方面的成就，其侧重点在各种科技实验和简易实用技术方面。该节目一般安排一段时间播一个系列，每次播出一个主题，以便能将某项新技术的研究和应用的全过程介绍给听众，电台还乐意为感兴趣的听众提供所需的文字材料。

The Making of a Nation（建国史话） 这一专题节目向听众介绍美利坚合众国从十三个殖民地区域到现代工业国的孕育、诞生以及形成超级大国的历史过程，并以历史为线索，特定的历史时期为单位，以重大的历史事件为主题材来叙述各个党派、各届总统和政府的历史作用与贡献。这是每个英语学习者都应了解的基本知识。The Making of a Nation每逢星期四播出。这是个系列节目，坚持收听，则有助于系统了解美国的历史概况。

American Mosaic（美国万花筒） American Mosaic是一个radio magazine（广播杂志）节目。该节目题材广泛、内容丰，展示着美国社会文化生活中比较轻松愉快的生活画面；听众收听该节目就如同在阅读一本图文并茂的杂志。它每次有三到五个小节目，涉及音乐、图书、技术和教育等方面的内容。我们既可以从中欣赏到著名歌唱的优秀歌曲，对美国音乐有所了解，又可以获取一些生动有趣的现代美国社会生活知识，随着播音员那亲切悦耳的声音步入美国风景如画的大好河山；同时还能听到世界各地的听众提出的有关英语语方文学等方面的问题和电台的解答。

American Stories（美国故事） 这一专题材节目安排在每星期六晚上播出。这样能使听众在学习和工作之余，得以轻松一下头脑。我们可以通过这一美国文学的“窗口”，接触各种流派、各类名家的文学作品。了解美国英语的时代特色，欣赏、学习美国人民运用语方的技巧，并从那些佳作名篇中获得艺术享受。该节目对短篇故事采取一次播一篇的方式，对中、长篇小说则先进行简写加工，再分几次播出全文。在播出故事正文之前，播音员常常先介绍故事的主要情节。对需要分几次节目时间播出的中长篇，在播第二或以后各部分之前，主持人还先重述已播部分的故事梗概，以唤起听众的回忆，使故事听起来更加连贯。</description>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          <item>
            <title>Climate Group: Summer 2024 Was Hottest on Record (2024/9/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/climate-group-summer-2024-was-hottest-on-record.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A European climate service says summer 2024 was the hottest on record. The declaration makes it even more likely that this year will also turn out to be the warmest ever measured.</p>
<p>The summer heat data came from the European Union's Copernicus Climate Change Service. <a class="wsw__a" href="https://climate.copernicus.eu/about-us">Copernicus</a> aims to provide detailed data on “past, present and future climate in Europe and the rest of the world.”</p>
<p>The service said that during the months of June, July and August, temperatures worldwide averaged 16.8 degrees Celsius. That was 0.03 degrees warmer than in 2023.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Children cool off as they play on a fountain at Stavros Niarchos Foundation Cultural Center, in Athens, Greece, July 18, 2024. (AP Photo/Petros Giannakouris)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-8369-08dcacd63f83_cx0_cy8_cw94_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Children cool off as they play on a fountain at Stavros Niarchos Foundation Cultural Center, in Athens, Greece, July 18, 2024. (AP Photo/Petros Giannakouris)</span></div>
<p>Copernicus records only date back to 1940. But American, British and Japanese records go back to the mid-19th century. Those records suggest the last 10 years have been the hottest since official climate data measurements started.</p>
<p>Copernicus Director Carlo Buontempo told The Associated Press the Augusts in both 2024 and 2023 tied for the hottest Augusts at 16.82 degrees Celsius. The service reported July was the first time in more than a year that the world did not set a record. But because June 2024 was so much hotter than June 2023, this summer as a whole was the hottest, it said.</p>
<p>Buontempo noted that the high temperatures also likely pushed air <strong>humidity</strong> levels to record highs during the past summer.</p>
<p>The Copernicus chief said all the latest data suggests 2024 will likely break the record for the warmest year ever recorded. “In order for 2024 not to become the warmest on record, we need to see very significant <strong>landscape</strong> cooling for the remaining few months,” Buontempo added. But he noted, that “doesn't look likely.”</p>
<p>Climate scientists say the record temperatures have real <strong>consequences</strong> for many people around the planet.</p>
<p>Jonathan Overpeck is a climate scientist at the University of Michigan. He told the AP the continued warming will lead to “more misery around the world” in places seeing the most extreme temperatures.</p>
<p>Overpeck suggested Phoenix, Arizona as an example. The southwestern American city has already experienced more than 100 days of temperatures over 37.8 degrees Celsius this year.</p>
<p>“With longer and more severe heat waves come more severe <strong>droughts</strong> in some places, and more intense rains and flooding in others,” he said. “Climate change is becoming too <strong>obvious</strong>, and too costly, to ignore,” Overpeck added.</p>
<p>Jennifer Francis is a climate scientist at the Woodwell Climate Research Center in Cape Cod, Massachusetts. She said more communities worldwide are now having to deal with “violent and dangerous” conditions that include extreme heat, floods, wildfires and high winds.</p>
<p>In an email to the AP, Francis compared people living in areas with extreme climate to those living in conflict areas. She said that in both cases, people get so used to the situation they can become “<strong>deaf</strong>” to the severe conditions surrounding them every day.</p>
<p>Copernicus chief Buontempo noted an El Ni<i></i>241;o weather system fueled part of last year's record heat. El Ni<i></i>241;o is a warming of surface temperatures in the eastern and central Pacific Ocean. The event usually causes hot, dry weather in Asia and Australia. It can also drive weather changes in other parts of the world.</p>
<p>But the El Ni<i></i>241;o effect has ended, Buontempo said. Now, human-caused climate change from fossil fuel use is again the main driver of increased temperatures, he said.</p>
<p>“It's really not surprising that we see this, this heat wave, that we see these temperature extremes,” Buontempo said. “We are <strong>bound</strong> to see more.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>humidity</strong> <em>– n. </em>a measurement of how much water there is in the air</p>
<p><strong>landscape</strong> <em>– n. </em>the appearance of an area of land</p>
<p><strong>consequence </strong><em>– n.</em> the result of an action or situation, especially one with a bad result</p>
<p><strong>drought </strong><em>– n.</em> a long period when there is little or no rain and people do not have enough water</p>
<p><strong>obvious </strong><em>– adj. </em>easy to understand or see</p>
<p><strong>deaf </strong><em>– adj. </em>to ignore something because it is too often seen or heard</p>
<p><strong>bound </strong><em>– adj. </em>very likely</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How Bad Are Ultraprocessed Foods? (2024/9/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/how-bad-are-ultraprocessed-foods.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Most Americans eat ultraprocessed foods every day. These are foods that you cannot make at home because they contain flavors and chemicals that change the taste or feel of the food.</p>
<p>Such food may also go through preparation methods that are not possible in a home kitchen. They are usually high in salt, sugar and fat. Americans may eat them in the form of sugary cereals at breakfast, frozen pizzas at dinner, and in-between bites like potato chips, sodas and ice cream.</p>
<p>Ultraprocessed foods make up about 60 percent of the American diet. For children and teenagers, it is even higher – about two-thirds of what they eat.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A customer makes a purchase at a convenience store in Boston in this July 12, 2005 file photo. (AP Photo/Lisa Poole, file)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-795e-08dcc9034574_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A customer makes a purchase at a convenience store in Boston in this July 12, 2005 file photo. (AP Photo/Lisa Poole, file)</span></div>
<p>Scientists have connected eating ultraprocessed foods to poor health results. Being overweight is one such result and that may lead to diabetes and heart disease. Other possible health risks include depression and <strong>dementia</strong>. One recent study suggested that eating these foods may raise the risk of early death.</p>
<p>Nutrition science is complex, though, and most research so far has found connections -- not proof -- regarding the health effects of these foods.</p>
<p>Food manufacturers argue that processing increases food safety and food supplies. They say it also offers a low-cost, easy way to provide a <strong>diverse</strong> and nutritious diet.</p>
<p>The Associated Press asked several nutrition experts to explain these foods so that people can make informed choices.</p>
<p><strong>What are ultraprocessed foods?</strong></p>
<p>Most foods are processed, whether it is by freezing, grinding, <strong>fermentation</strong>, <strong>pasteurization</strong> or other means. In 2009, Brazilian <strong>epidemiologist</strong> Carlos Monteiro and his team first proposed a way to classify foods by how much they are processed, not by their nutrient content. This is called the Nova classification system. It is used by international bodies like the World Health Organization.</p>
<p>Kevin Hall is a researcher who studies <strong>metabolism</strong> and diet at the National Institutes of Health. He said that foods at the top of the Nova four-level <strong>scale</strong> are foods prepared with industrial processes and ingredients such as additives, colors and <strong>preservatives</strong> that you could not use in a home kitchen.</p>
<p>"These are most, but not all, of the packaged foods you see," Hall said.</p>
<p><strong>Are ultraprocessed foods harmful?</strong></p>
<p>Not all processing is unhealthy, Hall noted. Whole-grain bread, yogurt, tofu and infant <strong>formula</strong> are all highly processed, for example. But they are also nutritious.</p>
<p>Still, many studies suggest that diets high in ultraprocessed foods are tied to poor health results. The exact cause is still unclear.</p>
<p>Hall and his partners carried out a small study with 20 people who came to live at a health center for a month. Some of the people ate ultraprocessed foods, while others ate unprocessed foods. The two groups got the same amount of calories, sugar, fat, fiber and nutrients for two weeks. They could eat as much as they liked.</p>
<p>When people ate the diet of ultraprocessed foods, they took in about 500 calories per day more than when they ate unprocessed foods, researchers found. They gained an average of about 1 kilogram during the study period. People who ate only unprocessed foods for the same amount of time lost about 1 kilogram.</p>
<p>A new study is currently taking place and its results should appear next year.</p>
<p><strong>Should ultraprocessed foods be regulated?</strong></p>
<p>Dr. Neena Prasad is director of the Bloomberg Philanthropies' Food Policy Program. She said such foods are often made to be both low-cost and very tasty.</p>
<p>"You just can't stop eating them," Prasad said. She said she believes leaders have enough facts to change policies. This could mean raising taxes on sugary drinks, limiting salt in these foods and controlling how advertisers sell the foods to children.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, Food and Drug Administration Commissioner Robert Califf told a group of food policy experts that ultraprocessed foods are a complex subject. However, Califf said, "We've got to have the scientific basis and then we've got to follow through."</p>
<p><strong>How should consumers manage ultraprocessed foods at home?</strong></p>
<p>Aviva Musicus is science director for the Center for Science in the Public Interest. She said buyers should check information printed on food containers and make choices based on the current U.S. Dietary Guidelines.</p>
<p>"We have really good evidence that added sugar is not great for us. We have evidence that high-<strong>sodium</strong> foods are not great for us," she said.</p>
<p>Musicus added, "We have great evidence that fruits and vegetables which are <strong>minimally</strong> processed are really good for us."</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jonel Aleccia reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>dementia</strong> – <em>n</em>. a mental illness that causes someone to be unable to think clearly or to understand what is real and what is not real</p>
<p><strong>diverse </strong>– <em>adj</em>. made up of people or things that are different from each other</p>
<p><strong>convenient</strong> – <em>adj</em>. allowing you to do something easily or without trouble</p>
<p><strong>fermentation</strong> – <em>n</em>. to go through a chemical change that results in the production of alcohol</p>
<p><strong>pasteurization</strong> – <em>n</em>. a process in which a liquid (such as milk or cream) is heated to a temperature that kills harmful germs and then cooled quickly</p>
<p><strong>epidemiology</strong> – <em>n. </em>the study of how disease spreads and can be controlled</p>
<p><strong>metabolism</strong> – <em>n.</em> the chemical processes by which a plant or an animal uses food, water, and the like5 to grow and heal and to make energy</p>
<p><strong>scale</strong> –<em> n</em>. a range of levels of something from lowest to highest</p>
<p><strong>sodium</strong> – <em>n</em>. a soft silver-white element that is found in salt, baking soda, and other compounds</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Deadly Typhoon Yagi Hits Factories in Northern Vietnam (2024/9/10) | 台风“摩羯”给越南北部工厂造成沉重打击</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/deadly-typhoon-yagi-hits-factories-in-northern-vietnam.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>A powerful ocean storm caused deadly floods and landslides in the northern part of Vietnam over the weekend. Typhoon Yagi is the strongest such storm to hit the country in years.<br/>周末，一场强大的海洋风暴在越南北部造成了致命的洪水和山体滑坡。台风“摩羯”是多年来袭击该国的最强风暴。</p><p>In Phu Tho province, a bridge over the Red River collapsed Monday. Reports said 10 cars and trucks and two motorbikes fell into the river. Rescuers saved three people from the river. Thirteen others are missing.<br/>在富寿省 ，一座横跨红河的桥梁周一坍塌。报道称，10辆汽车、卡车和两辆摩托车掉进了河里。救援人员从河里救出了三个人。另有13人失踪。</p><p>In Cao Ban province, a landslide pushed a bus carrying 20 people into a flooded stream.<br/>在高平省，一场山体滑坡将一辆载有20人的公共汽车推入洪水中。</p><p>In the northern town of Sa Pa, a popular area for foreign visitors, a landslide killed six people on Sunday.<br/>在北部城镇萨帕这个外国游客的热门地区，周日发生了一场山体滑坡，造成六人死亡。</p><p>The storm is responsible for at least 59 deaths in Vietnam, officials said.<br/>官方表示，这场风暴在越南造成至少59人死亡。</p><p>Yagi effects Vietnam's industry<br/>台风“摩羯”对越南工业的影响</p><p>Northern Vietnam is a center for manufacturing. Many foreign companies have operations there, and it is a base for export activity.<br/>越南北部是制造业中心。许多外国公司在那里开展业务，它也是出口基地。</p><p>State newspaper Lao Dong reported many businesses were closed Monday because of heavy damage. The storm destroyed several factories. Others had water leaks that damaged goods and costly equipment.<br/>越南官媒《劳动报》报道称，周一许多企业因严重受损而关闭。这场风暴摧毁了几家工厂。其他工厂则发生漏水，毁坏了货物和昂贵的设备。</p><p>Damage to electrical equipment in Haiphong and Quang Ninh provinces caused power outages Monday. The two provinces are industrial centers for export goods. Factories for electric vehicle maker VinFast, Pegatrong, a supplier for Apple, and electronics supplier USI were among those without power.<br/>海防省和广宁省的电力设备损坏导致周一停电。这两个省是出口商品的工业中心。电动汽车制造商VinFast、苹果供应商和硕以及电子产品供应商USI的工厂都处于停电状态。</p><p>Prime Minister Pham Minh Chinh visited the port city of Haiphong on Sunday and approved aid worth $4.6 million.<br/>越南总理范明政周日访问了港口城市海防，并批准了价值460万美元的援助。</p><p>Korean manufacturer LG Electronics reported no injuries among its employees. But it said the storm flooded a building that stored its finished products, including refrigerators and washing machines. Hong Sun, the chair of the South Korean business association in Vietnam, said there was a lot of damage.<br/>韩国制造商LG电子报告称，其员工没有受伤。但该公司表示，风暴淹没了一座储存其成品的建筑，包括冰箱和洗衣机。韩国驻越南商会主席洪荪表示，损失惨重。</p><p>State-operated power company EVN said more than 5.7 million customers had lost power and many power lines had been broken.<br/>国有电力公司越南电力集团表示，超过570万客户断电，许多电力线被破坏。</p><p>Bruno Jaspaert is head of DEEP C, a Belgian industrial developer and operator. Jaspaert oversees factories in Haiphong and Quang Ninh provinces. He said, “Everyone is scrambling to make sites safe, and stocks dry.”<br/>布鲁诺·贾斯帕尔特是比利时工业开发商和运营商DEEP C的负责人。贾斯帕尔特负责监管海防省和广宁省的工厂。他说：“每个人都在争先恐后地确保厂址安全，库存干燥。”</p><p>The typhoon made landfall on Saturday in northeast Vietnam. At its strongest, the storm had winds measured at 149 kilometers an hour.<br/>这场台风于周六在越南东北部登陆。风暴最强时，风速达每小时149公里。</p><p>By Sunday, the storm had weakened to a tropical depression, a storm below the level of a typhoon. However, Vietnam's weather agency continues to warn of landslides.<br/>截至周日，风暴已减弱为热带低气压，其强度低于台风。然而，越南气象局继续警告山体滑坡风险。</p><p>VN Express reported that the water levels of several rivers in northern Vietnam remain dangerously high.<br/>《越南快报》报道称，越南北部几条河流的水位仍然高得危险。</p><p>The deadly storm also affected other parts of Southeast Asia. Reports say 20 people in the Philippines and four in southern China also died in the storm. On China's Hainan Island, officials reported that more than 50,000 homes were damaged or destroyed.<br/>这场致命的风暴也影响了东南亚的其他地区。报道称，菲律宾有20人，中国南部也有4人在风暴中丧生。在中国海南岛，官员们报告说，有5万多所房屋受损或被毁。</p><p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.<br/>我是小马里奥·里特。(21VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Could Electricity for Bitcoin Mining Become Energy for AI? (2024/9/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/could-electricity-for-bitcoin-mining-become-energy-for-ai.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>U.S. technology companies are increasingly purchasing or<strong> leasing</strong> energy <strong>assets</strong> held by <strong>bitcoin</strong> miners.</p>
<p>These moves come as technology companies hurry to secure a supply of electricity for their growing artificial intelligence (AI) and cloud computing data centers.</p>
<p>Those data centers are driving the fastest increase in U.S. electricity demand since 2000. The demand is growing faster than the <strong>electricity grid</strong>. That means big technology companies, like Amazon and Microsoft, are aiming to secure large amounts of electricity.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A group of buildings housing cryptocurrency miners sits in the foreground of a power generating station at the Scrubgrass Plant in Kennerdell, Pennsylvania, U.S., March 8, 2022. Picture taken March 8, 2022. (REUTERS/Alan Freed)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/144aa8b5-ad35-4706-b267-e0cca74f3300_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A group of buildings housing cryptocurrency miners sits in the foreground of a power generating station at the Scrubgrass Plant in Kennerdell, Pennsylvania, U.S., March 8, 2022. Picture taken March 8, 2022. (REUTERS/Alan Freed)</span></div>
<p>Growing power demand is affecting the cryptocurrency mining industry – an industry that uses a lot of energy.</p>
<p>Some miners are making a profit by leasing or selling their power-connected <strong>infrastructure </strong>and centers. But other miners cannot get enough electricity to stay in business.</p>
<p>Greg Beard is chief of Stronghold Digital Mining, a publicly traded bitcoin mining company based in Pennsylvania.</p>
<p>"The AI battle for <strong>dominance </strong>is a battle being had by the biggest and best <strong>capitalized </strong>companies in the world and they care like their lives depend on it that they win," he said. "Do they care about what they pay for power? Probably not."</p>
<p>Electric Power Research Institute is a non-profit energy research company based in Palo Alto, California. It said in May that data centers could use up to nine percent of total electricity produced in the U.S. by 2030. That is more than double their current use. This change comes as technology companies are paying a lot to grow their computing centers.</p>
<p>The International Energy Agency (IEA) says that data centers currently account for about 1 to 1.3 percent of world electricity use. Crypto mining uses 0.4 percent. The IEA says that difference is expected to grow.</p>
<p>Experts expect 20 percent of bitcoin mining power<strong> capacity</strong> to move to AI by the end of 2027. Over the past year, bitcoin miners have increasingly competed with AI data center owners for the same power production centers and business deals. That is what heads of more than six publicly traded U.S. crypto mining companies told Reuters.</p>
<p>One example took place in Pennsylvania. Marathon Digital Holdings is the world's biggest publicly traded bitcoin miner. Two <strong>sources</strong> who know about the situation said the company was among those considering a nuclear-powered data center owned by Talen Energy in Pennsylvania. But technology company Amazon bought the center in a deal announced in March.</p>
<p>Many large miners that own land and are connected to power centers are changing the way they do business. They are marketing their property and energy services to AI and cloud computing companies and doing less crypto mining.</p>
<p>"We've gotten a lot of interest from everyone from an Amazon or Google," said Kerri Langlais. He is an official for bitcoin miner TeraWulf. The company has a center in New York that can produce 770 megawatts of electricity.</p>
<p>Core Scientific is a crypto miner that a court recently permitted to restructure after its earlier financial failure. In June, Core Scientific became the first bitcoin miner to announce a major agreement. The deal was to lease its power-connected production centers to the company CoreWeave, which is supported by Nvidia. The deals are estimated to be worth more than $6.7 billion over 12 years.</p>
<p>Several miners have since said they would lease or act as <strong>subcontractors</strong> to develop AI data centers.</p>
<p>Morgan Stanley said providing electricity for AI and cloud computing could be profitable for big crypto miners. The investment bank said it could make their centers as much as five times more valuable.</p>
<p>Morgan Stanley also said technology companies could save billions of dollars by buying or leasing space from a miner with at least 100 megawatts of electricity production. It said such deals could cut the wait times for a data center to launch by about 3.5 years.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Laila Kearney and Mrinalika Roy reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>lease</strong> <em>– v.</em> to use (something) for a period of time in return for payment</p>
<p><strong>asset </strong><em>–n.</em> something that is of value that can usually be exchanged for money</p>
<p><strong>bitcoin</strong> <em>–n.</em> a digital currency created for use in online transactions</p>
<p><strong>electricity grid</strong> <em>–n. </em>the system of electricity generation, transmission and distribution that covers a large area of a country</p>
<p><strong>infrastructure</strong> <em>– n.</em> the resources (such as buildings or equipment) required for an activity</p>
<p><strong>dominance</strong> <em>–n.</em> the ability to control</p>
<p><strong>capitalized</strong> <em>— adj.</em> to have a lot of money or to possess the ability to borrow or get money from investors easily</p>
<p><strong>capacity </strong><em>– n. </em>power to produce, perform, or deploy</p>
<p><strong>source</strong><em> –n.</em> the provider of information about a subject</p>
<p><strong>subcontractor</strong> <em>– n.</em> an individual or business contracting to perform part or all of another's contract</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>SpaceX Mission to Include First Spacewalk for Private Citizens (2024/9/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/spacex-mission-to-include-first-spacewalk-for-private-citizens.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A private space <strong>mission</strong> will seek to launch non-astronauts to a high orbit and include the first private spacewalks in history.</p>
<p>The American space company SpaceX's flight is cleared to launch from Florida's Kennedy Space Center beginning September 7. The American space agency NASA operates the center. The exact launch date will depend on weather conditions.</p>
<p>American businessman Jared Isaacman organized and paid for the mission, called <a class="wsw__a" href="https://polarisprogram.com/dawn/" target="_blank">Polaris Dawn</a>. He and three people will crew the mission. Isaacman is the head of payment processing company Shift4Payments. He has an estimated personal worth of $2 billion. But he has not said publicly how much he paid SpaceX for the Polaris Dawn mission.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Anna Menon, Scott Poteet, Jared Isaacman and Sarah Gillis, crew members of Polaris Dawn, a private human spaceflight mission, attend a press conference at the Kennedy Space Center in Cape Canaveral, Florida, U.S. August 19, 2024. (REUTERS/Joe Skipper)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/8114e020-690b-45ec-b003-d3fedfcf902e_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Anna Menon, Scott Poteet, Jared Isaacman and Sarah Gillis, crew members of Polaris Dawn, a private human spaceflight mission, attend a press conference at the Kennedy Space Center in Cape Canaveral, Florida, U.S. August 19, 2024. (REUTERS/Joe Skipper)</span></div>
<p>The crewmembers will travel in SpaceX's Crew Dragon spacecraft on a SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket. The company expects the spacecraft to reach an altitude of about 1,400 kilometers. That would be the highest any crewed mission has reached since NASA's Apollo program ended in the early 1970s.</p>
<p>Isaacman is the mission commander for Polaris Dawn. Also taking part in the flight will be Scott Poteet, a retired U.S. Air Force Colonel and two SpaceX employees, Sarah Gillis and Anna Menon. Gillis is a mission specialist at SpaceX, while Menon is a lead space operations engineer. The crew is expected to spend five days in orbit.</p>
<p>Polaris Dawn will reach its highest altitude on its first day. The Crew Dragon will briefly enter the Van Allen radiation belt, an area filled with high-energy charged particles that can present health risks to humans over extended periods.</p>
<p>This will provide a chance to test the effectiveness of SpaceX's newly designed spacesuits. SpaceX says the clothing is equipped with data instruments, cameras and improved <strong>mobility</strong> systems. SpaceX says tests of the spacesuit will help the company design and develop future space missions to the moon and Mars.</p>
<p>A statement by SpaceX <a class="wsw__a" href="https://polarisprogram.com/dawn/">said</a> one main goal of Polaris Dawn will be to carry out research “with the aim of better understanding the effects of spaceflight and space radiation on human health.”</p>
<p>Speaking about the mission's risks, Isaacman told reporters, "Whatever risk is <strong>associated</strong> <strong>with</strong> it, it is worth it." He added, "We have no idea what it could do to really change the <strong>trajectory</strong> of humankind ... there has to be some first steps in this direction."</p>
<p>The crew will orbit nearly three times higher than the International Space Station (ISS). But this is far short of the record-breaking distance of over 399,117 kilometers set by NASA's Apollo 13 crew in 1970.</p>
<p>Isaacman is expected to guide the other crew members on the mission's planned spacewalk on day three of the mission. Each member is expected to spend about 20 minutes in space.</p>
<p>So far, only government astronauts from the U.S., former Soviet Union and Russia, the European Space Agency, Canada and China have carried out spacewalks. More than 270 spacewalks, using American and Russian spacesuits, have been carried out from the ISS since its launch in 2000, Reuters news agency reports.</p>
<p>The next day will be spent testing laser-based satellite communication between the spacecraft and Starlink, SpaceX's internet satellite system. The laser method – which has also been tested by NASA – is designed to greatly increase space communication speeds.</p>
<p>The crew also plans to carry out 40 experiments aimed at improving our understanding of human health during long space missions. Among these will be tests with special contact lenses containing microelectronics that can continuously identify changes in eye pressure and shape.</p>
<p>At the end of the mission, Crew Dragon will aim for a parachute landing off the coast of Florida. A SpaceX recovery ship will be waiting for the crew's arrival.</p>
<p>Polaris Dawn is the first of three planned missions under the Polaris program. The second Polaris mission will also use a Dragon capsule, while the third and final is expected to use SpaxeX's Starship rocket. SpaceX chief Elon Musk has said his company plans to use Starship to carry future space travelers to the moon and Mars.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from Reuters, Agence France-Presse, SpaceX and Polaris.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>mission</strong><em> – n. </em>an important project or trip, especially involving space travel</p>
<p><strong>mobility</strong> <em>– n. </em>the ability to walk and move freely</p>
<p><strong>associate </strong><em>– </em><em>v. </em>to connect someone or something in your mind with someone or something else</p>
<p><strong>trajectory </strong><em>– n.</em> the curved path an object follows after it has been thrown or shot into the air</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Gazan Teen Musician Sings for Children at War (2024/9/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/gazan-teen-musician-sings-for-children-at-war.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In the war-damaged streets of northern Gaza's Jabalia refugee camp, 15-year-old Youssef Saad rides his bicycle with his musical instrument <strong>strapped</strong> on his back. The instrument he carries is called an oud. The sound of the oud is common in much Middle Eastern music.</p>
<p>Saad is bringing his instrument to a day center for children in the camp. There, he plays the oud and sings for children who have suffered through 11 months of war.</p>
<p>Saad says he tries to offer the children a little happiness or a way to temporarily forget about their difficult situation.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this frame captured from video, Palestinian teenager Youssef Saad sits on the rubble of his house as he plays oud to bring joy to children, amid Israel-Hamas conflict, in Jabalia refugee camp in the northern Gaza Strip September 2, 2024. (REUTERS/Mahmoud Issa)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/392454cc-1821-461a-832a-c00a0a264626_cx0_cy5_cw89_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this frame captured from video, Palestinian teenager Youssef Saad sits on the rubble of his house as he plays oud to bring joy to children, amid Israel-Hamas conflict, in Jabalia refugee camp in the northern Gaza Strip September 2, 2024. (REUTERS/Mahmoud Issa)</span></div>
<p>"The homes in my city were once full of dreams," Saad said. As he spoke, he looked at the destroyed buildings in the refugee camp. Before the war, the refugee camp had a large population. “Now, they're gone,” he said.</p>
<p>Saad was studying music at the Edward Said National Conservatory of Music in nearby Gaza City before the war started. Like many other buildings, the conservatory was destroyed during the fighting. Saad and his four <strong>siblings</strong> are now living with relatives after his own home was destroyed.</p>
<p>Saad's father, a government worker with the Palestinian Authority, always supported Saad's dream of becoming a musician. Saad now centers his efforts on playing his oud and singing at the Jabalia center for children.</p>
<p>The war started after the Palestinian Islamist group Hamas attacked Israel on October 7 last year. Hamas terrorists killed some 1,200 people and took 250 hostages from southern Israel, according to Israeli estimates.</p>
<p>Since then, Israel has sought to destroy Hamas in Gaza. According to the Hamas-run health ministry, almost 41,000 Palestinians have been killed in the conflict. Airstrikes and fighting have destroyed thousands of buildings in Gaza.</p>
<p>"Every house holds a tragedy," Saad said. "Some have lost their mother, others their father, their neighbor, or their friend."</p>
<p>Even with the danger, Saad has a strong desire to continue his work with the children.</p>
<p>"We try to help improve their mental health, even if it means putting myself at risk," he said. "This is my duty to the children."</p>
<p>Saad added that he lives by an expression that carries him through the darkest days: "If you live, live free, or die standing like trees."</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith adapted this story for VOA Learning English based on reporting from Reuters news agency. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>strap </strong><em>-v</em>. to secure or carry an object using flexible material such as leather or nylon.</p>
<p><strong>sibling(s) </strong><em>- n</em>. one of two or more persons having the same parents; brothers and sisters</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>‘Dead Giveaway’ Is Not as Dark as It Sounds (2024/9/8)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/dead-giveaway----not-as-dark-as-it-sounds.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">07 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories</em> from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>On this program we explore words and expressions in the English language. We give examples, notes on usage and sometimes use them in short conversations.</p>
<p>Today we talk about an expression that sounds very serious and dangerous: a <u>dead giveaway</u>. A “giveaway” is just as it sounds: You give something to someone else.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - An archeologist holds an ancient mummified bird, found inside the burial site, Tomb of Tutu, at al-Dayabat, Sohag, Egypt, April 5, 2019. (Reuters/Mohamed Abd El Ghany)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/034E3BBC-76CB-4FEE-8297-E958461D2688_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - An archeologist holds an ancient mummified bird, found inside the burial site, Tomb of Tutu, at al-Dayabat, Sohag, Egypt, April 5, 2019. (Reuters/Mohamed Abd El Ghany)</span></div>
<p>But a <u>dead giveaway</u> has nothing to do with tragedy or death.</p>
<p>In this expression, the word “dead” has another meaning you might not have known about.</p>
<p>In some common usages, the adjective “dead” can mean exact, correct or complete. For example, if someone is <u>dead right</u>, they are completely correct and there is no doubt about it. And, if someone is <u>dead wrong</u>, they are totally wrong.</p>
<p>In some trades, the word “dead” is a really good thing. For example, when something is <u>dead center</u>, it is exactly at the center. In building, <u>dead level</u> means perfectly <strong>horizontal</strong>—just what you want. However, you never say “dead plumb.” Plumb already means perfectly <strong>vertical</strong>.</p>
<p>So, a <u>dead giveaway</u> is a detail or action that gives away the truth completely and totally. It is like a <strong>clue</strong> that answers a question. A <u>dead giveaway</u> shows a truth, fact, or <strong>intention</strong> in an <strong>obvious </strong>way.</p>
<p>In other words, a <u>dead giveaway</u> leaves little room for misunderstanding.</p>
<p>Now, let's hear the expression in some examples.</p>
<p><em>A completely dark house and a huge pile of mail outside the door were two <u>dead giveaways</u> that no one had been home in quite some time.</em></p>
<p><em>She said that she was staying home for the night. But with all the <strong>makeup</strong> on her face, her hair <strong>styled</strong>, and her party clothes on, her appearance was a <u>dead giveaway</u>. She was clearly going out. </em></p>
<p><em>The expression on his face was a <u>dead giveaway</u> that he was guilty. He couldn't even look me in the eyes! </em></p>
<p>English has another expression that is similar. A <u>telltale sign</u> is an important detail or fact the clarifies the truth. It gives more supporting evidence.</p>
<p>We often pair telltale with the words “sign” or “<strong>symptom</strong>.”</p>
<p>Let's hear some examples:</p>
<p><em>Well, my friend has missed work all week and hasn't responded to my calls. Those may be <u>telltale symptoms</u> of a bigger problem. </em></p>
<p><em>When the parents returned from their trip, they saw <u>telltale signs</u> everywhere in the house that their children had thrown a party. </em></p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this <em>Words and Their Stories.</em></p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>horizontal </strong><em>–n.</em> a line that is goes from side to side perfectly as though it is following the horizon</p>
<p><strong>vertical </strong><em>–adj.</em> going up and down at a right angle from the horizontal</p>
<p><strong>intention </strong><em>–n.</em> what someone means to do</p>
<p><strong>obvious </strong><em>–adj.</em> without doubt or confusion; clear and straightforward</p>
<p><strong>symptom </strong><em>–n.</em> the sign that something is present, especially a disease</p>
<p><strong>makeup </strong><em>–n.</em> products that are put on the face to improve a person's appearance</p>
<p><strong>styled </strong><em>–adj.</em> being formed and shaped to look appealing to others</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>South Korea’s Kimchi Threatened by Warming Weather (2024/9/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/south-korea-s-kimchi-threatened-by-warming-weather.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>One of the most popular foods in South Korea is kimchi. It is a kind of <strong>fermented</strong> cabbage or other vegetables. Now farmers, manufacturers and scientists say climate change is affecting the quality and quantity of the napa cabbage used to make the dish.</p>
<p>Cabbage grows best in cooler climates. Growers usually plant it in mountainous areas where temperatures during the summer growing season used to stay mostly below 25 degrees Celsius.</p>
<p>Studies show that warmer weather tied to climate change is now threatening these crops. There may even come a time when it will be too hot for South Korea to be able to grow napa cabbage.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Kimchi in a jar at the Kimchi Culture Institute in Namyangju, South Korea, August 21, 2024. (REUTERS/Kim Soo-hyeon)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/ee2ae5e9-a271-4fc2-95bf-dfb34d4073ef_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Kimchi in a jar at the Kimchi Culture Institute in Namyangju, South Korea, August 21, 2024. (REUTERS/Kim Soo-hyeon)</span></div>
<p>Lee Young-gyu studies diseases that attack plants. He said the best temperatures for cabbage are between 18 and 21 degrees Celsius.</p>
<p>In the fields and in <strong>kitchens</strong> - both in factories and homes - farmers and kimchi makers are already feeling the change.</p>
<p><strong>Spicy</strong>, fermented kimchi is made from other vegetables such as radish, cucumber, and green onion, but the most popular form is still mostly cabbage.</p>
<p>The Agriculture Ministry calls Lee Ha-yeon a Kimchi Master because of her knowledge of kimchi. She said that in higher temperatures, the heart of the cabbage goes bad, and the root softens.</p>
<p>"If this continues, then in the summertime we might have to give up cabbage kimchi," said Lee.</p>
<p><strong>Shrinking crop area</strong></p>
<p>The government <strong>statistics</strong> agency reports the area of highland cabbage farmed last year was about 4,000 hectares. That is less than half of what it was 20 years ago.</p>
<p>The Rural Development Administration, a state farming organization, predicts that the farmed area for napa cabbage will shrink in the next 25 years to just 44 hectares. They expect there will be no cabbage grown in the highlands by 2090.</p>
<p>Researchers point to three reasons for such a small area of crops. They include higher temperatures, unpredictable heavy rains and unwanted insects and diseases that become more difficult to control in the warmer and longer summers.</p>
<p>South Korea's kimchi industry is already fighting lower-priced imports from China, which are mostly served in restaurants. Those imports rose by almost seven percent for the year through the end of July. That is the highest level ever.</p>
<p><strong>New cabbage varieties</strong></p>
<p>The government is trying to prevent high prices and shortages by storing large amounts of cabbage. Scientists are also racing to develop crop <strong>varieties</strong> that can grow in warmer climates, handle changes in rainfall and resist <strong>fungal</strong> infections.</p>
<p>Seventy-one-year-old Kim Si-gap is a farmer who has worked in the cabbage fields of the eastern region of Gangneung all his life. Kim fears these varieties will be more costly to grow. And they might not taste the same.</p>
<p>"When we see the reports that there will come a time in Korea when we can no longer grow cabbage, it was shocking on the one hand and also sad at the same time," Kim said.</p>
<p>"Kimchi is something we cannot not have on the table. What are we going to do if this happens?"</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Sebin Choi, Hyun Young Yi, Daewoung Kim and Jihyun Jeon reported this story for Reuters. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>ferment</strong> – v. to go through a chemical change that results in the production of alcohol</p>
<p><strong>kitchen </strong><em>–n.</em> a room where cooking is done</p>
<p><strong>spicy</strong> - <em>of food: </em>flavored with or containing strong spices and especially ones that cause a burning feeling in your mouth</p>
<p><strong>statistic</strong> – <em>n</em>. number that represents a piece of information (such as information about how often something is done, how common something is, or the like)</p>
<p><strong>variety</strong> <em>– n.</em> a particular kind of person or thing</p>
<p><strong>fungal </strong><em>–adj.</em> related to fungus, a form of life that is neither plant nor animal such as mushrooms</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How to Summarize (2024/9/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/how-to-summarize.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Yutaro in Japan about how to summarize what you hear or read.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/ffd46340-4068-4ddf-9eee-82598b433e09_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>I enjoy listening to VOA Learning English every night. I have a question about "summarizing." How do I summarize a speech, paper, or other <strong>text</strong> I've listened to? I have to improve my summary skills to pass the upcoming entrance exam.</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>Thank you for writing to us, Yutaro. I'm happy to answer this question.</p>
<p>“Summarize” is the verb form of the word “summary.” A summary briefly explains the main ideas of a piece of writing or a speech but does not include all the details. It is often only one or two <strong>paragraphs</strong> long.</p>
<p>Being able to summarize is a useful skill to have, not only for passing exams but also for working in professions. To summarize well, you need to separate the main ideas from less important details.</p>
<p>You can use the following method to do this:</p>
<p>First, read or listen to the material one time without writing any notes. This will help your mind <strong>focus </strong>on understanding the ideas. Next, read or listen again. But this time, write notes and be sure to identify the main ideas along with some details. You can mark main ideas by putting a star next to them, underlining them, or using a colored pen to mark them.</p>
<p>Next, take a separate piece of paper and try to write only the main ideas. Then, decide which details are necessary to include so that the main ideas are clear. Remember, in a summary, you cannot include every detail. This is sometimes difficult to do at first and requires careful thought.</p>
<p>If you can, let a few hours pass between the time when you first take notes and the time when you write the main ideas. This is a good way to see if you can remember and organize the main points in your mind.</p>
<p>You can also try the following method to prepare a summary:</p>
<p>Try to explain the material as if you were talking about it with your friends or family. In those situations, you would naturally just focus on the main ideas and possibly add a few important details. <strong>Practice</strong> explaining the ideas by speaking out loud. When you speak, you will probably discover the things you can explain clearly and those things you need to <strong>check</strong> again.</p>
<p>Finally, you can write the summary, keeping in mind the way you presented the main ideas when you spoke about them.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, do you have a question about American English? Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>text</strong><strong> </strong>–n. written words; a piece of writing</p>
<p><strong>paragraph </strong><em>–n. </em>usually a group of sentences that explain one idea</p>
<p><strong>focus</strong> <em>–v.</em> to direct your attention on something</p>
<p><strong>practice</strong> –v. to do a task several times in an effort to learn it and to do it better</p>
<p><strong>check</strong><strong> </strong>–v. to look or read over something you have already done to make sure it is correct</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Question if Melting Ice in Antarctica Will Continue to Increase (2024/9/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/scientists-question-if-melting-ice-in-antarctica-will-continue-to-increase.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Increasing amounts of ice have been melting on the continent of Antarctica over the past ten years. Now, scientists are wondering if the increase in melting is temporary or if it will continue—and perhaps melt even faster—for years into the future.</p>
<p>Nearly 1,500 experts who study Antarctica gathered in southern Chile last week to share results of their research. They discussed the extreme weather events that struck parts of the continent this year: heavy rainfall, unusually warm temperatures, and strong dry winds.</p>
<p>The researchers say these events added to recent increases in melting. However, detailed weather data for Antarctica dates back only about 40 years. That is one reason climate scientists are unsure if the current melting is temporary or the beginning of a longer <strong>trend</strong>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This 2020 photo provided by the British Antarctic Survey shows the Thwaites glacier in Antarctica. (David Vaughan/British Antarctic Survey via AP, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/fe01afdc-9d71-4e31-90f2-0732713c9818_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This 2020 photo provided by the British Antarctic Survey shows the Thwaites glacier in Antarctica. (David Vaughan/British Antarctic Survey via AP, File)</span></div>
<p>NASA estimates show a possible 58-meter rise in the average worldwide sea level if all Antarctic ice melted. Studies have shown that about a third of the world's population lives below 100 vertical meters of sea level.</p>
<p>Liz Keller is a paleoclimate specialist from the Victoria University of Wellington in New Zealand. She says scientists have never before seen Antarctic ice melting so quickly. She also spoke about the increasing amounts of carbon dioxide gas, CO2, in the earth's atmosphere.</p>
<p>“You might see the same rise in CO2 over thousands of years, and now it's happened in 100 years," Keller said. Carbon dioxide traps heat in the atmosphere.</p>
<p>Mike Weber is a paleooceanographer from the University of Bonn in Germany. He studies the movements of Antarctic ice over thousands of years. He said records dating back 21,000 years show at least eight times when the ice melted quickly. He added that the data show the periods of ice loss sometimes lasted for hundreds of years. This led to much higher sea levels around the world.</p>
<p>Weber said scientists want to know if the melting seen during the last ten years has started a melting trend that will last for centuries.</p>
<p>"Maybe we're entering such a <strong>phase</strong> right now," he said. "If we are, at least for now, there will be no stopping it."</p>
<p>Some of the scientists in Chile agreed that the most harmful rise in sea level can still be avoided if fossil fuel <strong>emissions</strong> decrease. Weber noted that when glaciers melt, the earth's land can rise because there is less weight pushing it down. Recent research suggests that if the melting does not happen too quickly, the rising land could nearly equal the rise in sea level. But if the melting happens too quickly, the rise in land could not meet the increase in sea level.</p>
<p>"If we keep emissions low, we can stop this eventually," said Weber. "If we keep them high, we have a runaway situation and we cannot do anything."</p>
<p>Mathieu Casado is a paleoclimate and polar meteorologist at France's Climate and Environment Sciences Laboratory. He has examined ice from all over Antarctica to estimate temperatures dating back 800,000 years.</p>
<p>Casado said that the last time the Earth was this warm was 125,000 years ago and that sea levels then were 6 to 9 meters higher. He and other scientists said the speed and amount at which carbon is entering the atmosphere has never been so high.</p>
<p>Gino Casassa is a glaciologist and head of the Chilean Antarctic Institute. He said that current estimates show sea levels rising by 4 meters by 2100 and more if emissions continue to grow.</p>
<p>"What happens in Antarctica doesn't stay in Antarctica," said Casassa, adding that global atmospheric, ocean and weather systems are linked to the continent.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Alexander Villegas reported this story for Reuters news agency. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>trend </strong><em>-n. </em>a tendency or development continuing over a period of time</p>
<p><strong>phase </strong><em>-n. </em>a particular stage or period of time in a process</p>
<p><strong>emissions </strong><em>-n. </em>gases released into the atmosphere</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Japan Considers Four-day Work Weeks (2024/9/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/japan-considers-four-day-work-weeks.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Japan is a nation so hardworking that the Japanese language has a term for working oneself to death. Now, the government is trying to deal with a labor shortage.</p>
<p>One solution is to get more people and companies to accept four-day workweeks. The Japanese government first supported a shorter working week in 2021. Few companies have signed on, however. The Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare said only about eight percent of companies permit three days off a week, while seven percent give their workers the required one day off.</p>
<p>Hoping to get small and medium-sized businesses to change, the government started a "work style reform" campaign. It pushes shorter hours and other <strong>flexible </strong>plans for work along with paid time off and limits on overtime. The labor ministry recently started offering free services and resources to help companies make the change.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Commuters walk in a passageway during a rush hour at Shinagawa Station, Feb. 14, 2024, in Tokyo. " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/83f41a40-d8a8-4b01-9e53-5818368a08f8_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Commuters walk in a passageway during a rush hour at Shinagawa Station, Feb. 14, 2024, in Tokyo. </span></div>
<p><strong>'Innovating how we work'</strong></p>
<p>A ministry website explains the "hatarakikata kaikaku" campaign, which means "<strong>innovating</strong> how we work." It says that when workers can choose how they work, they will have a better outlook on the future and the economy will grow.</p>
<p>The department handling the new support services for businesses says only about three companies have asked for their advice.</p>
<p>Such changes will not come easily in the Japanese culture, where being a “workaholic,” or frequently working overtime, has long been highly valued. That is credited for the country's national recovery and fast economic growth after World War II.</p>
<p>There is great pressure to be the same as the others in one's work group. People usually take vacations at the same time of year as their co-workers. Although the law and labor agreements limit overtime, some work longer hours without pay.</p>
<p><strong>Death from overwork</strong></p>
<p>A recent government report dealt with "karoshi." That is the Japanese term meaning "death from overwork.” The report said Japan has at least 54 such deaths a year, including from heart attacks.</p>
<p>Tim Craig wrote a book called <em>Cool Japan: Case Studies from Japan's Cultural and Creative Industries</em>.</p>
<p>"Work is a big deal here. It's not just a way to make money, although it is that, too," said Craig.</p>
<p>Some officials think it is time to change that way of thinking to save the workforce. Japan's birth rate continues to fall, and the work culture is said to be one reason for that. Government reports expect that, at the current rate, the working age population will drop by 40 percent to 45 million by 2065.</p>
<p>Supporters of the three-days-off model say it helps people remain in the workforce longer. It would give them more time to raise children and care for older relatives. For retirees living on retirement pensions, it would provide additional income.</p>
<p><strong>More time for family</strong></p>
<p>Akiko Yokohama works at Spelldata, a technology company that lets employees work a four-day work week. She takes Wednesdays off along with Saturdays and Sundays. The extra day off allows her to get her hair done, go to other <strong>appointments</strong> or go shopping.</p>
<p>Her husband works in real estate. He also gets Wednesdays off but works weekends, which is common in his industry. Yokohama said that it lets <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_VCzGJW20">her</a> and her husband go on midweek family outings with their elementary-school age child.</p>
<p>But there are signs of change. A few companies, including Uniqlo, Ricoh and Hitachi have begun offering a four-day workweek.</p>
<p>A recent Gallup public opinion study measured employee <strong>engagement</strong>. Gallup said Japan has among the least engaged workers of all nationalities it has studied. Only six percent of the Japanese who answered described themselves as engaged at work compared to the worldwide average of 23 percent.</p>
<p>That means relatively few Japanese workers felt happy and highly involved in their workplace. Most were putting in their hours without investing <strong>passion</strong> or energy.</p>
<p>Kanako Ogino is president of Tokyo-based NS Group. She thinks offering flexible hours is needed for filling jobs in the service industry, where women are most of the work force. The company offers 30 different <strong>scheduling</strong> patterns, including a four-day workweek, but also taking long periods off in between work.</p>
<p>To ensure none of the NS Group's workers feel out of place for choosing a different schedule, Ogino asks each of her 4,000 employees twice a year how they want to work. Voicing your own needs is disapproved in Japan, where you are expected to sacrifice for the common good.</p>
<p>"The view in Japan was: You are cool the more hours you work, putting in free overtime," Ogino said with a laugh. "But there is no dream in such a life."</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins. And I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Yuri Kageyama reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>flexible</strong> – <em>adj</em>. easily changed</p>
<p><strong>overtime </strong>– <em>n</em>. time spent working at your job that is in addition to your normal working hours</p>
<p><strong>innovate</strong> – <em>v</em>. to do something in a new way</p>
<p><strong>appointment </strong>–n. an activity that you need to go to at a certain time such as a visit to a doctor or dentist</p>
<p><strong>engagement</strong> – <em>n</em>. the act or state of being involved with something</p>
<p><strong>passion</strong> – <em>n</em>. a strong feeling of enthusiasm or excitement for something or about doing something</p>
<p><strong>schedule</strong> – <em>v</em>. to plan (something) at a certain time</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Bob Dylan Teaches You about Questions, Count Nouns (2024/9/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/bob-dylan-teaches-you-about-questions-count-nouns.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Nobel prize winner Bob Dylan is considered to be one of the best American <strong>songwriters</strong>.</p>
<p><em>The answer, my friend, is blowin' in the wind </em></p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/751c1814-7982-4e08-8553-d7162a1152b4_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p><em>The answer is blowin' in the wind</em></p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p>In today's <em>Everyday Grammar</em>, we will explore how <em>Blowin' in the Wind</em>, a famous Bob Dylan song, can teach you about English grammar. You will learn about question words, nouns and more.</p>
<p>Let's begin by listening to part of the song:</p>
<p><strong>Blowin' in the Wind</strong></p>
<p><em>Yes, and how many years must a mountain exist </em></p>
<p><em>Before it is washed to the sea? </em></p>
<p><em>And how many years can some people exist </em></p>
<p><em>Before they're allowed to be free?</em></p>
<p>Dylan's song has a group of questions, one after the other, followed by an answer:</p>
<p><em>The answer, my friend, is blowin' in the wind </em></p>
<p><em>The answer is blowin' in the wind</em></p>
<p><strong>Questions</strong></p>
<p>Let's explore the grammar of the words in greater detail. In English, we use question words – what, where, how - to ask for information.</p>
<p>The word “how” generally asks about manner – the way in which something is done. For example, imagine you saw a <strong>circus</strong> performer swallow fire.</p>
<p>You might ask them:</p>
<p><em>How did you do that?</em></p>
<p>But when used with words such as “much” and “many,” how asks about <strong>quantities</strong>.</p>
<p>For example, you might hear an American ask the following about a price:</p>
<p><em>How much money does it cost?</em></p>
<p>Or</p>
<p><em>How much [money] does it cost?</em></p>
<p>Here is another example of a quantity question:</p>
<p><em>How many people came to the Bob Dylan concert?</em></p>
<p>But, how do we know when to use “much” and when to use “many?</p>
<p><strong>Noncount vs. count nouns</strong></p>
<p>The answer is about nouns.</p>
<p>We describe nouns as either common or proper. Common nouns include words such as music, song or guitar. The words themselves do not point to an exact, specific thing. Proper nouns include words with an exact, single meaning - Bob Dylan, the United States of America, <em>Blowin' in the Wind</em> and so on.</p>
<p>There are two kinds of common nouns – count and noncount nouns. Count nouns include words like guitar or song. You can count guitars and songs. Consider the following statements:</p>
<p><em>I own five guitars. </em></p>
<p><em>I wrote 3 songs.</em></p>
<p>The question form “how many...” is used with plural count nouns. For example:</p>
<p><em>How many guitars do you own? </em></p>
<p><em>I own five guitars.</em></p>
<p>Noncount nouns include words like money or music.</p>
<p><em>I need to make money. </em></p>
<p><em>I love music.</em></p>
<p>In general, the question form “how much...” is used with noncount nouns.</p>
<p><em>How much money did you spend on that new guitar? </em></p>
<p><em>I spent all of the money that I earned last week!</em></p>
<p>How does this discussion connect with the Bob Dylan song?</p>
<p><strong>A series of questions using countable nouns</strong></p>
<p>If you listen carefully to the Bob Dylan song, you will notice that the structure “how many...” plays an important part.</p>
<p><em>Yes, and how many times can a man turn his head</em></p>
<p><em>And<strong> pretend</strong> that he just doesn't see? </em></p>
<p>And consider these lines:</p>
<p><em>Yes, and how many ears must one man have </em></p>
<p><em>Before he can hear people cry? </em></p>
<p><em>Yes, and how many deaths will it take till he knows </em></p>
<p><em>That too many people have died?</em></p>
<p>Questions about count nouns make the base of Dylan's song. He does not sing about noncount nouns. He does not ask “how much...”?</p>
<p>And the answer to his questions is always the same:</p>
<p><em>The answer, my friend, is blowin' in the wind </em></p>
<p><em>The answer is blowin' in the wind</em></p>
<p><strong>Closing thoughts</strong></p>
<p>The next time you listen to any song in English, try to look for some kind of <strong>pattern</strong>.</p>
<p>One way to think about Dylan's song is that it is about questions, answers and count nouns. But other songs have different structures, ideas and grammar points. By carefully studying songs, you can learn a lot about English grammar.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>John Russell wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. Caty Weaver was the editor.</em></p><div id="bottom">
<ins class="adsbygoogle" data-ad-client="ca-pub-3585518775245612" data-ad-format="auto" data-ad-slot="9284795419" data-full-width-responsive="true" style="display:block; text-align:center;"></ins>
<script>(adsbygoogle =window.adsbygoogle ||[]).push({});</script></div>
<p><em>______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>songwriter</strong> <em>– n.</em> a person who writes the words or music to songs</p>
<p><strong>quantity </strong><em>– n.</em> an amount or number of something</p>
<p><strong>pretend</strong><em> – v.</em> to act as if something is true when it is not true</p>
<p><strong>ear </strong><em>– n.</em> the part of the body that you hear with</p>
<p><strong>pattern</strong><em> – n.</em> the regular and repeated way in which something happens or is done</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Tech Tip: How to Make Your Smartphone Last Longer (2024/9/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/tech-tip-how-to-make-your-smartphone-last-longer.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">04 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Many people are now holding on to their smartphones longer than in the past. This is true for several reasons. The cost of phones has been rising for years. And device <strong>updates</strong> are no longer as meaningful as before.</p>
<p>This has made it even more important for smartphone users to take good care of their devices. But how long can a smartphone user expect their device to last? Many experts say if they are cared for effectively, phones can last up to five years, possibly even longer.</p>
<p>Chris Hauk is a technology expert with the website <a class="wsw__a" href="https://pixelprivacy.com/">Pixel Privacy</a>. He told The Associated Press (AP), “As long as you take care of your phone and keep it updated, you're going to get at least four or five good years of use out of it."</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file photo, the iPhone 15 Pro is shown after its introduction on the Apple campus, Sept. 12, 2023, in Cupertino, Calif. (AP Photo/Jeff Chiu, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-b1df-08dcc937ae4b_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">In this file photo, the iPhone 15 Pro is shown after its introduction on the Apple campus, Sept. 12, 2023, in Cupertino, Calif. (AP Photo/Jeff Chiu, File)</span></div>
<p>The AP offers these additional tips for smartphone users looking to keep their devices for as long as possible.</p>
<p><strong>Battery care</strong></p>
<p>One of the most important elements affecting smartphone life is the <strong>battery</strong>.</p>
<p>iPhone maker Apple <a class="wsw__a" href="https://support.apple.com/en-gb/105105">says</a> a rechargeable battery's age has little to do with when it was manufactured. Instead, it depends on a complex mix of things, including temperature and charging history. “As lithium-ion batteries chemically age, the amount of charge they can hold <strong>diminishes</strong>, resulting in reduced battery life and reduced <strong>peak </strong>performance,” Apple says.</p>
<p>Samsung, which uses the Android operating system in its smartphones, says its lithium-ion batteries perform best when kept above a 50 percent charge. The company advises against running the battery completely down.</p>
<p>In an <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.samsung.com/nz/support/mobile-devices/tips-for-battery-charging-and-how-to-make-your-battery-last-longer/?srsltid=AfmBOoqq5ryP3FW-5ayEv5LdwNOY3djQadld6M7Z_oX6FA4azys6RGJK">online guide</a>, Samsung also said that repeatedly letting the battery go to zero percent may shorten its life and decrease overall performance. “If this happens, you'll need to charge the battery more frequently and it may last only a few hours before needing a charge.”</p>
<p><strong>Avoid extreme temperatures</strong></p>
<p>Apple says its batteries already warm up as they charge, so phones should not be charged in very hot temperatures. Charging an iPhone in heat above 35 degrees Celsius, for example, “can permanently reduce battery lifespan.”</p>
<p>Samsung also says extreme heat or cold can damage batteries. It warns users not to leave their phones inside vehicles or other contained spaces in very hot or cold weather.</p>
<p>Google created the Android operating system and makes Pixel smartphones. It warns that hot batteries lose power faster, even when not being used.</p>
<p><strong>Change your power settings </strong></p>
<p>Look at changing your smartphone settings so <strong>apps</strong> and other device operations use less power. Doing this can extend your battery's daily life and give more time between charges.</p>
<p>Examples include turning down the phone's screen brightness, changing to a dark theme and making the screen power off sooner. You can also look at battery usage in the device's settings to identify power-hungry apps that can be turned off or removed.</p>
<p>Also, if an iPhone's power level drops below 10 percent, users can turn on the low power setting to stretch battery life before the next charge. Android phones have a similar “power saving mode.” But while this setting can be left on all the time, experts say doing so can affect the phone's overall performance.</p>
<p>Samsung says another power-saving move is to turn off Bluetooth or Wi-Fi when they are not being used. Apple, however, advises iPhone users to leave these on because they use very little power when not connected.</p>
<p><strong>Use protection</strong></p>
<p>Many smartphone users already know the benefits of using screen protectors and device cases. Experts advise not using plastic versions, which can damage the phone's face. Device website iFixit suggests choosing ones made with either Thermoplastic polyurethane (TPU) material – which combines both plastic and rubber – or <strong>tempered </strong>glass. Both offer more solid protection.</p>
<p><strong>Keep your device clean</strong></p>
<p>Smartphones can collect dirt and other materials that can block port openings and hurt performance. Experts say a toothpick or toothbrush can be used to get rid of much of these substances. But they advise users to make sure the process is removing the material, not pushing it deeper inside.</p>
<p><strong>Update your device</strong></p>
<p>Software is another important part in extending a phone's lifespan. Experts suggest downloading the latest operating system updates often. This will limit problems related to the device's privacy, security and battery operations.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>update</strong> <em>– n. </em>when new information or features are added to an existing thing</p>
<p><strong>battery</strong> <em>– n. </em>a device that chemically stores electricity so it can be used as direct current in electrical circuits such as computers and motors</p>
<p><strong>diminish </strong><em>– </em><em>v. </em>to become less or to make something become less</p>
<p><strong>peak </strong><em>– adj.</em> the highest level or value of something</p>
<p><strong>app</strong> <em>– n. </em>a computer program that is designed to do one task or set of tasks and is usually aimed at use on mobile devices</p>
<p><strong>tempered </strong><em>– </em><em>adj. </em>treated with material to increase the strength and effectiveness of something</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Employers Use Wearable Devices to Measure Workers’ Temperature (2024/9/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/employers-use-wearable-devices-to-measure-workers-temperature.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">04 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>On a hot summer day, workers recently worked to remove asbestos and <strong>hazardous</strong> waste at Oak Ridge National Laboratory in Tennessee. It is a former nuclear center that the government wants to tear down.</p>
<p>The men wore full-body protective clothing and used respirators to clean the air they breathe. But the clothing does not protect them from high temperatures inside the building and inside their heavy clothing. On their arms, they wear devices that record their heart rates, movements and levels of exertion. The aim is to look for heat stress.</p>
<p>Stephanie Miller oversees safety and health for the company responsible for the cleanup. She watches a computer to observe each worker's data looking for danger of overheating.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="A SlateSafety armband is worn by Wyatt Fischer, a furnace mason employee at Cardinal Glass, Thursday, Aug. 22, 2024, in Menomonie, Wis. (AP Photo/Abbie Parr)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-88ab-08dcc6a89151_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">A SlateSafety armband is worn by Wyatt Fischer, a furnace mason employee at Cardinal Glass, Thursday, Aug. 22, 2024, in Menomonie, Wis. (AP Photo/Abbie Parr)</span></div>
<p>Miller said, “Heat is one of the greatest risks that we have in this work, even though we deal with high radiation, hazardous chemicals and heavy metals.”</p>
<p><strong>Heat in the workplace</strong></p>
<p>The issue of heat in the workplace has been getting more attention since a 2021 report from the research organization Atlantic Council. The group said the United States loses an average of $100 billion each year from “heat-<strong>induced</strong>” reductions in productivity.</p>
<p>The Environmental Protection Agency said from 1992 to 2022, 986 people died from heat-related causes in U.S. workplaces.</p>
<p>Employers have measured heat-related stress by checking employees' temperatures with thermometers. More recently, firefighters and military members have swallowed thermometer <strong>capsules</strong>.</p>
<p>As the world experiences record-high temperatures, employers are exploring wearable technologies, like <strong>sensors</strong> and <strong>armbands</strong>, to help keep workers safe. They collect body temperature and warn workers to take breaks when they get too hot.</p>
<p>Perrigo, a drug company, gave SlateSafety <strong>armbands</strong> to more than 100 employees at its baby food factory. The devices estimate the wearer's body temperature. A reading of 101.3 results in an alert, or a warning.</p>
<p>Another device from the Massachusetts company Epicore Biosystems uses sweat to find out if a worker is overheating.</p>
<p>Experts say the effectiveness of some devices remains unproven although research has shown that some successfully predict body temperature. A 2022 study said age, sex, and the amount of water in the air make it difficult to measure body temperature.</p>
<p><strong>Privacy concerns</strong></p>
<p>However, some groups worry that employers will use the technology to punish people for taking needed breaks.</p>
<p>Travis Parsons is with the Laborers' Health and Safety Fund of North America, a labor rights group. Parsons said, “Any time you put a device on a worker, they're very concerned about <strong>tracking</strong>, privacy, and how are you going to use this against me.”</p>
<p>United Cleanup Oak Ridge is the partnership that is responsible for cleaning up the nuclear reactor in Tennessee. The company says it uses medical examinations to make work decisions. Miller, the health supervisor said the company sent a few employees to see their personal doctors who found out they had heart problems.</p>
<p>At Perrigo, safety official Rob Somers said supervisors look at information on people with several alerts and speak to them to see if there is “a reason why they're not able to work in the environment.”</p>
<p>Adam Schwartz is with the Electronic Frontiers Foundation, a civil liberties group based in San Francisco. He said the idea that companies could keep years of medical information on employees raises privacy concerns. He said the information could be used to withhold health plans or dismiss workers.</p>
<p>Schwartz said, “The device could hurt...because you could raise your hand and say, ‘I need a break,' and the boss could say, ‘No, your heart rate is not <strong>elevated</strong>, go back to work.'”</p>
<p>To reduce such risks, employers should permit workers to accept or reject using the devices. They could process only necessary information and <strong>delete</strong> the information in 24 hours, Schwartz said.</p>
<p>Ikusei Misaka, a professor at Tokyo's Musashino University, raised another concern. Misaka noted that information gathered from wearing such devices could result in workers getting unwanted marketing for goods or services.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Cathy Bussewitz reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>hazardous</strong> <em>–adj. </em>dangerous</p>
<p><strong>-induced </strong><em>–adj.</em> -produced</p>
<p><strong>capsule </strong>–n. a rounded piece of medicine or medical device meant to be swallowed</p>
<p><strong>sensor </strong>–n. an electrical device that measures something in the physical world and turns it into an electrical signal</p>
<p><strong>armband </strong><em>–n.</em> something that is worn on the arm that can have a device attached to it</p>
<p><strong>tracking</strong> <em>–n. </em>following something or someone to find out more about it</p>
<p><strong>elevate </strong><em>–v.</em> to lift something up or bring it to a higher level</p>
<p><strong>delete </strong><em>–v.</em> to completely remove something so that it is no longer there</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Women in Chad Seek Right to Own, Control Land (2024/9/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/women-in-chad-seek-right-to-own-control-land.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>When Milla Nemoudji <strong>divorced </strong>her husband following years of physical abuse, she found herself without a way to earn a living. The 28-year-old lived in a village in southern Chad. Though she grew up in a farming family, she struggled to earn money in a community where men usually control <strong>access</strong> to land.</p>
<p>Divorce is rare in Chad, and she received little support. She sold fruits and other goods. And in the rainy season, she worked in fields as a laborer.</p>
<p>Last year, however, she joined a women's collective that arrived in her village, Binmar. The village is just outside of Chad's second-largest city, Moundou.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Twenty-eight-year-old Milla Nemoudji, a woman who was divorced by her husband following years of physical abuse, is photographed in a village of Binmar, Chad, Friday, July 19, 2024. (AP Photo/Robert Bociaga)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-2abd-08dcc8ffb2d0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Twenty-eight-year-old Milla Nemoudji, a woman who was divorced by her husband following years of physical abuse, is photographed in a village of Binmar, Chad, Friday, July 19, 2024. (AP Photo/Robert Bociaga)
</span></div>
<p>The collective gave Nemoudji access to land. It also gave her the ability to make decisions on its use. She farmed cotton, peanuts and sesame and earned enough money to pay for basic needs.</p>
<p>The struggle for land rights comes from Chad's dual legal system. Recent government laws give any citizen the right to own land. But in rural areas, people follow customary law instead of the modern government's law. And village chiefs control who can use land.</p>
<p>The village chiefs require yearly payments. Women in these villages often cannot own or <strong>inherit</strong> land. That leaves them dependent on male family members. It also limits their chance to have more influence in their society. And it gives them fewer choices when they are the victims of <strong>domestic violence</strong>.</p>
<p>Nemoudji told reporters with the Associated Press, "There's no one to come to your aid, although everyone knows that you are suffering.”</p>
<p>She added, "If women weren't losing access to farmlands, they would dare to leave their husbands earlier."</p>
<p><strong>Collective land use</strong></p>
<p>Adèle Noudjilembaye founded N-Bio Solutions, the collective Nemoudji joined, in 2018. It is a rare program in Chad that negotiates on behalf of women with traditional chiefs. The chiefs connect the collective to local people with available land they are willing to <strong>lease</strong>.</p>
<p>Noudjilembaye runs five collectives so far, and each has around 25 members.</p>
<p>These efforts are slowly gaining popularity. But Noudjilembaye said that some women who face domestic violence do not leave their situation “because of financial dependency, fear of societal judgement or lack of support.”</p>
<p>In Chad, life is difficult for women who attempt to <strong>assert</strong> their rights.</p>
<p>"The system failed me when I sought help after my husband burned down my house," Nemoudji said. When she reported the incident to the village chief, "nothing was done to solve my dispute."</p>
<p>Despite the lack of support from village leaders and local officials, Nemoudji and other women in Binmar have found strength in the collective.</p>
<p>Marie Depaque is another village woman who struggled financially after her second husband refused to support her children from her first marriage. She said, "Our fight for land rights is not just about economic survival but also about justice, equality and the hope for a better future."</p>
<p>Nemoudji dreams of better educational <strong>opportunities</strong> for the children in her community so they can break the cycle of poverty and violence. She works in the community for changes in the land ownership system.</p>
<p>"Knowing my rights means I can seek help from <strong>authorities</strong> and demand justice," she said.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Robert Bociaga reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>divorce</strong> – v. to legally end your marriage with (your husband or wife)</p>
<p><strong>access</strong> – <em>n</em>. a way of being able to use or get something</p>
<p><strong>inherit</strong> – <em>v</em>. to receive (money, property, etc.) from someone when that person dies</p>
<p><strong>domestic violence</strong> – <em>n.</em> violent or aggressive behavior within the home, typically involving the violent abuse of a spouse or partner.</p>
<p><strong>lease</strong> – <em>v. </em>to create a legal agreement that lets someone use a car, house, or land for a period of time in return for payment</p>
<p><strong>assert</strong> – <em>v</em>. to state (something) in a strong and definite way</p>
<p><strong>opportunity</strong> – <em>n</em>. an amount of time or a situation in which something can be done</p>
<p><strong>authorities</strong> – <em>n</em>. <em>(pl.)</em> people who have power to make decisions and enforce rules and laws</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Why Is Polio Still a Problem? (2024/9/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/why-is-polio-still-a-problem.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Polio was driven out of much of the world more than 30 years ago after a series of successful vaccination campaigns. But the viral disease is still spreading in a small number of nations.</p>
<p>The recent discovery of the first polio case in Gaza in 25 years led world health officials to set new goals to get rid of the disease in all areas.</p>
<p><strong>What is polio?</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A Palestinian child is vaccinated against polio, amid the Israel-Hamas conflict, in Deir Al-Balah in the central Gaza Strip, September 1, 2024. (REUTERS/Hussam Al-Masri)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/cf690179-c80a-4f07-ab79-af98aac4e9e4_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A Palestinian child is vaccinated against polio, amid the Israel-Hamas conflict, in Deir Al-Balah in the central Gaza Strip, September 1, 2024. (REUTERS/Hussam Al-Masri)</span></div>
<p>Polio is an infection caused by a virus that mostly affects children under the age of five. Most infected people do not have any <strong>symptoms</strong>. But some can experience a high body temperature, headaches, <strong>vomiting</strong> and <strong>stiffness</strong> of the backbone, or spine.</p>
<p>The World Health Organization (WHO) says polio can affect the nervous system and cause <strong>paralysis</strong> within hours. The U.N. agency estimates 1 in 200 polio cases results in permanent paralysis, usually of the legs. Among children who are paralyzed, up to 10 percent die when their breathing muscles stop working.</p>
<p>The virus spreads from person to person, entering the body though the mouth. It is most often spread through contact with the waste from an infected person. Sometimes, it is also passed through water or food.</p>
<p><strong>How bad was polio in the past?</strong></p>
<p>Polio has existed for hundreds of years. The Associated Press says that Ancient Egyptian writings show children using sticks to walk and having wasted legs or arms, suggesting the effects of polio.</p>
<p>Before the first vaccine was developed in the 1950s, polio was among the world's most feared diseases. A 1916 outbreak in New York killed more than 2,000 people. The worst recorded U.S. outbreak in 1952 killed more than 3,000 people. Many who survived polio suffered lifelong effects, including paralysis and deformed limbs. Others whose breathing muscles were paralyzed required specialized lung treatments.</p>
<p><strong>When did the campaign to destroy polio begin?</strong></p>
<p>The WHO passed a resolution in 1988 calling for polio to be eradicated, or destroyed, worldwide. The effort followed a successful campaign against smallpox eight years earlier.</p>
<p>The WHO's first plan was to <strong>eradicate</strong> polio by 2000. The U.N. agency cooperated with the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, UNICEF and Rotary International. The campaign centered on increasing the production of a vaccine and launching vaccination efforts. As a result, polio cases dropped by more than 99 percent.</p>
<p>Afghanistan and Pakistan are the only countries where the spread of polio has never been stopped. There have also been outbreaks in several other countries, mostly in Africa. The WHO and its partners now aim to eradicate polio by 2026.</p>
<p><strong>Why have efforts to fight polio taken so long?</strong></p>
<p>Health experts say stopping polio outbreaks requires vaccinating at least 95 percent of the world's population. Vaccinating people is more difficult in nations that have conflicts or weak health systems.</p>
<p>The vaccine given by mouth does not cost a lot to manufacture and is better at preventing infection. But it contains weakened, live polio virus. In rare cases, the vaccine can spread or cause polio in unvaccinated people. In even rarer cases, live virus from the vaccine can <strong>mutate</strong> into a new form that could start new outbreaks.</p>
<p>Health officials have become more successful at reducing the number of cases caused by the natural polio virus. The majority of infections in the world today are related to the vaccine.</p>
<p>Scott Barrett is a professor at Columbia University in New York City who has studied polio eradication. He told the AP, “The problem with trying to eradicate polio is that the need for <strong>perfection</strong> is so great and there are so many weak links.” He added that while the technical ability to destroy polio exists, “We live in a <strong>vastly</strong> imperfect world.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>symptom </strong><em>– n. </em>a physical feeling or problem that suggests a person has a particular sickness</p>
<p><strong>vomit </strong><em>–v.</em> to expel what is in the stomach through the mouth</p>
<p><strong>stiffness </strong><em>–n. </em>a difficulty in either slowness or pain in moving a part of the body</p>
<p><strong>paralysis</strong> <em>– n. </em>being unable to move all of part of the body because of sickness or injury</p>
<p><strong>eradicate </strong><em>–v.</em> to completely remove or destroy</p>
<p><strong>mutate </strong><em>– </em><em>v. </em>to cause a gene to change and create an unusual characteristic in a plant or animal</p>
<p><strong>perfection </strong><em>–n.</em> a state in which no error or fault exists</p>
<p><strong>vastly </strong><em>– adv.</em> to a very large extent</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Schools Use Money, Fun, Support to Get Students to Class (2024/9/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/us-schools-use-money-fun-support-to-get-students-to-class.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Flerentin Jean-Baptiste missed school so often that he had to repeat his first year at Medford High School near Boston.</p>
<p>Jean-Baptiste said, at school, "You do the same thing every day." He was <strong>absent</strong> 30 days in his first year.</p>
<p>Then the <strong>principal</strong> of the school did something different: She let students play organized sports during lunch — if they attended all their classes. In other words, she offered high school students a play period that is usually part of the school day for young children.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Flerentin “Flex” Jean-Baptiste, 16, of Medford, Mass., poses for a photo at Medford High School, Friday, Aug. 2, 2024, in Medford. (AP Photo/Josh Reynolds)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-a769-08dcc0c19c33_cx1_cy0_cw84_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Flerentin “Flex” Jean-Baptiste, 16, of Medford, Mass., poses for a photo at Medford High School, Friday, Aug. 2, 2024, in Medford. (AP Photo/Josh Reynolds)</span></div>
<p>"It gave me something to look forward to," said 16-year-old Jean-Baptiste. The following year, he cut his absences in half. Schoolwide, the share of regularly absent students dropped from 35 percent in March 2023 to 23 percent in March 2024. That was one of the biggest reductions among Massachusetts high schools.</p>
<p>The Associated Press and Stanford University economist Thomas Dee have studied attendance numbers from 42 states and Washington, D.C. They found that years after the school closings from the COVID-19 pandemic, schools in nearly every state are still struggling with attendance.</p>
<p>About one in four students in the 2022-23 school year were <strong>chronically</strong> absent. That means they missed at least 10 percent of the school year. That number represents about 12 million children in states reporting numbers of absent students.</p>
<p>Before the pandemic, only 15 percent of students missed school that often.</p>
<p>After spending as much as a year at home during the pandemic, many children see school as more than they can handle, uninteresting or socially <strong>stressful</strong>. Some children and parents are deciding it is no problem to stay home. That makes completing class work even harder.</p>
<p>In all but one state, Arkansas, absence rates remain higher than they were before the pandemic. Still, the problem appears to have passed its highest point; almost every state saw absenteeism go down at least a little during the two full school years ending in 2023.</p>
<p>Schools are trying to identify students with attendance problems so they can help. They are also trying to communicate better with parents. Some parents might not know their child is missing a lot of school or its effects on their performance.</p>
<p>Experts say schools must get creative to meet their students' needs.</p>
<p><strong>Pay money or care about students</strong></p>
<p>In Oakland, California, chronic absenteeism in public schools sharply rose from 29 percent before the pandemic to 53 percent during the 2022-23 school year. Officials asked students what would make them want to come to class. They answered, money and a <strong>mentor</strong>.</p>
<p>In spring 2023, the Oakland school district received a <strong>grant</strong> to pay 45 students $50 weekly to attend school every day. Sixty percent of those in the program improved their attendance. Zaia Vera is the district's head of social-emotional learning. Vera said paying students cannot continue for a long time, but many absent students lacked dependable housing or were helping to support their families. "The money is the <strong>hook</strong> that got them in the door."</p>
<p>A caring teacher made a difference for 18-year-old Golden Tachiquin. She completed her studies at Oakland's Skyline High School this spring. Coming back to school after the pandemic, she felt lost and <strong>anxious</strong>. She later realized these feelings made her feel physically sick. She was absent at least 25 days that year.</p>
<p>One Afro-Latina teacher seemed to understand her culturally and made Tachiquin feel she belonged in class. Tachiquin already received good grades.</p>
<p>In Massachusetts, Medford High School requires administrators to welcome and talk with students each morning, especially those who miss a lot of class.</p>
<p>But playtime at lunch has had the greatest effect on improved attendance, Principal Marta Cabral said. High school students need freedom and a chance to move their bodies, she said. "They're here for seven hours a day. They should have a little fun."</p>
<p><strong>Long-term problems</strong></p>
<p>Many of the reasons given for students missing school early in the pandemic are still in place. They include financial difficulty, transportation problems, mild illness and mental health struggles.</p>
<p>For example, a study from the University of Southern California said parents reported that almost one fourth of chronically absent students had emotional or behavioral problems, compared with just seven percent of those with good attendance.</p>
<p>At Fresno's Fort Miller Middle School, half of the students were chronically absent. Two reasons kept coming up: dirty clothing and no transportation. The school bought a washer and dryer for families to use. It also provided a vehicle to pick up students who missed the bus. Fresno's chronic absenteeism improved to 35 percent during the school year ending in 2023.</p>
<p>Fourteen-year-old Melinda Gonzalez missed the school bus about once a week. So, she called for rides from the school vehicle.</p>
<p>"I don't have a car; my parents couldn't drive me to school," Gonzalez said. "Getting that ride made a big difference."</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p>And I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jocelyn Gecker, Bianca Vázquez Toness and Sharon Lurye reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>absent</strong><em> – adj.</em> not present at a usual or expected place</p>
<p><strong>chronically</strong> – adv. in a way that is continuing or occurring again and again for a long time</p>
<p><strong>stressful</strong><em> – adj.</em> making you feel worried or anxious</p>
<p><strong>mentor</strong> – <em>n</em>. someone who teaches or gives help and advice to a less experienced and often younger person</p>
<p><strong>grant </strong><em>–n.</em> an amount of money from a government or organization meant for a specific purpose and which does not have to be repaid</p>
<p><strong>hook</strong> – <em>n. </em>something (such as part of a song) that attracts people's attention</p>
<p><strong>anxious</strong> – <em>adj</em>. afraid or nervous especially about what may happen</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Ukraine's Children Celebrate First Day of School, But Missiles Still Fly (2024/9/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/ukraine-s-children-celebrate-first-day-of-school-but-missiles-still-fly.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Schoolchildren in the southern Ukrainian city Zaporizhzhia celebrated the traditional first day of school on Sunday. The ceremonies began just hours after warnings of Russian air raids sounded through the city.</p>
<p>Zaporizhzhia is just 40 kilometers from the war's front. That danger is never far from the minds of teachers and families at one of the city's schools.</p>
<p>Russian artillery and missiles strike there so often that local officials were forced to ban large gatherings. Only students starting their first and last years could take part in the ceremony.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="First-graders attend the traditional ceremony for the first day of school in Zaporizhzhia, Ukraine, Sunday Sept. 1, 2024. (AP Photo/Evgeniy Maloletka)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/17dfd924-8623-4c5c-86f9-bda21cb4ef31_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">First-graders attend the traditional ceremony for the first day of school in Zaporizhzhia, Ukraine, Sunday Sept. 1, 2024. (AP Photo/Evgeniy Maloletka)
</span></div>
<p>The Associated Press is not identifying the school for security reasons.</p>
<p><strong>Limited space in shelter</strong></p>
<p>The children wore traditional Ukrainian clothing and carried flowers. Each first year student held the hand of a final year student in a small parade.</p>
<p>The school once had 800 students but about 300 fled the city seeking safer places. The remaining children <strong>alternate</strong> one week of study at school with one week of online study. That is because the school's bomb shelter can hold only around 250 people.</p>
<p>That shelter is about 75 meters away from the main school building, across an open playground. School director Kostiantyn Lypskyi said the youngest students work in a classroom just above the underground shelter. The rest of the school operates in the main building.</p>
<p><strong>Lessons held underground</strong></p>
<p>“We prepared everything for the new school year. We equipped the <strong>bunker</strong> in case of air <strong>alarms</strong>, so children will have a safe space because our school will continue lessons during the air raid alarms in the bunker,” he said.</p>
<p>Sunday's ceremony went on without problems.</p>
<p>Olha Komarova-Lesko is the mother of an 11th <strong>grader</strong> and a 6th grader. She said she was hopeful for the coming school year. She sees it as the best solution for the present conditions.</p>
<p>“We are happy that the children had the chance to go to the celebration today just as in the prewar times,” she said, “This is really exciting and joyful.”</p>
<p>Russia launched large numbers of missiles and drones on the capital Kyiv Monday, wounding three people and damaging schools. On Tuesday, Russian missiles killed at least 41 people and wounded over 180 in Poltova, a city in the central eastern part of Ukraine.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Lori Hinnant </em><em>reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>despite</strong> –<em> prep.</em> in defiance or contempt of;<strong> </strong>without being prevented by</p>
<p><strong>bunker</strong> – <em>n</em>. a strong building that is mostly below ground and that is used to keep people safe from attacks</p>
<p><strong>alarm</strong> – <em>n</em>. a device that makes a loud sound as a warning or signal</p>
<p><strong>grader</strong> – <em>n</em>. US: a student in a particular grade in school</p>
<p><strong>alternate</strong> – <em>v.</em> to place or do (different things) so that one follows the other in a repeated series</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>AI App Helps People with ADHD (2024/9/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/ai-app-helps-people-with-adhd.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>Becky Litvintchouk did not think she would be able to finish the many tasks needed to start her own business. She has Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder, or ADHD. It affects every part of her life and hurts her ability to <strong>focus</strong> on one thing at a time.</p>
<p>So, two years ago, she turned to artificial intelligence, or AI. She uses an app called Claude. It helps her decide which contracts are the best for her cleaning-wipes business, GetDirty. Using the app means she does not need to read each contract, word for word. She also created business plans by telling the <strong>generative</strong> AI bot what her goals were. It then created steps for her to reach them.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Entrepreneur Becky Litvintchouk works on her computer at a co-working space on Monday, Aug. 12, 2024, in New York. (AP Photo/Andres Kudacki)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-5ed1-08dcc6ac6364_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Entrepreneur Becky Litvintchouk works on her computer at a co-working space on Monday, Aug. 12, 2024, in New York. (AP Photo/Andres Kudacki)</span></div>
<p>“It's been just massively <strong>instrumental</strong>. I probably would not be where I am today,” Litvintchouk said of using AI.</p>
<p>People with ADHD experience difficulties with focusing, organizing and controlling<strong> </strong>urges. Experts say generative AI tools can help them finish tasks more quickly.</p>
<p>However, they also warn that such tools should not replace traditional treatments for ADHD. Some experts also have concerns about possibly using AI too much. They also worry about privacy risks.</p>
<p><strong>Will apps replace ADHD treatment?</strong></p>
<p>John Mitchell is an associate professor at Duke University School of Medicine in North Carolina. He said that AI apps should be used as “one tool in a toolbox.” AI should not take the place of traditional treatments, such as developing organizational skills or taking medications.</p>
<p>He compared using AI to help ADHD with swimming and staying alive in the water. “If you're kind of <strong>treading water</strong> in your job and AI's a <strong>life</strong> <strong>preserver</strong>, well, that's great you're staying above water.” But, he added, “you still don't know how to swim.”</p>
<p><strong>What else can the apps do?</strong></p>
<p>Litvintchouk, a married mother of four living in New York City, dropped out of high school and left the workforce. Research shows that these things are more likely to happen to people with ADHD.</p>
<p>Aside from helping with her business, she uses ChatGPT to help with food shopping. Food shopping and meal planning are tasks that can be difficult for people with ADHD because these tasks require organizational skills.</p>
<p>After sharing her method with another mom with ADHD, she decided more people needed to know about it. She started making videos on TikTok about the AI tools she uses to help with her ADHD struggles.</p>
<p>Generative AI tools can help people with ADHD break down big tasks into smaller, more doable steps. Chatbots can offer advice for specific things and make people feel like they are talking with a real person. Some AI apps can also help with reminders and productivity.</p>
<p>Software engineer Bram de Buyser said he created Goblin.tools with his <strong>neurodivergent</strong> friends in mind. The tool's most popular feature is the “magic to-do.” A user can enter a task and the bot will create a to-do list. It can even break down large items on the list into smaller tasks.</p>
<p>“I'm not trying to build a cure,” de Buyser said, “but something that helps them out (for) two minutes out of the day that they would otherwise struggle with.”</p>
<p><strong>What kinds of problems could apps create?</strong></p>
<p>Russell Fulmer is a professor at Husson University in the northeastern state of Maine. He described the research around AI and ADHD as “<strong>inconclusive</strong>.” In other words, the results of its usefulness are still not known.</p>
<p>Experts say they see how AI can have a positive effect on the lives of people with anxiety and ADHD. But, Fulmer said, such tools may not work well for everyone, including people of color with ADHD. He pointed to chatbot responses that have been racist and unfair toward certain groups of people at times.</p>
<p>Valese Jones is a publicist and founder of Sincerely Nicole Media. She was <strong>diagnosed</strong> with ADHD as a child. She uses AI bots to help with reading and responding to emails as well as proofreading public relations plans. But chatbot responses do not always go along with who she really is.</p>
<p>“There are <strong>cadences</strong> in my writing where you can kind of pick up on the fact that I'm southern, and that's on purpose,” said Jones, who is Black. She purposefully writes in a way that shows her culture. However, the responses she gets back from bots often do not show that.</p>
<p>Software engineer de Buyser said that using AI chatbots as a personal assistant has a big upside: They are never tired and never sleep.</p>
<p>The downside? They also create privacy issues. When you give an AI chatbot your personal information, emails, calendar and personal writings, you are giving it to a big company, he warned.</p>
<p>And that's the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p>And I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Kenya Hunter reported this story for The Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted the story for Learning English.</em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>focus</strong> <em>-n.</em> a center of activity, attraction, or attention</p>
<p><strong>generative </strong><em>-adj. </em>having the power or function of generating, originating, producing, or reproducing</p>
<p><strong>instrumental </strong><em>-adj. </em>serving as a crucial means, agent, or tool</p>
<p><strong>tread water </strong><em>-v. </em>while in deep water a person float in an upright position by moving their legs slightly</p>
<p><strong>life</strong> <strong>preserver </strong><em>-n. </em>a device (such as a life jacket or life buoy) designed to save a person from drowning by providing buoyancy in water</p>
<p><strong>neurodivergent </strong><em>-adj. </em>having or relating to a disorder or condition (such as autism spectrum disorder, attention deficit disorder, dyslexia, or obsessive-compulsive disorder) that impacts the way the brain processes information : exhibiting or characteristic of variations in typical neurological development</p>
<p><strong>inconclusive </strong><em>-adj. </em>leading to no conclusion or definite result</p>
<p><strong>diagnose </strong><em>-n.</em> to recognize (something, such as a disease) by signs and symptoms</p>
<p><strong>cadence </strong><em>-n. </em>a rhythmic sequence or flow of sounds in language</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What Is the Oropouche Virus Found in US Travelers to Cuba? (2024/9/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/what-is-the-oropouche-virus-found-in-us-travelers-to-cuba.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>American health officials have identified a virus spread by insects in more than 20 people who visited Cuba. The virus is officially called Oropouche. It is also known as sloth fever.</p>
<p>The U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) said August 27 it had received reports of 21 cases in the United States. All of the cases – 20 in Florida and one in New York – involved people who had traveled to Cuba.</p>
<p>European health officials said they had identified 19 cases of the virus, nearly all of them in travelers.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image provided by the USDA Agricultural Research Service shows a closeup of a mosquito on human skin. (USDA Agricultural Research Service via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-30ce-08dcc8675abf_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image provided by the USDA Agricultural Research Service shows a closeup of a mosquito on human skin. (USDA Agricultural Research Service via AP)</span></div>
<p>The CDC <a class="wsw__a" href="https://wwwnc.cdc.gov/travel/notices/level1/oropouche-fever-brazil">explains</a> that Oropouche is usually spread through the bites of small flies called midges, as well as mosquitoes. Signs, or symptoms, of the sickness usually start three to 10 days after an insect bite. They can include headache, high temperature, joint <strong>stiffness</strong>, stomach problems and sensitivity to light.</p>
<p>The CDC says most virus cases last from three to six days and people generally recover without any long-term effects. There is currently no <strong>specific</strong> treatment or vaccine for the sickness.</p>
<p><strong>Where did Oropouche come from?</strong></p>
<p>The Oropouche virus is native to forested <strong>tropical</strong> areas. It was first identified in 1955 in the Caribbean island nation of Trinidad and Tobago. The virus was named after a nearby village and water system.</p>
<p>The sickness is sometimes called sloth fever because scientists investigating the virus found it in a three-toed sloth. Researchers believed the sloths were important in spreading the virus between insects and animals.</p>
<p><strong>How does it spread?</strong></p>
<p>The virus is spread to humans by small biting flies called midges, and by some kinds of mosquitoes. Humans have become infected while visiting forested areas and are believed to be responsible for helping the virus make its way to towns and cities. So far, person-to-person transmission, or spread, has not been documented.</p>
<p><strong>How many cases have there been?</strong></p>
<p>The virus has recently caused large outbreaks in Amazon areas where it was known to exist. It has also been found in new areas of South America and the Caribbean. About 8,000 local infections have been reported in Bolivia, Brazil, Colombia, Cuba, and Peru.</p>
<p>Most patients returning from Cuba reported their symptoms between May and July. Three of the patients were hospitalized, with no deaths reported, the CDC <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/volumes/73/wr/mm7335e1.htm?s_cid=mm7335e1_w">said</a> in its <em>Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report</em>.</p>
<p><strong>What are the symptoms and treatments?</strong></p>
<p>Symptoms can seem similar to other tropical diseases like dengue, Zika or malaria. The most common ones include <strong>fever</strong>, headaches and muscle pains. Some infected people also suffer from <strong>diarrhea</strong>, unsettled stomach, <strong>vomiting</strong> or skin reactions.</p>
<p>Some patients can suffer symptoms repeatedly. And one in 20 people may experience more severe symptoms like bleeding, meningitis and encephalitis. The virus rarely causes death, although there were recent reports of deaths in two healthy young people in Brazil.</p>
<p>There are no vaccines to prevent infections and no medicines are currently available to treat the symptoms.</p>
<p><strong>Are there other concerns?</strong></p>
<p>In Brazil, officials are investigating reports that infections might be passed on from pregnant women to their unborn babies. This kind of spread was documented during Zika outbreaks nearly 10 years ago.</p>
<p>The CDC has issued guidance that pregnant women should avoid non-necessary travel to Cuba. The agency also suggested that all travelers take steps to prevent insect bites, such as using insect <strong>repellents</strong> and wearing long-sleeved shirts and long pants.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press and Reuters reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>stiff </strong><em>– adj. </em>hard and difficult to move</p>
<p><strong>specific </strong><em>– adj. </em>exact or containing details</p>
<p><strong>tropical</strong> <em>– adj. </em>from or in the hottest parts of the world</p>
<p><strong>fever </strong><em>– </em><em>n. </em>a high body temperature caused by sickness</p>
<p><strong>diarrhea </strong><em>– n.</em> a sickness in which a person's solid waste is more liquid than usual and comes out of the body more often</p>
<p><strong>vomit</strong> <em>– v. </em>to have the food, liquid, etc., that is in your stomach come out through your mouth because you are sick</p>
<p><strong>repellent </strong><em>– </em><em>n. </em>a substance used to keep insects away</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Man Jailed for Poaching, Now Protects Zimbabwe’s Natural Resources (2024/9/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/a-man-jailed-for-poaching-now-protects-zimbabwe-s-natural-resources.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">02 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A Zimbabwean who formerly hunted animals illegally is now in a program that turns such poachers into protectors of wildlife.</p>
<p>Forty-seven-year-old Tembanechako Mastick grew up hunting, a tradition in his community. He also planted crops and raised farm animals, or livestock. But dry weather conditions made farming less profitable. So, he turned to illegal hunting, also called poaching.</p>
<p>Then, last year, he got caught. Mastik had poached some small <strong>game</strong> from Savé Valley Conservancy. It is one of the largest private game reserves in Africa. Mastick was jailed for nearly three months.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Tembanechako Mastick, a former poacher who now teaches conservation, poses inside his cattle pen in Chiredzi, Zimbabwe near the Save Valley Conservancy, Wednesday, July 10, 2024. (AP Photo/Tsvangirayi Mukwazhi)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-c7d1-08dcc3b61757_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Tembanechako Mastick, a former poacher who now teaches conservation, poses inside his cattle pen in Chiredzi, Zimbabwe near the Save Valley Conservancy, Wednesday, July 10, 2024. (AP Photo/Tsvangirayi Mukwazhi)</span></div>
<p>Now, he is in a program that aims to turn poachers into <strong>conservationists</strong>.</p>
<p>Recently, Mastick was with a group of men. They found the <strong>den</strong> of some hyenas that had recently attacked livestock. The bones of the goats showed what happened. Some of the men suggested using fire to burn any hyenas remaining in the den. But Mastick warned against killing the animals, whether for <strong>revenge</strong> or for meat.</p>
<p>He said, “I began to realize that animals are for the benefit of the entire community, so poaching is a selfish act.”</p>
<p>Spreading that message is not easy. Across southern Africa, conflict between humans and wild animals is increasing. Dry weather, illegal hunting, tree-clearing, and the changing of forest to farmland have pushed wildlife closer to people.</p>
<p>Elephants raid vegetable gardens. Lions, hyenas, wild dogs and jackals target cattle and goats of farmers. D<i><i>onkey</i></i>s that work on farms are not safe either.</p>
<p>Zimbabwe's parks agency said it has received three to four thousand calls about wildlife problems in the past three years. Tinashe Farawo of the Zimbabwe National Parks and Wildlife Management Authority said the conflicts are likely to increase during the dry months ahead.</p>
<p>Mastick remembers when there were good harvests of corn, millet and cotton. The wild animals stayed in the forest back then.</p>
<p>He said the problems began after the country's land reform program went into effect in 2000. People started farming on land held by the Savé Valley Conservancy. The Conservancy said it lost 30 percent of the wildlife habitat on its 303,000 hectares of land.</p>
<p>At the same time, drought hit Mastick's village. “...Lions began targeting our livestock. Elephants also became a problem, hyenas too,” he said. There was not enough land to feed livestock, and people from neighboring villages crossed into the reserve to get wood.</p>
<p>Dingani Masuku of the conservancy said, “All resources are <strong>scarce</strong>. So we have to compete (with animals) for those resources...The resources are getting <strong>leaner</strong> and leaner.”</p>
<p>Mastick often has to calm angry villagers who have lost livestock. He knows about the problem. He starts each day by counting his own cattle, goats and d<i><i>onkey</i></i>s. Once he had 45 goats. Now, he has only 10. Wild animals have eaten the rest. Mastick himself has bites from animals including from a leopard attack.</p>
<p>“Without crop harvests we have to turn to livestock to raise money for school fees, food and other necessities so people are justified to be angry,” he said. But he added, “I help them understand that killing the animals is not the solution.”</p>
<p>Part of his message is that jail is difficult. His family suffered while he was in prison because he had been the family's only<strong> </strong>earner.</p>
<p>Several of his 20 children stopped going to school.</p>
<p>But in jail, he learned new skills including <strong>carpentry</strong>. Now, he makes chairs and tables in his workshop that have been popular with visitors and locals. Men visit his workshop, and Mastick tells them about conservation. He also speaks at village gatherings, funerals and community meetings.</p>
<p>There is no information about poaching in the area. But Mastick believes the number of poachers has dropped since he started his efforts.</p>
<p>Masuku of the Conservancy said people believe Mastick and gain hope from his work as a carpenter.</p>
<p>He said, “People know that he has been through it, he has been there and that poaching does not pay and that is why he is reforming.”</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Farai Mutsaka reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>game </strong><em>–n.</em> animals that can be hunted</p>
<p><strong>conservationist</strong><em> –n. </em>a person who protects and manages natural resources, so they last for the future</p>
<p><strong>den</strong> <em>–n.</em> a cave or hole where animals shelter</p>
<p><strong>revenge </strong><em>–n.</em> when a person sets out to punish someone who hurt them in some way</p>
<p><strong>scarce </strong><em>–adj.</em> difficult to find</p>
<p><strong>lean </strong><em>–adj.</em> thin or having little or nothing</p>
<p><strong>breadwinner </strong><em>–n.</em> the person whose income supports a family</p>
<p><strong>carpentry </strong><em>–n.</em> the job of making things out of wood</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Experts Question Boeing's Space Business after Starliner Failures (2024/9/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/experts-question-boeing-s-space-business-after-starliner-failures.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Experts and people in the space industry say NASA's decision to send Boeing's Starliner <strong>capsule</strong> home without astronauts was not unexpected. They also said it follows years of problems with Boeing's space business.</p>
<p>Taking NASA astronauts Butch Wilmore and Suni Williams to the International Space Station (ISS) was supposed to have been a turning point for Starliner. The operation had suffered years of delays and technical problems.</p>
<p>Reuters news agency examined financial securities reports for Boeing and reported on what it had found. Reuters estimated that Starliner has cost Boeing $1.6 billion in cost <strong>overruns</strong> since 2016.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this photo provided by NASA, Boeing's Starliner spacecraft is docked to the Harmony module of the International Space Station on July 3, 2024, seen from a window on the SpaceX Dragon Endeavour spacecraft docked to an adjacent port. (NASA via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/59d789d3-1bdb-487a-a48f-6b50917e3079_cx0_cy0_cw95_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this photo provided by NASA, Boeing's Starliner spacecraft is docked to the Harmony module of the International Space Station on July 3, 2024, seen from a window on the SpaceX Dragon Endeavour spacecraft docked to an adjacent port. (NASA via AP)</span></div>
<p>The Starliner spacecraft was launched from Cape Canaveral, Florida, on June 5. Astronauts Wilmore and Williams were to stay at the ISS for about eight days. But problems with Starliner have extended that NASA <strong>mission</strong> to eight months.</p>
<p>Starliner's <strong>propulsion</strong> system failed, and NASA judged the <strong>thrusters</strong> were not safe to attempt a return to Earth with a crew.</p>
<p>Instead, NASA announced that a SpaceX Crew Dragon capsule<strong> </strong>will return<strong> </strong>Wilmore and Williams to Earth in early 2025. SpaceX, led by Elon Musk, is the other company that NASA has contracted to develop crewed space vehicles. The June mission was meant to be a final test for NASA to approve Starliner for normal spaceflights.</p>
<p><strong>Questions for Boeing and its leadership</strong></p>
<p>Boeing's new leader Kelly Ortberg now must decide whether to continue developing the program or sell it. Ortberg also faces problems from failures by the company's airplane manufacturing business.</p>
<p>NASA administrator Bill Nelson said he spoke to Ortberg recently. Nelson reported that the talk left him completely sure that Starliner would fly astronauts again.</p>
<p>Reuters asked Boeing representatives if the company would stay in the program after Starliner's current operation. A Boeing spokesperson chose not to comment on the question, telling Reuters that the company is centering its attention on getting the spacecraft back safely.</p>
<p>"I am not sure the decision will ultimately be NASA's," said Lori Garver. Garver is a former NASA deputy administrator and a main designer of NASA's Commercial Crew Program.</p>
<p>Ortberg started as Boeing's leader on August 8. He is trying to persuade Boeing workers, investors, airlines and the public that safety problems at the company are now under control.</p>
<p>Experts say Boeing will probably keep Starliner in operation. They say this is partly because Boeing has experienced similar cost overruns in its defense business.</p>
<p>In the future, Starliner could serve customers other than NASA. These could include operators of private space stations meant to replace the ISS after 2030.</p>
<p><strong>NASA faces decisions </strong></p>
<p>NASA considers Boeing an important <strong>backup</strong> to Musk's SpaceX.</p>
<p>Boeing has spent more than half of its $4.5 billion NASA contract, which was given in 2014. Starliner has not yet received certification, or final approval for normal use. The contract includes six Starliner missions after the capsule is certified. Although the contract has a fixed price, NASA increased its value by $300 million.</p>
<p>SpaceX's Crew Dragon was certified in 2020. It has carried out 10 missions for NASA with a crew. The company's first contract was worth $2.6 billion. NASA bought more Crew Dragon missions to take the place of Boeing's delayed missions. As a result, the value of SpaceX's contract rose to $4.9 billion.</p>
<p>Boeing may have to carry out the same astronaut mission to the ISS again in order to get NASA certification for the capsule. The company already had to repeat an uncrewed 2022 mission at a cost of nearly $500 million. It has been five years since Starliner's first uncrewed test failed because of several important software problems.</p>
<p>In 2019, NASA's inspector general's office estimated both companies' cost per mission. It said Crew Dragon's mission price of carrying one astronaut into space was about $55 million while Starliner's cost was $90 million.</p>
<p><strong>Questions about workforce and suppliers</strong></p>
<p>For years, Boeing's space business has been losing skilled employees. Many former employees joined competitors SpaceX and Jeff Bezos' Blue Origin. Ten people who spoke to Reuters and who worked for Boeing's space business said the company's structure made designing spacecraft more complex than it is for SpaceX.</p>
<p>Boeing, in a statement to Reuters, said the company is proud of its Starliner workforce. It also said that it has admitted problems with its workforce and with suppliers when reporting on its earnings to shareholders.</p>
<p>Throughout Starliner's development, the propulsion system and sometimes the software have failed. New problems were found just hours before the spacecraft made its first attempt to launch this summer. Helium gas, used to pressurize the propellant, was leaking through a small opening.</p>
<p>NASA considered the leak low risk. The agency permitted Starliner to launch. But officials said the propulsion system had a "design <strong>vulnerability</strong>" that Boeing must deal with before its next mission.</p>
<p>The Space Launch System, or SLS, is another problem for Boeing's space division. The SLS is expected to be the launch vehicle for America's program to return to the moon. But the program has faced years of delays and is billions of dollars over budget.</p>
<p>NASA's inspector general's August report said there were deep problems with quality control at Boeing. The report added that Boeing's SLS workforce in Michoud, Louisiana, lacks enough "aerospace production experience, training, and <strong>instruction</strong>."</p>
<p>A Boeing representative said the company disagrees with much of the report, "including any suggestion that our Michoud workforce is unqualified."</p>
<p>Unlike Starliner, NASA pays the cost of delays and development problems with SLS. Inspector general reports have repeatedly said that the cost overruns are not fully known because NASA does not account for them correctly.</p>
<p>NASA is trying to give ownership of SLS to Boeing and co-contractor Northrop Grumman to bring the costs down. However, experts say such a deal is unlikely.</p>
<p>Richard Aboulafia is an aerospace business adviser. He said Boeing's other businesses are strong, but he wonders about its space division. He thinks Ortberg will negotiate with NASA to make Starliner workable. However, he is not persuaded that that move is the right one.</p>
<p>"If I were an adviser to Kelly Ortberg, which I'm not, I'd say...for space, well boss, you might want to consider selling it," Aboulafia said.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver. And I'm Mario Ritter.</p>
<p><em>Joey Roulette reported this story for Reuters. Caty Weaver adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>____________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>capsule </strong><em>– n.</em><strong> </strong>a part of a spacecraft that carries astronauts or the most important equipment in the vehicle system</p>
<p><strong>overrun </strong><em>–n.</em><em> </em>a situation when more money is needed to complete a project than had been planned</p>
<p><strong>mission </strong><em>–n.</em> a space flight (or an official task) which as a specific set of goals and requirements</p>
<p><strong>propulsion </strong><em>–n.</em> a system that causes a vehicle to move</p>
<p><strong>thruster </strong><em>–n.</em> a device that helps control a spacecraft in space</p>
<p><strong>backup </strong><em>–n.</em> another choice that can be used if something fails</p>
<p><strong>vulnerability </strong><em>–n.</em> a weakness</p>
<p><strong>instruction </strong><em>–n.</em> things that need to be taught to a person so they can complete a task</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Labor Day in the US (2024/9/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/labor-day-in-the-us.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By VOA</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Labor Day is a national holiday to celebrate workers in the United States. The holiday, on the first Monday of September, is on September 2 this year.</p>
<p>For Americans, the holiday also informally marks the end of summer. The hot days of summer turn to cooler days ahead. Students are returning to school. Many celebrate the holiday with an outdoor <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/tasty-travels-barbecue-american-food-tradition/3949118.html">barbecue</a> or one more weekend at the beach.</p>
<p><strong>Origin of Labor Day</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Iron worker Robert Farula marches up Fifth Ave. carrying an American flag during the Labor Day parade on Sept. 8, 2012, in New York. (AP Photo/Mary Altaffer, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-ce39-08dcc6bf668f_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Iron worker Robert Farula marches up Fifth Ave. carrying an American flag during the Labor Day parade on Sept. 8, 2012, in New York. (AP Photo/Mary Altaffer, File)</span></div>
<p>But Labor Day started with a struggle.</p>
<p>On May 1, 1889, workers demonstrated on the streets of Paris, France. The demonstration led to International Labor Day. Most countries in the world, except the United States and Canada, celebrate Labor Day on the first of May.</p>
<p>The first American Labor Day celebration was held on September 5, 1882, in New York City. About 10,000 workers marched through the streets to show the strength of labor organizations.</p>
<p>For many years after that, American workers used the first Monday in September to demand better working conditions and pay. Several U.S. cities and states began to recognize the day as Labor Day. In 1894, President Grover Cleveland signed a bill into law making it a national holiday.</p>
<p>Music was a part of many Labor Day marches.</p>
<p>One American labor song is called <em>Bread and Roses</em>. It is based on a 1911 poem by James Oppenheim. The poem speaks about the women's labor movement. At that time, conditions in factories, where many women worked, were horrible. A fire at a clothing factory in New York killed 146 people. Most of the victims were immigrant women.</p>
<p><strong>Labor Day activities</strong></p>
<p>For the three-day Labor Day weekend, many Americans head to airports and highways for end-of-summer escapes. They visit beaches, mountains or lakes. Some prepare outdoor cookouts for family and friends.</p>
<p>The <a class="wsw__a" href="https://newsroom.acg.aaa.com/aaas-travel-trends-and-tips-for-labor-day-weekend/">American Automobile Association (AAA) said</a>, “Americans see the extended Labor Day weekend as an <strong>opportunity</strong> to say <strong>farewell</strong> to summer with one final trip.” The group said Labor Day weekend travel in the U.S. went up nine percent compared to last year.</p>
<p>Robert F. Moss is a barbecue expert and historian. He wrote the book <em>Barbecue: The History of an American Institution</em>. Moss said barbecue was already an American tradition when the labor movements developed in the late 19th century. He noted that it was a natural way to celebrate as large groups gathered.</p>
<p>“It still has a lot of that same communal sense, gathering around the grill, eating together,” he told the Associated Press.</p>
<p><strong>Not wearing white after Labor Day</strong></p>
<p>Americans also have a saying that one should not wear white after Labor Day.</p>
<p>That may sound strange, but it is true. Many Americans put away their white clothes on Labor Day and do not wear them again until the following May, after Memorial Day.</p>
<p>One reason for the clothing custom relates to the season. In the U.S., the months between June and September are summer. The weather is usually hot and people wear light-colored clothing to keep cool.</p>
<p>Clothing experts say it likely goes back to the Gilded Age — the same period in the late 1800s that started Labor Day. Wealthy New Yorkers in places such as Newport, Rhode Island, would put away their cool, white clothing at the end of the summer. And they returned to the city with darker, heavier clothes for dirt-packed streets.</p>
<p>After the pandemic, many businesses and people have turned to more relaxed clothing. So the saying, or rule, might not be true anymore.</p>
<p>But you may want to be careful about wearing white to an American-style Labor Day barbecue. The trouble is not fashion – it is <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/ketchup-an-american-condiment-with-an-asian-connection/3961575.html">ketchup</a>. If it spills, the popular red tomato sauce can ruin that nice set of white clothes.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith. And I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Hai Do, Mario Ritter Jr., Kelly Jean Kelly, Jerilyn Watson and Nancy Steinbach contributed to this report. Additional information came from The Associated Press and the AAA.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>opportunity</strong> - n. chance, occasion</p>
<p><strong>farewell</strong> - n. goodbye</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Nigerian Herders Bring Cows to City in Search of Grass (2024/9/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/nigerian-herders-bring-cows-to-city-in-search-of-grass.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Angry drivers <strong>honk</strong> as <strong>cattle</strong> slowly march across and feed on the grass in the middle of the streets. It is a common sight for drivers in Nigeria's capital city Abuja. For the young <strong>herder</strong> guiding them, Ismail Abubakar, it is just another day.</p>
<p>Abubakar did not choose to bring his cattle to the city center. His family is from Katsina State in northern Nigeria, where a changing climate turned <strong>grazing</strong> lands into a desert. He moved to Idu — a rural less developed part of Abuja — many years ago. But it now has a large train station and many homes and businesses.</p>
<p>Herders like Abubakar usually bring their cattle to the wild countryside to graze. But the need for housing, crop farming and climate change are taking away the land and their way of life.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A boy guides cattle on a road in Abuja, Nigeria, Friday, Aug. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Olamikan Gbemiga)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-7903-08dcc779917a_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A boy guides cattle on a road in Abuja, Nigeria, Friday, Aug. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Olamikan Gbemiga)</span></div>
<p>To keep cattle off Abuja's streets, some suggest that herders need to start buying private land and operating like other businesses. But to do that, they would need money and government support.</p>
<p>Baba Ngelzarma is the president of Miyetti Allah Cattle Breeders Association of Nigeria, a herders' support group. He said, "The herders take the cattle wherever they can find green grasses and water at least for the cows to survive, not minding whether it is the city or somebody's land.”</p>
<p>He added that part of the problem is the lack of government support for the industry, such as water, animal care, and price control. The government announced a new ministry to support the industry in July. But it does not have a minister yet.</p>
<p><strong>Fewer places to go</strong></p>
<p>Nigeria is home to over 20 million cows, mostly owned by herders from the Fulani ethnic group. The country has the fourth-largest cattle population in Africa. Its <strong>dairy</strong> market is valued at $1.5 billion. But, the US International Trade Administration says imports meet about 90 percent of local demand.</p>
<p>It shows how poorly organized the industry is, Ngelzarma said, as cows affected by constant moving and poor diets cannot produce milk.</p>
<p>There are four areas surrounding Abuja that have been put aside for cattle grazing. But they are not readily available and have been taken by other crop farmers and illegal settlers, Ngelzarma added.</p>
<p>Without grazing land, herders set up settlements anywhere and stay for as long as they can before land owners claim it or the government builds on it.</p>
<p>Mohammed Abbas is a 67-year-old herder. He has repeatedly had to move over the years. Most of his current settlement in the city's Life Camp neighborhood has been taken over by a newly constructed gas station. The remaining land will soon be claimed by another owner.</p>
<p>Abbas said that he would have to sell all his cows to have enough money to buy land for a settlement. It means that he would have nothing left “to put on the land.”</p>
<p>Hassan Mohammed's family now occupies a piece of land near the Idu train station. Once a large area of grassland, the area has turned into housing and roadways. Despite repeated orders from the owners to leave, Mohammed said that his family would stay put, using the land as their home base while taking their cattle elsewhere each day for grazing.</p>
<p>“Many don't have anywhere to call home, so they just find somewhere to sleep at night with the cattle,” said Mohammed. “But for us, we are not leaving except there is a new place within Abuja.”</p>
<p>Folawiyo Daniel is an Abuja-based housing developer. He said the issue is a failure of urban planning and urged the government to bring back grazing areas in the city for herders.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Taiwo Adebayo reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>honk </strong>– <em>v</em>. <em>of a horn</em>: to make a loud sound</p>
<p><strong>cattle</strong> – <em>n.</em> cows, bulls, or steers that are kept on a farm or ranch for meat or milk</p>
<p><strong>herder</strong> – <em>n</em>. a person who gathers and moves (a group of animals)</p>
<p><strong>graze</strong> – v. <em>of an animal:</em> to eat grass or other plants that are growing in a field, pasture, or the like</p>
<p><strong>dairy</strong> – <em>n.</em> milk or food made from milk (such as ice cream, cheese, or yogurt)</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>An Eye for an Eye (2024/9/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/an-eye-for-an-eye.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo and Mario Ritter</span><br/><span class="datetime">31 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Today we talk to you about expressions dealing with payback, getting even, and <strong>revenge</strong>.</p>
<p>When a person wants to <u>even the <strong>score</strong></u>, that person might have the <strong>proverb</strong> <u>an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth</u> in mind.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This April 12, 2018 photo shows a very close up image of a woman's eye. (AP Photo/Patrick Sison)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-3685-08db70f22800_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This April 12, 2018 photo shows a very close up image of a woman's eye. (AP Photo/Patrick Sison)</span></div>
<p>The <em>Merriam-Webster</em> online dictionary describes it as a “repayment in kind as revenge for an injustice.”</p>
<p>In kind means “in the same way.”</p>
<p>The expression <u>an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth</u> is ancient. It appears in <em>The Bible</em> and in <em>The Code of Hammurabi</em>, a set of laws written by the ancient Babylonian king of that name.</p>
<p><u>An eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth</u> describes a way of thinking. It is the idea that <strong>retaliating </strong>in kind is the best way to deal with a crime or some other offense.</p>
<p>It is the idea that a person who causes someone to suffer should suffer in the same amount and in the same way. For example, if someone did something to hurt you, you would want to hurt them equally.</p>
<p>To remind others of the proverb, people often simply say <u>an eye for an eye.</u></p>
<p>For some people, every second counts when they are looking <u>to settle a score</u>. For others, the revenge method might require patience. Some people wait years or a lifetime to get their revenge.</p>
<p>The way people <u>settle the score</u> can be very different. Some cultures have this expression: <u>Revenge is a dish best served cold</u>. The idea is that <u>settling the score</u> over time without emotion is the best way.</p>
<p>A similar expression is <u>tit</u><u> for tat</u>.</p>
<p><u>Tit for tat</u> is often used to describe diplomatic disagreements between nations. It is hundreds of years old. Both “tit” and “tat” mean the same thing: a “strike” or a “blow.” Experts say the expression changed from <u>tip for tap</u> to its present form after years of sound changes in the English language.</p>
<p><u>Tit for tat</u> <strong>literally</strong> means <u>blow for blow</u>. <em>Merriam-Webster</em> says it is: “An equal return given for some wrong that's been done.”</p>
<p>Now, let's hear two friends use some revenge expressions.</p>
<p><em>A: Did you hear what happened to Tom? Someone <strong>slashed</strong> his tires! It cost him hundreds of dollars to replace the ruined tires. </em></p>
<p><em>B: That sounds awful. Does he know who did it? </em></p>
<p><em>A: He suspects it was his ex-girlfriend, Diana. </em></p>
<p><em>B: Why?</em></p>
<p><em>A: Well, he scratched up the paint on her car last week. I'm still friends with Diana and she told me a security camera caught him doing it. It cost her hundreds of dollars to repaint her car. </em></p>
<p><em>B: Well, it sounds like they're even now. You know, <u>an eye for an eye</u> and all that</em>...</p>
<p>And that's Words and Their Stories. Until next time ...</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo and Mario Ritter wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em><u><i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;_____________________________________________</u></em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>revenge </strong><em>–n.</em> hurting someone because they hurt you first</p>
<p><strong>score </strong><em>–n.</em> an accounting in numbers or some other measure that shows who is winning and who is losing in a competition</p>
<p><strong>proverb </strong><em>–n.</em> a short saying that expresses what people recognize as a truth or important idea</p>
<p><strong>retaliate</strong><em> –v. </em>to strike back against a wrong or attack</p>
<p><strong>literally </strong><em>–adv.</em> formally defined as</p>
<p><strong>slash </strong><em>–v.</em> to use a knife or similar instrument to cut into something and severely damage it</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How to Prevent Jet Lag, Enjoy Travel (2024/8/31)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/how-to-prevent-jet-lag-enjoy-travel.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">30 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Many travelers face a common problem: jet lag.</p>
<p>It is the feeling of tiredness people get when traveling a long distance, resulting in a difference in daylight hours. Nobody wants to miss the fun because they are too tired to enjoy their vacation.</p>
<p>Here are some tips on how to deal with jet lag:</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A holiday traveler looks out at a airplane at Salt Lake City International Airport, in Salt Lake City, July 3, 2024. (AP Photo/Rick Bowmer, File)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-45c7-08dcc2e4ca64_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A holiday traveler looks out at a airplane at Salt Lake City International Airport, in Salt Lake City, July 3, 2024. (AP Photo/Rick Bowmer, File)
</span></div>
<p><strong>What is jet lag?</strong></p>
<p>Scientists define jet lag as the effect on the human body of traveling across <strong>time zones</strong>. Sofia Axelrod studies <strong>circadian</strong> <strong>rhythms</strong> at Rockefeller University in New York. She said a circadian rhythm is like a biological clock programmed into almost every cell in the body.</p>
<p>"The clock is set by the 24-hour light and dark <strong>pattern</strong>," Axelrod said. "Every morning when we wake up, specialized (light) receptor cells in our <strong>retina</strong> receive a daylight signal, which is <strong>transmitted</strong> to the brain and from there, (to) the whole body."</p>
<p>When we travel to another time zone, our eyes do not receive the daylight signal at the usual time. This causes our “internal clocks” to reset. But that process can take a while. During that period, we feel the effects of jet lag.</p>
<p><strong>Is jet lag preventable?</strong></p>
<p>People who travel long distances often want to prevent jet lag. One way has a high cost.</p>
<p>Malcolm von Schantz is a professor who specializes in circadian rhythms at Northumbria University in Newcastle, England. He said that paying a lot for a bigger seat and more space in an airplane can prevent sleep <strong>deprivation</strong>.</p>
<p>He knows most people cannot pay so much to travel. But he said timing your flights can help. For example, he suggests flying from Europe to North America during the day, so that it is evening when passengers land and they can get to sleep.</p>
<p>"If you take the evening flight instead, you'll be woken up at midnight to be served breakfast and land an hour or two later, when both jet lag and sleep deprivation will hit you hard," he said.</p>
<p>Von Schantz also said flying in newer model passenger jets, like the Airbus A350 or Boeing 787 Dreamliner, might help. He said those planes can maintain a more <strong>comfortable</strong> atmosphere inside, causing less tiredness.</p>
<p><strong>What should you do when you arrive?</strong></p>
<p>Experts say being in sunlight is important to resetting your internal body clock. That could mean either avoiding morning sun or seeking it out, depending on where you started.</p>
<p>Getting light in the morning will move your body clock forward, while light exposure in the early evening will delay it. Sleeping for a short time during the day is acceptable, but scientists warn against sleeping for longer periods later in the day. Doing so might make it harder to sleep through the night.</p>
<p><strong>Are there supplements or medicines for jet lag?</strong></p>
<p>The brain naturally produces a chemical <strong>hormone</strong> called melatonin when the body thinks it is night. Taking melatonin as a supplement can be helpful. But it is not available everywhere and, in some countries like Britain and France, you need a doctor's permission.</p>
<p>Von Schantz said that one of the good effects of melatonin is that you can start taking it before you travel, to begin the process of resetting your internal clock.</p>
<p>"If you're in a part of the world where melatonin is available <strong>over the counter</strong>, you can combine the effects of light and melatonin to achieve the advance or delay (in your body clock) that you need," he said.</p>
<p><strong>What can you do to deal with the effects of jet lag?</strong></p>
<p>Russell Foster of Oxford University wrote a book on circadian rhythms. He said business travelers might want to consider arriving a day or two ahead of any important meetings or events. Being jet-lagged can lead to unwise decisions and unpleasant emotions.</p>
<p>Tourists might not need to think as clearly as business travelers, but they should still be careful, he said. He advises tourists to get enough sleep before doing anything that might be risky or that requires a lot of attention, like driving.</p>
<p>Foster said he tries to increase his exposure to light when he arrives at a new place to prevent jet lag. But he also has another method if light does not help: he drinks coffee.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Maria Cheng reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>jet lag</strong><em> – n.</em> a tired and unpleasant feeling that you sometimes get when you travel by airplane to a place that is far away</p>
<p><strong>time zone</strong> – <em>n</em>. any one of the world's 24 divisions that has its own time</p>
<p><strong>circadian rhythm</strong> – <em>n</em>. repeated activity in an organism that happens in 24-hour periods</p>
<p><strong>pattern </strong>–n. a regular or repeated happening</p>
<p><strong>retina</strong> – <em>n</em>. the sensitive tissue at the back of the eye that receives images and sends signals to the brain about what is seen</p>
<p><strong>deprivation</strong> – <em>n</em>. the state of not having something that people need</p>
<p><strong>comfortable </strong>–adj. to feel good and to not feel pain or discomfort</p>
<p><strong>hormone </strong>–n. a chemical produced by the body that influences how the body grows and develops</p>
<p><strong>over the counter</strong> – <em>expression</em>. available for purchase without a special note (called a prescription) from a doctor</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>'The Murders in the Rue Morgue,' by Edgar Allen Poe, Part Three (2024/8/31)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/murders-in-rue-morgue-edgar-allen-poe-part-three.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By The story was originally</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">30 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>
<em>We present the third of five parts of the short story "The Murders in the Rue Morgue," by Edgar Allen Poe. The story was originally adapted and recorded by VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>My <strong>housemate</strong> in Paris, August Dupin, was an interesting young man with a busy, forceful mind. This mind could, it seemed, look right through a man's body into his deepest soul.</p>
<p>After reading in the newspaper about the terrible murder of a woman and her daughter, Dupin was <strong>consumed</strong> with the mystery. He questioned the ability of the Paris police to solve the crime. I told Dupin that it seemed to me that it was not possible to explain the strange details surrounding the killings.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/086fca59-1403-43a6-bd32-4490b048ecf6_w100_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>“No, no. I think you are wrong. A mystery it is, yes. But there must be an answer. There must! Let us go to the house where it happened and see what we can see. I know the head of the police, and he will permit our visit. It will be interesting and give us some pleasure.”</p>
<p>I thought it strange that Dupin thought the activity would give us pleasure. But I said nothing.</p>
<p>It was late in the afternoon when we reached the house on the Rue Morgue. It was easily found, for there were still many persons — in fact, a crowd, standing there looking at it. Before going in, we walked all around it, and Dupin carefully looked at the <strong>neighboring</strong> houses as well. I could not understand the reason for such great care.</p>
<p>Finally, we entered the house. We went up the stairs to the room where the daughter's body was found. Both bodies were in the room now. The police had left the room as they had found it in every other way. I saw nothing beyond what the newspaper had told us.</p>
<p>Dupin looked with great care at everything, at the bodies, the walls, the fireplace, the windows. Then we went home. Dupin said nothing. I could see the cold look in his eyes, which told me that his mind was working, working busily, quickly.</p>
<p>Dupin said nothing about our exploration until the next morning when he suddenly asked me a question.</p>
<p>“Did you not notice something especially strange about what we saw at the house on the Rue Morgue?”</p>
<p>“Nothing more than what we both read in the newspaper, which was unusual indeed. How shall we explain the horrible force, the unusual strength used in these murders? And whose were the voices that were heard? No one was found except the dead women; yet there was no way for anyone to escape. And the wild condition of the room; the body which was found head-down in the chimney; the terrible broken appearance of the body of the old lady, with its head cut off-- these are all so far from what might be expected that the police are standing still; they don't know where to begin.”</p>
<p>“These things are unusual, indeed, but they are not deep mysteries. We should not ask, ‘What has happened?' but ‘What has happened that has never happened before?' In fact, the very things that the police think cannot possibly be explained are the things which will lead me to the answer. Indeed, I believe they have already led me to the answer.”</p>
<p>I was so surprised that I could not say a word. Dupin looked quickly at the door.</p>
<p>“I am now waiting for a person who will know something about these murders, these wild killings. I do not think he did them himself. But I think he will know the killer. I hope I am right about this. If I am, then I expect to find the whole answer, today. I expect the man here — in this room — at any <strong>moment</strong>. It is true that he may not come, but he probably will.”</p>
<p>“But who is this person? How did you find him?”</p>
<p>“I'll tell you. While we wait for this man we do not know — for I have never met him — while we wait, I will tell you how my thoughts went.”</p>
<p>Dupin began to talk. But it did not seem that he was trying to explain to me what he had thought. It seemed that he was talking to himself. He looked not at me, but at the wall.</p>
<p>“It has been fully proved that the voices heard by the neighbors were not the voices of the women who were killed. Someone else was in the room. It is therefore <strong>certain</strong> that the old woman did not first kill her daughter and then kill herself. She would not have been strong enough to put her daughter's body where it was found. And the manner of the old lady's death shows that she could not have caused it herself. A person can kill himself with a knife, yes. But he surely cannot cut his own head almost off, then drop the knife on the floor and jump out the window. It was murder, then, done by some third person — or persons. And the voices heard were the voices of these persons. Let us now think carefully about the things people said about those voices. Did you <strong>notice</strong> anything especially strange in what was told about them?”</p>
<p>“Well, yes. Everybody agreed that the low voice was the voice of a Frenchman, but they could not agree about the high voice.”</p>
<p>“Ah! That was what they said, yes, but that was not what was so strange about what they said. You say you have noticed nothing that makes their stories very different from what might have been expected. Yet there was something. All these persons, as you say, agreed about the low voice, but not about the high hard voice. The strange thing here is that when an Italian, an Englishman, a Spaniard, and a Frenchman tried to tell what the voice was like, each one said it sounded like the voice of a foreigner. How strangely unusual that voice really must have been! Here are four men from four big countries, and not one of them could understand what the voice said; each one gave it a different name.</p>
<p>“Now, I know that there are other countries in the world. You will say that <strong>perhaps</strong> it was the voice of someone from one of those other lands — Russia, perhaps. But remember, not one of these people heard anything that sounded like a separate word.</p>
<p>Here, Dupin turned and looked into my eyes.</p>
<p>“This is what we have learned from the newspaper. I don't know what I have led you to think. But I believe that in this much of the story there are enough facts to lead us in the one and only direction to the right answer. What this answer is, I will not say...not yet. But I want you to keep in mind that this much was enough to tell me what I must look for when we were in that house on the Rue Morgue. And I found it!</p>
<p>“What did I first look for? The path of escape, of course. I mean, we agree the killers were not <strong>ghosts</strong>; they could not move through walls. So, how did they escape?</p>
<p>“At first I saw no way out. It had been necessary for the neighbors to break down the door in order to enter the room. There was no other door. The opening above the fireplace is too narrow for even a child to go through. That leaves only the windows. We must make that exit somehow possible.</p>
<p>“Remember, there are two windows in the room. Both of them, you will remember, are made of two parts; to open the window one must lift up the bottom half. One of these windows is easily seen; the lower part of the other is out of sight behind the big bed. I looked carefully at the first of these windows. It was firmly closed, <strong>fastened</strong>, like the door, on the inside. To keep the window closed, to fasten it, someone had put a strong iron <strong>nail</strong> into the wood at the side of the window in such a way that the window could not be raised. At least it seemed that the nail held the window closed. The nail was easy to see. There it was. And the people who discovered the killings used their greatest strength and could not raise the window. I, too, tried to raise the window and could not.</p>
<p>“I went to the second window and looked behind the bed at the lower half of the window. There was a nail here, too, which held the window closed. Without moving the bed, I tried to open this window also, and again I could not do so. But I did not stop looking for an answer there.”</p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>housemate </strong>– <em>n</em>. a person who lives in the same house with another person but is not a part of that person's family</p>
<p><strong>consume</strong>(<strong>d</strong>) – <em>v.</em> to take all of a person's attention, energy or time</p>
<p><strong>neighboring</strong> – <em>adj.</em> near or next to something or someone</p>
<p><strong>moment</strong> – <em>n.</em> a very short period of time</p>
<p><strong>certain </strong>– <em>adj.</em> used with <em>it</em> to say that something is known to be true or correct</p>
<p><strong>notice</strong> – <em>v</em>. to become aware of something or someone by seeing or hearing it</p>
<p><strong>perhaps</strong> – <em>adv.</em> possibly but not certainly</p>
<p><strong>ghost</strong>(<strong>s</strong>) – <em>n</em>. the soul of a dead person thought of as living in an unseen world or as appearing to living people</p>
<p><strong>fasten</strong>(<strong>ed</strong>) – <em>v</em>. to attach something or join two things or two parts of something especially by using a pin, nail or something else</p>
<p><strong>nail</strong> – <em>n.</em> a long, thin piece of metal that is sharp at one end and flat at the other end and that is used chiefly to attach things to wood</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Learning English Expressions or Idioms (2024/8/31)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/learning-english-expressions-or-idioms.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">30 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we consider expressions, or idioms, and offer some advice for learning them.</p>
<p>An idiom is an expression formed from two or more words. But an idiom's meaning often cannot be understood just by knowing each of the words in it.</p>
<p>Let's look at the following sentence as an example:</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-31a7-08dcc6d1af4a_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p><em>We want our students to think <u>outside the box</u>.</em></p>
<p>Here, the words <u>outside the box</u> form an idiom. If you only heard this one sentence, you might not be sure what it means. But people use idioms in connection to situations. For that reason, they usually say more than one sentence, and this can help you understand the idiom. For example:</p>
<p><em>We want our students to think <u>outside the box</u>. That's why we push them to find creative ways to solve problems. </em></p>
<p>By looking at these two sentences together, it can be easier to understand the meaning of <u>outside the box</u>. It means to think in new or creative ways.</p>
<p>In addition to considering the situation to help you understand the meaning of idioms, here is some other advice:</p>
<ul>
<li>Digital translation tools continue to improve, but you should avoid translating the idioms directly, word-for-word, into your native language.</li>
<li>When you hear a short group of words that seem very unrelated to a subject under discussion, those words will often be an idiom.</li>
<li>Be sure to learn the tone, or feeling, an idiom carries with it. The best way to learn about the tone of idioms is to ask native speakers about them. Native speakers might also be able to tell you if an idiom is commonly or rarely used.</li>
</ul>
<p>When learning English, it will likely be easier for you to understand idioms than to use them in speaking.<em> </em>However, if you can use idioms correctly, that can help deepen your connection to native speakers.</p>
<p>With thousands of idioms in English, there is a lot to learn. But do not <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/words-and-their-stories-boxing-expressions/2510976.html">throw in the towel</a>, in other words, do not give up. Instead, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/7071060.html">knock yourself out</a>, or try hard, and do your best to learn them. And you will feel <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/6665119.html">proud as a peacock</a>!</p>
<p>You can learn all about idioms by following our <em><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/z/987">Words and Their Stories</a></em> program or you can download <em><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/7759089.html">In the Loop</a></em>, a guide to American English Idioms.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, do you have a question about American English? Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>UN Chief Issues Urgent Warning of Danger from Rising Pacific Sea Levels (2024/8/30) | 联合国秘书长就太平洋海面上升风险发出紧急警告</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/un-chief-issues-urgent-warning-of-danger-from-rising-pacific-sea-levels.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>United Nations Secretary-General Antonio Guterres says that rising ocean temperatures present urgent risks for people living in the Pacific Islands.<br/>
联合国秘书长安东尼奥·古特雷斯表示，海洋温度上升给太平洋岛屿居民带来了紧迫的风险。</p>
<p>Guterres made the comment while at the Pacific Islands Forum taking place in Tonga. The country is a collection of about 170 islands in the southwestern Pacific Ocean.<br/>
古特雷斯在汤加举行的太平洋岛屿论坛上发表了上述评论。该国由太平洋西南部约170个岛屿组成。</p>
<p>The U.N. chief said studies suggest the southwestern Pacific faces more extreme sea level rise than other parts of the world. The problem, he added, is linked to sea temperatures in the area that in some cases are three times higher than worldwide levels.<br/>
联合国秘书长表示，研究表明，太平洋西南地区的海平面上升比世界其他地区更为极端。他补充说，这个问题与该地区的海水温度有关，在某些情况下，该地区海水温度是全球水平的三倍。</p>
<p>Warmer temperatures cause water to expand and this can cause sea level rise.<br/>
温度升高会导致水膨胀，这可能会导致海平面上升。</p>
<p>"I am in Tonga to issue a global SOS – Save Our Seas – on rising sea levels," Guterres said.<br/>
古特雷斯说：“我在汤加是为了对海平面上升发出全球SOS——救救我们的海洋。”</p>
<p>The U.N. leader said that rising seas were "amplifying” the number and severity of storms and coastal flooding across the area. He said such flooding can destroy fisheries, damage crops and poison water. “All this puts Pacific Island nations in grave danger," he said.<br/>
这位联合国领导人表示，海平面上升正在“放大”该地区风暴和沿海洪水的发生次数和严重程度。他说，这种洪水会破坏渔业、破坏农作物和污染水。他说，“这些都让太平洋岛国处于严重危险之中。”</p>
<p>A report recently released by the U.N.'s World Meteorological Organization showed ocean temperatures in the southwestern Pacific are increasing at up to three times the worldwide rate.<br/>
联合国世界气象组织最近发布的一份报告显示，太平洋西南地区的海洋温度上升速度是全球的三倍。</p>
<p>Guterres said the Pacific islands are especially at risk because much of their land is “just one to two meters above sea level."<br/>
古特雷斯表示，太平洋岛屿尤其面临风险，因为它们的大部分土地“仅高出海平面一到两米”。</p>
<p>And, he added, "Half the infrastructure is within 500 meters of the sea."<br/>
他补充道，而且“一半的基础设施距离大海不到500米。”</p>
<p>Many scientists blame the planet's rising temperatures on pollution from fossil fuel use. Guterres said the Pacific Islands can expect additional sea level rise of 15 centimeters by 2050 if the pollution levels do not drop.<br/>
许多科学家将地球气温上升归咎于使用化石燃料造成的污染。古特雷斯表示，如果污染水平不下降，到2050年，太平洋岛屿的海平面预计将进一步上升15厘米。</p>
<p>Guterres urged world leaders to greatly increase the level of climate-related investments, especially for at-risk countries, to help fight the problem.<br/>
古特雷斯敦促世界各国领导人大幅提高与气候相关的投资水平，特别是对高风险国家的投资，以帮助应对这一问题。</p>
<p>Delegates to the 2023 U.N. climate change conference approved the establishment of a "loss and damage" fund to help poor nations deal with climate disasters.<br/>
2023年联合国气候变化大会的代表们批准设立一个“损失和损害”基金，以帮助贫困国家应对气候灾害。</p>
<p>"Developed countries must deliver on their finance commitments,” Guterres said. He added that one commitment calls for doubling financing to at least $40 billion a year by 2025.<br/>
古特雷斯说：“发达国家必须履行其财政承诺。”他补充说，其中一项承诺要求到2025年将资金翻一番，达到每年至少400亿美元。</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.<br/>
我是布莱恩·林恩。(21VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Florida’s Snake Hunters (2024/8/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/florida-s-snake-hunters.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>It is after midnight when the windshield <strong>fogs</strong> up on Thomas Aycock's pickup truck. He smiles as he slowly drives through the sawgrass and down dirt roads deep in the Florida Everglades.</p>
<p>His foggy windshield confirms what he knows. When the dew point drops in the middle of the night, it is perfect time for pythons.</p>
<p>“I catch more pythons when that happens,” Aycock said. The retired U.S. Army veteran always takes part in the Florida Python Challenge. The wildlife commission runs the 10-day event. The aim is to get people interested in finding and catching the snakes.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Thomas Aycock, left, and Tom Rahill show off an invasive Burmese python caught earlier, as they wait for sunset to hunt pythons on Aug. 13, 2024, in the Florida Everglades. (AP Photo/Wilfredo Lee)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-cb83-08dcc6adfeef_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Thomas Aycock, left, and Tom Rahill show off an invasive Burmese python caught earlier, as they wait for sunset to hunt pythons on Aug. 13, 2024, in the Florida Everglades. (AP Photo/Wilfredo Lee)</span></div>
<p>There is a reason for the timing of the event. Pythons usually <strong>hatch</strong> from their eggs each August before finding their way into the <strong>swamp</strong>.</p>
<p>Aycock works for the Florida Fish and Wildlife Conservation Commission. He has hunted Burmese pythons in the Everglades for 11 years. Aycok loves snakes. And he loves preserving the Everglades. He understands the “greater ecological issue with these pythons.”</p>
<p>The <strong>invasive</strong> Burmese pythons are doing very well in Florida's <strong>preserved</strong> wetlands. Pythons have no natural <strong>predators</strong>. And they are threatening Florida's <strong>native</strong> snakes and mammals. The United States Geological Survey (USGS) estimates tens of thousands live in South Florida.</p>
<p>The snakes are destroying local wildlife. In one 2012 study, the USGS found that populations of raccoons had declined by 99.3 percent, opossums by 98.9 percent and bobcats by 87.5 percent since the early 2000s. Controlling this hungry snake, scientists say, is a critical goal.</p>
<p>More than 600 hunters took part in this year's challenge. Their goal is to beat last year's top total of 209 pythons killed. The hunter who kills the most wins $10,000.</p>
<p>The competition is designed to create understanding about Florida's python problem. It has succeeded in doing that. The event has drawn famous people and has led to some reality television shows.</p>
<p>But the need for python control remains urgent.</p>
<p>Since 2017, Florida has been paying about 100 <strong>contractors</strong> to catch the snakes year-round. That project is shared by the wildlife agency and the South Florida Water Management District. Through 2023, more than 18,000 pythons have been removed from the wild. Contractors like Aycock have removed about 11,000.</p>
<p>The pay is average. Hunting along backroads pays $13 an hour. Walking through the swamp pays $18 an hour. Contractors also get paid per snake: $50 for the first 1.2 meters in length, plus more for longer snakes.</p>
<p>“You're not going to make a living doing this full-time. There's no way you could do it,” Aycock said.</p>
<p>Florida does not permit hunters to use firearms to kill pythons<strong>.</strong> Catching them is a hands-on exercise.</p>
<p>Aycock goes into the wetlands to check on known hatching spots and grabs at them when he can. But mostly he drives down empty roads at night, shining a strong light into the swamps.</p>
<p>He says these bug-filled drives help his mental health. Sometimes he brings along fellow members of the Swamp Apes, a mental health non-profit organization for veterans. The group catches invasive snakes in the wild, clears overgrown areas, and works toward environmental preservation.</p>
<p>The group's founder, Tom Rahill, is also a snake hunting contractor. He knows the swamp so well that he can smell a python's “musk” odor. He says he can feel when a snake is near.</p>
<p>There is an art to catching a snake, the hunters say. The methods change from hunter to hunter. Some use a snake hook and then jump on them before putting them into bags. Rahill likes using his hands -- if the snake is calm enough.</p>
<p>“Instead of jumping on the snake, you just kind of gently get up to it and then just pick it up,” he said.</p>
<p>But the snakes are not always calm. Sometimes a hunter needs a helper to keep the snake <strong>uncoiled</strong> until it calms down and can be contained to prevent escape.</p>
<p>Once the snakes are caught, the hunters have 24 hours to take them to the wildlife agency. It is illegal for any person other than a <strong>licensed</strong> contractor to transport a live, invasive snake.</p>
<p>Aycock takes them home first to be “humanely killed.”</p>
<p>“That's the part of the job that I really just ... hate,” he said. “I hate having to kill snakes.”</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Stephany Matat reported this story for The Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>fog (up)</strong> <em>– v.</em> when small particles of water floating in the atmosphere are near the ground and on surfaces</p>
<p><strong>hatch</strong> <em>– v. </em>to emerge from an egg, chrysalis, or pupa</p>
<p><strong>swamp </strong><em>– n. </em>wet spongy land often partly covered with water</p>
<p><strong>invasive</strong> <em>– adj. </em>tending to spread especially in a quick or aggressive manner: such as<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>preserved </strong><em>– v. </em>to keep safe from injury, harm, or destruction</p>
<p><strong>predator</strong> <em>– n. </em>an animal that obtains food mostly by killing and eating other animals</p>
<p><strong>native </strong><em>– adj. </em>living or growing naturally in a particular region</p>
<p><strong>contractor </strong><em>– n. </em>a person who contracts to perform work or provide supplies at a certain price or within a certain time</p>
<p><strong>coiled </strong><em>– v. </em>to wind into or lie in loops, rings, or a spiral : <strong>uncoiled </strong><em>– v. </em>to unwind from a coil and become straight</p>
<p><strong>licensed </strong><em>– adj. </em>having permission granted by competent authority to engage in a business or occupation or in an activity otherwise unlawful</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>If You Learn Conditionals, You'll Be Glad You Did! (2024/8/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/if-you-learn-conditionals-you-ll-be-glad-you-did.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Adam Brock</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>
In this week's episode of Everyday Grammar, we are going to talk about <strong>conditionals</strong>. We use conditionals to show that something is true only when something else is true. Conditionals offer endless possibilities for creative and <strong>imaginative</strong> expression.</p>
<p><strong>Present real conditional</strong></p>
<p>The present real conditional is the most <strong>basic</strong> kind of conditional. Basically, <em>when A happens, B happens</em>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/77c20b4b-9201-4f25-a3a2-de2c72878152_tv_w100_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>Here's an example of a present real conditional:</p>
<p>"If it rains, I bring an umbrella."</p>
<p>Conditionals have two parts: the <em>if</em> <strong>clause</strong>: "if it rains," and the <em>result </em>clause: "I bring an umbrella." You could also say "I bring an umbrella if it rains."</p>
<p>Poets and songwriters often use conditionals in their work. Listen for the present real conditional in this song by American songwriter Bob Dylan.</p>
<p>"If you see her, say hello. She might be in Tangier ..."</p>
<p>Notice that the verbs <em>see</em> and <em>say</em> are both in the present <strong>tense</strong> for the present real conditional.</p>
<p><strong>Present unreal conditional</strong></p>
<p>The next conditional that we're going to talk about is the present <strong>unreal</strong> conditional. Use the present unreal conditional to talk about what you would do in an unreal, or imaginary situation: <em>If A happened, B would happen.</em></p>
<p>For example, "If I were you, I would take the job." The key word is <em>would; </em>it makes the conditional unreal<em>. Would </em>can only be used in the <em>result clause</em> of the sentence. Here's an example from American singer Johnny Cash.</p>
<p>"If I were a carpenter<br/>
And you were a lady<br/>
Would you marry me anyway?<br/>
Would you have my baby?"</p>
<p>To form a present unreal conditional, use a simple past verb in the <em>if </em>clause. In the <em>result</em> clause, use <em>would</em> followed by a simple present verb.</p>
<p>Use the verb <em>were</em> for all nouns in the<em> if</em> clause of the sentence. For example, "If she <em>were</em> an animal, she would be a cat." In informal speech, people might say, "If she <em>was </em>an animal, she would be a cat." But you should avoid this in formal writing.</p>
<p><strong>Future real conditional</strong></p>
<p>Now let's talk about the future real conditional: <em>If A happens, B will happen</em>.</p>
<p>To make a future real conditional, use <em>will</em> in the result clause. For example, "If your plane is late, I <em>will </em>wait in the car." Use the future real conditional to talk about possible situations in the future.</p>
<p>Speakers sometimes use the future real conditional to threaten others. Listen to actor Liam Neeson in the 2013 movie "Taken." In this scene of the movie, Neeson's character is on the phone threatening the man who kidnapped his daughter.</p>
<p>"If you let my daughter go now, that'll be the end of it. I will not look for you. I will not pursue you. But if you don't, I will look for you, I will find you, and I will kill you."</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p>This is only a quick introduction to conditionals. In a future episode of Everyday Grammar, we will talk about past and mixed conditionals. Until then, we will leave you with country music stars Johnny Cash and June Carter.</p>
<p>"If you were a carpenter<br/>
And I were a lady<br/>
I'd marry you anyway<br/>
I'd have your baby"</p>
<p></p><p>I'm Jonathan Evans.</p>
<p><em>Adam Brock wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. Jill Robbins and Ashley Thompson were the editors.</em></p>
<p><em>______________________________________________</em></p>
<table cellpadding="3" class="wsw__table"><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" style="width:500px">
<p>REFERENCE – Three common conditionals (incomplete list)</p>
</td></tr><tr></tr><tr><td> </td><td>If clause</td><td>Result clause</td></tr><tr><td>Present Real</td><td>
<p>If you <strong>see </strong>her,</p>
<p><em>Simple present</em></p>
</td><td>
<p><strong>say</strong> hello.</p>
<p><em>Simple present</em></p>
</td></tr><tr><td>Present Unreal</td><td>
<p>If I <strong>were </strong>you,</p>
<p><em>Simple past</em></p>
</td><td>
<p>I <strong>would leave</strong>.</p>
<p><em>Would + simple present</em></p>
</td></tr><tr><td>Future Real</td><td>
<p>If your plane <strong>is </strong>late,</p>
<p><em>Simple present</em></p>
</td><td>
<p>I <strong>will wait</strong> for you.</p>
<p><em>Simple future</em></p>
</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Lesson</h2>
<p><strong>conditional</strong> - <em>n.</em> a word, clause, or sentence that shows that something is true or happens only if something else is true or happens</p>
<p><strong>imaginative</strong> - <em>adj. </em>having or showing an ability to think of new and interesting ideas <strong>:</strong> having or showing imagination</p>
<p><strong>basic</strong> – <em>adj</em>. forming or relating to the first or easiest part of something</p>
<p><strong>clause</strong> - <em>n</em>. <em>grammar</em> <strong>:</strong> a part of a sentence that has its own subject and verb</p>
<p><strong>tense</strong> - <em>n.</em> a form of a verb that is used to show when an action happened</p>
<p><strong>unreal</strong> - <em>adj.</em> not real; not true</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Study Amazon Dolphins in Effort to Prevent Deaths (2024/8/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/scientists-study-amazon-dolphins-in-effort-to-prevent-deaths.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>About 200 freshwater dolphins were found dead in Lake Tefé of the Amazon River in Brazil during a period of severe dry weather last year.</p>
<p>That is why a team of biologists, animal doctors, and fishermen temporarily captured some river dolphins recently to study their health. The researchers hope the findings will help protect the dolphins from another weather disaster.</p>
<p>One of the captured dolphins was a female with her <strong>offspring</strong> nearby. Fishermen were careful not to injure her and kept her close to her offspring to avoid <strong>stressing</strong> the animals.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Field researchers from the Mamirau&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;225; Institute of Sustainable Development check the health of a rare Amazon river dolphin, also known as the pink river dolphin, in Lake Tef&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;233;, Amazonas state, Brazil, August 19, 2024. (REUTERS/Bruno Kelly)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-61ee-08dcc391f9bf_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Field researchers from the Mamirau<i>&amp;#</i>225; Institute of Sustainable Development check the health of a rare Amazon river dolphin, also known as the pink river dolphin, in Lake Tef<i>&amp;#</i>233;, Amazonas state, Brazil, August 19, 2024. (REUTERS/Bruno Kelly)</span></div>
<p>"She relaxed and we could do all the tests. She appeared in good health," said project leader Miriam Marmontel. She is a researcher at the Mamirauá Institute of Sustainable Development based in Tefé, Brazil. The organization planned the temporary capture of up to 20 dolphins.</p>
<p>The team took blood from the animals and performed other medical tests. The work included removing a small amount of fat to see if harmful chemicals were in the dolphin's body. They also put microchips in the animals to follow their movements.</p>
<p>The Solim<i></i>245;es River feeds water into Lake Tefé. Unusually dry weather last year caused water <strong>levels</strong> in the river to drop. As a result, the water became warmer than usual. Thousands of fish also died in the Amazon rivers because of a lack of oxygen in the water.</p>
<p>Many Amazon river dolphins are the color pink. They are found only in the rivers of South America, and they are among only a few kinds of freshwater dolphins still living in the world. Because they reproduce slowly, threats to their environment can more easily reduce their populations.</p>
<p>Marmontel said researchers hope to better understand what caused last year's deaths, so that experts and officials can react faster to the effects of this year's dry weather.</p>
<p>"We aim to learn more about the health of the dolphins at a time when water begins to go down and temperatures start to rise, so we can identify the changes and know whether they are due to higher temperatures or a <strong>toxin</strong> or pollutant in the water," she told Reuters.</p>
<p>The river dolphin research project received financial support from the National Marine Mammal Foundation of California in the United States. That organization's researchers helped examine the dolphins using <strong>ultrasound</strong> technology.</p>
<p>Marmontel said most of the dolphins that died last year were in Lake Tefé. The lake is very close to the Solim<i></i>245;es River.</p>
<p>The lake's waters reached 40.9 degrees Celsius during the 2023 dry season, more than 10 degrees higher than the average for that time of year. The water is now at 30 degrees Celsius, said Ayan Fleischmann. He is a geosciences researcher at the Mamirauá Institute.</p>
<p>Environmental activists have blamed climate change for the severe dry weather that made the river water warmer than normal. However, El Ni<i></i>241;o, the periodic and natural Pacific Ocean warming weather event could also have brought about last year's dry weather in the Amazon.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Bruno Kelly reported this story for Reuters. Andrew Smith adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>offspring </strong><em>-n. </em>an animal or child as related to its parent</p>
<p><strong>stress </strong><em>-v. </em>to cause worry or anxiety</p>
<p><strong>level </strong><em>-n. </em>the height of the surface of a body of water or other substance</p>
<p><strong>toxin </strong><em>-n. </em>a poisonous substance produced by animals, plants, or bacteria</p>
<p><strong>ultrasound </strong><em>-n. </em>sound waves that are used to get images of the inside of a human or animal body</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Humans Show Birds How to Fly South for Winter (2024/8/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/humans-show-birds-how-to-fly-south-for-winter.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Humans hunted and killed almost all northern bald ibis birds by the 17th century. But <strong>breeding</strong> and rewilding efforts over the last 20 years helped grow the bird population.</p>
<p>However, the birds do not know which direction to fly to <strong>migrate</strong> without the guidance of wild-born birds. So, humans are helping the birds learn their migration path.</p>
<p>The northern bald ibis once flew over North Africa, the Arabian Peninsula and much of Europe, including southern Germany's Bavaria. People liked eating the migratory birds, and they disappeared from Europe. A few groups of the birds survived in other places.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This photo provided by Waldrappteam Conservation &amp; Research shows the migration from Northern Bald Ibis, or the Waldrapp, supported by foster parents of the birds in a microlight aircraft. (Waldrappteam Conservation &amp; Research via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-1f07-08dcc6bcee1c_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This photo provided by Waldrappteam Conservation &amp; Research shows the migration from Northern Bald Ibis, or the Waldrapp, supported by foster parents of the birds in a microlight aircraft. (Waldrappteam Conservation &amp; Research via AP)</span></div>
<p>In 2002, a conservation and research group based in Austria stepped in to help. The group is called Waldrappteam; the birds are called Waldrapp in German. Scientists at Waldrappteam raise the birds and teach them how to fly to warmer areas.</p>
<p>Johannes Fritz is a biologist working with the team. He said, "We have to teach them the migration <strong>route</strong>.”</p>
<p>Fritz and the Waldrappteam have increased the number of northern ibis in Central Europe from zero to almost 300 since the start of their project in 2002.</p>
<p>Fritz said the group's work is the first attempt to reintroduce a continentally <strong>extinct</strong> migratory bird species. He said his team found that, when released, the birds raised by humans flew in the wrong direction and died in the winter. The humans have led the birds now for 17 years to places like Tuscany, Italy. Due to climate change, they have had to change the <strong>route</strong> to a winter home. Now they help the birds fly to Andalusia in southern Spain.</p>
<p>To prepare them for travel, the humans begin working with the baby birds, or chicks, when they are just a few days old. The <strong>foster </strong>parent humans want the birds to connect with them so they will trust them along the migration route.</p>
<p>Barbara Steininger is one Waldrappteam foster mother. She said she acts like "their bird mom."</p>
<p>"We feed them, we clean them, we clean their nests. We take good care of them and see that they are healthy birds," she said. "But also we <strong>interact</strong> with them."</p>
<p>Steininger and the other foster parents then sit on the back of a very small aircraft, waving and cheering for the birds as they fly.</p>
<p>Fritz knew his work would be possible because he saw the work of Canadian inventor and naturalist Bill Lishman. Lishman taught Canadian geese to fly alongside his small plane beginning in 1988. He later guided endangered whooping cranes through safe routes.</p>
<p>Fritz's team efforts have worked. The first bird independently migrated back to Bavaria from Tuscany in 2011. The team hopes the Central European population will be more than 350 birds by 2028 and will not need human help to migrate.</p>
<p>This year, the route to Spain is longer than last year's path. Earlier this month from an airfield in upper Bavaria, the team guided 36 birds along one stage through blue skies and a wind from behind them that increased their speed.</p>
<p>The full <strong>journey</strong> to Spain could take up to 50 days. Fritz said the effort is bigger than just the northern bald ibises. He hopes the group's work offers a possibility for helping other threatened migratory <strong>species</strong> to fly.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Bobby Hardy and Stefanie Dazio reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>breeding </strong>– <em>n</em>. the activity of keeping and caring for animals or plants in order to produce more animals or plants of a particular kind</p>
<p><strong>migrate</strong> – <em>v. of a bird or animal</em>. to move from one area to another at different times of the year</p>
<p><strong>extinct</strong> – <em>adj</em>. no longer living</p>
<p><strong>route </strong>– <em>n</em>. a way to get from one place to another place</p>
<p><strong>foster</strong> – <em>v. </em>to provide the care that a parent usually gives to a child; to be or become the foster parent of a child</p>
<p><strong>interact</strong> – <em>v</em>. to talk or do things with others</p>
<p><strong>journey</strong> – <em>n</em>. an act of traveling from one place to another</p>
<p><strong>species</strong> – <em>n.</em> <em>biology. </em> a group of animals or plants that are similar and can produce young animals or plants</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>X Changes AI tool after Pressure to Reduce Misinformation (2024/8/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/x-changes-ai-tool-after-pressure-to-reduce-misinformation.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The social media service X has changed its artificial intelligence (AI) tool after several U.S. states warned that it was spreading election misinformation.</p>
<p>Earlier this month, secretaries of state in five states sent the owner of X, Elon Musk, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.sos.state.mn.us/media/6077/080524-secretaries-letter-to-x.pdf">a letter</a> requesting the change to its Grok AI tool.</p>
<p>X explains on its <a class="wsw__a" href="https://help.x.com/en/using-x/about-grok">Help Center</a> that Grok is designed to be used as an AI search assistant to help users find information online. Such tools are also known as chatbots or generative AI. Grok is only available to paid users of X's Premium and Premium+ services.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FIE - The X logo is shown on a computer screen in Belgrade, Serbia, July 24, 2023. (AP Photo/Darko Vojinovic, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-d2d9-08dcc6e3d6f9_cx17_cy3_cw82_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FIE - The X logo is shown on a computer screen in Belgrade, Serbia, July 24, 2023. (AP Photo/Darko Vojinovic, File)</span></div>
<p>In their letter, the secretaries of state expressed concern that the Grok tool was returning results that included misinformation about the U.S. presidential election process. The officials said that shortly after President Joe Biden ended his run for re-election, the Grok tool provided false information on state ballot requirements.</p>
<p>The misinformation included a statement that the <strong>deadline</strong> had passed in several states to make ballot changes for the nation's presidential election. The secretaries' wrote that the statement was completely false. In all the states identified by Grok, it was still possible for ballot changes to be made, the letter said.</p>
<p>The ballot changes increased in importance when the Democratic Party chose a new nominee, Vice President Kamala Harris, after Biden withdrew.</p>
<p>Former President Donald Trump is the Republican Party's nominee.</p>
<p>The letter recognized that Grok does warn its users that the AI tool might return false information. And it noted that the tool urges users not to depend completely on Grok for news and information.</p>
<p>However, the secretaries of state wrote, the false information about ballot deadlines was “captured and shared repeatedly in multiple posts - reaching millions of people.” In addition, they noted, Grok continued to repeat this false information for more than a week until it was corrected on July 31, 2024.</p>
<p>The secretaries of state requested that Grok instead direct users who enter search requests about election-related questions to an official government-run website for the latest voting information. The request aimed to send Grok users immediately and directly to an official election-related website.</p>
<p>The secretaries recently sent out a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.sos.state.mn.us/about-the-office/news-room/secretaries-of-state-welcome-changes-to-x-s-ai-search-assistant/">press release</a> confirming that Grok had made such a change. Before providing results to search requests about election matters, the tool now offers new user guidance. “For accurate and up-to-date information about the 2024 U.S. Elections, please visit Vote.gov,” Grok now says.</p>
<p>The state secretaries explained that <a class="wsw__a" href="https://vote.gov/">Vote.gov</a> is a politically neutral, “trustworthy” website operated by the U.S. government in partnership with state election officials. The website also receives support from government organizations that seek to prevent internet attacks that can block sites or take them offline.</p>
<p>All elections in the United States are operated by local officials supported and led by a state agency. Experts say because each state sets its own requirements and deadlines, it is important for voters to be connected to the most dependable information available.</p>
<p>Musk bought Twitter in 2022 and later renamed the service X. Activist groups have repeatedly raised concerns about a large increase in hate speech and misinformation appearing on the service after Musk became the owner. Some X critics have also said major employee cuts had left the company with ineffective content <strong>moderation</strong> methods that do not catch misinformation.</p>
<p>In their latest press release, the secretaries of state thanked X for agreeing to the change and said they hope the company will remain open to additional improvements to protect its users. They added, “Elections are a team effort, and we need and welcome any partners who are committed to ensuring free, fair, secure, and <strong>accurate</strong> elections.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters and Agence France-Presse and the Minnesota Secretary of State. </em></p>
<p><strong>_________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>deadline</strong> <em>– n. </em>a date or time by which something must be completed</p>
<p><strong>moderate</strong> <em>– v. </em>to make sure the rules of an internet discussion are not broken</p>
<p><strong>accurate </strong><em>– </em><em>adj. </em>correct or exact</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Colleges Change Rules for Campus Protests (2024/8/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/us-colleges-change-rules-for-campus-protests.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">27 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>As students return to college across the United States, administrators are preparing for new activism against the war in Gaza. Some have <strong>adopted</strong> new rules limiting protests. Last spring, college protests resulted in damage, conflict and arrests at several schools.</p>
<p>The summer break brought most protests to an end. But the results of the damage last spring are still being felt.</p>
<p>At Columbia University in New York City, Minouche Shafik resigned from her position as president earlier this month. In April, Shafik faced strong criticism from lawmakers over her response to protests at Columbia.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Student protesters gather inside their encampment on the Columbia University campus, April 29, 2024, in New York. (AP Photo/Stefan Jeremiah, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-2ec3-08dcc160da1c_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Student protesters gather inside their encampment on the Columbia University campus, April 29, 2024, in New York. (AP Photo/Stefan Jeremiah, File)</span></div>
<p><strong>New measures for campus demonstrations</strong></p>
<p>Some universities are putting new measures in place to avoid what happened at Columbia. The new rules include banning encampments and limiting the duration of demonstrations. They permit protests only in defined areas and restrict campus <strong>access</strong> to those with university identification.</p>
<p>Critics say some of the measures will hurt free speech.</p>
<p>The American Association of University Professors (AAUP) released a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.aaup.org/news/aaup-condemns-wave-administrative-policies-intended-crack-down-peaceful-campus-protest">statement</a> earlier this month condemning “overly restrictive policies” that would harm free expression.</p>
<p>The AAUP said, “Our colleges and universities should <strong>encourage</strong>, not suppress, open and <strong>vigorous</strong> dialogue and debate even on the most deeply held beliefs.”</p>
<p>The University of Pennsylvania has released “temporary guidelines” for student protests. Overnight demonstrations are banned, and the use of loud audio equipment is barred after 5 p.m. on days when classes are being held. Signs, posters, and banners must be removed after two weeks. The university says it remains supportive of freedom of speech and lawful <strong>assembly</strong>.</p>
<p>At Indiana University, protests after 11 p.m. are banned under a new “expressive activities policy” which took effect on August 1. The policy bars “camping” or placing a shelter on campus. Signs require approval from school officials.</p>
<p>The University of South Florida now requires approval for tents, <strong>canopies</strong>, banners, signs and <strong>amplifiers</strong>. “Speech, expression and assembly” rules bar demonstrations after 5 p.m. on weekdays and weekends. Protests are completely banned during the last two weeks of a <strong>semester</strong>.</p>
<p>Risa Lieberwitz is a Cornell University professor of labor and employment law and gives legal advice to the AAUP. Lieberwitz said, “I think right now we are seeing a resurgence of repression on campuses that we haven't seen since the late 1960s.”</p>
<p>However, university officials say free speech cannot interfere with learning. They say the updated rules improve safety on campus.</p>
<p><strong>Why are students protesting?</strong></p>
<p>Tensions at many universities increased after October 7, 2023, when Hamas militants attacked southern Israel. Hamas killed 1,200 people most of whom were civilians. Hamas also took about 250 people hostage. Israel's military operation to answer the attack has continued through the summer.</p>
<p>Many student protesters in the U.S. have promised to continue their activism against the Gaza war. They are fueled by information from Hamas's health ministry that says more than 40,000 people have died in the Gaza conflict.</p>
<p>Much of that tension appeared in the spring on Columbia's campus. On April 30, police with riot shields raided a building that pro-Palestinian protesters had occupied at Columbia. Earlier, police had cleared out a tent camp that protestors had set up.</p>
<p>Similar protests took place on <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/police-clear-protest-camps-at-several-us-colleges/7593871.html">campuses around the country</a>. It is estimated that more than 3,000 people were arrested in connection with the pro-Palestinian protests.</p>
<p>However, many of the students who were arrested during police actions have had their charges dismissed. Some are still waiting to learn what government lawyers decide. Others have faced suspension from school, had their <strong>diplomas</strong> withheld or faced other punishments.</p>
<p>Columbia only recently began permitting people with university identification or registered visitors onto campus. Officials said they wanted to limit possible “<strong>disruptions</strong>” at the start of the new semester.</p>
<p>Shafik of Columbia was among the university leaders who Congress called on in April to explain what was happening. Lawmakers accused her of not doing enough to deal with concerns about anti-Semitism at Columbia. She announced her resignation weeks before classes are to start on September 3.</p>
<p>Other university leaders have also stepped down in recent months.</p>
<p>University of Pennsylvania President Liz Magill resigned in December. She faced pressure after she appeared before Congress and was unable to say whether calls on campus for the genocide of Jewish people would violate school policy.</p>
<p>In January, Harvard University President Claudine Gay resigned after accusations of claiming others' writings as her own and her statement about free speech given to Congress.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p>And I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Nick Perry, Jake Offenhartz and Jocelyn Gecker reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English with additional AP reporting and other sources. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>adopt </strong><em>–v.</em> to accept and put in place</p>
<p><strong>access</strong></p>
<p><strong>encourage</strong> <em>–v.</em> to support and get people to do something</p>
<p><strong>vigorous </strong>–adj. done with energy and willingness</p>
<p><strong>assembly </strong><em>–n.</em> the lawful and peaceful gathering of people in public</p>
<p><strong>canopy </strong><em>–n.</em> a shelter similar to a tent but without sides</p>
<p><strong>amplifier </strong><em>–n</em>. a device that electronically makes a sound louder</p>
<p><strong>semester</strong> <em>–adj. </em>one half of a school year</p>
<p><strong>diploma </strong><em>–n.</em> a document that officially shows that a person has fulfilled requirements for a degree from a school or university</p>
<p><strong>disruption</strong> <em>–n.</em> an event that interferes with normal or necessary activities</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Cambodia Celebrates Return of Long-lost Ancient Cultural Pieces (2024/8/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/cambodia-celebrates-return-of-long-lost-ancient-cultural-pieces.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">27 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Cambodia has celebrated the return of numerous cultural art pieces stolen during the country's civil war period.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Hun Manet recently led a ceremony to welcome the pieces, called artifacts, back to Cambodia. The event took place at the nation's Peace Palace in Phnom Penh. The palace houses the government's official headquarters.</p>
<p>The Cambodian leader said a total of 70 ancient statues had been reunited with the country's people. Most of the pieces are believed to have been stolen during Cambodia's civil war period, from 1967 until 1975.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this photo released by Agence Kampuchea Press (AKP), Cambodian Prime Minister Hun Manet prays with others during a ceremony for the return of artifacts in Peace Palace in Phnom Penh, Cambodia, Thursday, Aug. 22, 2024. (AKP via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-8708-08dcc5f1f260_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this photo released by Agence Kampuchea Press (AKP), Cambodian Prime Minister Hun Manet prays with others during a ceremony for the return of artifacts in Peace Palace in Phnom Penh, Cambodia, Thursday, Aug. 22, 2024. (AKP via AP)</span></div>
<p>At the time, the communist Khmer Rouge ruled Cambodia. It is blamed for the killings of more than 1 million Cambodians during its rule and years of unrest and economic difficulties.</p>
<p>Multiple international efforts over the years have helped Cambodia get back its artistic and archaeological treasures. The stolen artifacts include ancient pieces from Asia as well as artwork lost or stolen in conflict areas such as Syria, Iraq and Nazi-occupied Europe.</p>
<p>“A total of 70 Khmer cultural objects have been returned through a range of different processes,” Cambodia's Ministry of Culture and Fine Arts said in a statement. These included voluntary returns, negotiations, seizures and legal processes.</p>
<p>The statement said the returned artifacts included important Hindu and Buddhist pieces from the 9th-to-14th-century. Among them were “priceless stone statues” representing <strong>mythical</strong> Hindu figures, it added.</p>
<p>Hun Manet said that from 1996 until last month, 1,098 artifacts had been returned to Cambodia. About half were from private collections and half from foreign groups or governments.</p>
<p>Officials said the 70 items presented included 14 that arrived from New York's Metropolitan Museum of Art in early July. The rest, from private collectors, arrived in late July.</p>
<p>The pieces that came from the Metropolitan Museum were bought and trafficked by well-known art dealer Douglas Latchford. He had been <strong>indicted</strong> in 2019 on charges linked to an effort that sought to sell stolen Cambodian artifacts on the international art market. Latchford, who died the following year, had denied any involvement in smuggling.</p>
<p>A statement from the U.S. Embassy in Cambodia said the U.S. government had assisted the country with the return of over 150 ancient cultural pieces. Embassy official Bridgette Walker told ceremony attendees that the United States had long been a dependable partner “for protecting the cultural <strong>heritage</strong> of Cambodia.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>mythical </strong><em>–</em><strong> </strong><em>adj.</em> existing in a myth: an ancient story about gods and brave people, often one that explains historical events</p>
<p><strong>indict</strong> <em>– v. </em>to officially accuse someone of a crime</p>
<p><strong>heritage </strong><em>– n.</em> the buildings, paintings, customs, etc. that are important to a culture or society</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Biggest Diamond in 100 Years Discovered in Botswana (2024/8/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/biggest-diamond-in-100-years-discovered-in-botswana.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">27 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Miners in Botswana recently unearthed what officials say is the second largest diamond in mining history. The country's president Mokgweetsi Masisi presented the large stone to the public at a ceremony last week.</p>
<p>The 2,492-<strong>carat</strong> gem is the biggest diamond to be discovered since 1905. The diamond weighs around a half-kilogram. Masisi was one of the first people to get to hold it.</p>
<p>He expressed surprise at the diamond's heaviness and told the gathering, “I am lucky to have seen it in my time."</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Botswana's President Mokgweetsi Masisi holds a large diamond discovered in Botswana at his office in Gaborone on August 22, 2024. (Photo by Monirul BHUIYAN / AFP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/16dfd8fc-3166-4560-b59a-93b62bd1dea2_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Botswana's President Mokgweetsi Masisi holds a large diamond discovered in Botswana at his office in Gaborone on August 22, 2024. (Photo by Monirul BHUIYAN / AFP)</span></div>
<p>Lucara Diamond, a Canadian mining company, found the stone. Company officials said it was too early to value the gem or decide how it would be sold. A smaller uncut diamond from the same mine in Botswana sold for a record $63 million in 2016.</p>
<p>Naseem Lahri is a director with Lucara's Botswana team. “This is history in the making,” she said of the new find. “I am very proud. It is a product of Botswana.”</p>
<p>Lucara said in a statement last week that the company recovered what it called an “exceptional” diamond from Karowe Mine in central Botswana. Company miners used X-ray technology that is designed to find large, high-value diamonds.</p>
<p>“We are <strong>ecstatic</strong> about the recovery of this <strong>extraordinary</strong> 2,492-carat diamond,” Lucara President and chief William Lamb said in a statement.</p>
<p>The weight would make it the largest diamond found in 119 years.</p>
<p>It also is the second-largest diamond ever mined, after the Cullinan Diamond. That 3,106-carat stone was unearthed in South Africa in 1905. The Cullinan was the source of several famous cut gems, including some among the British Crown Jewels.</p>
<p>Botswana, a country of 2.6 million people in southern Africa, is the second-biggest producer of natural diamonds behind Russia.</p>
<p>The Karowe Mine has produced four other diamonds over 1,000 carats in the last decade.</p>
<p>Before this discovery, the Sewelo diamond, which was found at the Karowe Mine in 2019, was recognized as the second-biggest mined diamond in the world at 1,758 carats. French <strong>fashion</strong> business Louis Vuitton bought the diamond. The sale price was not publicized.</p>
<p>A British jeweler bought the 1,111-carat Lesedi La Rona diamond, also from Botswana's Karowe Mine, for $53 million in 2017. A Karowe diamond named The Constellation is the holder of the record $63 million sales price.</p>
<p>Diamonds form when carbon atoms are pushed close together by intense pressure conditions deep underground. Scientists say most diamonds are at least a billion years old and some of them more than 3 billion years old.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Sello Motseta reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>carat </strong><em>– n. </em>a unit of weight for precious stones that is equal to about 200 milligrams</p>
<p><strong>ecstatic </strong><em>– adj.</em> describes a state of overwhelming emotion</p>
<p><strong>extraordinary </strong>–<em> adj.</em> going beyond what is usual, regular <strong>fashion </strong><em>– n.</em> the prevailing style during a particular time</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Telegram Chief Pavel Durov Arrested in France (2024/8/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/telegram-chief-pavel-durov-arrested-in-france.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The founder and chief executive of the Telegram messaging service, Pavel Durov, was arrested in France over the weekend.</p>
<p>The reports said police detained Durov Saturday night at Le Bourget airport in Paris. Durov holds citizenship in both France and Russia. He landed in France after a flight from Azerbaijan, French broadcasters LCI and TF1 reported.</p>
<p>French media reported on Monday that Durov's arrest was linked to a French investigation that found evidence that Telegram had failed to reduce the spread of illegal material on its service.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This file photo shows Telegram co-founder Pavel Durov, following his meeting with Indonesian Communication and Information Minister Rudiantara in Jakarta, Indonesia on Aug. 1, 2017. (AP Photo/Tatan Syuflana, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-a144-08dcc5fb4c1d_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This file photo shows Telegram co-founder Pavel Durov, following his meeting with Indonesian Communication and Information Minister Rudiantara in Jakarta, Indonesia on Aug. 1, 2017. (AP Photo/Tatan Syuflana, File)</span></div>
<p>French President Emmanuel Macron said the arrest was “in no way a political decision.” He said on the social media service X that France “is deeply committed” to freedom of expression. But he added, “Freedoms are upheld with in a legal <strong>framework</strong>.”</p>
<p>The arrest of the 39-year-old Durov was reportedly sought by a French investigative agency that examines crimes against minors. The French media says officials are investigating crimes including <strong>money</strong> <strong>laundering</strong>, drug trafficking and other offenses.</p>
<p>In a statement issued Monday, Telegram said the company obeys all European Union laws, including the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://commission.europa.eu/strategy-and-policy/priorities-2019-2024/europe-fit-digital-age/digital-services-act_en">Digital Services Act</a>. It added that Telegram's <strong>moderation</strong> methods operate within industry standards and are always being improved.</p>
<p>Durov “has nothing to hide and travels frequently in Europe,” the company said. The statement added, “It is <strong>absurd</strong> to claim that a <strong>platform</strong> or its owner are responsible for abuse of that platform."</p>
<p>Representatives for Durov could not be immediately reached for comment. French law enforcement officials also offered no comment because the investigation is ongoing.</p>
<p>Durov founded Telegram with his brother in reaction to Russian government efforts to crush large pro-democracy protests that took place in Moscow at the end of 2011 and 2012. The demonstrations led the Russian government to introduce new restrictions on internet operations in the country. Durov left Russia in 2014.</p>
<p>Russia's agency that governs technology companies at one time tried to block Telegram but was unsuccessful in fully restricting the service. In March, the government said it was working with Telegram to remove content that violated Russian laws.</p>
<p>The messaging service is currently a popular source of news in Ukraine, The Associated Press (AP) reports. Telegram is reportedly used by both government officials and the media to share information on Ukraine's war with Russia. It has also been used to send missile and air raid warnings to citizens during the conflict.</p>
<p>Western governments have criticized Telegram for having weak moderation policies that are supposed to identify and remove illegal material. Experts say the lack of enforcement makes it easier for individuals to commit crimes such as money laundering and drug trafficking on the service.</p>
<p>David Thiel is a researcher at Stanford University in California. He has investigated the use of online services to carry out child <strong>exploitation</strong>. Thiel told the AP that compared to other messaging services, Telegram is “less secure (and) more <strong>lax</strong>” in identifying and removing illegal content.</p>
<p>In addition, Telegram “appears basically <strong>unresponsive</strong> to law enforcement,” he added. As an example, Thiel said that while the messaging service WhatsApp registered 1.3 million reports of possible child exploitation in 2023, Telegram did not send any.</p>
<p>In a statement to the AP earlier this month, Telegram said it actively works to fight the misuse of its service. The company said it uses a combination of <strong>monitoring</strong> methods and user reports in order to remove banned content. “Each day, millions of pieces of harmful content are removed,” it added.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press, Reuters and Agence France-Presse reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>framework </strong>–n. the supporting structure of something<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>money laundering </strong><em>– n.</em> the crime of moving money that has been obtained illegally through banks and other businesses in order to make it seem like the money operations are legal</p>
<p><strong>moderate</strong> <em>– v. </em>to make sure the rules of an internet discussion are not broken</p>
<p><strong>absurd </strong><em>– adj.</em> unreasonable or outrageous</p>
<p><strong>platform </strong><em>– n.</em> a company or service that permits someone to tell a large number of people about ideas or products</p>
<p><strong>exploit</strong> <em>– v. </em>to use someone or something unfairly for your own advantage</p>
<p><strong>lax </strong><em>– adj.</em> without much care, attention or control</p>
<p><strong>unresponsive </strong><em>– adj. </em>not reacting in a quick or positive way</p>
<p><strong>monitor </strong><em>– v.</em> to carefully watch something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>For Exercising, When and How Should You Stretch? (2024/8/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/for-exercising-when-and-how-should-you-stretch.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>Years ago, the traditional advice was to do some stretching before<em> </em>exercising. Over the years, that advice changed to stretching after<em> </em>exercising. It turns out that both advice can be true. And that can lead to some confusion.</p>
<p>Stretching can help make you more <strong>flexible</strong>.<strong> </strong>The more you stretch, the more you improve the <strong>range of motion</strong> in your joints. This not only feels good, but it also can prevent injury and lead to better physical results.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Panamanian gymnast Hillary Heron stretches as she trains for the Olympics at the No Limits Gymnastics Center in Panama City, Saturday, June 15, 2024, ahead of the Games in Paris. (AP Photo/Matias Delacroix, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-c71c-08dcb7c64554_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Panamanian gymnast Hillary Heron stretches as she trains for the Olympics at the No Limits Gymnastics Center in Panama City, Saturday, June 15, 2024, ahead of the Games in Paris. (AP Photo/Matias Delacroix, File)</span></div>
<p>David Behm researches human body movements at Memorial University of Newfoundland in St. John's, Canada. Speaking with the Associated Press, he offers advice on when to stretch and how to do it safely.</p>
<p><strong>Warm up first</strong></p>
<p>It is almost always good to stretch. However, Behm, says it is better if you warm up first. He suggests light <strong>aerobic</strong> activity such as jogging, walking or cycling for five to 10 minutes.</p>
<p>He suggests to follow that warm-up movement with <strong>static</strong> stretching. This traditional way of stretching involves reaching your body into different positions and holding them for about one minute each.</p>
<p>Then you can do <strong>dynamic</strong> stretching related to specific exercises or activities. This is where you warm up the muscles with repeated movements like leg lifts.</p>
<p><strong>Expand your definition of ‘stretching'</strong></p>
<p>Should you always stretch before exercising? If it is traditional static stretching, not necessarily, Behm says.</p>
<p>The better questions, he says, are, “Should people increase their range of motion? Should people have better flexibility? And that is yes, because it helps prevent injuries. It helps with health. But you don't have to stretch to achieve that.”</p>
<p>Resistance training, for example, can be an effective form of stretching. Doing a chest press increases range of motion in your arm and chest muscles. Whether you use barbells, dumbbells or machines, there is no need to stretch beforehand. However, Behm warns to start with a small amount of weight to warm up and then add more to train.</p>
<p>He adds that you do not need to stretch first if you are going for a short run. Simply start with a slow jog to warm up and then increase the speed.</p>
<p><strong>Don't do it if it hurts</strong></p>
<p>After exercise, light stretching is fine, as long as you do not feel pain, Behm says. Because your muscles will be warm by that point, overdoing it makes you more likely to injure yourself.</p>
<p>Foam rollers can help with muscle recovery and have been shown to increase range of motion as well as stretching.</p>
<p><strong>Do some static stretching before sports</strong></p>
<p>If you're playing a sport, Behm says, static stretching beforehand helps reduce muscle and <strong>tendon</strong> injury.</p>
<p>Sports like gymnastics, ice skating, and golf require a great range of motion. For these activities, he suggests extra stretching specific to those sports.</p>
<p>“If you're going to do an explosive movement, change of direction, <strong>agility</strong>, sprint, any of these explosive activities that involve your muscles and tendons,” he said, “you're going to be stronger if you do static stretching.”</p>
<p>People can especially get in trouble when they go back to a sport they used to play. Stretching can prepare muscles that may be out of shape. Also, he says to stretch both sides of your body equally. Lacking flexibility on one side also can lead to injury.</p>
<p><strong>Sounds simple. Why all the confusion?</strong></p>
<p>Different studies over the years have led to different advice about stretching before exercise. Behm says that is partly because some studies did not consider real-life conditions. Also, some researchers designed studies with high-performance athletes in mind and not regular people.</p>
<p>“If you're Usain Bolt, it makes a difference,” he said. For the rest of us ... not so much.</p>
<p>And that's the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report. I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Albert Stumm reported this story for The Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><em>________________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"> </h2>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>flexible </strong><em>– adj.</em> capable of being bent</p>
<p><strong>range of motion</strong> <em>– n. </em>the extent or limit to which a part of the body can be moved around a joint or a fixed point</p>
<p><strong>aerobic</strong> <em>– adj. </em>of, relating to, or being activity which increases the body's demand for oxygen thereby resulting in marked temporary increase in respiration and heart rate</p>
<p><strong>static </strong><em>– adj. </em>standing or fixed in one place</p>
<p><strong>dynamic </strong><em>– adj. </em>always active, moving or changing</p>
<p><strong>tendon </strong><em>– n. </em>a tough cord or band of dense white connective tissue that links a muscle to some other part (as a bone)</p>
<p><strong>agility </strong><em>– n. </em>the quality or state of being able to move quickly and easily</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Sea Lions Gather on California Beach, People Should Let Them Rest (2024/8/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/sea-lions-gather-on-california-beach-people-should-let-them-rest.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hundreds of California <strong>sea lions </strong>have taken over San Carlos Beach in Monterey, California, causing officials to close the area to people.</p>
<p>Drawn to the animals, people still gather to take photos as they rest and play on the sand and in the water. While sea lions, or eared seals, are often seen at certain beaches up and down the California coast, locals say they have never seen so many of them in Monterey.</p>
<p>Lisa Uttal is a <strong>marine</strong> biologist with the Monterey Bay National Marine Sanctuary. She said it was unclear exactly why the sea lions chose San Carlos Beach, but they may be <strong>attracted</strong> to the food supply in nearby waters. Almost all the seals gathered on the beach were male, she said.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Sea lions congregate at San Carlos Beach while local authorities decided to temporarily close the beach in Monterey, CA. August 22, 2024. (REUTERS/Carlos Barria)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-7775-08dcc3abebbd_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Sea lions congregate at San Carlos Beach while local authorities decided to temporarily close the beach in Monterey, CA. August 22, 2024. (REUTERS/Carlos Barria)</span></div>
<p>Uttal explained that the seals move to the northern coast from Ventura and the Channel Islands. “They are incredibly mobile. They're usually chasing the food.” She noted that the Monterey Bay National Marine Sanctuary has many different kinds of sea life. Uttal expects the sea lions to remain on San Carlos Beach for three to four weeks.</p>
<p>Marge Brigadier is a volunteer with Monterey Bay National Marine Sanctuary's Bay Net program. She said people should not get too close to the sea lions or try to make them move away. The U.S. Marine Mammal Protection Act of 1972 is the law that prevents people from harming them.</p>
<p>"People just need to think about how they would feel if they were resting on their bed taking a <strong>nap</strong> and something big kept coming and chasing them out of the house," Brigadier said.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Dylan Bouscher </em><em>reported this story for </em><em>Reuters</em><em>. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>sea lion</strong> – <em>n. </em>an eared seal occurring mainly on Pacific coasts, the large male of which has a mane on the neck and shoulders.</p>
<p><strong>marine</strong> – <em>adj</em>. of or relating to the sea or the plants and animals that live in the sea</p>
<p><strong>mammal</strong><em> – n.</em> a type of animal that feeds milk to its young and that usually has hair or fur covering most of its skin</p>
<p><strong>attract</strong> – <em>v</em>. to cause (someone) to choose to do or be involved in something</p>
<p><strong>nap</strong> – <em>n</em>. a short period of sleep especially during the day</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>NASA Launches Instrument to Measure World’s Carbon, Methane (2024/8/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/nasa-launches-instrument-to-measure-world-s-carbon-methane.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The American space agency NASA has launched an instrument to measure the world's carbon and methane levels in an effort to help fight climate change.</p>
<p>The instrument is attached to a satellite called Tanager-1. It launched August 16 aboard a SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket from NASA's Vandenberg Space Force Base in California. Ground controllers reported they successfully established communications with the satellite shortly after launch.</p>
<p>A statement from NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.jpl.nasa.gov/news/nasa-designed-greenhouse-gas-detection-instrument-launches">said</a> the satellite is equipped with a gas-seeking instrument powered with “imaging spectrometer technology.” A spectrometer is an instrument used to study the chemical composition and structures of substances.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Smoke rises from a coal-powered steel plant at Hehal village near Ranchi, in the eastern state of Jharkhand, Sept. 26, 2021. (AP Photo/Altaf Qadri, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-87df-08db2f047806_cx0_cy7_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Smoke rises from a coal-powered steel plant at Hehal village near Ranchi, in the eastern state of Jharkhand, Sept. 26, 2021. (AP Photo/Altaf Qadri, File)</span></div>
<p>NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL) developed the imaging spectrometer instrument. The joint project also involved other organizations, including Planet Labs PBC. The private company helped build the Tanager-1 satellite.</p>
<p>Tanager-1 is one of two satellites developed as part of the public-private partnership the Carbon Mapper Coalition. The other satellite has not yet been launched.</p>
<p>The coalition <a class="wsw__a" href="https://carbonmapper.org/">says</a> it aims to support the collection of detailed data on methane and carbon dioxide <strong>emissions</strong> worldwide. The coalition hopes to use the data to drive reductions in methane and carbon pollution. Scientists have linked carbon and methane emissions to warming temperatures on Earth. Many climate experts blame most of the warming on pollution caused by human activities.</p>
<p>NASA says the instrument aboard Tanager-1 measures “hundreds of wavelengths of light that are <strong>reflected</strong> by Earth's surface.” This method permits the instrument to find sources of carbon and methane based on the light wavelengths they show.</p>
<p>The process produces “fingerprints” that the imaging spectrometer can identify, NASA said. This data can be used to provide highly detailed information on where the world's carbon and methane come from. The level of detail is so exact, it can even identify “individual <strong>facilities </strong>and equipment,” the space agency added.</p>
<p>Laurie Leshin is director of the JPL, which is based in Pasadena, California. She said in a statement the imaging spectrometer technology is the product of more than 40 years of development at NASA. Leshin said such detailed emissions data can help policymakers, governments and environmental organizations worldwide.</p>
<p>When fully operational, Tanager-1 will aim to capture data across 130,000 square kilometers of Earth's surface each day. This will permit scientists to identify specific gas clouds releasing carbon dioxide and methane. NASA said the collected data will be publicly available online at the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://data.carbonmapper.org/">Carbon Mapper data portal</a>.</p>
<p>NASA says about half of methane emissions worldwide are caused by human activities. The biggest polluters are called “super <strong>emitters</strong>,” said Carbon Mapper Coalition chief executive Riley Duren. He told the Reuters news agency that super emitters produce more than 100 kilograms of methane per hour. This level of release could add up to 20 to 60 percent of an area's total emissions in some industries, Duren said.</p>
<p>In addition, the agency noted, “There is now 50 percent more carbon dioxide in the atmosphere than there was in 1750, an increase largely due to the <strong>extraction</strong> and burning of coal, oil, and (natural) gas.”</p>
<p>Duren said in a statement the Carbon Mapper Coalition is a good example “of how organizations from different <strong>sectors</strong> are uniting around a common goal of addressing climate change.” He added that having the ability to exactly identify the sources of carbon and methane “can drive significant action around the world to cut emissions now.”</p>
<p>The launch of Tanager-1 came after NASA's February <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/nasa-launches-new-satellite-to-study-oceans-atmosphere/7480106.html">deployment</a> of the PACE satellite. It is designed to closely study the world's oceans and atmosphere. PACE stands for Plankton, Aerosol, Cloud, Ocean Ecosystem. The satellite will spend at least three years studying the environment from an orbit 676 kilometers above the Earth's surface.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from Reuters, NASA and the Carbon Mapper Coalition. </em></p>
<p><strong>____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>emission</strong> <em>– n.</em> the act of sending something out such as a gas, heat, or light</p>
<p><strong>reflect</strong> <em>– n. </em>to send back or bouncer off of something</p>
<p><strong>facility </strong><em>– n.</em> the place where a particular activity happens</p>
<p><strong>emit </strong><em>– v. </em>to send out gas, heat, light etc. into the air</p>
<p><strong>extract </strong><em>– v.</em> to take something out, especially by force</p>
<p><strong>sector </strong><em>– n. </em>one part of a country's economy</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Nuns Trouble Companies with Investment Activism (2024/8/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/us-nuns-trouble-companies-with-investment-activism.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In the American state of Kansas, a group of religious women have been calling on large companies to change the way they do business.</p>
<p>The women are Catholic Benedictine religious workers called nuns. They live together in a <strong>monastery</strong> called Mount Saint Scholastica. The nuns, who call themselves sisters, pray and <strong>chant</strong> three times a day in their small church. Members of the Benedictine Order have followed this way of life for about 1,500 years.</p>
<p>But the sisters also put their money into investments in several companies. This gives them the right to propose changes to company policies at regular shareholder meetings that involve important decisions.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Sister Barbara McCracken looks through prior resolutions filed against various corporations, including Alphabet, Meta, Netflix and Chevron, at the Mount St. Scholastica Benedictine monastery in Atchison, Kan., Tuesday, July 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Jessie Wardarski)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-d02c-08dcc1ea141e_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Sister Barbara McCracken looks through prior resolutions filed against various corporations, including Alphabet, Meta, Netflix and Chevron, at the Mount St. Scholastica Benedictine monastery in Atchison, Kan., Tuesday, July 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Jessie Wardarski)</span></div>
<p>For example, the women asked oil company Chevron to consider more carefully its human rights policies. They asked Amazon to publish how much money the company spends trying to influence government officials. And they proposed that several manufacturers of medical drugs reconsider ownership rights called patents that, they said, increase drug prices. Patents legally protect a company's right to manufacture and sell a product that it developed or owns for a limited time.</p>
<p>“Some of these companies, they just really hate us,” said Sister Barbara McCracken. She leads the nuns' <strong>corporate</strong> responsibility program. She added that, because they are a small group of women, the large companies might consider them like an unwanted insect.</p>
<p>Until the 1990s, the nuns had few investments. That changed as they began to invest money to care for older sisters as the community aged.</p>
<p>They invest what little money they have in corporations that meet their religious <strong>ideals</strong>. But they also invest in some that do not meet their ideal. So, they push those companies to change policies they consider harmful.</p>
<p>Sister Rose Marie Stallbaumer supervised the community's finances for years. She said it was important that the group “invested in a responsible way.” She added that they wanted to make sure their investments did not bring harm to others.</p>
<p>The sisters at St. Scholastica and other Benedictine groups work closely with the Interfaith Center for Corporate Responsibility (ICCR). The ICCR is an organization based in New York City that involves religious groups in organizing to push companies to change their policies.</p>
<p>Tim Smith is a policy advisor for the center. He said the Benedictine nuns have been an important part of ICCR for years. He said that while it can take years to see companies change, the sisters “have the <strong>endurance</strong> of long-distance runners.”</p>
<p>Support for many of the changes the nuns seek has grown over the years. Early on, their resolutions received less than 10 percent support from shareholders. But in some cases, they have received 30 percent or even over 50 percent support.</p>
<p>Pushing companies to change comes naturally to McCracken. She has been a peace activist for many years. “There's not a protest she wouldn't go to,” said Sister Anne Shepard. She said McCracken's past involved anti-war, anti-racism, and <strong>union</strong>-supporting demonstrations.</p>
<p>McCracken entered the Benedictine community in 1961. She calls herself unusual for a person who lives in a monastery because she “hates to miss a party.” She and the other sisters follow the Benedictine rule to “pray and work.”</p>
<p>At the center of much of what they do is the belief that the wealthy have too much, the poor have too little, and more should be shared for the <strong>benefit</strong> of everyone.</p>
<p>“To me, it's a continuation of Catholic social teaching,” McCracken said of their activist investing.</p>
<p>Care for the environment has long been of central importance to Mount St. Scholastica members. Their college's graduates include Wangari Maathai, the Kenyan environmental activist and Nobel Peace Prize winner. Maathai died in 2011.</p>
<p>One of their top concerns is climate change. They use much of their 21 hectares of land for solar panels, community gardens and 18 beehives that produced about 360 kilograms of honey last year.</p>
<p>Their activism has often led to criticisms that they are too politically liberal. They recently received attention after they responded to statements made by Harrison Butker, a professional American football player. Butker had given a speech at nearby Benedictine College—cofounded by the Benedictine nuns. In the speech, he suggested that most of the women there would be more excited to be wives and mothers than anything else.</p>
<p>In a written statement, the sisters expressed concern with the idea “that being a homemaker is the highest calling for a woman.”</p>
<p>The nuns are not married and do not have children. Many of the sisters have <strong>doctoral degrees</strong>. Most have worked in professions. Members of their group include a doctor, a lawyer of Catholic Church law, and a professional violinist.</p>
<p>The sisters received angry phone calls after they released their statement. At the same time, the nuns are strong supporters of the team Butker plays for, the nearby Kansas City Chiefs. They often wear the team's red and gold colors to religious services on days when the team is playing.</p>
<p>Sister Mary Elizabeth Schweiger helped write the nuns' statement. “It came from a very basic understanding of who we are and the values that we hold true,” Schweiger said. “We just thought that voice had to be heard because we believe very much in being inclusive.”</p>
<p>Sister McCracken said that following their religious beliefs brings them into contact with political and economic issues. “It's just the nature of being an active citizen,” she said.</p>
<p>McCracken is nearly 85 years old and cannot be as active as she once was. But pushing companies to change gives her “a sit-down job when you can't go to the streets.”</p>
<p>The members of Mount St. Scholastica do not retire, not really.</p>
<p>“We don't use that word,” McCracken said. She added that if they still have the ability think clearly, “we just keep going, you know?”</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins. And I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Tiffany Stanley reported this story for the Associated Press. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>monastery </strong><em>–n.</em> a place were members of a religious order (usually monks) live</p>
<p><strong>chant </strong><em>–n.</em> words that are repeated, often as part of a religious ritual</p>
<p><strong>corporate </strong><em>–adj.</em> related to a business corporation or to actions taken as a group under organizing rules</p>
<p><strong>ideal </strong><em>–n. </em>an idea that people want to copy or embody</p>
<p><strong>benefit </strong><em>–n.</em> a good result from an action or decision</p>
<p><strong>endurance </strong><em>–n.</em> the ability to continue doing something for a long time</p>
<p><strong>union </strong><em>–n.</em> a labor group that supports workers' causes often in opposition to officials of the companies that employ the workers</p>
<p><strong>doctoral degree </strong><em>–n.</em> the highest degree offered by a university</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Uganda’s Motorcycle Taxis Resist Safety Rules (2024/8/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/uganda-s-motorcycle-taxis-resist-safety-rules.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>For tens of thousands of men in Uganda's capital, driving a motorcycle <strong>taxi</strong> is a way to make a living. For others, the vehicles known as boda-bodas are a necessary but dangerous form of transportation in a disorderly city.</p>
<p>The young men sit on motorcycles in the morning heat. When they see someone who might be a passenger, they start their machines and compete to offer the person a ride.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Drivers of motorcycle taxis, known locally as boda-bodas, ride with passengers on a street in Kampala, Uganda, on July 18, 2024. (AP Photo/Hajarah Nalwadda )" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-d000-08dcc2dce787_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Drivers of motorcycle taxis, known locally as boda-bodas, ride with passengers on a street in Kampala, Uganda, on July 18, 2024. (AP Photo/Hajarah Nalwadda )</span></div>
<p>The motorcycle taxis are everywhere in East African capitals like Nairobi and Kigali. But in Kampala, the numbers are huge. The city of 3 million people has no mass transportation system and a high rate of unemployment. There are around 350,000 boda-bodas. The men driving them come from all parts of Uganda. They say there are no other jobs for them.</p>
<p><strong>Nothing to do</strong></p>
<p>"We just do this one because we have nothing to do," said one driver, Zubairi Idi Nyakuni. "All of us here...they have their degrees, they have their master's (degrees), but they are just here. They have nothing to do."</p>
<p>The city has tried to control them and remove them from the central business area. But it is not easy. The government fears what might happen if they anger a large group of jobless men.</p>
<p>Charles Mpagi is a spokesperson for Tugende, a company based in Kampala that finances boda-boda purchases. He said, "You have quite a large number of people that are young, who can't find jobs...and they do not have <strong>significant</strong> <strong>alternative</strong> income to get into other <strong>enterprises</strong>."</p>
<p>About 76 percent of Uganda's 43 million people are under 35, according to government figures. There are few jobs for them. The central bank reports that just one percent of Ugandan workers make $270 or more in monthly pay.</p>
<p>Uganda's unemployment rate for people between 18 and 30 was 17 percent in 2021 - higher than for other age groups. For young people in urban areas, it was 19 percent.</p>
<p>President Yoweri Museveni has held power since 1986. He has long welcomed the support of boda-boda men, who create a loud presence at his political rallies. Museveni has gifted boda-bodas to supporters and is reducing the three-year licensing fee from nearly $100 to about $35.</p>
<p><strong>'Border, border!'</strong></p>
<p>Motorcycles first appeared on the Uganda-Kenya border during political instability in the 1970s. The term "boda-boda" comes from the way drivers used to shout "border, border" at possible <strong>customers</strong>.</p>
<p>At the time, they were also a way to transport <strong>smugglers</strong> and their <strong>merchandise</strong>. Today, they are everywhere in Uganda, taking children to school, people to offices, the sick to <strong>clinics</strong> and even the dead to their burials.</p>
<p>Each year, police reports say that motorcycle taxis help carry out violent crime. The Ministry of Works and Transport also reports that the number of deadly accidents related to motorcycles across Uganda grew from 621 in 2014 to 1,404 in 2021.</p>
<p>Road safety regulations for motorcycles were first approved in 2004. But traffic police are often unable to make arrests for motorcyclists breaking the law. They fear fights because drivers quickly come to support one another.</p>
<p>Many boda-boda men pay the owner of their vehicle every month. Failure to pay means the boda-boda driver loses his job along with the motorcycle.</p>
<p>Innocent Awita, a boda-boda man who left school in 2008, said there was "too much pressure" to keep his motorcycle. He pays $4 a day and pays for fuel and repairs. Some days are better than others, but Awita said he sometimes goes without enough earnings to make the daily payment.</p>
<p>"I can work for three days without getting anything. But if I get something the next day, that can save my life," he said.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Rodney Muhumuza reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>taxi </strong><em>–n.</em> a vehicle whose driver you pay for transportation service</p>
<p><strong>alternative</strong> – <em>adj</em>. offering or expressing a choice</p>
<p><strong>enterprise</strong> –<em> n. </em>a business organization</p>
<p><strong>customer </strong><em>–n.</em> a person or group who buys goods or services</p>
<p><strong>smuggle</strong> – <em>v</em>. to move (someone or something) from one country into another illegally and secretly</p>
<p><strong>merchandise </strong><em>–n.</em> goods that are for sale to the public</p>
<p><strong>clinic </strong>–n. a small health center that treats minor or simple health problems</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Reaching the 'Tipping Point' (2024/8/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/reaching-the-tipping-point.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">24 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Today we talk about an important time in a movement or experience. It is the moment when something cannot be stopped. There is a <strong>momentum</strong> or force pushing something forward or making it more known or popular.</p>
<p>One term for that kind of moment is <u>tipping point</u>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Some experts say deforestation in the Amazon is reaching a tipping point. This sky view shows deforestation near a forest on the border between Amazonia and Cerrado in Nova Xavantina, Mato Grosso state, Brazil on July 28, 2021. (REUTERS/Amanda Perobelli)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/80650000-c0a8-0242-e8ec-08dabf375251_cx10_cy11_cw89_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Some experts say deforestation in the Amazon is reaching a tipping point. This sky view shows deforestation near a forest on the border between Amazonia and Cerrado in Nova Xavantina, Mato Grosso state, Brazil on July 28, 2021. (REUTERS/Amanda Perobelli)</span></div>
<p>The online dictionary <em>Merriam-Webster</em> defines <u>tipping point</u> as “the critical point in a situation, process, or system beyond which a <strong>significant</strong> and often unstoppable effect or change takes place.”</p>
<p>The<u> tipping point</u> can also be the time at which a change or an effect cannot be stopped.</p>
<p>For example, some scientists believe Earth may have passed the <u>tipping point</u> in global warming. Efforts taken now will not prevent environmental disaster. It is too late to stop the damage. In other words, <u>that ship has sailed</u>. When something reaches a <u>tipping point</u> it is too late to turn back. It is a <u>point of no return</u>.</p>
<p>Here is another definition. The online <em>Cambridge Dictionary</em> defines the <u>tipping point</u> as “a time during an activity or process when an important decision has to be made or when a situation changes completely.”</p>
<p>Used this way, we often say we reach, <strong>approach</strong>, or near a tipping point. Here are some examples:</p>
<p><em>In class, the students' anger toward their teacher reached a <u>tipping point.</u> She had again given them a test on a subject she hadn't taught.</em></p>
<p><em>Prices at the food store are nearing a <u>tipping point</u>. If they go much higher, people will just shop elsewhere. </em></p>
<p>Malcolm Gladwell wrote about the subject in his book <em>Tipping Point</em> published in 2002. He describes <u>tipping point</u> this way: “<u>The tipping point</u> is that magic moment when an idea, <strong>trend</strong>, or social behavior crosses a <strong>threshold</strong>, tips, and spreads like wildfire.”</p>
<p>For example, you could say, “The writer's best-selling second book was the <u>tipping point </u>in her career. Now, everything she publishes is popular!”</p>
<p>And that's the end of this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>.</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>momentum </strong><em>– n.</em><strong> </strong>strength or force gained by motion or by a series of events</p>
<p><strong>significant</strong> <em>– adj. </em>having much importance</p>
<p><strong>approach </strong><em>– v. </em>to draw closer to</p>
<p><strong>trend </strong><em>– n. </em>a current style or preference</p>
<p><strong>threshold </strong><em>– n. </em>the place or point of entering or beginning</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Harlem Celebrates Its Rebirth after 50 Years (2024/8/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/harlem-celebrates-its-rebirth-after-50-years.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">23 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In the 1970s, a lack of community investment resulted in a large number of people leaving Harlem, a well-known New York City neighborhood in northern Manhattan.</p>
<p>Nearly 50,000 people, about a third of the area's population, left to escape violence, crime and poor living conditions. Among those who left was LeeSandra Moore's mother who moved to the state of Virginia. “It was a <strong>scary</strong> time,” said Moore, now 52 and still living in Harlem. “I couldn't blame her for that.”</p>
<p>Those who stayed were mostly poor, Black families. They lived through unrest that followed the 1964 killing of an unarmed Black teenager and the killings of Black leader Malcolm X in 1965 and Rev. Martin Luther King Jr. in 1968.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A man walks past a mural in the Harlem neighborhood of New York, Thursday, Aug. 15, 2024. (AP Photo/Pamela Smith)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-f84f-08dcc20d5b18_cx0_cy7_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A man walks past a mural in the Harlem neighborhood of New York, Thursday, Aug. 15, 2024. (AP Photo/Pamela Smith)</span></div>
<p>News reports described Harlem as a “sinking ship.”</p>
<p>Percy Sutton was president of the local Manhattan government at the time. As the city's highest-<strong>ranking</strong> Black official, he knew Harlem needed a lift and started a <strong>festival</strong> called Harlem Day in 1974.</p>
<p>Sutton called up elected officials. He gathered actors, like Sidney Poitier and Ruby Dee, entertainers, including Tito Puente and Max Roach, and the poet Maya Angelou to celebrate the first Harlem Day. It honored Harlem's history and shows how the neighborhood became known as "Black Mecca” or the center of Black arts, culture and businesses.</p>
<p>“It was such a successful day,” said Lloyd Williams — one of Harlem Day's co-founders and the current president of the Greater Harlem Chamber of Commerce — that it became a week-long yearly event called Harlem Week.</p>
<p><strong>The festival's 50th year</strong></p>
<p>This year, Harlem Week celebrated its 50th anniversary with 18 days filled with free programming.</p>
<p>The celebration included food, Broadway performances, an Apollo Hour, and a tribute to entertainer Harry Belafonte. It offered financial education and career training, and for children, back-to-school backpacks.</p>
<p>One important part of Harlem Week was an effort to deal with Harlem's long-standing health crises. Medical volunteers checked blood pressure and tested for cancer and diabetes. People learned about drug use, HIV/AIDS and healthy aging.</p>
<p>Rev. Al Sharpton leads the National Action Network in Harlem. He said, "Harlem Week has been the <strong>constant</strong> line through the last 50 years of America's most historic Black neighborhood."</p>
<p>Organizers and people say Harlem Week has brought new life to the area. The once-deserted neighborhood is now home to restored buildings, new businesses, and immigrants. The streets are filled with jazz, reggae, R&amp;B, and gospel music traditions.</p>
<p><strong>Big stores vs. small shops</strong></p>
<p>Moore, the Harlem native whose mother moved to Virginia, watched as big national stores moved in. Sometimes they took the place of local shops and made rents go up. "Some of that is okay, but what about the small business where you can get that great sandwich?" she asked. Moore wants people to eat less fast food, so she teaches healthy eating and cooking to young local students.</p>
<p>At Harlem Week, Moore represented GirlTrek, a national movement of Black women supporting health through walking. She said, "I feel like I should have left a long time ago, but something about Harlem draws me back to it."</p>
<p>Moore continued, "Harlem is my beginning. Harlem is my future. Harlem is a huge part of what makes me who I am."</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Ryan Doan-Nguyen reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>scary</strong>- <em>adj</em>. causing fear</p>
<p><strong>rank </strong>– <em>v</em>. to place (someone or something) in a particular position among a group of people or things that are being judged according to quality, ability, size, etc.</p>
<p><strong>festival - </strong><em>n</em>. a special time or event when people gather to celebrate something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Speaking Fluently (2024/8/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/speaking-fluently.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">23 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Aaron Ali in Sudan about how to become a fluent speaker.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-a1c6-08dcc14f4076_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>I have been learning English since 2010, but I can't speak English fluently, even now. Could you tell me how to get my English fluent?</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>Thank you for writing to us, Aaron Ali. I'm happy to answer this question.</p>
<p>To help you reach your goal, consider the following two questions:</p>
<p>1. What is making it difficult for you to become fluent?</p>
<p>2. Are you getting the input and practice with English that you need? Input means the language you listen to and read.</p>
<p>Being fluent does not mean speaking a language without any mistakes. Instead, fluency is the ability to speak without stopping too much. It is also the ability to speak about a large number of issues.</p>
<p>Try to identify what is preventing you from being fluent. Maybe you worry about making grammar mistakes. Maybe pronunciation problems slow you down. Perhaps you simply might not know enough words. Or, you might need more confidence, or belief in yourself. If that is the case, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/how-to-gain-confidence-in-your-english-speaking/5750911.html">our VOA Learning English article linked here</a> gives advice for gaining more confidence in your speaking.</p>
<p><strong>Two things to know</strong></p>
<p>People generally need two things to become fluent. The first thing they need is to know a lot of words and expressions. You should listen to and read English that you can mostly understand but that also helps you learn a few new expressions at a time.</p>
<p>Remember, you can be fluent even if you make many grammar mistakes. But you cannot speak fluently if you do not know enough words and expressions.</p>
<p>The second thing learners need is a lot of practice speaking in different kinds of situations.</p>
<p>Try to find an English-speaking partner and practice often. Online sites can help you find a language partner. You can have a conversation with this person over a mobile phone or computer. And this <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/five-tips-for-great-language-exchanges/5175780.html">VOA Learning English article</a> gives advice for great language exchanges.</p>
<p><strong>Other suggestions</strong></p>
<p>Practice speaking about particular <strong>topics</strong>. For example, if you are interested in health and exercise, learn the words and expressions connected to that topic. Next, try to write about it. Writing can help you organize your ideas and remember vocabulary. Last, practice speaking about the topic, using the special vocabulary you have learned.</p>
<p>Storytelling is another way to practice. It helps you learn expressions and grammatical forms. Tell a story many times. That will help you feel what it is like to speak fluently.</p>
<p>Reading out loud is another way to practice, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/early-literacy-fluency/7155518.html">and the video and article linked here</a> gives advice about doing that.</p>
<p>Finally, our <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/z/6042">How to Pronounce</a> series shows you how to say common phrases quickly and easily.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, do you have a question about American English? Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.<em> </em></p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><em>_______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>topic </strong><em>-n. </em>a subject under consideration or discussion</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Astronomy Group Joins Effort to Establish Time Zone on the Moon (2024/8/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/astronomy-group-joins-effort-to-establish-time-zone-on-the-moon.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>An international group of astronomers has joined efforts seeking to establish a separate time zone for the moon.</p>
<p>The French-based International Astronomical Union (IAU) recently approved a resolution on the matter during the group's General Assembly meeting in Cape Town, South Africa.</p>
<p>The resolution calls on space organizations around the world to cooperate on establishing a <strong>standard </strong>clock for the moon.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="An aircraft passes in front of the moon, with a red glow attributable to smoke particles carried in the upper atmosphere from North American wildfires, a day ahead of the full super moon, as seen from Parliament Hill in London, Britain, August 18, 2024. (REUTERS/Toby Melville)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-2186-08dcc0d71094_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">An aircraft passes in front of the moon, with a red glow attributable to smoke particles carried in the upper atmosphere from North American wildfires, a day ahead of the full super moon, as seen from Parliament Hill in London, Britain, August 18, 2024. (REUTERS/Toby Melville)</span></div>
<p>The moon's orbital movements around Earth make one day on the lunar surface equal to 29.5 Earth days. And because the moon has less gravity compared to Earth, time moves slightly faster there, about 58.7 microseconds quicker each day.</p>
<p>Susan Stewart is an astronomer with the U.S. Naval Observatory. She helped create the resolution at the IAU conference. Stewart told The Associated Press the aim of the measure is quite simple: “To work together to establish (a) standard time.”</p>
<p>Currently, moon operations run on the time of the country that is launching spacecraft. But supporters of creating a separate time zone say this method will have to change; more countries and private space companies are starting to launch their own moon missions.</p>
<p>Last year, the European Space Agency (ESA) pushed for the creation of a lunar clock. And earlier this year, the White House directed the U.S. space agency NASA and other agencies to come up with a timekeeping plan for the moon by the end of 2026.</p>
<p>ESA noted communication and navigation systems built for the moon will perform much better if they use “the same timescale.” In addition, a separate time zone will support “the many other crewed and uncrewed missions” planned for the future, ESA said.</p>
<p>In the past, NASA also considered establishing a separate time zone for the International Space Station (ISS). But the agency decided against it. Instead, the ISS runs on Coordinated Universal Time, or UTC, which is based on time kept by atomic clocks. NASA officials say this system helps ease the time difference between NASA and the Canadian Space Agency, as well as other space partners in Russia, Japan and Europe.</p>
<p>The international team looking at establishing a lunar time zone has said it is still deciding whether a single organization should be chosen to set and keep time on the moon.</p>
<p>Bijunath Patla is a physicist at the U.S. Commerce Department's National Institute of Standards and Technology. He told the AP that astronomers are still deciding on how a lunar clock would work. Patla said, “I think the community has realized that this needs to be done. And this is the beginning.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press and Reuters reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>standard</strong> <em>– n.</em> a particular level of quality that is set for multiple things</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Australia Moves Forward with Major Renewable Energy Project (2024/8/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/australia-moves-forward-with-major-renewable-energy-project.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A plan to build a huge solar farm in Australia is a step closer after the Australian government gave environmental approvals for the $19 billion project recently.</p>
<p>Australian company Sun Cable plans to build a 12,400-hectare solar farm in a remote area of northern Australia. The farm will send electricity to the city of Darwin via an 800-kilometer overhead transmission line. Then the power will be transported to large industrial <strong>customers</strong> in Singapore through a 4,300-kilometer submarine cable.</p>
<p>The Australia-Asia PowerLink project aims to deliver up to 6 gigawatts of green electricity each year. Such a project, Australian Environment Minister Tanya Plibersek suggested, would “help turn Australia into a renewable energy superpower” and<strong> boost</strong> its economy.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - The Williamsdale Solar Farm, shown from the air and located south of Canberra, Australia, on Oct. 15, 2020, has about 30 hectares (74 acres) of solar panels. (Mick Tsikas/AAP Image via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/70d00805-4f3f-4f66-8e55-a2f8a7e34233_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - The Williamsdale Solar Farm, shown from the air and located south of Canberra, Australia, on Oct. 15, 2020, has about 30 hectares (74 acres) of solar panels. (Mick Tsikas/AAP Image via AP)</span></div>
<p>Plibersek said in a written statement, “It will be the largest solar <strong>precinct</strong> in the world...”</p>
<p>The project was first backed by Australian mining businessman Andrew Forrest and Atlassian co-founder Mike Cannon-Brookes. The plans were discussed during a state visit by then-Singapore Prime Minister Lee Hsien Loong and Australian Prime Minister Anthony Albanese as part of a “Green Economy” agreement in 2022.</p>
<p>In January 2023, the project collapsed when Sun Cable was involved in a financing dispute between Forrest and Cannon-Brookes. By May of that year, a group led by Cannon-Brookes' Grok Ventures acquired the company, finalizing the takeover in September 2023.</p>
<p>SunCable Australia's managing director Cameron Garnsworthy said it was pleased to have cleared a major legal issue. He added that the company will now put its efforts into the next stage of planning to work towards "a Final Investment Decision targeted by 2027.”</p>
<p>The company said electricity supply would begin in the early 2030s.</p>
<p>Energy has been a politically charged issue for nearly 20 years in Australia. The country depends on coal and gas as well as money from exporting those fuels to help support its economy.</p>
<p>This dependence on <strong>fossil fuels</strong> has historically made it one of the world's worst <strong>greenhouse gas</strong> emitters on a per capita basis.</p>
<p>Australia's main opposition party in June announced plans to build the country's first nuclear power plants as early as 2035. The announcement ensures the major parties will be divided on how to reduce Australia's greenhouse gas emissions at elections due within a year.</p>
<p>The parties have not gone to an election with the same carbon reduction policies since 2007.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Keiran Smith reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>customer </strong><em>-- n. </em>one that buys a good or service</p>
<p><strong>boost</strong><em> -- v. </em>increase, raise</p>
<p><strong>precinct</strong> <em>-- n.</em> a part of a territory with definite bounds often established for administrative purposes</p>
<p><strong>fossil fuel </strong><em>-- n.</em> a fuel (such as coal, oil, or natural gas) formed in the earth from plant or animal remains</p>
<p><strong>greenhouse gas</strong> <em>-- n.</em> any of various gaseous compounds (such as carbon dioxide or methane) that absorb infrared radiation and trap heat in the atmosphere</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
