<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>VOA Special English</title>
        <link>https://www.21voa.com/special_english/</link>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <itunes:category>ESL</itunes:category>
        <itunes:author>VOA</itunes:author>
        <description>美国之音（以下称VOA）的英语节目，按播音速度可分为两种：Standard English （标准英语）和 Special English（特别英语）。

Special English 又叫“慢速英语”，是VOA 专为全世界非英语国家初学英语的听众安排的一种简易、规范的英语广播节目。该节目创始于50年代末期，是VOA 的专家们研究如何与世界各地的英语学习者进行交际的产物。它正式开播于1959年10月。当时只面向欧洲和中东，但由于这个节目适合许多国家英语学习者的需要，所以它的广播对象不久就扩大到世界其他地区，并很快在全世界范围内产生了广泛的影响。现在这个节目对欧洲、非洲和拉丁美洲每晚广播一次，对加勒比地区每晚广播一次（星期天除外），对东南亚广播次数最多，每天上午两次，晚上三次。

30多年来，VOA 为了办好Special English节目，进行了大量的调查研究工作，对播音速度、内容及用词范围都作了具体规定，基本上达到了既能为英语学习者提供信息，又不损害英语本身风格的目的，使之成为VOA 独具特色，拥有最大量听众的节目。

美国著名词汇学家S. B. Flexmer 指明了Special English的三条标准，也就是它所“特别”的地方：

1、它是一种由美国人最常用的1500个基本单词为主体构成的美国英语；

2、它用简短、明晰的句子写作和广播；

3、它以每分钟90个单词的速度，即2/3的Standard English（标准英语）速度进行广播。

Special English的节目可分为两大类：一类是新闻节目；一类是专题节目。

1．新闻节目

VOA Special English 的新闻广播向听众提供世界范围内的政治、经济、军事、外交、国际关系、宗教、天气以及各种重大事件和珍闻奇事等各个方面的信息，每天向东南亚地区广播五次，早上两次，晚上三次，每逢半点播出。

Special English新闻节目每次长约十分钟，大都播出十条左右新闻，近一千个单词，每条新闻多为一分钟，但偶尔也有长达两分钟的要闻。除头条新闻外，每条新闻都由一个电头引导，这样显得结构分明，条理清晰，适宜初学英语的人收听。在节目结束之前，播音员常常用三四句话重播其中三条新闻的提要以加深听众对要闻的印象。

Special English新闻中70%左右的内容与同时整点播出的Standard English新闻相同，但相同新闻的先后次序有所变动。每次节目的开头和结尾大同小异，格式比较固定。

2．专题节目（一）

Special English的专题节目（Feature Programs）,从时间上看，可分为两大类：一是每五分钟一次的专题，二是每十五分钟一次的专题。本节先介绍每项五分钟一次的专题材节目。

Special English五分钟一次的专题材节目安排在Special English新闻节目之后和（或）每十五分钟一次的专题材节目之前播出，每星期播七次。根据内容，可分为三个小类，即：Science Report（科学报道），逢星期一、三、五播出，每天播六遍；Agriculture Report（农业报道），逢星期二、四播出，每天播六遍；Words And Their Stories（词语掌故），逢星期六和星期天播出，每天播五遍。这三个专题材各具特色，具有相对的独立性，听众每听完一个节目，都会获得一个完整的印象。

Science Report（科学报道）这一专题材节目每周向听众介绍三篇有关现代科学技术最新发展情况的报道，涉及物理、化学、天文至高无上理、生物、环卫、心理、教育、医学和计算机等方面。适宜理工科大学生和科技工作者收集信息，积累资料，学习科技英语。

Agriculture Report（农业报道） Agriculture Report是为农业科技工作者和生产者安排的一个专题。它专门报道世界各国，特别是美国现代农业生产的最新成文汇报总务科 学家对农业生产某一方面的研究进展，以及他们对影响农业生产的某一自然现象进行分析和研究的近况。此外，它还经常向听众介绍发展中国家家业生产的一些有益经验等内容。

Words And Their Stories（词语掌故）这一专题节目，旨在向学习英语的听众介绍美国英语中生动有趣的词语和惯用法，并从科学研究和通俗词源学的角度来解释它们的含意、产生的背景及其在使用过程中的演变情况等。它通过讲故事的形式讲解每一个词语。这是VOA Special English中的优秀节目之一，是学习美国英语的极好材料。通过收听这一节目，听众不仅能学到娓娓动听的掌故和地道的美国英语，而且能增加美国的社会文化背景知识，历史传统与现状的了解。

VOA 为了更好地办好这个节目，便于听众收听学习，于1978年编辑出版了一本名为Words And Their Stories的书，共收集一百篇故事，作者是Herbert Sutcliffe, Harold Bermen 及VOA 该节目的部分编辑人员。在每次的实际广播中，播音员都以此书为蓝本，再根据需要对原稿进行适当增删。按每周两个故事计算，此书的一百个故事还不能满足一年的播音需要。于是编辑们就是重播部分词语掌故的同时，不断增加许多新的词语掌故，及时将词源学家的最新研究成果和不断增加的新词汇介绍给听众。收听实践证明，初学者在收听过程中必然会遇到许多人名、地名和一些较难的句子，有时甚至在听完之后还很难理解所播词语的确切含义及其汉语意思，为此，听众可参看1983年由中国对外翻译出版公司出版的该书英汉对照本中的有关部分。

3．专题节目（二）

VOA Special English的专题节目，除上节谈的五分钟一次的以外，还有本节要介绍的每十五分钟一次的节目。这类节目共有七个不同的小专题，以星期为单位循环，每天分四次复播出一个专题，但星期日和星期六的两个专题材每晚只播三遍，每次节目约十分钟，继每次五分钟的专题节目之后播出。

这类专题节目的基本结构是，在特定的伴声中先报告当次节目的名称，并扼要介绍其主要内容，然后播送节目正文。最后，在伴乐声中报告节目主持人和撰稿人的姓名，以邀请听众在下周的这个时间继续收听该节目而结束。

People in America（美国人物志） 这是有关美国历史名人的一个专题节目，每逢星期天晚上播出。它向听众介绍在美国历史上产生过重大影响、起过重要作用、作出了突出贡献的科学、文学、政治、或其他各方面的历史人物。节目一般都对他们的生平事迹进行简要的叙述，对其贡献作出评介，类似人物小传。有的重要人物事迹很多，必须用两次或几次的节目时间进行联播。对这样的节目要坚持收听，才会获得完整的印象。

TThis is America（今日美国） This Is America向听众介绍美国人民的生活、学习、工作和娱乐情况，是英语学习者解美国社会的一条渠道。该专题大都一个节目一个整体，每逢星期一晚播出。

Science in the News（科学新闻） 这一专题材主要对新近的科学技术新闻进行综述或摘要广播。向听众介绍世界各国在自然、医学、疾病、原子能、航天等方面的科研动态、成果、突破性进展及存在的困难。涉及当今世界人们普遍关心的重大问题，如核事故、航天飞机爆炸、自然灾害、环境污染和爱滋病等等。每逢星期二播出，每次播一到五条新闻摘要。

Explorations（自然探索） 每逢星期三晚上，听众可以收听到Explorations这一专题节目。该专题既涉及人类遨游太空、探索原子、研究自身、改造自然的现代技术，也报道发展中国家开发新资源，利用新工艺改善人民生活等方面的成就，其侧重点在各种科技实验和简易实用技术方面。该节目一般安排一段时间播一个系列，每次播出一个主题，以便能将某项新技术的研究和应用的全过程介绍给听众，电台还乐意为感兴趣的听众提供所需的文字材料。

The Making of a Nation（建国史话） 这一专题节目向听众介绍美利坚合众国从十三个殖民地区域到现代工业国的孕育、诞生以及形成超级大国的历史过程，并以历史为线索，特定的历史时期为单位，以重大的历史事件为主题材来叙述各个党派、各届总统和政府的历史作用与贡献。这是每个英语学习者都应了解的基本知识。The Making of a Nation每逢星期四播出。这是个系列节目，坚持收听，则有助于系统了解美国的历史概况。

American Mosaic（美国万花筒） American Mosaic是一个radio magazine（广播杂志）节目。该节目题材广泛、内容丰，展示着美国社会文化生活中比较轻松愉快的生活画面；听众收听该节目就如同在阅读一本图文并茂的杂志。它每次有三到五个小节目，涉及音乐、图书、技术和教育等方面的内容。我们既可以从中欣赏到著名歌唱的优秀歌曲，对美国音乐有所了解，又可以获取一些生动有趣的现代美国社会生活知识，随着播音员那亲切悦耳的声音步入美国风景如画的大好河山；同时还能听到世界各地的听众提出的有关英语语方文学等方面的问题和电台的解答。

American Stories（美国故事） 这一专题材节目安排在每星期六晚上播出。这样能使听众在学习和工作之余，得以轻松一下头脑。我们可以通过这一美国文学的“窗口”，接触各种流派、各类名家的文学作品。了解美国英语的时代特色，欣赏、学习美国人民运用语方的技巧，并从那些佳作名篇中获得艺术享受。该节目对短篇故事采取一次播一篇的方式，对中、长篇小说则先进行简写加工，再分几次播出全文。在播出故事正文之前，播音员常常先介绍故事的主要情节。对需要分几次节目时间播出的中长篇，在播第二或以后各部分之前，主持人还先重述已播部分的故事梗概，以唤起听众的回忆，使故事听起来更加连贯。</description>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          <item>
            <title>When in Rome … (2024/10/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/when-in-rome.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>One of the best things about traveling to a new country is learning about new traditions and customs. They can be very different from our own.</p>
<p>When visiting a foreign county, it is smart to follow the local social rules and customs of the people who live there. This can make your stay easier and more enjoyable.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A street vendor sells hats in front of the Colosseum in Rome, Monday, July 17, 2023. (AP Photo/Gregorio Borgia)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-d9e1-08db86e11944_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A street vendor sells hats in front of the Colosseum in Rome, Monday, July 17, 2023. (AP Photo/Gregorio Borgia)</span></div>
<p>Today we talk about <strong>fitting in </strong>with the way local people do things. We talk about an expression that goes all the way back to ancient Rome:</p>
<p><u>When in Rome, do as the Romans do.</u></p>
<p>This expression means that when we visit a place, we should follow the customs and norms of that place. This expression shows an <strong>attitude</strong> or <strong>mindset</strong>: You are willing to change your way of doing things to fit in with those around you.</p>
<p>The place does not have to be a new country. It can simply be a new situation or environment. For example, let's say you usually speak very loudly. But when visiting an art museum or library, you whisper in a low voice. You follow the rules of that place. <u>When in Rome ...</u></p>
<p>English speakers often shorten the expression to <u>“when in Rome...”</u></p>
<p>This expression has another meaning. When you are in an unfamiliar situation, you should follow the lead of those who know the rules. These people know how to <strong>behave </strong>with others. They know how to play the game. They know how to work within the system. They don't do things differently. They<strong> blend</strong><strong> in</strong>.</p>
<p>But what does Rome have to do with following other people's customs? Several websites describe how the expression may have begun. And if they are correct, this expression is very old.</p>
<p>Here is how the story goes:</p>
<p><em>During the time of the Roman Empire more than 1500 years ago, a Christian leader, Saint Augustine, moved from Rome to Milan. Once in the new city, he found some parts of religious life to be different. For example, in Rome he <strong>fasted,</strong> or did not eat, on Saturday. But in Milan, people did not fast on Saturday. Another church leader, Saint Ambrose, gave him some advice. St. Ambrose said that when he goes to Rome he fasts on Saturdays. But when he is in Milan, he does not. Problem solved.</em></p>
<p>This good advice, or proverb, has survived over the years. Some word experts say it first appeared in English around 500 years ago.</p>
<p>But we still use it to this day -- either to give advice or to describe a situation where we have to change our behavior to fit in.</p>
<p>Let's hear another example.</p>
<p><em>A: How was your trip to see your brother's family?</em></p>
<p><em>B: It was really fun. Different but fun. </em></p>
<p><em>A: How was it different?</em></p>
<p><em>B: Well, they live in the country and love to hunt and fish. So, that's what I did all week. It was great! </em></p>
<p><em>A: I am so surprised. I didn't think you were the <strong>outdoorsy</strong> type.</em></p>
<p><em>B: I'm not! But <u>when in Rome ...</u></em></p>
<p><em>A: With that attitude, it's <strong>no wonder</strong> you had a fun trip!</em></p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>.</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>__________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>fit in </strong><em>–v. (phrasal)</em> to behave in a way that is like other people near, so they do not form bad opinions about you</p>
<p><strong>attitude </strong><em>–n.</em> the way you think or feel about someone or something</p>
<p><strong>mindset </strong>–n. a way of thinking</p>
<p><strong>behave </strong>–v. the way a person acts</p>
<p><strong>blend</strong><strong> in </strong><em>–v. (phrasal)</em> to not bring attention to oneself</p>
<p><strong>fast </strong>–v. to not eat for a period of time, often for religious reasons<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>outdoorsy<em> </em></strong><em>–adj. (informal) </em>enjoying or accustomed to nature and wild areas</p>
<p><strong>no wonder<em> </em></strong><em>–interjection </em>it is not a surprise<em> </em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Weather Experts: ‘We Cannot Control Hurricanes’ (2024/10/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/weather-experts-we-cannot-control-hurricanes.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A series of powerful hurricanes have affected millions of people in the United States in recent weeks.</p>
<p>Some people are wondering if scientists could control extreme weather events. However, experts say hurricanes are far too powerful for humans to control.</p>
<p>Climate change is leading to increasingly powerful storms. This has led to greater attention on the possibilities of geoengineering.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A Bayou West resident and friend try to salvage items from her home after an apparent tornado touched down on the central beach community after Hurricane Milton in Vero Beach, Fla., Oct.11, 2024. (Kaila Jones/USA Today Network via Reuters)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f407c0c7-2c38-4f45-85bc-d1258491eddd_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A Bayou West resident and friend try to salvage items from her home after an apparent tornado touched down on the central beach community after Hurricane Milton in Vero Beach, Fla., Oct.11, 2024. (Kaila Jones/USA Today Network via Reuters)</span></div>
<p>Geoengineering involves futuristic ideas for <strong>reversing</strong> or lessening climate change. But many scientists have serious concerns about unwanted results.</p>
<p>Hurricanes are an example of the uncontrollable, disordered power of Earth's weather. Experts say there is no clear evidence from research to show humans might be able to control such strong storms.</p>
<p>Kristen Corbosiero is a professor of atmospheric and environmental sciences at the University at Albany. Corbosiero is a weather expert, or meteorologist. She said: "If meteorologists could stop hurricanes, we would stop hurricanes. If we could control the weather, we would not want the kind of death and destruction that's happened."</p>
<p><strong>Weather experts' opinions on controlling hurricanes</strong></p>
<p>National Hurricane Center tropical <strong>analysis</strong> chief Chris Landsea said that a fully developed hurricane releases heat energy that is the equal to a 10-megaton nuclear bomb every 20 minutes. That is more than all the energy used at a given time by human beings.</p>
<p>Chris Field is director of the Stanford Woods Institute for the Environment in California. He said scientists are learning of the many ways that climate change is making hurricanes more powerful and destructive. Warmer oceans add energy and more water to the warming atmosphere. That water becomes strong rainfall.</p>
<p>Colorado State University hurricane researcher Phil Klotzbac said the amount of energy a hurricane generates is much more than humans have the power to control. But people have still made attempts to control the storms.</p>
<p><strong>Historical efforts to control hurricanes</strong></p>
<p>Jim Fleming is a professor at Colby College in Maine. He has studied historical efforts to control the weather. He said humans do not even come close to having the practical technology to successfully control the weather.</p>
<p>Fleming described one attempt in 1947. The General Electric company partnered with the U.S. military to drop dry ice from Air Force planes into the path of a hurricane to try to weaken it. It did not work.</p>
<p>Some attempts or ideas could even make the storms worse or cause greater harm. One especially dangerous idea was to use a nuclear bomb, which would cause radiation and not be strong enough to change the storm, Kristen Corbosiero said.</p>
<p>Bringing cooling <strong>icebergs</strong> or adding chemicals to cause rain also are ideas that do not work, scientists say.</p>
<p><strong>Engineering the climate</strong></p>
<p>Modern geoengineers would operate differently. Today's geoengineers are thinking about how to <strong>reverse</strong> the damage humans have already caused.</p>
<p>Scientists in the field say one of the most promising ideas they see based on computer models is <strong>solar</strong> geoengineering. The method would involve lifting small particles into the upper atmosphere to return some of the sunlight back into space, cooling the planet a little. Still, supporters of the idea know that it comes with risks.</p>
<p>Two years ago, the American Geophysical Union (AGU) announced it was forming an <strong>ethics </strong>agreement for climate intervention. The AGU is the largest society of scientists who study climate issues.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Melina Walling and Seth Borenstein </em><em>reported this story for the </em><em>Associated Press</em><em>.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>geoengineering </strong>– <em>n</em>. large-scale manipulation of a specific process central to controlling Earth's climate for the purpose of obtaining a specific benefit</p>
<p><strong>reverse</strong> – <em>v. </em>to change (something) to an opposite state or condition</p>
<p><strong>analysis</strong> –<em> n.</em> a careful study of something to learn about its parts, what they do, and how they are related to each othe</p>
<p><strong>iceberg</strong> – <em>n.</em> a very large piece of ice floating in the ocean</p>
<p><strong>solar</strong> – n. of or relating to the sun</p>
<p><strong>ethics</strong> –<em> n</em>. n area of study that deals with ideas about what is good and bad behavior</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How to Improve Your Spelling (2024/10/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/how-to-improve-your-spelling.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Guillermo in Argentina about how to spell words in English.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4ec92eba-4c0f-40d5-9a0e-3106d24bba11_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>When I hear some new words in English, I can find their meaning, but for me, the spelling is always difficult. Can you please give me [some] advice?</p>
<p>Thank you,</p>
<p>Guillermo</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Guillermo.</p>
<p>English spelling can be difficult for several reasons. For many letters in the English alphabet, a letter can represent several sounds.</p>
<p>Let's listen to the sound the letter “A” makes in each of the following six words:</p>
<p><em>cat</em></p>
<p><em>day</em></p>
<p><em>father</em></p>
<p><em>ball</em></p>
<p><em>many</em></p>
<p><em>attack</em></p>
<p>Can you hear the difference between the two letters “A” of the last word? Let's listen again.</p>
<p><em>attack</em></p>
<p>The first syllable made the quick schwa sound “/<strong><i></i>601;/</strong>”.</p>
<p>Because an English letter can make different sounds, words that have similar spellings can sound different from each other, as in these examples:</p>
<p><em>lemon </em>and<em> demon</em></p>
<p><em>daughter </em>and<em> laughter</em></p>
<p><em>war </em>and<em> far</em></p>
<p>In addition, words that have different spellings can sound the same. These are called homophones, as in these examples:</p>
<p><em>pause </em>and<em> paws</em></p>
<p><em>rode </em>and<em> road</em></p>
<p><em>deer </em>and<em> dear</em></p>
<p>But that's not all. In many words, some letters are silent—they are not pronounced at all, like the letter “b” at the end of the word “climb”.</p>
<p>You can see from all of the above examples that you cannot only use the sounds of words to know how to spell them. So, what should you do?</p>
<p><strong>Spelling rules</strong></p>
<p>Fortunately, English does have some general rules for spelling.</p>
<p>For example, a famous rule that children learn in school is “<em>I</em> before <em>e</em> except after <em>c.”</em> This gives us the spelling of words such as:</p>
<p><em>piece</em></p>
<p><em>niece</em></p>
<p><em>receive</em></p>
<p>But be careful! There are still many words in English that break the spelling rules. The word “science,” for example, breaks the “I before e” rule. For words such as these, you simply have to memorize how to spell them. And how can you do that?</p>
<p><strong>Memorizing words</strong></p>
<p>The best way to help your memory is to read as much as possible and practice writing. Writing can test how well you know how to spell. Most computer programs also include a spell-checker, where misspelled words are underlined in a color. This helps you see any spelling mistakes you have made and also shows you the correct spelling.</p>
<p><strong>Recognizing patterns</strong></p>
<p>In addition to rules, there are spelling <strong>patterns</strong>. You can group words into the pattern they follow. For example, some words that have the spelling -ough include:</p>
<p><em>rough, tough, cough, though, </em>and <em>bought</em>.</p>
<p>Notice, however, that with these examples, the letters -ough made three different vowel sounds:</p>
<p><em>rough, cough, though</em></p>
<p>This again shows the need to memorize spellings because the sound of the word will not always tell you how to spell it.</p>
<p><strong>Having fun</strong></p>
<p>Lastly, becoming good at spelling can be enjoyable. Think of it like a game or other activity you enjoy. Over time, you will feel good as you learn to spell more and more words. There are many books, websites, and apps designed for spelling practice. Try to use these and practice your spelling.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? We'd like to hear from you. Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please include where you are from in your email, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>pattern </strong>–n. a regular or repeated happening</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Han Kang, First South Korean Writer to Win Nobel in Literature (2024/10/11)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/han-kang-first-south-korean-writer-to-win-nobel-in-literature.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">10 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>South Korean writer Han Kang won the 2024 Nobel Prize in Literature on Thursday. The Swedish Academy's Nobel Committee said her work “confronts historical <strong>traumas</strong> and exposes the <strong>fragility</strong> of human life.”</p>
<p>Born in 1970, Han Kang is the first South Korean to win the literature prize. Kang began her career in 1993 with the publication of several poems in <em>Literature and Society</em>. She published her first story in 1995 with <em>Love of Yeosu.</em></p>
<p>In 2016, Kang won the Man Booker International Prize for <em>The Vegetarian.</em> It tells the story of a woman's decision to stop eating meat and her family's worry about her mental health. The <strong>novel</strong> was the first of her books to be translated into English and was seen as her major international breakthrough.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Han Kang speaks to the media after winning the Man Booker International prize for fiction for her book 'The Vegetarian' in London, Tuesday, May, 16, 2016. Kang has won the Nobel Prize for Literature. (AP Photo/Alastair Grant, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01e877c5-133c-4c36-8e44-b7776aa637a0_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Han Kang speaks to the media after winning the Man Booker International prize for fiction for her book 'The Vegetarian' in London, Tuesday, May, 16, 2016. Kang has won the Nobel Prize for Literature. (AP Photo/Alastair Grant, File)</span></div>
<p>In a talk with the Booker Prizes, published last year, Kang said the book was written during a difficult period in her life. She questioned whether she could finish the story or even survive as a writer.</p>
<p>"I was suffering from severe <strong>arthritis</strong>...To this day, I feel awkward when I hear about the novel's ‘success,'” she said.</p>
<p>In the novel <em>Human Acts</em>, Kang explored the 1980 killing of hundreds of students and unarmed civilians by the South Korean military in the city of Gwangju, where she grew up.</p>
<p>"In seeking to give voice to the victims of history, the book confronts this episode with <strong>brutal</strong> actualization and, in so doing, approaches the <strong>genre</strong> of witness literature," the Academy said.</p>
<p><strong>One of two South Korean Nobel winners</strong></p>
<p>Kang is the second South Korean to win a Nobel Prize. Former South Korean President Kim Dae-jung received the Nobel Peace Prize in 2000 for his efforts to restore democracy in the South and improve relations with North Korea.</p>
<p>The literature prize has long faced criticism that it is too centered on European and North American writings. It has also been awarded mainly to male writers. Kang is only the 18th woman to receive the award among more than 100 winners.</p>
<p>Past winners of the prize include well-known writers like Irish poet W.B. Yeats, American writer Ernest Hemingway and Colombia's Gabriel Garcia Marquez. In 2016, American singer Bob Dylan also received the prize “for having created new poetic expressions within the great American song tradition”</p>
<p>Mats Malm is Permanent Secretary of the Swedish Academy. He told reporters, “I was able to talk to Han Kang over the phone. She was having an ordinary day, it seems, she had just finished <strong>supper</strong> with her son."</p>
<p>The prize comes with a money award of $1.1 million.</p>
<p>I'm Mario J. Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Jill Robbins adapted the story for Learning English based on reports from Reuters and The Associated Press.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>trauma </strong>– <em>n.</em> a very difficult or unpleasant experience that causes someone to have mental or emotional problems usually for a long time</p>
<p><strong>fragile</strong> – <em>adj</em>. easily broken or damaged</p>
<p><strong>novel</strong> <em>– n.</em> a long written story usually about imaginary characters and events</p>
<p><strong>arthritis</strong><strong> </strong>– <em>n.</em> a disease that causes the joints of the body to become swollen and painful</p>
<p><strong>brutal</strong> – <em>adj</em>. very direct and accurate in a way that is harsh or unpleasant</p>
<p><strong>genre</strong> - <em>n</em>. a particular type or category of literature or art</p>
<p><strong>supper</strong> – <em>n</em>. the evening meal — used especially to refer to an informal meal that you eat at home</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>UN: Crime Groups in Southeast Asia Find Success on Telegram (2024/10/11)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/un-crime-groups-in-southeast-asia-find-success-on-telegram.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">10 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Powerful crime groups in Southeast Asia use the messaging app Telegram widely, the United Nations said in a report on Monday. It said the app's use led to major changes in the way such groups carry out large criminal operations.</p>
<p>The U.N. Office on Drugs and Crime (UNODC) produced the report. The investigators say stolen data, including credit card information, passwords and <strong>browser</strong> history, are openly traded on the app. The app has many channels and little content supervision, the report said.</p>
<p>Criminals on the app also sell tools used for cybercrime, including so-called <strong>deepfake</strong> software and data-stealing <strong>malware</strong>. And, criminal <strong>cryptocurrency</strong> exchanges carry out business on Telegram also, the report said.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Telegram app logo is seen in this illustration taken, August 27, 2024. (REUTERS/Dado Ruvic/Illustration)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4b0d8111-f03c-44a1-b2cc-c8cfacb24f2a_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Telegram app logo is seen in this illustration taken, August 27, 2024. (REUTERS/Dado Ruvic/Illustration)</span></div>
<p>"We move 3 million USDT stolen from overseas per day," the report quoted one advertisement as saying in Chinese.</p>
<p>There is "strong evidence of underground data markets moving to Telegram and <strong>vendors</strong> actively looking to target transnational organized crime groups based in Southeast Asia," the report said.</p>
<p>Southeast Asia has emerged as a center for a multibillion-dollar online crime industry that targets victims across the world. Many industry members are Chinese criminal groups that operate from large, protected complexes using trafficked workers. The industry makes between $27.4 billion to $36.5 billion yearly, the UNODC said.</p>
<p>In August, French police arrested Telegram's leader Pavel Durov in Paris. Officials charged him with permitting criminal activity on the site, including the online spread of sexual images of children.</p>
<p>Telegram, which has close to 1 billion users, did not immediately answer a request for comment</p>
<p>Following his arrest, Durov said the app would surrender users' IP addresses and phone numbers to French officials making legal requests. He also said the app would remove some tools that have been abused for illegal activity.</p>
<p>The report said the huge amount of profit earned by criminal groups in the area led them to change their operating methods. They established new business models and added technologies to their systems, including malware, generative artificial intelligence and deepfakes, officials say.</p>
<p>The UNODC said it had identified more than ten deepfake software service providers “targeting criminal groups involved in cyber-enabled <strong>fraud</strong> in Southeast Asia."</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Reuters reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong><strong> </strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>browser - </strong><em>n. </em>a computer program used for accessing sites or information on a network (such as the World Wide Web)</p>
<p><strong>deepfake - </strong><em>n. </em>an image or recording that has been convincingly altered and manipulated to misrepresent someone as doing or saying something that was not actually done or said</p>
<p><strong>malware - </strong><em>n. </em>software designed to interfere with a computer's normal functioning</p>
<p><strong>cryptocurrency - </strong><em>n.</em><strong> </strong>any form of currency that only exists digitally, that usually uses a decentralized system for issuing new units and reording transactions, and that relies on cryptography to prevent fraudulent transactions</p>
<p><strong>vendor - </strong><em>n. </em>seller</p>
<p><strong>fraud - </strong><em>n. </em>the use of dishonest methods to cheat another person of something valuable</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: US Hurricanes Much Deadlier Than Government Estimates (2024/10/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/study-us-hurricanes-much-deadlier-than-government-estimates.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A new study says hurricanes in the United States are hundreds of times deadlier than government estimates say. In fact, the research finds, they result in more American deaths over the long term than car accidents or wars.</p>
<p>The study found the average storm that hits the U.S. <strong>contributes</strong> to the early deaths of 7,000 to 11,000 people over a 15-year period.</p>
<p>Solomon Hsiang is a climate economist at Stanford University in California. Hsiang co-wrote the study with Rachel Young of the University of California Berkeley.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This GOES-16 GeoColor satellite image taken at 12:15 p.m. EDT and provided by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shows Hurricane Milton in the Gulf of Mexico, off the coast of Mexico's Yucatan Peninsula on Oct. 8, 2024. (NOAA via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/744bf985-5557-411a-bd23-eb4d9cd90b7e_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This GOES-16 GeoColor satellite image taken at 12:15 p.m. EDT and provided by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shows Hurricane Milton in the Gulf of Mexico, off the coast of Mexico's Yucatan Peninsula on Oct. 8, 2024. (NOAA via AP)</span></div>
<p>“After each storm there is sort of this surge of additional <strong>mortality</strong> in a state that's been <strong>impacted </strong>that has not been <strong>previously</strong> documented or<strong> associated</strong> with hurricanes in any way,” Hsiang said.</p>
<p><em>Nature</em> magazine published the study.</p>
<p><strong>Researchers take a wider look </strong></p>
<p>The research considers hurricane deaths in a new way: through examination of long-term public health and economic effects of what is called <strong>excess</strong> mortality. The investigators looked at individual state death rates following 501 separate storms in the United States between 1930 and 2015. Their research shows a sudden rise or “bump” in death rates after each storm.</p>
<p>Similar examinations are done for heat waves and other health threats like pollution and disease, Hsiang said. They compare death rates to pre-storm times while accounting for other influences that could be causing change to those rates, he said.</p>
<p>Hsiang said additional research is needed to learn how storms contribute to deaths after the bad weather passes. But he theorized that storms cause major stress as well as environmental changes, including the spread of poisonous substances. He also said the economic cost of storms can leave people unable to pay for health care and other necessities.</p>
<p><strong>Early deaths</strong></p>
<p>“When someone dies a few years after a hurricane hit them, the cause will be recorded as a heart attack, stroke or respiratory failure,” said Texas A&amp;M University climate scientist Andrew Dessler. He was not part of the study but has done similar research on heat and cold deaths.</p>
<p>Hsiang said he and Young were surprised when they examined hundreds of bumps and found they stretch out over 15 years.</p>
<p>It's “almost like a <strong>trickle</strong> of mortality, like each month we're talking about five to 10 individuals who are dying earlier than they would have otherwise," Hsiang said.</p>
<p>These deaths are of people who did not realize their health issues were connected to storms that took place years earlier. But, Hsiang said, that is what the data shows: "They would not have died at those times had the storm not arrived.”</p>
<p>The numbers proved so high that the researchers kept looking for mistakes in their work. “It took years for us to really fully accept that this was happening," Hsiang said.</p>
<p><strong>How big are the numbers?</strong></p>
<p>Storms are a factor in between 55,000 to 88,000 excess deaths each year, the study found. Over the 85 years included in the study, the team found that between 3.6 million and 5.2 million people died in connection with storm experience. That is more than the two million car accident deaths over that same period, the study said.</p>
<p>Hsiang said he and Young saw a <strong>trend</strong> of increasing hurricane-connected deaths, mostly as a result of population growth. Beginning in 2000, there was a big jump in the total volume of storms hitting large populations, he said.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong><strong> </strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>contribute </strong><em>– v. </em>to have a part in bringing about something</p>
<p><strong>mortality</strong> <em>– n. </em>the death of large numbers (as of people or animals)</p>
<p><strong>previously</strong> <em>– adv. </em>going before in time or order</p>
<p><strong>associate </strong><em>– v. </em>to link or connect</p>
<p><strong>trickle </strong><em>– n. </em><strong> </strong>to move or go one by one or little by little</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Tech Tip: Instagram’s New Tools to Protect Young Users (2024/10/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/tech-tip-instagram-s-new-tools-to-protect-young-users.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Meta's Instagram service recently introduced some built-in tools designed to protect young users. The changes also give parents more control over their children's accounts to improve safety and limit the amount of time spent on the social networking <strong>app</strong>.</p>
<p>Instagram <a class="wsw__a" href="https://about.fb.com/news/2024/09/instagram-teen-accounts/#:~:text=Teens%20under%2016%20will%20need%20their%20parent's%20permission%20to%20use,to%20turn%20on%20parental%20supervision.">says</a> the new tools aim to “<strong>reassure</strong> parents that teens are having safe experiences.” The main change was the establishment of Teen Accounts, which Meta says was developed “with parents and teens in mind.”</p>
<p>The Associated Press offers the following tips as a guide for parents to get the most out of the new tools.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file photo, students use their cellphones as they leave for the day the Ramon C. Cortines School of Visual and Performing Arts High School in downtown Los Angeles, Aug. 13, 2024. (AP Photo/Damian Dovarganes, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/170a62cc-b678-4c17-bb1e-a11dbfe92812_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this file photo, students use their cellphones as they leave for the day the Ramon C. Cortines School of Visual and Performing Arts High School in downtown Los Angeles, Aug. 13, 2024. (AP Photo/Damian Dovarganes, File)</span></div>
<p><strong>What limits will young users have? </strong></p>
<p>Instagram already restricts anyone under 13 from signing up for the service. Now, teen accounts will <strong>automatically</strong> be set to private. That means they will have to accept or reject requests from new followers. Other users will not be able to see a teen user's posts and videos or communicate with the account.</p>
<p>Teens will also face messaging restrictions. They can only receive direct messages from people they are following or who follow them. But they can still send messages to other accounts.</p>
<p>Teen Accounts will also restrict certain kinds of material, or content. This will include sensitive subjects such as videos of people fighting or content that pushes methods to improve appearance. In addition, Instagram's anti-bullying tools will be set to the highest level to prevent offensive words and phrases in comments and direct message requests.</p>
<p>To restrict usage time, teens will get a message to stop using the app after it has been open for more than an hour. This message can be ignored, however.</p>
<p><strong>Can the new limits be changed?</strong></p>
<p>The new limits will be turned on automatically for all teens. But 16 and 17-year-olds will have the ability to turn them off. Children under 16 will need parental permission to do so.</p>
<p>Teens might also seek to lie about their age to get around the restrictions. But Meta has made it more difficult for them to do so. Young users are required to confirm their ages by uploading an identification card or by sending a short video of themselves.</p>
<p>Instagram says it will also begin testing artificial intelligence (AI) software early next year that will aim to prevent false birth dates from being accepted.</p>
<p><strong>New controls for parents </strong></p>
<p>If a parent does not think the limits for their child are strong enough, they can add more protective controls. For example, a parent has the ability to see who their teen has traded messages with within the past seven days.</p>
<p>The new tools also provide controls for parents to set daily limits for Instagram use. A parent can also block a teen from using Instagram during specific times of the day and follow subjects they are seeing.</p>
<p><strong>How to set up parental controls</strong></p>
<p>To set up additional controls, a parent first needs to set up family <strong>supervision</strong> on his or her account. On the mobile app, this can be done by going into settings and scrolling to find the family center to activate the tools.</p>
<p>Next, the Teen Account will have to invite a parent. This will be in the form of a link the teen can send by text message to the parent. After accepting the invite, the teen user has 48 hours to confirm the parent's response.</p>
<p><strong>Can I use the teen settings right away?</strong></p>
<p>The restrictive tools will be automatically activated for anyone under 18 who now signs up for Instagram in the U.S., Britain, Canada and Australia. For existing accounts, the restrictions will be put in place by mid-November.</p>
<p>The protections will be available for teens in the European Union's 27 countries beginning later this year. And the rest of the world will get Teen Accounts for Instagram in January. Meta says it will also bring the changes to other services like Facebook next year.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English, with additional information from Meta.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>app </strong><em>– n. </em>a small computer program that can be put onto a mobile phone or other electronic device</p>
<p><strong>reassure </strong><em>– v. </em>to say something to stop someone from worrying</p>
<p><strong>automatic </strong><em>– adj.</em><em> </em>working by itself with little human control</p>
<p><strong>supervise </strong><em>– v. </em>to watch a person or activity to make sure things are being done correctly, safely, etc.</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Win Nobel in Chemistry for Predicting, Designing Proteins (2024/10/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/scientists-win-nobel-in-chemistry-for-predicting-designing-proteins.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">09 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Three scientists who developed methods to predict the structure of proteins and build new ones have won the Nobel Prize in Chemistry.</p>
<p>The winners were American David Baker, a professor at the University of Washington; Briton Demis Hassabis, head of Google's DeepMind research laboratory in London; and American John Jumper, a top researcher at DeepMind. The lab centers on artificial intelligence (AI) methods.</p>
<p>Protein is one of the most important substances to life on Earth. Baker succeeded in building new kinds of proteins. Hassabis and Jumper solved a problem that had existed for 50 years. They were finally able to use AI to predict the structure of proteins.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This combo of pictures show American biochemist David Baker, from left, American researcher John Jumper and Demis Hassabis, CEO of DeepMind Technologies, the AI division behind Gemini. (UW Medicine/Google DeepMind via AP/AP Photo/Jeff Chiu)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e4fa581a-667d-405e-a799-0eb7806b00c9_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This combo of pictures show American biochemist David Baker, from left, American researcher John Jumper and Demis Hassabis, CEO of DeepMind Technologies, the AI division behind Gemini. (UW Medicine/Google DeepMind via AP/AP Photo/Jeff Chiu)</span></div>
<p>The Nobel Committee for Chemistry said the discoveries “hold enormous potential.”</p>
<p>For example, committee members said the ability to build new proteins could lead to the discovery of new drugs and vaccines. It could also help scientists develop extremely small materials, called nanomaterials, and small sensors.</p>
<p>Heiner Linke is Chair of the Nobel Committee for Chemistry. He said the award honored research that made connections for the first time between amino acid sequences and protein structures.</p>
<p>“That was actually a grand challenge in chemistry, and in particular biochemistry” for many years, Linke said.</p>
<p><strong>Designing and predicting proteins</strong></p>
<p>Baker first designed a new protein in 2003. Since then, his research group has produced many different proteins. “It seems that you can almost construct any type of protein now with this technology,” said Professor Johan Aqvist of the Nobel committee.</p>
<p>The committee said Hassabis and Jumper created an AI model called AlphaFold2. It has been able to predict the structure of nearly all 200 million proteins researchers have identified.</p>
<p>Linke said, “Proteins are the molecules that enable life. Proteins are building blocks that form bones, skin, hair and tissue.” He added, “To understand how life works, we first need to understand the shape of proteins.”</p>
<p>Linke said that in 2020, Hassabis and Jumper were able to use AI methods to finally “<strong>crack the code</strong>.” That made it possible to predict the complex structure of “any known protein in nature.”</p>
<p>There are many possible uses for the technology. Researchers should be able to use it to better understand how organisms develop resistance to antibiotics. They might also be able to create images of chemical substances called enzymes that can break down plastic.</p>
<p>The committee said Baker had developed “computational tools” that enable scientists to design new proteins with new shapes and <strong>functions</strong>.</p>
<p>Baker noted that Hassabis and Jumper's work in AI had greatly helped his team.</p>
<p>“The <strong>breakthroughs</strong> made by Demis and John on protein structure prediction really highlighted to us the power that AI could have,” he said. “And that led us to <strong>apply</strong> these AI methods to protein design and that has greatly increased the power and <strong>accuracy</strong>.”</p>
<p>Baker was asked during a phone call with Nobel officials and reporters if he had a favorite protein. He said it would be difficult to choose. But he noted that one designed during the pandemic proved to be effective in protecting against the coronavirus.</p>
<p>“And I've been very excited about the idea of a <strong>nasal spray</strong>, of little designed proteins, that would protect against all possible pandemic viruses.” Baker said.</p>
<p>Hassabis is a leader in Britain's technology industry. He received a knighthood earlier this year for his work in AI. He helped establish DeepMind in 2010. Google later bought the lab.</p>
<p>DeepMind first gained wide attention by developing an AI system that was able to defeat the human world champion in the Chinese game of Go faster than expected.</p>
<p>This year's Nobel Prize in Chemistry is worth about $1 million. Half of the prize will go to Baker. Hassabis and Jumper will share the other half.</p>
<p>Award ceremonies for the 2024 Nobel Prize winners will be held on December 10.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Daniel Niemann and Mike Corder reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>to crack the code </strong>–idiom to discover something that is hidden or very difficult to know</p>
<p><strong>function</strong> <em>–n. </em>the job that something does</p>
<p><strong>breakthrough</strong> <em>–n.</em> a sudden jump in knowledge or ability</p>
<p><strong>apply </strong>–v. to use a method or practice to carry out a task or operation</p>
<p><strong>accuracy </strong>–n. exactly showing the true value or condition of something</p>
<p><strong>nasal spray </strong>–n. a liquid that is sprayed into the nose to ease discomfort or support health</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>In Changing Climate, Scientists Develop Stronger Seeds for India (2024/10/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/in-changing-climate-scientists-develop-stronger-seeds-for-india.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Unpredictable rains and increasing heat are making life more difficult for the people of Rayanpet, a village in southern India. The conditions are also damaging the rice crops grown there.</p>
<p>P. Ravinder Reddy, a former soldier, started farming on his family's land 16 years ago. He said, "We used to know when it would rain and for how long.”</p>
<p>That meant they used to know when to plant. Now, he said, it is not so predictable. Sometimes there is too much rain. Sometimes there is no rain at all.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="P. Ravinder Reddy, a farmer, applies fungicide to peanut seeds before sowing in Rayanpet village of Telangana state, India, Wednesday, Sept. 25, 2024. (AP Photo/Mahesh Kumar A.)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f1ae7734-ed23-441a-92cd-cab78bc29044_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">P. Ravinder Reddy, a farmer, applies fungicide to peanut seeds before sowing in Rayanpet village of Telangana state, India, Wednesday, Sept. 25, 2024. (AP Photo/Mahesh Kumar A.)</span></div>
<p>Agricultural research organizations in India have been working for years to engineer rice seeds that can survive in a changing climate. Reddy has been experimenting with new kinds of rice for the past five years. The new rice plants are producing more grain with less water. They are also more disease resistant.</p>
<p>Reddy says he has planted them across part of his 10-hectare field. He still grows some of the older kinds because there is a demand for them. But he said, “I think in a few years, we will use only these <strong>tougher</strong> seeds."</p>
<p>India is one of the world's largest producers and <strong>consumers</strong> of wheat and rice. Research organizations in that country and around the world have worked for years to produce seeds that are better able to handle <strong>drought</strong>, unseasonal rains, plant diseases and more.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, a United Nations report said more than 700 million people suffered from hunger last year. More than one-third of the worldwide population does not have the money to buy healthy foods.</p>
<p><strong>Defending against climate shocks</strong></p>
<p>India has nearly 120 million farmers. Most have less than two hectares of land. Unpredictable rainfall, rising temperatures and increased <strong>pest </strong>problems all threaten their ability to grow food.</p>
<p>Experts say the dangers to rice include increasing salt content in groundwater, heavy rainfall over short periods, long periods of drought and increasing nighttime temperatures.</p>
<p>Some farmers are turning to methods of natural farming to deal with climate change. But that can mean reduced <strong>yields</strong>. India's federal government is also urging the use of climate-<strong>resilient </strong>seeds that result in better yields.</p>
<p><strong>Government research support</strong></p>
<p>Ashok Kumar Singh is former director of New Delhi-based Indian Agriculture Research Institute. He has overseen the creation of many successful rice varieties that withstand pests and plant diseases. His organization has helped release more than 2,000 climate-resilient kinds of seed in the last 10 years.</p>
<p>"We really need these seeds to deal with these multiple <strong>issues </strong>created by global warming," Singh said.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi released 109 climate-resilient seeds for several different crops. India's federal government has announced plans to make sure at least 25 percent of rice-growing fields in the country will be planted with climate-resilient seeds in the coming winter crop season.</p>
<p>In Rayanpet village, Reddy is preparing to plant rice seeds for the winter season in a few weeks.</p>
<p>"It is good to keep trying new seeds, as after some time all of them will have some issue or the other," Reddy said. “If the government can also make sure we get good prices for our crops after harvest, that would help farmers like us a great deal.”</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Sibi Aras </em><em>reported this story for the </em><em>Associated Press</em><em>.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>tough</strong> – <em>adj</em>. strong and not easily broken or damaged</p>
<p><strong>consumer</strong> – <em>n</em>. a person who buys goods and services</p>
<p><strong>drought</strong> – <em>n</em>. a long period of time during which there is very little or no rain</p>
<p><strong>pest </strong>– <em>n</em>. an animal or insect that causes problems for people</p>
<p><strong>yield</strong> – <em>n. </em>the amount of something that is produced by a plant, farm, or the like</p>
<p><strong>issue –<em> </em></strong><em>n</em>. problem or concern</p>
<p>especially by damaging crops</p>
<p><strong>resilient </strong>– <em>adj</em>. able to become strong, healthy, or successful again after something bad happens</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Developers of AI Methods Win Nobel Prize in Physics (2024/10/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/developers-of-ai-methods-win-nobel-prize-in-physics.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">08 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Two early developers of artificial intelligence (AI) have won this year's Nobel Prize in Physics.</p>
<p>American John Hopfield is with Princeton University in New Jersey. Geoffrey Hinton is a citizen of Canada and Britain who works at the University of Toronto.</p>
<p>The Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences honored them for helping “to develop methods that are the foundation of today's powerful machine learning.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="The 2024 Nobel Prize winners in Physics, professor John Hopfield, left, of Princeton University, and professor Geoffrey Hinton, of the University of Toronto, Tuesday, Oct. 8, 2024. (Princeton University via AP and Noah Berger/AP Photo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/71730729-6d5b-4062-aebb-7eccfce76f73_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">The 2024 Nobel Prize winners in Physics, professor John Hopfield, left, of Princeton University, and professor Geoffrey Hinton, of the University of Toronto, Tuesday, Oct. 8, 2024. (Princeton University via AP and Noah Berger/AP Photo)</span></div>
<p>The 76-year-old Hinton is known as the Godfather of artificial intelligence for his part in developing machine learning. However, he also has warned that AI has created threats to humanity.</p>
<p>Ellen Moons is a member of the Nobel committee at the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences. Moons said the two scientists “used fundamental <strong>concepts</strong> from <strong>statistical</strong> physics to design artificial <strong>neural</strong> networks that <strong>function</strong> as <strong>associative memories</strong> and find <strong>patterns</strong> in large data sets.”</p>
<p>Moons added that their research has been used to make progress in physics but has also become part of people's daily lives. Technologies like facial recognition and language <strong>translation</strong> are used every day.</p>
<p>Hinton predicted that AI would have a “huge influence” on civilization and will bring improvements to productivity and health care. He told reporters and Royal Academy officials that, “It would be comparable to the Industrial Revolution.”</p>
<p>The Industrial Revolution was a period of intensive development of machines and manufacturing that started more than 250 years ago in Britain.</p>
<p>Hinton said, “Instead of exceeding people in physical strength, it's going to exceed people in intellectual ability.” But Hinton also expressed concern about the possible bad results of AI, especially noting, in his words, “the threat of these things getting out of control.”</p>
<p>The Nobel committee also recognized the possible damage the discoveries that it was honoring could cause. Moons said AI's “development has also raised concerns about our future. Collectively, humans carry the responsibility for using this new technology in a safe and ethical way for the greatest benefit of humankind.”</p>
<p><strong>What they did</strong></p>
<p>In the 1980s, Hinton helped to develop a method known as backpropagation, which is used to “train” computers to learn.</p>
<p>Later, he headed a team at the University of Toronto that won the ImageNet computer competition in 2012 for designing a “neural network.”</p>
<p>Hinton and AI scientists Yoshua Bengio and Yann LeCun won the Turing Award in 2019. It is the top award in computer science. That year, Hinton told the Associated Press about the reaction he and his fellow researchers received over their work.</p>
<p>“They thought we were very misguided and what we were doing was a very surprising thing for apparently intelligent people to waste their time on. My message to young researchers is, don't be put off if everyone tells you what you are doing is silly.”</p>
<p>Hopfield is now 91 years old. The Nobel committee said he “invented a network that uses a method for saving and recreating patterns.”</p>
<p>Hinton used Hopfield's network to create a new network using a different method known as the Boltzmann machine. The committee said this “machine” can learn to recognize elements in a particular kind of data.</p>
<p>“What fascinates me most is still this question of how mind comes from machine,” Hopfield said in a video posted online by The Franklin Institute after it awarded him a physics prize in 2019.</p>
<p>The Nobel Prize in Physics is valued at $1 million. Swedish inventor Alfred Nobel created the prizes to honor discoveries that help humanity. The first prizes were awarded in 1901.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, the prize in chemistry will be announced, on Thursday, the prize for literature, and Friday, the peace prize. And, the Nobel for economics will be announced on Monday.</p>
<p>The winners receive their prizes in ceremonies held on December 10.</p>
<p>I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>Daniel Niemann and Mike Corder reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>concept</strong> <em>–n.</em> a general idea</p>
<p><strong>statistical</strong> <em>–adj. </em>related to facts or information that is in the form of numbers</p>
<p><strong>associative</strong> <em>–adj. </em>of or relating to association, connection or linkage</p>
<p><strong>memory</strong> <em>–n. </em>the power or process of reproducing or recalling what has been learned and retained especially through associative mechanisms</p>
<p><strong>neural</strong> <em>–adj.</em> like a brain or nerve cells</p>
<p><strong>function </strong><em>–n.</em> the job or task that something does</p>
<p><strong>pattern </strong><em>–n.</em> images, objects or elements that are repeated in a recognizable way</p>
<p><strong>translation </strong><em>–n.</em> to take writing in one language and recreate its meaning in another language</p>
<p><strong>consequence </strong><em>–n.</em> the results of an action</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Do Students in American Schools Read Long Books Anymore? (2024/10/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/do-students-in-american-schools-read-long-books-anymore.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">08 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Teachers in many English classes across America are having students read fewer full-length books.</p>
<p>Recently, the Associated Press explored the issue in education.</p>
<p>It reports that students instead are given only short parts of books. Educators said this is because they believe current students have shorter attention <strong>spans </strong>than those of the past. The teachers might feel pressure to prepare students for state and nationwide examinations know as standardized tests. They also might believe that short pieces of writing will help students in the modern, digital world.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Chris Stanislawski, 14, of Garden City, N.Y., didn't finish any books in his 8th grade English class, in part because their google classroom had detailed summaries of each chapter of every book. (AP Photo/Brittainy Newman)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a578a476-7602-4a77-a64c-80bde33408cc_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Chris Stanislawski, 14, of Garden City, N.Y., didn't finish any books in his 8th grade English class, in part because their google classroom had detailed summaries of each chapter of every book. (AP Photo/Brittainy Newman)</span></div>
<p>The National Council of Teachers of English is a professional organization for teachers based in Champaign, Illinois. In 2022, the group released a statement about reading. “The time has come to decenter book reading and <strong>essay</strong>-writing as the <strong>pinnacles</strong> of English language arts education,” the group said.</p>
<p>Seth French helped write the statement. He said the idea was not to remove books but to teach media <strong>literacy</strong> and have students read things in which they are interested. French taught an English class before becoming a dean at Bentonville High School in the state of Arkansas. He had students read plays, poetry and articles but only one book as a class.</p>
<p>He said, “A lot of our students are not interested in some of these texts that they didn't have a choice in.”</p>
<p>Not everyone thinks English reading should involve only short, digital pieces of writing.</p>
<p>Maryanne Wolf studies the human brain at UCLA in Southern California. Wolf said deep reading is important to strengthen connections in the brain tied to critical thinking skills, background knowledge and empathy.</p>
<p>She said educators must give students a chance to learn through what she described as “<strong>immersion</strong> into the lives and thoughts of others.”</p>
<p><strong>Less reading</strong></p>
<p>There is not a lot of information on how many books American students are required to read in school. But in general, students are reading less.</p>
<p>Federal data from last year shows 14 percent of young people said they read for fun every day. In 2012, that percentage was 27 percent.</p>
<p>Some teachers say reduced reading has its roots in the COVID-19 crisis.</p>
<p>Kristy Acevedo teaches English at a vocational high school in New Bedford, Massachusetts.</p>
<p>“There was a <strong>trend</strong>, it happened when COVID hit, to stop reading full-length novels because students were in <strong>trauma</strong>; we were in a pandemic. The problem is we haven't quite come back from that,” she said.</p>
<p>Other teachers blame standardized testing and the influence of education technology.</p>
<p>Some students struggle to read. Only one third of fourth and eighth graders reached reading <strong>proficiency</strong> in the 2022 National Assessment of Educational Progress.</p>
<p>Leah van Belle is the director of the non-profit literacy coalition 313Reads in Detroit, Michigan. Van Belle said, when her son read the book <em>Peter Pan</em> in elementary school, it was too difficult for most children. She said her son's school does not have a library.</p>
<p>Still, she said it makes sense for English classes to use shorter reading material.</p>
<p>“As an adult, if I want to learn about a <strong>topic</strong> and research it, be it personal or professional, I'm using interactive digital text to do that,” she said.</p>
<p><strong>Too many things to do</strong></p>
<p>Even in schools with many resources, time is always in short supply.</p>
<p>Terri White teaches at South Windsor High School in Connecticut. White no longer assigns the book <em>To Kill a Mockingbird</em> to her class.</p>
<p>She assigns about one third of the book and provides a synopsis, or a very short version, of the rest. White says the reason is that the class has to move quickly so she can teach all the required material.</p>
<p>White also assigns less homework because students have sports and other activities. She said she wanted her class to be “more about helping student become stronger and more critical readers, writers and thinkers, while taking their social-emotional well-being into account.”</p>
<p>The synopses method alone, however, can harm student critical thinking skills says Alden Jones, a literature professor at Emerson College in Boston, Massachusetts.</p>
<p>Jones assigns fewer books than before but gives more small tests to make sure students are reading.</p>
<p>“We don't value the thinking time that we used to have. It's all time we could be on our phone accomplishing tasks,” she said.</p>
<p>Will Higgins is an English teacher at Dartmouth High School in Massachusetts. Higgins said he still believes in teaching the <strong>classics</strong>. But he said students do not have enough time, so teachers have cut back on the number of books they teach.</p>
<p>“We haven't given up on <em>Jane Eyre</em> and <em>Pride and Prejudice</em>. We haven't given up on <em>Hamlet </em>or <em>The Great Gatsby</em>,” he said. But Higgins admitted giving up on assigning a long book like <em>A Tale of Two Cities</em> by Charles Dickens.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr. And I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Sharon Lurye reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>assign </strong>–v. to give someone a task to do</p>
<p><strong>span </strong><em>–n. </em>a length of something such as a time period or the extent of a bridge</p>
<p><strong>standardized test</strong><em> –n.</em> a test that is the same for all people taking it which is used to measure a person's abilities in a subject</p>
<p><strong>essay</strong> –n. a short piece of writing about one topic</p>
<p><strong>pinnacle </strong>–n. the highest point of something</p>
<p><strong>literacy </strong>–n. the ability to read</p>
<p><strong>trend </strong>–n. the direction in which a happening is going</p>
<p><strong>trauma </strong>–n. a difficult or painful experience</p>
<p><strong>topic </strong>–n. subject</p>
<p><strong>immersion </strong>–n. absorbing involvement</p>
<p><strong>proficiency</strong> –n. the ability to do something skillfully and well</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Two Americans Win Nobel Prize in Medicine for microRNA Discovery (2024/10/8)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/two-americans-win-nobel-prize-in-medicine-for-microrna-discovery.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">07 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Two Americans have won the 2024 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine for their discovery of genetic material called microRNA.</p>
<p>Victor Ambros is a professor at the University of Massachusetts and Gary Ruvkun is a Harvard University professor.</p>
<p>The Nobel Assembly at the Karolinska Institute, a group of 50 professors, decided to award the two for identifying genetic molecules that help control how genes work.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="This photo combo shows 2024 Nobel Prize winners in physiology or medicine Gary Ruvkun, American molecular biologist, left, and Victor Ambros,, Oct. 7, 2024, in Newton, Mass. (AP Photo/Steven Senne)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/16d98d78-382d-43b7-bc77-95d7c262d3df_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">This photo combo shows 2024 Nobel Prize winners in physiology or medicine Gary Ruvkun, American molecular biologist, left, and Victor Ambros,, Oct. 7, 2024, in Newton, Mass. (AP Photo/Steven Senne)</span></div>
<p>The Nobel Assembly said the discovery is “proving to be <strong>fundamentally</strong> important for how organisms develop and <strong>function</strong>.”</p>
<p>In explaining the importance of the work, the group said it “revealed a completely new <strong>principle</strong> of gene regulation that turned out to be <strong>essential</strong> for multicellular organisms, including humans.”</p>
<p><strong>RNA and microRNA</strong></p>
<p>RNA takes genetic information from DNA through a process called transcription. RNA then becomes involved in protein production or other activities within the cell.</p>
<p>Ambros and Ruvkun found that microRNA, or very short chains of molecules, are needed for normal genetic development. The committee said changes in the way that microRNA functions can lead to major genetic changes, or mutations, over time. Nobel's website said the changes can lead to diseases such as cancer, diabetes and autoimmune diseases.</p>
<p>Ambros carried out research that helped lead to the discovery at Harvard University. Ruvkun researched at Massachusetts General Hospital and Harvard Medical School.</p>
<p><strong>Early research</strong></p>
<p>At first, Ambros and Ruvkun were interested in genes that control when genetic developments take place. These developments ensure that different kinds of cells develop at the right time.</p>
<p>The scientists studied the genetic material of a one-millimeter-long worm C. elegans which is commonly used for research. They studied two mutant strains of worms that displayed defects in the timing of activation of genetic programs during development. They wanted to identify the mutated genes in the worms and what the genes did.</p>
<p>After some time, they finally found that microRNA controlled the mutation. They also believe that this mutation has permitted organisms to change, or evolve, over hundreds of millions of years.</p>
<p>Dr. Claire Fletcher is a cancer researcher with Imperial College London. Fletcher said the discovery of microRNA has opened new ways for treating cancer.</p>
<p>Fletcher said that microRNA provides genetic instructions that tell cells to make new proteins. “MicroRNA <strong>alters</strong> how genes in the cell work,” said Fletcher, who is not associated with the Nobel prize.</p>
<p>“We can take a microRNA that we know alters the activity of that gene and we can deliver that particular microRNA to cancer cells to stop that mutated gene from having its effect,” Fletcher added.</p>
<p>Last year's Nobel Prize in Medicine or Physiology was also awarded for developments related to RNA. Hungarian-American Katalin Karikó and American Drew Weissman were recognized for discoveries that enabled messenger RNA, or mRNA, vaccines for COVID-19.</p>
<p>The Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine is valued at about $1 million. Swedish inventor Alfred Nobel established the Nobel Prizes to recognize important discoveries that have aided humanity.</p>
<p>Thomas Perlmann is the Secretary-General of the Nobel Committee. He said it took a long time before Ruvkun came to the phone, but he was “happy, when he understood what it was all about.”</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Daniel Niemann, Mike Corder and Maria Cheng reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>fundamentally </strong><em>–adv.</em> forming the most basic or important part of something</p>
<p><strong>function</strong> <em>–n. </em>the job that something does</p>
<p><strong>principle</strong> <em>–n. </em>a fact or law of nature that explains how something works</p>
<p><strong>essential </strong><em>–adj.</em> very important</p>
<p><strong>alter </strong><em>–v.</em> to change</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Severe Obesity Increases in US (2024/10/8)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/severe-obesity-increases-in-us.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">07 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Body weight continues to be a big public health issue in the United States. New government research suggests that the condition of having far too much fat stored in the body – severe obesity – has increased greatly over the past ten years.</p>
<p>The U.S. obesity rate is about 40 percent, says a 2021-2023 study of about 6,000 people. Almost one in 10 of those questioned reported severe obesity, the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) found. Women were nearly two times as likely as men to report severe obesity.</p>
<p>The overall obesity rate appeared to decrease in comparison to the 2017-2020 survey. But the change was not considered <strong>statistically </strong>meaningful. In other words, the numbers are small enough that there is a mathematical chance the rates did not truly drop.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A subject's waist is measured during an obesity prevention study in Chicago on Jan. 20, 2010. (AP Photo/M. Spencer Green, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/3b396f05-d39b-4e93-9838-ae3bce9e26da_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A subject's waist is measured during an obesity prevention study in Chicago on Jan. 20, 2010. (AP Photo/M. Spencer Green, File)</span></div>
<p>Dr. Samuel Emmerich is the CDC public health officer who led the latest study. He said it is too soon to know whether new treatments for obesity, including weight-loss drugs such as Wegovy and Zepbound, can help ease the disease.</p>
<p>“We simply can't see down to that detailed level to <strong>prescription</strong> medication use and compare that to changes in obesity <strong>prevalence</strong>,” Emmerich said. He added, “Hopefully that is something we can see in the future.”</p>
<p>The results show that the overall obesity rate in the U.S. has not changed much in ten years. The rate of severe obesity climbed from almost eight percent in the 2013-2014 study to almost 10 percent in the most recent one.</p>
<p>Before that, obesity had increased quickly in the U.S. since the 1990s, federal studies showed.</p>
<p>Measures of obesity and severe obesity are based on the body mass index (BMI), a computation involving height and weight. People with a BMI of 30 are considered obese. Those with a BMI of 40 or higher have severe obesity.</p>
<p>Solveig Cunningham is an Emory University global health professor who specializes in obesity.</p>
<p>Cunningham said, “Seeing increases in severe obesity is even more alarming because that's the level of obesity that's most highly associated with some of the highest levels of <strong>cardiovascular </strong>disease and <strong>diabetes</strong> and lower quality of life.”</p>
<p>Cunningham, who was not involved in the new study, said it is not clear why rates of severe obesity are going up. Cunningham also said it is not clear why severe obesity rates were higher among women.</p>
<p>Reasons could include the effects of hormones, the effects of childbearing or other causes that require further study, she said.</p>
<p>The new study also found that obesity rates varied by education. Almost 32 percent of people with a bachelor's degree or higher reported having obesity. In comparison, about 45 percent of those with some college or less had obesity.</p>
<p>The new report follows the release earlier this month of data from U.S. states and territories that showed that in 2023, the rate of obesity differed widely by place.</p>
<p>The highest obesity levels were in West Virginia. Around 41 percent of adults in the state are obese.</p>
<p>The lowest levels were in Washington, D.C., with less than 24 percent of adults being obese.</p>
<p>Obesity rates were highest in the Midwest and the South.</p>
<p>All U.S. states and territories had obesity rates higher than 20 percent. In 23 states, more than 1 in 3 adults had obesity, the data showed. Before 2013, no state had a rate that high, said Dr. Alyson Goodman, who leads a CDC team focused on population health.</p>
<p>Color-coded maps show the obesity rates across the U.S.</p>
<p>“Sometimes, when you look at all that red, it's really discouraging,” Goodman said.</p>
<p>But, she added, recent attention on understanding obesity as a metabolic disease and new drug treatments give her hope.</p>
<p>Preventing obesity is most important, Cunningham said, starting in early childhood. And for people already dealing with obesity, preventing additional weight gain should be the goal.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell. And I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>Jonel Aleccia reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>statistically </strong><em>– adv. </em>of or relating to the principles of statistics</p>
<p><strong>prescription</strong> <em>– n.</em> a written direction for a therapeutic or corrective agent</p>
<p><strong>prevalence </strong><em>– n.</em> the percentage of a population that is affected with a particular disease at a given time</p>
<p><strong>cardiovascular<em> </em></strong><em>– adj.</em> of, relating to, or involving the heart and blood vessels</p>
<p><strong>diabetes </strong><em>– n. </em>a variable disorder of carbohydrate metabolism</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Japanese Theater Shares Cultural Similarities in Britain (2024/10/8)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/japanese-theater-shares-cultural-similarities-in-britain.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">07 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A playhouse in London, Britain and a theater from Osaka, Japan, are working together to prove cultural differences between the two countries are only on the surface.</p>
<p>London's Charing Cross Theatre and Osaka's Umeda Arts Theater first worked together on a performance in 2019. After a break caused by the pandemic, they are jointly <strong>staging</strong> two plays in London this month. The plays are rooted in Japanese culture and deal with secretive relationships, but the concerns are universal.</p>
<p>Actor Susan Momoko Hingley spoke of Japan's export of culture, including films and television series. She told the Reuters news agency, "It's really about getting great stories from all sorts of different cultures to Britain and to the West."</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Actors Susan Momoko Hingley and Mark Takeshi Ota perform in the production of " arts="" britain="" handout="" in="" london="" mark="" one="" reuters="" senior="" september="" small="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/97f2e708-09d8-4469-b08f-9ba0d885327d_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg" step="" theater="" via=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Actors Susan Momoko Hingley and Mark Takeshi Ota perform in the production of "One Small Step" in London, Britain, September 27, 2024. (Umeda Arts Theater/ Mark Senior/Handout via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>She stars in <em>One Small Step,</em> written by Takuya Kato. It tells the story of a couple working for a company that is colonizing the moon. The plot becomes more complex with the news the woman is pregnant. It raises concerns <strong>audiences</strong> almost anywhere can relate to about motherhood, career and inequality between men and women.</p>
<p><strong>All about equality</strong></p>
<p>Kato, who is also the play's director, said, "In terms of equity, I think nowadays many people often say that we are <strong>striving</strong> for fairness within companies, within societies and between individuals."</p>
<p>"But I think it is something that we understand with our heads but might not necessarily <strong>grasp</strong> it with our hearts,” he added.</p>
<p>The London production, Kato said, gave new life to his play "at the <strong>intersection</strong> of two different cultures." He noted that for Japanese creative industries, the market within Japan may not be enough to support them. Working with companies in other countries helps the theater companies and expands knowledge of the culture.</p>
<p>"If we don't grow the part of coproductions, which we have traditionally struggled with, it would be difficult to survive as both an industry and culture in the future," he said.</p>
<p><strong>Second play to come</strong></p>
<p>Following <em>One Small Step</em>, which runs until October 9, Charing Cross Theatre will host <em>Tattooer </em>later in the month. The play, by another Japanese writer, Takuya Kaneshima, tells the story of a tattoo artist.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Marie-Louise Gumuchian and Barbara Lewis </em><em>reported this story for Reuters.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>stage</strong> – <em>v</em>. to produce (a play, performance, etc.) on a stage</p>
<p><strong>audience</strong> – <em>n.</em> the people who watch, read, or listen to something</p>
<p><strong>strive</strong> – <em>v.</em> to try very hard to do or achieve something</p>
<p><strong>grasp</strong> – <em>v.</em> to understand (something that is complicated or difficult)</p>
<p><strong>intersection</strong> –<em> n.</em> the place or point where two or more things come together</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Replanting Same Trees Cannot Replace Burned Forests (2024/10/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/study-replanting-same-trees-cannot-replace-burned-forests.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Camille Stevens-Rumann recently sat on the ground and measured small trees to see how much they had grown in seven months.</p>
<p>She found they had grown five to 10 centimeters. Her team had planted several different kinds of trees, known as evergreens, two years ago in an area of the Rocky Mountains in Colorado, which had burned in a fire in 2020.</p>
<p>Stevens-Rumann and other researchers want to learn the relationship between tree growth and <strong>elevation</strong>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A Colorado Forest Restoration Institute researcher at Colorado State University touches a test seedling in June 2024, in Bellvue, Colorado. (AP Photo/Brittany Peterson)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4af66e2b-aa66-446f-a0f3-1db899255923_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A Colorado Forest Restoration Institute researcher at Colorado State University touches a test seedling in June 2024, in Bellvue, Colorado. (AP Photo/Brittany Peterson)</span></div>
<p>Researchers say there are not enough small trees or seeds from living trees to replace burned trees. Even if there were enough, they say the U.S. does not have the workers to plant and care for them.</p>
<p>The Forest Service said the biggest delays they meet while replanting on public land are preparing environmental and cultural studies and preparing burned areas, so they are safe to plant. That can take years.</p>
<p>Stevens-Rumann said, "We're in a place of such <strong>drastic</strong> climate change that we are not talking about whether or not some of these places will be a different kind of forest, but whether or not they will be forests at all."</p>
<p><strong>Hotter fires</strong></p>
<p>In the past, the U.S. was able to replant burned forests. But the researchers say larger, more intense fires are destroying trees that normally provide seeds. They say the fires leave burn <strong>scars</strong> so large trees cannot naturally regrow.</p>
<p>Solomon Z. Dobrowski is a University of Montana forest management expert. He said more areas in the West need replanting after fires than can be replanted. He said at least 1.5 million hectares need to be replanted but officials are unable to do so. He said that number could <strong>triple</strong> by 2050.</p>
<p><strong>Targeted tree planting</strong></p>
<p>Matthew Hurteau is a forest ecologist at the University of New Mexico. He studied the way scarred forests had been replanted after a fire in 2011 at Los Conchas. That fire destroyed huge areas of ponderosa pine trees. Hurteau found most of the seedlings, or very young trees, had died from earlier replanting.</p>
<p>As a result, he planted seedlings of different <strong>species</strong> at several elevations and on hillsides facing different directions. Now he is watching carefully for changes in the soil and water.</p>
<p>Researchers say seedling survival is less likely at lower elevations. It is hotter, drier and more open there. Replanting the same trees in the same areas is likely to fail.</p>
<p>Jason Sieg is acting supervisor of the Arapaho and Roosevelt National Forests &amp; Pawnee National Grassland. He said the Forest Service rules require planting the same species at the same elevations as before a fire. But, he said, it is clear the agency will "need to be <strong>flexible</strong> moving forward."</p>
<p>For now, that might mean replanting at different elevations or collecting seeds from another place. Over time, researchers say it could require planting trees that are not native to the area. The idea has been debated but is gaining support.</p>
<p>"I've seen people go from saying, 'Absolutely, we cannot move trees around' to, 'Well, let's maybe let's try it at least, and do a few experiments to see if this will work,'" said Stevens-Rumann.</p>
<p>Environmental groups are working on private land burned by the Cameron Peak fire. They are replanting ponderosa pines 150 meters higher than where they used to grow, said Megan Maiolo-Heath. Maiolo-Heath is a spokesperson for the Coalition for the Poudre River Watershed.</p>
<p>So far, 84 percent of trees planted there last year are still alive.</p>
<p><strong>Problems with replanting</strong></p>
<p>The Forest Service is modernizing how it grows young trees. It is also studying ways to grow more or work with private industry, states and groups like the New Mexico Reforestation Center.</p>
<p>Experts say trees might never return to some areas. But it is important that the U.S. does as much as possible in a thoughtful way.</p>
<p>"Trees live for hundreds of years so we need to be thinking about what's right as we plant trees today," Hurteau said.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Tammy Webber, Brittany Peterson and Camille Fassett reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>various</strong> – <em>adj</em>. used to refer to several different or many different things or people</p>
<p><strong>elevation </strong>– <em>n</em>.<strong> </strong>the height of a place in relation to the level of the sea<em> </em></p>
<p><strong>drastic</strong> – <em>adj</em>. extreme in effect or action; severe or serious</p>
<p><strong>triple</strong> – <em>v</em>. to become three times as great or as many</p>
<p><strong>species</strong> – <em>n</em>. a group of animals or plants that are similar and can produce young animals or plants</p>
<p><strong>scar</strong> – <em>n.</em> a mark on something showing where it has been damaged</p>
<p><strong>flexible</strong> – adj. able to change or to do different things</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>NASA Follows Asteroid Moving Closer to Earth from Sun’s Orbit (2024/10/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/nasa-follows-asteroid-moving-closer-to-earth-from-sun-s-orbit.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists have discovered a small <strong>asteroid</strong> that recently moved closer to Earth's orbit. The object was first observed August 7 by two astronomers from Spain's Complutense University of Madrid.</p>
<p>The asteroid, named 2024 PT5, is believed to be about 10 meters long. It usually orbits around the sun. But Earth's gravitational forces recently pulled the object closer to our planet.</p>
<p>Scientists sometimes call such objects “mini-moons.” This is because they behave similarly to the permanent moon orbiting Earth when they are captured by gravity. But they are much smaller and only temporarily stay in Earth's orbit.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This file image shows a supermoon with a partial lunar eclipse rises over Lake Michigan in Chicago, Tuesday, Sept. 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Kiichiro Sato, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e23bba79-51ea-4edd-8299-bfd781d42074_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This file image shows a supermoon with a partial lunar eclipse rises over Lake Michigan in Chicago, Tuesday, Sept. 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Kiichiro Sato, File)</span></div>
<p>The American space agency NASA said <a class="wsw__a" href="https://blogs.nasa.gov/planetarydefense/2024/10/02/nasa-to-track-asteroid-2024-pt5-on-next-close-pass-january-2025/">in a statement</a> that 2024 PT5 is “not quite a mini-moon” because it will never be fully captured by Earth's gravity. However, it described the asteroid as “an interesting object” the agency plans to follow, or track, with radar-equipped telescopes. NASA noted the traveling asteroid presented no danger to Earth.</p>
<p>NASA and its international partners continuously search the skies for what scientists call near-Earth objects. Such objects include asteroids and <strong>comets</strong> that come within 50 million kilometers of Earth's orbit.</p>
<p>The search system, called ATLAS, involves four different telescopes. Two of the telescopes are based in Hawaii. Another operates in Chile and the other sits in South Africa. NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://atlas.fallingstar.com/">explains</a> that ATLAS is designed to search the whole sky several times each night looking for moving objects.</p>
<p>2024 PT5 was identified by the telescope observing station in Sutherland, South Africa. The discovery was made by two astronomers from Complutense University of Madrid – Carlos de la Fuente Marcos and Raúl de la Fuente Marcos. They recently <a class="wsw__a" href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2515-5172/ad781f">described</a> the find in the publication <em>Research Notes of the</em> <em>American Astronomical Society</em>.</p>
<p>The Spanish astronomers said it appeared 2024 PT5 is part of a group of near-Earth objects belonging to the Arjuna asteroid belt. The objects in this asteroid belt are believed to be “surrounding the path followed by the Earth-moon system,” they wrote.</p>
<p>Such objects are likely more common than we think, said Richard Binzel, an astronomer at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT). He was not involved in the latest research.</p>
<p>Binzel told The Associated Press, “This happens with some <strong>frequency</strong>, but we rarely see them because they're very small and very hard to <strong>detect</strong>.” But he noted that in recent years, progress in space observation technologies had made it possible to identify more of these moon-like objects.</p>
<p>Binzel added that currently, it is not known whether the asteroid broke off from a larger asteroid. He said the space rock might even be a piece of our moon “that got <strong>blasted</strong> out.” NASA said such an asteroid could have been created by our moon being struck by an asteroid a very long time ago.</p>
<p>One of the discovering scientists, Carlos de la Fuente Marcos, told the AP in an email that because of its size and brightness, 2024 PT5 can only be seen from Earth with special equipment.</p>
<p>NASA said teams at the agency's Center for Near Earth Object Studies are continually tracking the movements of 2024 PT5. The center expects the asteroid to remain at a distance about nine times farther away from Earth than the moon. Scientists say it will remain gravitationally linked to Earth until November 25.</p>
<p>NASA plans to use its large Goldstone Solar System Radar observer to follow the asteroid. The object is set to make another close pass of Earth in January 2025, when it should stay about five times the distance between Earth and the moon. 2024 PT5 is then expected to turn away from Earth “as it continues its orbit around the sun,” NASA said.</p>
<p>After that, the asteroid is not expected to pass close by Earth until 2055.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, NASA and </em><em>Research Notes of the</em> <em>American Astronomical Society.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>asteroid </strong><em>– n. </em>a rocky object that goes around the sun like a planet</p>
<p><strong>comet </strong><em>– n. </em>an object in space that leaves a bright line behind it in the sky</p>
<p><strong>frequency</strong><em> – n. </em>how often something happens</p>
<p><strong>detect </strong><em>– v. </em>to discover or identify something, especially something that is difficult to see hear, smell, etc.</p>
<p><strong>blast </strong><em>– n. </em>an explosion</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Japan’s Kojima Has History of Making Blue Jeans (2024/10/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/japan-s-kojima-has-history-of-making-blue-jeans.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In the Japanese town of Kojima, the main road is named Jeans Street.</p>
<p>This street is where people from around the world come to visit. The drink machines at the train station have images of <strong>jeans </strong>on them. The roads are painted blue, with the lines at the edges colored pink and white, the<strong> trademark </strong>of Kojima jeans' <strong>seams</strong>.</p>
<p>With about 40 jeans manufacturers and stores, including cafes, the area gets about 100,000 visitors a year, the Japan National Tourism Organization said.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Shigeru Uchida, a weaver at Momotaro Jeans, holds a wooden shuttle next to a vintage loom machine in Kojima, Okayama prefecture, Japan, on Sept. 4, 2024. (AP Photo/Ayaka McGill)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1748e24d-25f2-4b69-a9f0-d97080b3d834_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Shigeru Uchida, a weaver at Momotaro Jeans, holds a wooden shuttle next to a vintage loom machine in Kojima, Okayama prefecture, Japan, on Sept. 4, 2024. (AP Photo/Ayaka McGill)</span></div>
<p>Japanese jeans are often costly, dark and <strong>durable</strong>. Although a small part of the global jeans market, Japanese jean makers have developed a <strong>reputation</strong> for quality and attention to detail.</p>
<p>Kojima is where popular <strong>brands </strong>like Big John are made. The city now supplies international clothing brands, including Gucci.</p>
<p>Emma McClendon of St. John's University in New York said that the Japanese industry has not taken a mass marketing path. Instead, the jean industry pays careful attention to creating quality products that collectors might like.</p>
<p>In Kojima, Jeans Street is small and uncrowded. Each company in the area is small, hiring about 100 people.</p>
<p>What you will find are workers taking pride in “monozukuri,” or “making things.” The term suggests careful attention to detail.</p>
<p>This idea can be found throughout Japan, from carmakers to the local tofu store.</p>
<p>“More like making a <strong>kimono</strong>” is the way Yoshiharu Okamoto, a <strong>dyeing craftsman</strong> at Kojima-based manufacturer Momotaro Jeans, puts it.</p>
<p>His hands and nails are colored blue from putting threads of cotton into a big container of coloring called dye.</p>
<p>He knows by smell and feel the right state of the indigo coloring, which he compares to a living thing. He says it is a 365-days-a-year job, as the dye has to be checked and mixed every day.</p>
<p>“It's not that easy to get this special color,” Okamoto told the Associated Press recently. “It's my life.”</p>
<p>The dark color is so special it has earned the name “Japan blue" or “tokuno blue,” meaning “especially <strong>concentrated</strong> blue.”</p>
<p>Jeans made in Kojima are costly. The jeans can cost from $230 per pair to $1,400 or more.</p>
<p>Thomas Stege Bojer is founder of Denimhunters, an online site for people who like jeans and the cotton material they are made out of — denim.</p>
<p>He says Japanese brands use “raw denim” that ages well and lasts a long time. He pointed to the jeans as part of a movement known as “slow clothing."</p>
<p>The idea is to produce fewer, but higher quality pieces of clothing. The movement came as a reaction to low-cost, mass-produced clothes.</p>
<p>“We just make too many clothes...I think, and we need to slow down,” Bojer said from his home near Copenhagen, Denmark.</p>
<p>McClendon said the Japanese industry is “shifting the <strong>conversation</strong> around jeans to be about <strong>heritage</strong> elements, about educating consumers on historical details as a form of quality.”</p>
<p>Momotaro Jeans, for example, come with a lifetime guarantee. Tears and other problems get fixed at no cost, within reason.</p>
<p>Japan Blue Co., which runs Momotaro, a brand that began in 2006, said yearly sales totaled about $11 million for the latest year. About 40 percent of sales come from outside Japan.</p>
<p>Masataka Suzuki, president and chief operating officer at Japan Blue, said the area has a strong industrial history.</p>
<p>In the past, industry centered around sewing heavy materials, including military clothes and obi sashes for kimonos, as well as the cotton and indigo-dyeing native to the area.</p>
<p>The jeans are for life, Suzuki said. The jeans slowly change depending on how they are worn and how the wearer lives.</p>
<p>“We want to create a product that is a<strong> testament</strong> to a person's life,” he said.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Yuri Kageyama reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>jeans</strong><em> – n.</em> plural pants usually made of denim</p>
<p><strong>trademark</strong> <em>–n. </em>a characteristic or feature firmly associated with a person or thing</p>
<p><strong>seam </strong><em>–n.</em> the joining of two pieces (as of cloth or denim) by sewing usually near the edge</p>
<p><strong>durable</strong><em> –adj.</em> strong and able to last a long time</p>
<p><strong>reputation</strong> <em>–n.</em> the opinion that people have of a company or a person</p>
<p><strong>brand</strong> <em>–n.</em> a particular kind of product that has a name recognized by a lot of people</p>
<p><strong>kimono</strong> <em>–n.</em> a traditional Japanese clothing consisting of a long robe with wide sleeves</p>
<p><strong>dye</strong> <em>- v.</em> to impart a new and often permanent color</p>
<p><strong>craftsman</strong> <em>–n.</em> a person (especially a man) who is skilled in a craft</p>
<p><strong>concentrated</strong> <em>–adj.</em> very dense or thick</p>
<p><strong>conversation</strong> <em>–n.</em> a spoken exchange of opinions or ideas</p>
<p><strong>heritage</strong><em> –n.</em> tradition</p>
<p><strong>testament </strong>–<em>n.</em> a proof or tribute</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Is ‘Pie in the Sky’ Just a Dream? (2024/10/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/is-pie-in-the-sky-just-a-dream.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>On this program, we explore words and expressions in the English language. We give examples, notes on usage, and sometimes, we use them in short conversations.</p>
<p>Today we talk about the sweet dish at the end of a meal -- the dessert. One of the most famous kinds of dessert is pie. With a <strong>buttery crust</strong> and sweet fillings like apple, berries, or banana cream, a well-made pie is a dreamy food, indeed.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This photo shows citrus pumpkin meringue pie in Concord, New Hampshire, October 12, 2015. (AP Photo/Matthew Mead)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/F4273A16-11CB-4FC3-895A-1FCF29915CEC_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This photo shows citrus pumpkin meringue pie in Concord, New Hampshire, October 12, 2015. (AP Photo/Matthew Mead)</span></div>
<p>And that gives us the expression <u>pie in the sky</u>.</p>
<p>Imagine a perfect pie coming down to you from the sky. That is like a dream. And a <u>pie in the sky</u> is a dream, too.</p>
<p>Anything described as<u> pie-in-the-sky</u> is fun to daydream about but is very unlikely to happen. When we act in a <u>pie-in-the-sky</u> manner, we are being <strong>foolishly optimistic</strong>.</p>
<p>Any industry or area of life can have <u>pie-in-the-sky</u> ideas. So, you can use this expression for different situations.</p>
<p>In business, let's say a company has lost money for two straight years. But the company chief promised increased earnings in the coming year. Her claims, as they say, were simply <u>pie in the sky</u>. She had no business plan or data to support them.</p>
<p>An unpublished writer may have <u>pie-in-the-sky</u> dreams about her book being turned into a multi-million dollar film project.</p>
<p>A teacher may have <u>pie-in-the-sky</u> wishes that all his students complete their homework on time.</p>
<p><u>Pies in the sky</u> are empty promises or empty wishes. They are wishful thinking. They are as unlikely as tasty pies falling from the sky.</p>
<p>American English has another similar expression: <u>pipe dream</u>. The expression is also used to describe a plan, hope, or wish that is highly unlikely to happen.</p>
<p>However, this expression does not come from a tasty <strong>bakery</strong>. Word experts say it started in <strong>opium dens</strong>. Here, people would smoke opium in long pipes and then fall into a dreamlike state where nothing seemed real.</p>
<p>Now let's hear two friends using the expressions <u>pipe dream</u> and <u>pie in the sky</u>.</p>
<p><em>A: Hey, did you hear about Sarah? She's moving to Spain! </em></p>
<p><em>B: Really? Last week, she told me she was having trouble paying her <strong>rent</strong>. </em></p>
<p><em>A: Well, she told me this morning that she's moving to Madrid to open a bakery. </em></p>
<p><em>B: Sarah? Open a bakery? That sounds like a total <u>pie in the sky</u> to me. She can't even make toast.</em></p>
<p><em>A: You know, it sounded like <u>a pipe dream</u> when she told me. She didn't have details. Just a lot of dreamy talk. </em></p>
<p><em>B: Well, if she wants to turn her <u>pie-in-the-sky</u> bakery dream into a reality, I'd advise her to do one thing first – learn how to bake. </em></p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>. Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>butter </strong><em>-n.</em><strong> </strong>a solid yellow fatty food made by churning milk or cream :<strong> buttery </strong><em>-adj. </em>containing or spread with butter</p>
<p><strong>crust </strong><em>-n. </em>the pastry shell of a pie</p>
<p><strong>foolishly </strong><em>-adv. </em>having or showing a lack of good sense, judgment, or discretion</p>
<p><strong>optimistic </strong><em>-adj. </em>feeling or showing hope for the future</p>
<p><strong>bakery </strong><em>-n. </em>a place where bread, cakes, and pastry are made or sold</p>
<p><strong>opium </strong><em>-n. </em>a bitter brownish addictive narcotic drug that consists of the dried latex obtained from immature seed capsules of the opium poppy</p>
<p><strong>den </strong><em>-n. </em>a dirty run-down place in which people live or gather<em> </em></p>
<p><strong>rent </strong><em>-n. </em>money paid for the use of property <strong>: </strong>a periodic payment made by a tenant to the owner for the use of the owner's property</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Spanish Scientist Uses Bacteria to Repair 18th-century Artworks (2024/10/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/spanish-scientist-uses-bacteria-to-repair-18th-century-artworks.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Spanish scientist Pilar Bosch has found a way to use bacteria to repair 18th-century paintings.</p>
<p>Bosch, a microbiologist, tells Reuters she got the idea for the method while considering possibilities for a paper toward her doctoral degree. During this process, she discovered someone else's paper that suggested bacteria can be used to <strong>restore</strong> artworks.</p>
<p>At around the same time, Bosch learned that her mother was struggling to find a good method for restoring 18th-century paintings. The paintings, by Spanish artist Antonio Palomino, sat in Santos Juanes – one of the oldest <strong>churches</strong> in the city of Valencia.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Jose Luis Regidor, restorer and director of the project, joins Pilar Roig Picazo and Pilar Bosch Roig for a picture at the Church of Santos Juanes, in Valencia, Spain, September 16, 2024. (REUTERS/Eva Manez)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1920a006-bb87-41db-88e6-d6603f41dea3_cx10_cy16_cw89_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Jose Luis Regidor, restorer and director of the project, joins Pilar Roig Picazo and Pilar Bosch Roig for a picture at the Church of Santos Juanes, in Valencia, Spain, September 16, 2024. (REUTERS/Eva Manez)</span></div>
<p>Bosch said her mother, Pilar Roig, noted how difficult the restoration process at the church was. One reason was the <strong>glue </strong>used to remove the paintings from the walls in the 1960s. The substance was nearly impossible to remove completely.</p>
<p>"My mother had a very difficult problem to solve and I found a paper about bacteria used to clean frescoes in Italy," Bosch said. A fresco is a kind of painting that often appears across a large wall.</p>
<p>Bosch added she decided to write her doctoral paper on the same subject. That was more than ten years ago. Today, she gets to work with her mother on the church restoration. They are using the bacteria method to remove glue from artworks. The $4.46 million project is being financed by local organizations.</p>
<p>The process involves feeding small amounts of the glue – made from animal collagen – to the bacteria. After a time, the bacteria begins to naturally produce enzymes to break down the glue.</p>
<p>The mother-daughter team then mixes the bacteria with a natural algae-based substance, called a gel, and places it onto the paintings. They say that after about three hours, the gel mixture is removed, leaving the paintings glue-free.</p>
<p>Bosch's mother, now 75, noted that in the past, restorers of artworks had to use traditional cleaning methods that "took hours and damaged the painting." She noted that several other relatives in the family also work in art restoration. Bosch agreed, saying the work "certainly runs in the family."</p>
<p>Bosch has also used her bacteria removal process in other restoration projects in Italy and Spain. And, she is now training other scientists to use a different kind of bacteria to clear walls of painted <strong>graffiti</strong>.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Reuters reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>restore</strong> <em>– v. </em>to repair something old</p>
<p><strong>church </strong><em>– n. </em>a building where people go to worship God</p>
<p><strong>glue</strong> <em>– n. </em>a substance used to stick things together</p>
<p><strong>graffiti </strong><em>– n.</em> writings or art painted on walls and public places, usually illegally</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>A Municipal Report by O. Henry (2024/10/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/municipal-report-o-henry-american-stories.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Henry and</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>
<em>Our story today is called "A Municipal Report." It was written by O. Henry and first published in 1904. Here is Shep O'Neal with the story.</em></p>
<p>It was raining as I got off the train in Nashville, Tennessee -- a slow, gray rain. I was tired so I went straight to my hotel.</p>
<p>A big, heavy man was walking up and down in the hotel lobby. Something about the way he moved made me think of a hungry dog looking for a bone. He had a big, fat, red face and a sleepy expression in his eyes. He introduced himself as Wentworth Caswell -- Major Wentworth Caswell -- from "a fine southern family." Caswell pulled me into the hotel's barroom and yelled for a waiter. We ordered drinks. While we drank, he talked continually about himself, his family, his wife and her family. He said his wife was rich. He showed me a handful of silver coins that he pulled from his coat pocket.</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4d1679b4-84c6-4de2-929e-448ae4c5044c_w100_r1.png"/></div>
<p>By this time, I had decided that I wanted no more of him. I said good night.</p>
<p>I went up to my room and looked out the window. It was ten o'clock but the town was silent. "A nice quiet place," I said to myself as I got ready for bed. Just an ordinary, sleepy southern town."</p>
<p>I was born in the south myself. But I live in New York now. I write for a large magazine. My boss had asked me to go to Nashville. The magazine had received some stories and poems from a writer in Nashville, named Azalea Adair. The editor liked her work very much. The <strong>publisher </strong>asked me to get her to sign an agreement to write only for his magazine.</p>
<p>I left the hotel at nine o'clock the next morning to find Miss Adair. It was still raining. As soon as I stepped outside I met Uncle Caesar. He was a big, old black man with fuzzy gray hair.</p>
<p>Uncle Caesar was wearing the strangest coat I had ever seen. It must have been a military officer's coat. It was very long and when it was new it had been gray. But now rain, sun and age had made it a <strong>rainbow</strong> of colors. Only one of the buttons was left. It was yellow and as big as a fifty cent coin.</p>
<p>Uncle Caesar stood near a horse and carriage. He opened the carriage door and said softly, "Step right in, sir. I'll take you anywhere in the city."</p>
<p>"I want to go to eight-sixty-one Jasmine Street," I said, and I started to climb into the carriage. But the old man stopped me. "Why do you want to go there, sir? "</p>
<p>"What business is it of yours?" I said angrily. Uncle Caesar relaxed and smiled. "Nothing, sir. But it's a lonely part of town. Just step in and I'll take you there right away."</p>
<p>Eight-sixty-one Jasmine Street had been a fine house once, but now it was old and dying. I got out of the carriage.</p>
<p>"That will be two dollars, sir," Uncle Caesar said. I gave him two one-dollar bills. As I handed them to him, I noticed that one had been torn in half and fixed with a piece of blue paper. Also, the upper right hand corner was missing.</p>
<p>Azalea Adair herself opened the door when I knocked. She was about fifty years old. Her white hair was pulled back from her small, tired face. She wore a pale yellow dress. It was old, but very clean.</p>
<p>Azalea Adair led me into her living room. A damaged table, three chairs and an old red sofa were in the center of the floor.</p>
<p>Azalea Adair and I sat down at the table and began to talk. I told her about the magazine's offer and she told me about herself. She was from an old southern family. Her father had been a judge.</p>
<p>Azalea Adair told me she had never traveled or even attended school. Her parents taught her at home with private teachers. We finished our meeting. I promised to return with the agreement the next day, and rose to leave.</p>
<p>At that moment, someone knocked at the back door. Azalea Adair whispered a soft apology and went to answer the caller. She came back a minute later with bright eyes and pink cheeks. She looked ten years younger. "You must have a cup of tea before you go," she said. She shook a little bell on the table, and a small black girl about twelve years old ran into the room.</p>
<p>Azalea Adair opened a tiny old purse and took out a dollar bill. It had been fixed with a piece of blue paper and the upper right hand corner was missing. It was the dollar I had given to Uncle Caesar. "Go to Mister Baker's store, Impy," she said, "and get me twenty-five cents' worth of tea and ten cents' worth of sugar cakes. And please hurry."</p>
<p>The child ran out of the room. We heard the back door close. Then the girl screamed. Her cry mixed with a man's angry voice. Azalea Adair stood up. Her face showed no emotion as she left the room. I heard the man's rough voice and her gentle one. Then a door slammed and she came back into the room.</p>
<p>"I am sorry, but I won't be able to offer you any tea after all," she said. "It seems that Mister Baker has no more tea. Perhaps he will find some for our visit tomorrow."</p>
<p>We said good-bye. I went back to my hotel.</p>
<p>Just before dinner, Major Wentworth Caswell found me. It was impossible to avoid him. He insisted on buying me a drink and pulled two one-dollar bills from his pocket. Again I saw a torn dollar fixed with blue paper, with a corner missing. It was the one I gave Uncle Caesar. How strange, I thought. I wondered how Caswell got it.</p>
<p>Uncle Caesar was waiting outside the hotel the next afternoon. He took me to Miss Adair's house and agreed to wait there until we had finished our business.</p>
<p>Azalea Adair did not look well. I explained the agreement to her. She signed it. Then, as she started to rise from the table, Azalea Adair <strong>fainted</strong> and fell to the floor. I picked her up and carried her to the old red sofa. I ran to the door and yelled to Uncle Caesar for help. He ran down the street. Five minutes later, he was back with a doctor.</p>
<p>The doctor examined Miss Adair and turned to the old black driver. "Uncle Caesar," he said, "run to my house and ask my wife for some milk and some eggs. Hurry!"</p>
<p>Then the doctor turned to me. "She does not get enough to eat," he said. "She has many friends who want to help her, but she is proud. Mrs. Caswell will accept help only from that old black man. He was once her family's <strong>slave</strong>."</p>
<p>"Mrs. Caswell." I said in surprise. "I thought she was Azalea Adair."</p>
<p>"She was," the doctor answered, "until she married Wentworth Caswell twenty years ago. But he's a hopeless drunk who takes even the small amount of money that Uncle Caesar gives her."</p>
<p>After the doctor left I heard Caesar's voice in the other room. "Did he take all the money I gave you yesterday, Miss Azalea?" "Yes, Caesar," I heard her answer softly. "He took both dollars."</p>
<p>I went into the room and gave Azalea Adair fifty dollars. I told her it was from the magazine. Then Uncle Caesar drove me back to the hotel.</p>
<p>A few hours later, I went out for a walk before dinner. A crowd of people were talking excitedly in front of a store. I pushed my way into the store. Major Caswell was lying on the floor. He was dead.</p>
<p>Someone had found his body on the street. He had been killed in a fight. In fact, his hands were still closed into tight <strong>fists</strong>. But as I stood near his body, Caswell's right hand opened. Something fell from it and rolled near my feet. I put my foot on it, then picked it up and put it in my pocket.</p>
<p>People said they believed a thief had killed him. They said Caswell had been showing everyone that he had fifty dollars. But when he was found, he had no money on him.</p>
<p>I left Nashville the next morning. As the train crossed a river I took out of my pocket the object that had dropped from Caswell's dead hand. I threw it into the river below.</p>
<p>It was a button. A yellow button...the one from Uncle Caesar's coat.</p>
<p><em>You have just heard the story "A Municipal Report." It was written by O. Henry and adapted by Dona de Sanctis. Your narrator was Shep O'Neal.</em></p>
<p><em>_______________________________</em><span style="font-size: 9pt;">____________________________________________</span></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>continually </strong>- <em> adv.</em> doing something without interruption, not stopping or ending</p>
<p><strong>rainbow</strong> - <em>n. </em>a curved line of different colors that sometimes appears in the sky when the sun shines through rain</p>
<p><strong>publisher</strong> - <em>n</em>. a person or company that produces books, magazines, etc.</p>
<p><strong>faint</strong> - <em>v.</em> to suddenly become unconscious</p>
<p><strong>slave</strong> - <em>n.</em>someone who is legally owned by another person and is forced to work for that person without pay</p>
<p><strong>fist</strong> - <em>n</em>. the hand with its fingers bent down into the palm</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Obviously and Apparently (2024/10/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/obviously-and-apparently.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Martha about the usage of two adverbs commonly used in spoken English.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/3391f298-20c9-41e5-832c-c2614fac2c5b_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>I'm wondering if you could help me [explain] the difference between “obviously” and “apparently.”</p>
<p>Thank you,</p>
<p>Martha</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>Thank you for writing to us, Martha. I'm happy to answer this question.</p>
<p>Let's look at the adjective form of these words first.</p>
<p>If something is “obvious,” that means it is easy to see or understand. For example, it is obvious that an elephant is bigger and heavier than a dog. But some things are only obvious if you have enough experience or knowledge. For example, if a car needs fixing, it may be obvious to a skilled worker what repairs are needed. But the repairs might not be obvious to a person who lacks experience with cars.</p>
<p>The adjective “apparent” also describes something that is easy to see or understand. But we probably use the word “apparent” less often than the word “obvious.” “Apparent” can sound a little more <strong>formal</strong> than “obvious” in some situations.</p>
<p>Both “obvious” and “apparent” can be followed by the preposition “to” plus an object pronoun, as in the following examples:</p>
<p><em>It's obvious to me that he is unhappy.</em></p>
<p><em>It was apparent to him that no one in the office had the right skills for the job. </em></p>
<p>Next, let's look at the adverbial forms: “obviously” and “apparently.”</p>
<p>Unlike the adjective forms, these two words differ in terms of how easily we can understand or know something.</p>
<p>When we use the word “apparently,” we are expressing the idea that we think we know something is true. However, this idea is usually based on information we have heard or read rather than our own direct experience.</p>
<p>For example, if you say, “Apparently, he's not a very good teacher,” that means you have heard reports that the person is not a good teacher. At the same time, you do not know for sure if it is true. That is because you do not have direct experience yourself with the teacher.</p>
<p>On the other hand, if you say, “He's obviously not a very good teacher,” that means you have—or think you have—enough information to be sure that you are correct. It also means you think others should easily understand or agree with what you are saying.</p>
<p>We can use “obviously” or “apparently” as the first word in a sentence, followed by a comma, as in these examples:</p>
<p><em>Obviously, we need to practice more if we want to improve.</em></p>
<p><em>Apparently, it's hard to find a good restaurant in that area. </em></p>
<p>We can also place these adverbs next to the verb:</p>
<p><em>She apparently needs a lot of help.</em></p>
<p><em>He obviously feels very strongly about this issue. </em></p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? We'd like to hear from you. Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please include where you are from in your email, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>formal</strong> - <em>adj.</em> following or agreeing with established form, custom, or rule</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Argentine Town Struggles with Parrot Invasion (2024/10/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/argentine-town-struggles-with-parrot-invasion.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">03 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The Argentine town of Hilario Ascasubi near the country's Atlantic coast has a problem not many places have ever had.</p>
<p>It has too many parrots.</p>
<p>Biologists say thousands of the green-yellow-and-red birds have invaded the town. These experts say deforestation has driven the birds' migration.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Parrots stand on an switch box and cables in the town of Hilario Ascasubi in Argentina on September 23, 2024. (REUTERS/Agustin Marcarian)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4af06d18-356a-4d61-a1cd-6ca8e08d9c06_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Parrots stand on an switch box and cables in the town of Hilario Ascasubi in Argentina on September 23, 2024. (REUTERS/Agustin Marcarian)
</span></div>
<p>The problem is that the birds bite the town's electric <strong>cables</strong>. This is causing electricity outages. People living in the town are also unhappy about the birds' noise making and the birds' droppings, or waste that is getting everywhere.</p>
<p>Daiana Lera is a biologist. She said much of Argentina's forestland has been lost over the years. As a result, the parrots are going into the cities.</p>
<p>“The hillsides are disappearing, and this is causing them to come closer to the cities to find food, shelter and water,” Lera said.</p>
<p>In the past few years, the parrots have started to arrive in the autumn and winter to seek refuge. Local people say, at times, there are up to 10 parrots for each of the town's 5,000 human <strong>inhabitants</strong>. Only during the summer do the birds migrate south to the <strong>cliffs</strong> of Patagonia for <strong>breeding</strong> season.</p>
<p>Images show hundreds of birds <strong>perched</strong> on electric cables, buildings and churches.</p>
<p>Ramón Alvarez is a local reporter for Radio Taxi Fm. About the parrots, he said, “They bite and damage the cables, water can get into the wires when it rains....”</p>
<p>That affects Alvarez directly. “It goes without saying that when the power goes out, there is no radio,” he said.</p>
<p>The locals have tried different methods to scare away the birds, such as noise and even laser light. But nothing has worked.</p>
<p>“We need to start to restore our natural environments,” Lera said. “But until that happens, we have to think of strategies that allow us to live together in the most <strong>harmonious</strong> way possible in our towns.”</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Miguel Bianco and Agustin Marcarian reported this story for Reuters news agency. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>cable </strong><em>–n.</em> thick wires usually covered by plastic that carry electricity</p>
<p><strong>inhabitant</strong> <em>–n. </em>a person who lives in a particular place or area</p>
<p><strong>cliff</strong> <em>–n.</em> a high steep surface of rock, earth, or ice</p>
<p><strong>breeding </strong><em>–adj.</em> the producing and raising of plants or animals by sexual reproduction</p>
<p><strong>perch </strong><em>–v.</em> to sit or stand on a high place, especially for birds</p>
<p><strong>harmonious </strong><em>–adj.</em> <strong> </strong>marked by agreement in feeling or action; agreeable</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Moving Homeless People to Shelter Is Not Easy (2024/10/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/moving-homeless-people-to-shelter-is-not-easy.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Edgar Tapia works on the Homeless Outreach Team of San Francisco, California. He goes to places where people are living in the streets and tells them there is space for them in city shelters. He recently went into one San Francisco neighborhood on that mission.</p>
<p>He came to a group of <strong>tents</strong>, calling out greetings and offers of food and water bottles. He asked if anyone was interested in moving indoors. He had eight available beds in city shelters, he told them.</p>
<p>He reminded them that city street cleaners would be coming soon to clear the sidewalk.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Members of the San Francisco Homeless Outreach Team talk to a homeless person in the Mission District, Sept. 10, 2024, in San Francisco. (AP Photo/Terry Chea)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/16a0d647-15c6-4b64-8e48-439e2b26e5b1_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Members of the San Francisco Homeless Outreach Team talk to a homeless person in the Mission District, Sept. 10, 2024, in San Francisco. (AP Photo/Terry Chea)</span></div>
<p>One woman in a tent asked for health care kits and clothing. "Can we get some <strong>socks</strong>?" she asked.</p>
<p>Finding people to enter the city shelter is not an easy job. There are more shelter beds than ever before. San Francisco's <strong>mayor, </strong>London Breed, has said she will no longer permit people living outdoors when they know there is a place to stay indoors.</p>
<p><strong>Reasons to stay on the street</strong></p>
<p>Sometimes a person wants to move inside, but there are no beds. Other times, a bed is open but the person refuses the offer. Reasons include use of drugs and alcohol.</p>
<p>But outreach workers keep trying.</p>
<p>Jose Torres is a Homeless Outreach Team <strong>manager</strong>. He said that people on the street sometimes want to stay with their friends or dislike the shelter.</p>
<p>"Sometimes we get lucky and they accept the one thing we have available, and if that doesn't work, we try something else," he said. "It's that 'try again, try again' system."</p>
<p>Tapia was happy because a man he had been talking to for two months said he may be ready to accept a place in a shelter. The first time they talked, Tapia said, the man asked no questions and showed little interest. But the next time, the man asked what the shelters were like.</p>
<p>Tapia said, "I want to see these people off the streets. I want to see them do good."</p>
<p>The 41-year-old woman who asked for socks said her name was Mellie M. She said her group wants hotel rooms or an apartment. She wants a secure place to stay because she was raped while homeless.</p>
<p>"In order for us not to live in tents anymore," she said, "they need to give us a place that we can call home."</p>
<p>When Torres, the manager, arrived in one neighborhood, he got good news from other outreach workers. They told him that a <strong>client</strong> was moving into his own small apartment. That client is 71-year-old Larry James Bell.</p>
<p>Outreach worker Ventrell Johnson got emotional thinking about Bell. Just eight months ago, Bell was living under a plastic sheet. Johnson had gotten Bell a bed in a homeless shelter. Now, Bell was ready for his own place.</p>
<p>"I'd like to have a house one day," Bell said.</p>
<p>When Bell leaves the shelter, another bed becomes available for someone else. Johnson noted that people are a little more likely to accept shelter beds; now the city is pushing to remove the tents and temporary shelters from the streets.</p>
<p>By the end of their workday, outreach workers had found seven people for seven shelter beds.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Janie Har </em><em>reported this story for the </em><em>Associated Press</em><em>.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>tent</strong> – <em>n</em>. a portable shelter that is used outdoors, is made of cloth (such as canvas or nylon), and is held up with poles and ropes</p>
<p><strong>sock </strong>– <em>n</em>. a piece of clothing that is worn on your foot and that covers your ankle and sometimes the lower part of your leg</p>
<p><strong>client</strong> – <em>n</em>. a customer for a business or organization</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How Much Do You Know about Quantifiers? (2024/10/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/how-much-do-you-know-about-quantifiers.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Adam Brock</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>For VOA Learning English, this is <em>Everyday Grammar</em>.</p>
<p>Today we are going to talk about different ways of expressing quantity in English.</p>
<p>A <strong>quantifier </strong>is a word or number that shows an amount or number. You probably already know how to use common quantifiers like <em>much</em> and<em> many</em>. For example:</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/80470000-c0a8-0242-8421-08daad1f2a99_cx2_cy0_cw97_w100_r1.png"/></div>
<p><em>How many apples would you like?</em></p>
<p><em>How much fruit would you like?</em></p>
<p>The quantifier<em> many</em> is used before <em>apples</em>, which is a <strong>count noun</strong>. <em>Much</em> is used before <em>fruit</em>, a <strong>noncount noun</strong>.</p>
<p>Make sure you understand the difference between <strong>count nouns </strong>and <strong>noncount nouns </strong>before you study quantifiers. You can learn about count and noncount nouns in <a class="wsw__a" href="/preview/en-US-LEARN/a/3193621.html">last week's episode of Everyday Grammar</a>.</p>
<p>Quantifiers are adjectives and adjective phrases that go before nouns. They give information about <em>how much</em> or <em>how many</em> of an item you are talking about. Some quantifiers, like <em>many,</em> go only before count nouns. Others, like <em>much,</em> go only before noncount nouns. And a few quantifiers can go before count or noncount nouns.</p>
<p><strong>Quantifiers only used with count nouns</strong></p>
<p><em>One, each </em>and<em> every</em> are examples of count noun quantifiers.</p>
<p>Here are some examples:</p>
<p><em>One movie that I enjoy is “The Godfather.”</em></p>
<p><em>Each child is special.</em></p>
<p><em>Every member of the country club is rich.</em></p>
<p>With plural count nouns, just add <em>of the</em> between the quantifier and the noun it describes.</p>
<p><em>One of the boys is from China.</em></p>
<p><em>Each of the cars has air conditioning.</em></p>
<p><em>Every one of the students is smart.</em></p>
<p>Notice that <em>boys, cars</em> and<em> students</em> are plural nouns. But the verbs that follow them are singular. In most situations, <em>one, each and every</em> make the subject singular, even if the subject contains a plural noun.</p>
<p>This tricky rule confuses native speakers and English learners alike.</p>
<p>There are a few quantifiers related to the number <em>two</em>. You can say <em>I have two shoes</em>, <em>I have a couple of shoes, I have both shoes, </em>and<em> I have a pair of shoes</em>.</p>
<p>If you have more than two countable items, you can use <em>several, a few, many </em>and<em> a number of</em>.</p>
<p><em>I have several <strong>assignments</strong> due this week.</em></p>
<p><em>There are a few Thai restaurants in my town.</em></p>
<p><em>There are many ways to practice English.</em></p>
<p><em>A number of the cars are imported.</em></p>
<p><strong>Quantifiers only used with noncount nouns</strong></p>
<p>Now let's move on to quantifiers that only work with noncount nouns: <em>a little, much </em>and<em> a great deal of</em>. Here are some examples:</p>
<p><em>Could you loan me a little money?</em></p>
<p><em>The old woman has much wisdom to share.</em></p>
<p><em>There is a great deal of oil in Saudi Arabia.</em></p>
<p><em>Little</em> can go before a count noun if it is used as an adjective. For example, “The little boy is playing.” In this example,<em> little</em> does not refer to a number or quantity; it refers to the size of the boy.</p>
<p><strong>Quantifiers used with both count and noncount nouns</strong></p>
<p>There are several “safe” quantifiers that can go with both count and noncount nouns. <em>Some</em> is the most popular. <em>Most, plenty of, all </em>and <em>any </em>are other <strong>options</strong>. Listen for the quantifiers in these examples:</p>
<p><em>He cut some wood. (noncount noun)</em></p>
<p><em>Most Americans speak English. (count noun)</em></p>
<p><em>I have plenty of money. (noncount noun)</em></p>
<p><em>All children are special. (count noun)</em></p>
<p><em>Do you have any coffee? (noncount noun)</em></p>
<p>To refer to the<strong> absence </strong>or <strong>lack of</strong> something, simply use <em>no</em> before a count or noncount noun.</p>
<p><em>There was no rice left. (noncount noun)</em></p>
<p><em>There were no books in the library. (count noun)</em></p>
<p><em>She had no love for her ex-husband. (noncount noun)</em></p>
<p><em>No, when used as a quantifier, has the same meaning as zero.</em></p>
<p><em>Lots </em>and<em> a lot of</em> are very popular quantifiers — maybe too popular. Some English teachers do not like them. They think that <em>lots </em>and<em> a lot of</em> are overused and <strong>unsophisticated</strong>. You should avoid <em>lots </em>and<em> a lot of</em> in formal writing. Native speakers usually shorten <em>a lot of </em>to<em> “</em>a lotta” in casual speech.</p>
<p><strong>Few/a few vs. little/a little</strong></p>
<p>Listen carefully to these two sentences:</p>
<p><em>I have a few friends.</em></p>
<p><em>I have few friends</em>.</p>
<p>What is the difference? The first sentence contains the article <em>a</em>. This little word makes a big difference in meaning.</p>
<p><em>I have a few friends</em> <strong>focuses</strong> on a positive idea. The speaker is satisfied with the number of friends he has. The second sentence, <em>I have few friends</em>, focuses on a <strong>negative</strong> idea, his lack of friends. The speaker wishes he had more friends.</p>
<p>It might help to think of<em> few</em> as a half-empty glass of water. <em>A few</em> is like a half-filled glass of water. The amount of water is the same. But the speaker's attitude about the amount of water is different. <em>Few </em>and<em> a few</em> are only used before count nouns.</p>
<p>The same <strong>positive</strong>-negative <strong>distinction </strong>applies to <em>a little </em>and<em> little</em>. Use <em>little</em> and<em> a little</em> before noncount nouns.</p>
<p><em>I have a little money means the speaker has some money.</em></p>
<p><em>I have little money means the speaker does not have enough money.</em></p>
<p>Speaking of <em>little</em>, we have <em>little</em> time left for today's program. We hope you learned a few tips about how to use quantifiers.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p>And I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Adam Brock wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>__________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>quantifier</strong> – <em>grammatical term.</em> a determiner or pronoun indicative of quantity (e.g., all, both )</p>
<p><strong>count noun</strong> - <em>grammatical term. </em>a noun that can form a plural and, in the singular, can be used with the indefinite article</p>
<p><strong>noncount noun</strong> - <em>grammatical term. </em>a noun (such as “sand” or “butter”) that refers to something that cannot be counted<em> </em></p>
<p><strong>options </strong>– <em>n.</em> choices</p>
<p><strong>assignment </strong> - <em>n.</em> a job or duty that is given to someone : a task someone is required to do</p>
<p><strong>absence </strong>– <em>n.</em> a state or condition in which something expected, wanted, or looked for is not present or does not exist : a state or condition in which something is absent</p>
<p><strong>unsophisticated</strong> - <em>adj</em>. not complicated or highly developed; basic</p>
<p><strong>focus</strong> – <em>v.</em> to direct your attention or effort at something specific</p>
<p><strong>negative </strong> -<em> adj</em>. harmful or bad : not wanted</p>
<p><strong>positive </strong>– <em>adj.</em> good or useful</p>
<p><strong>distinction</strong> – <em>n.</em> the quality that makes a person or thing special or different</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Everest Growing Taller than Expected (2024/10/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/everest-growing-taller-than-expected.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Mount Everest, standing 8.85 kilometers above sea level, is Earth's tallest mountain.</p>
<p>And Mount Everest is still growing.</p>
<p>Mount Everest and the rest of the Himalayas are continuing on an upward movement that began at their birth around 50 million years ago. The mountains are a product of a collision between Eurasia and the Indian subcontinent.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Mount Everest or Sagarmatha (top), the highest peak in the world with an altitude of 8.848 meters is seen in this aerial view next to Mount Ama Dablam (bottom R) on April 22, 2007. (REUTERS/ Desmond Boylan/File Photo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/40c273c6-65b7-469f-bdfd-5b78400ac6c0_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Mount Everest or Sagarmatha (top), the highest peak in the world with an altitude of 8.848 meters is seen in this aerial view next to Mount Ama Dablam (bottom R) on April 22, 2007. (REUTERS/ Desmond Boylan/File Photo)</span></div>
<p>But Everest is growing more than expected. And, scientists now think they know the reason why.</p>
<p>Everest's growth has to do with the major joining, or merger, of two nearby river systems. The Kosi river joined with the Arun river around 89,000 years ago, the researchers estimated.</p>
<p>This change in the area's river system has led to Everest gaining around 15-50 meters in height.</p>
<p>That suggests an upward movement rate of about 0.2-0.5 millimeters per year.</p>
<p>The geological process at work, researchers said, is called isostatic rebound.</p>
<p>Isostatic rebound involves the rise of land masses on Earth's <strong>crust</strong> when the weight of the surface declines. The crust, Earth's outermost part, floats atop hot, semi-liquid rock.</p>
<p>In this case, the joining of the rivers resulted in increased <strong>erosion</strong> which carried off large amounts of rock and soil. This reduced the weight of the area near Everest.</p>
<p>"Isostatic rebound can be likened to a floating object adjusting its position when weight is removed," said Jin-Gen Dai of China University of Geosciences in Beijing.</p>
<p>Dai is one of the leaders of the study published recently in Nature Geoscience.</p>
<p>"When a heavy load, such as ice or eroded rock, is removed from the Earth's crust, the land beneath slowly rises in<strong> response</strong>, much like a boat rising in water when cargo is unloaded," Dai added.</p>
<p>The researchers, who used numerical models to study the development of the river system, estimated that isostatic rebound accounts for about 10 percent of Everest's yearly upward movement, or uplift rate.</p>
<p>This geological process is seen in other places around the world.</p>
<p>"A classic example is in Scandinavia, where the land is still rising in response to the melting of thick ice sheets that covered the <strong>region</strong> during the last Ice Age. This process continues today, affecting coastlines and landscapes, thousands of years after the ice retreated," Dai said.</p>
<p>Study co-writer Adam Smith, a University College London doctoral student, said GPS measurements show the continued rising of Everest and the rest of the Himalayas.</p>
<p>This uplift is faster than the continued surface erosion caused by wind, rain and river flow. As this erosion continues, Everest's uplift rate from isostatic rebound may increase, Smith said.</p>
<p>Neighboring mountains, including Lhotse, the world's fourth highest, and Makalu, the fifth highest, also get a boost from the same process. Lhotse is experiencing an uplift rate similar to Everest. Makalu has a slightly higher uplift rate.</p>
<p>Dai said that the research shows our planet's changing nature. Even a seemingly unchanging element like Mount Everest is "subject to ongoing geological processes, reminding us that Earth is constantly changing, often in ways<strong> imperceptible</strong> in our daily lives."</p>
<p>Earth's rigid outer part is divided into large plates that move slowly over time. The Himalayas rose following a collision between two plates.</p>
<p>Everest is located on the border between Nepal and the Tibet Autonomous Region of China. It was named for George Everest, a 19th century British <strong>surveyor</strong> in India.</p>
<p>"Mount Everest occupies a <strong>unique</strong> place in human consciousness," Dai said.</p>
<p>"Physically, it represents Earth's highest point," giving it a lot of importance simply because of its size, Dai explained.</p>
<p>He added that Everest has cultural importance to local Sherpa and Tibetan communities. Worldwide, Dai said, the mountain represents a big test for human endurance.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Will Dunham reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>crust</strong> <em>– n.</em> the outer part of a planet, moon, or asteroid</p>
<p><strong>erosion </strong><em>– n.</em> the process of diminishment or destruction by degrees</p>
<p><strong>response</strong> <em>– n.</em> something constituting a reply or reaction</p>
<p><strong>region</strong> <em>– n.</em> a broad geographic area distinguished by similar features</p>
<p><strong>imperceptible</strong> <em>– adj.</em> extremely slight, gradual, or subtle</p>
<p><strong>surveyor</strong><em> – n.</em> one who determines and delineate the form, extent, and position of a tract of land by taking measurements</p>
<p><strong>unique</strong> <em>– adj.</em> being without like or equal</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Short Corn Is Growing Stronger in US Midwest (2024/10/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/short-corn-is-growing-stronger-in-us-midwest.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Fields of tall corn plants are a common thing to see in the Midwest United States in late summer. They are as much a part of rural America as big red <strong>barns</strong> and cows.</p>
<p>But soon, tall corn plants might become shorter, replaced by plants only half as tall.</p>
<p>Cameron Sorgenfrey is a farmer in the Midwestern state of Iowa. He has been growing newly developed short corn for several years. His neighbors sometimes have questions about his smaller corn plants.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Cameron Sorgenfrey holds a tall corn stalk next to a short corn stalk along one of his fields, Monday, Sept. 16, 2024, in Wyoming, Iowa. (AP Photo/Charlie Neibergall)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1c557880-cf0a-4e32-a517-4d0796efd11f_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Cameron Sorgenfrey holds a tall corn stalk next to a short corn stalk along one of his fields, Monday, Sept. 16, 2024, in Wyoming, Iowa. (AP Photo/Charlie Neibergall)
</span></div>
<p><strong>Changing agriculture</strong></p>
<p>"As you drive across the Midwest, maybe in the next seven, eight, 10 years, you're going to see a lot of this out there," Sorgenfrey said. “I think this is going to change agriculture in the Midwest," he added.</p>
<p>Bayer Crop Science developed the short corn and tested it on 12,141 hectares in the Midwest. One promise the company made to farmers was a kind of corn that could survive powerful windstorms. The corn is not only shorter, but it also has a larger base. It can withstand winds of up to 80 kilometers per hour.</p>
<p>The smaller plants can grow closer together than taller kinds. That means farmers can grow more corn on the same amount of land, which increases their profits. This will help farmers facing lower corn prices in recent years. The smaller plants could also lead to less water use.</p>
<p>Dior Kelley is an assistant professor at Iowa State University. She is researching different possibilities for growing shorter corn. She said that because corn is the largest crop in the United States, more widespread use of the small kind will have a large effect.</p>
<p><strong>Huge difference</strong></p>
<p>"It is huge. It's a big, <strong>fundamental</strong> shift," Kelley said.</p>
<p>Last year, American farmers grew more than 363 million metric tons of corn. Most was used for animal feed, the fuel additive ethanol, or exported to other countries.</p>
<p>Scientists have long tried to develop better kinds of corn plants. But it has become more important for corn to grow even in very hot weather or when there is a lack of rain. Strong winds are another danger. In August 2020, a strong windstorm in the Midwest caused $11 billion in damage. It flattened both trees and corn plants only weeks before harvest time.</p>
<p>Kelley said she likes the idea of short corn. But she warns that short plants have their own problems to consider. For example, corn cobs that grow closer to the soil could be more at risk to diseases or mold.</p>
<p>Brian Leake is a Bayer spokesperson. He said the company has been developing short corn for more than 20 years. In a few years, he hopes farmers will be growing short corn everywhere.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Scott McFetridge </em><em>reported this story for the </em><em>Associated Press</em><em>.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>barn</strong> –<em> n</em>. a building on a farm that is used for storing grain and hay and for housing farm animals or equipment</p>
<p><strong>fundamental</strong> – <em>adj.</em> forming or relating to the most important part of something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Stair-climbing: A Sure Way to Burn Calories (2024/10/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/stair-climbing-a-sure-way-to-burn-calories.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>If you are trying to lose weight, climbing <strong>stairs</strong> as a regular exercise might be for you.</p>
<p>Stairs are available in many places. And research shows stair-climbing is more effective than walking on level ground.</p>
<p>“Overall, it is a fact that stair-climbing gets you fit faster and <strong>consumes</strong> more <strong>calories</strong>,” said Lauri van Houten, vice president of the International Skyrunning Federation. The organization oversees a number of activities that involve climbing.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - In this photo provided by ISF/Meeting, runner Yuri Yoshizumi competes during a race of Stairclimbing World Championships in Osaka, western Japan, on Nov. 19, 2023. (ISF/MEETING via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a5dd6596-206c-4b2f-90a3-272760d69d07_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - In this photo provided by ISF/Meeting, runner Yuri Yoshizumi competes during a race of Stairclimbing World Championships in Osaka, western Japan, on Nov. 19, 2023. (ISF/MEETING via AP)</span></div>
<p>“How many calories will I burn is the question everyone wants to know,” van Houten said. “Here's the good news: The overall energy <strong>expenditure</strong> of the exercise depends on your weight. Therefore, the more you weigh, the more you burn,” she said.</p>
<p>Research shows you burn about 20 times more calories going up stairs than walking on flat ground. Even going down stairs, you burn around five times more because your muscles have to work to slow the body.</p>
<p>That might be all you need to know if you are trying to lose weight.</p>
<p>Dr. Alberto Minetti of Italy's University of Milan has done a large amount of research on human movement — including stair-climbing. It is an exercise everyone can do and does not cost money, he said.</p>
<p>Minetti did the math to explain why going up stairs is so effective for burning calories in a short amount of time.</p>
<p>“To move 1 kilogram of body mass over one <strong>horizontal </strong>meter, you expend 0.5 calories,” he said.</p>
<p>But, he added, “If you move 1 kilogram of body mass <strong>vertically</strong> on stairs it's 10 calories. So it's 20 times the calories moving vertically rather than horizontally.”</p>
<p>Trained as a doctor, Minetti has spent his career as a researcher. He suggested that older people and beginner stair climbers watch their speed.</p>
<p>Minetti does his own stair-climbing at his home in Milan. He said he often takes a few deep breaths before going up the many stairs.</p>
<p>In a scientific study, Minetti makes the point that using your arms in stair-climbing adds extra power. <strong>Handrails</strong> offer safety, too.</p>
<p>The study notes that handrails are available along most stairs in very tall buildings. Using them increases “the muscle mass involved..." by getting the arms involved, the study shows.</p>
<p>“They are relatively small muscles in the arms, but better than nothing,” Minetti said.</p>
<p>If stair-climbing were an Olympic sport, Australian Suzy Walsham would own gold medals.</p>
<p>She has won 10 races up New York City's Empire State Building — officially 1,576 stairs — and five climbs up the Eiffel Tower. Overall, Walsham has won more than 100 international stair races, and was once considered the top woman in the sport.</p>
<p>When she was living in Singapore, Walsham climbed up her 29-story building — 37 times straight. It took over four hours with short breaks for coffee or water. She covered a vertical distance of 3,200 meters.</p>
<p>Walsham told the Associated Press that stair-climbing is a good form of exercise for many kinds of people.</p>
<p>“Many people struggle to run as they age,” she said, noting the exercise is “harder on the joints.”</p>
<p>She said stair training is a great substitute for running.</p>
<p>Stairs are everywhere — one flight, two flights at home, inside very large buildings, in stadiums, at work, in shopping malls, in the subway.</p>
<p>Stair-climbing does not take much time. It is easy to build up, adding a few flights of stairs every day or week. Stair-climbing can also help improve balance.</p>
<p>And it can easily become part of an exercise plan.</p>
<p>Yuri Yoshizumi won last year's women's division of the Stairclimbing World Championships in her native Osaka, Japan. She completed the 285-meter climb — 1,610 stairs — in 10 minutes, 20.06 seconds.</p>
<p>“Stair-climbing is an easy sport for beginners and the general public to get into,” Yoshizumi told the Associated Press in an email. She said the exercise helps to “strengthen your muscles and your cardiovascular system in a short amount of time.”</p>
<p>Yoshizumi noted that cities usually have many public stairways for people to climb.</p>
<p>“Just using the stairs instead of the <strong>escalators</strong> at (subway) stations and department stores is a good way to get some exercise,” she said.</p>
<p>I'm Ashley Thompson. And I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Stephen Wade reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>stairs </strong><em>-- n.</em> a series of steps or flights of steps for passing from one level to another</p>
<p><strong>consume</strong> <em>-- v.</em> to waste or burn away</p>
<p><strong>calorie</strong> <em>-- n.</em> an amount of food having an energy-producing value of one large calorie</p>
<p><strong>expenditure</strong> <em>-- n.</em> the act or process of spending or using</p>
<p><strong>horizontal</strong> <em>-- adv.</em> being on the same level</p>
<p><strong>vertically</strong> <em>-- adv.</em> going straight up or down from a level surface</p>
<p><strong>handrail</strong> <em>-- n.</em> a narrow rail for grasping with the hand as a support</p>
<p><strong>escalator</strong> <em>-- n.</em> a power-driven set of stairs arranged like an endless belt</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How Is Pennsylvania Testing Its Voting Machines? (2024/10/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/how-is-pennsylvania-testing-its-voting-machines.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Elections officials across Pennsylvania have begun testing their voting machines using a method known as <strong>logic</strong> and <strong>accuracy</strong> testing. It will be important to know how the machines will perform under the pressure of the hard use they will experience during the election.</p>
<p>All election equipment used by Pennsylvania <strong>counties</strong> is put through this pre-election “stress test.” A stress test is a way to find out how something performs under pressure.</p>
<p>Pennsylvania law requires all its counties to conduct logic and accuracy testing before any election. All other states do similar testing.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Voting equipment at the Allegheny County Election Division is prepared to be moved to polling sites.Thursday, Nov. 3, 2022. (AP Photo/Gene J. Puskar, File)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/bd010cef-39cd-4895-9c0b-2ecc7f0f9a52_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Voting equipment at the Allegheny County Election Division is prepared to be moved to polling sites.Thursday, Nov. 3, 2022. (AP Photo/Gene J. Puskar, File)
</span></div>
<p>Forrest Lehman is director of elections and registration in one Pennsylvania county. "Really, we are testing the voting system end to end," he said. "It's almost like we're running a small-<strong>scale</strong> election."</p>
<p><strong>How it works</strong></p>
<p>During logic and accuracy testing, election officials create <strong>sample</strong> ballots. Some of these are made to fail or cause errors in the machines. The officials put the samples through the machines to make sure they are counting votes accurately and noting errors.</p>
<p>Mark Lindeman is director of policy and strategy at Verified Voting, a group that studies voting technology in the U.S. He said that “logic and accuracy testing, combined with post-election <strong>audits</strong> of the voted ballots” show that “voting machines are doing what they're supposed to do.”</p>
<p><strong>Preparing for Election Day</strong></p>
<p>Pennsylvania counties have until 15 days before the election to confirm that they have completed the logic and accuracy test.</p>
<p>County officials must tell the heads of local political parties when and where they are doing the testing. The Pennsylvania Department of State says counties should also notify the public. The public can choose to observe the testing.</p>
<p>Snyder County Director of Elections Devin Rhoads said his county's testing is set to begin in October and finish in three days.</p>
<p>Rhoads said anybody who wants to watch Snyder County's testing is welcome.</p>
<p>"We're open and <strong>transparent</strong>," Rhoads said. "If I have a person who is questioning or doesn't believe in the system,” he says, he will show them how it works.</p>
<p>Other county election officials say they will run their tests over the coming weeks.</p>
<p>After the testing, officials reset the machines and keep them in a secure location until they go out to the voting places for Election Day.</p>
<p><strong>All eyes on Pennsylvania, other swing states</strong></p>
<p>Pennsylvania is considered an important swing state in this year's presidential election. A swing state is a state where candidates from the nation's two main political parties share similar levels of support among voters. This year, Democratic Vice President Kamala Harris and former Republican President Donald Trump are both seeking to win Pennsylvania's 19 electoral votes.</p>
<p>Election Day in the U.S. this year is November 5.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Josh Kelety </em><em>reported this story for the </em><em>Associated Press</em><em>.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>county </strong>-<em> n</em>. an area of a state or country that is larger than a city and has its own government to deal with local matters</p>
<p><strong>logic</strong> – <em>n</em>. a proper or reasonable way of thinking about or understanding something</p>
<p><strong>accuracy</strong> – <em>n</em>. the ability to work or perform without making mistakes</p>
<p><strong>sample </strong>– <em>adj</em>. used as an example of something</p>
<p><strong>scale</strong> – <em>n. </em>the size or level of something especially in comparison to something else</p>
<p><strong>audit</strong> - <em>n.</em> a careful check or review of something</p>
<p><strong>transparent</strong> – <em>adj</em>. honest and open; not secretive</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Use Habit Stacking to Help Get Healthy (2024/10/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/use-habit-stacking-to-help-get-healthy.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">30 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the Health &amp; Lifestyle report.</p>
<p>A woman in Portland, Oregon started her daily exercise <strong>habit</strong> with one activity – walking her dog. Lindsay Kee then added movements to this daily activity. Before leaving on the walk, she did some standing stretches. On her return, she did other exercises such as <strong>jumping jacks</strong>.</p>
<p>Over time, Kee added more exercises around the dog walk. She said adding exercises to an existing activity took the pressure off of creating a whole new daily exercise. And now more than a year later, she <strong>consistently</strong> exercises around the dog walk.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Habit stacking could be walking a pet and listening to news, a book, or podcast. Here a woman looks at her device while walking her dogs in a park in Tallinn, Estonia, Dec 16, 2020.(AP Photo/Raul Mee)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/196bc8da-45e6-42da-85f2-616f61a2223c_cx0_cy7_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Habit stacking could be walking a pet and listening to news, a book, or podcast. Here a woman looks at her device while walking her dogs in a park in Tallinn, Estonia, Dec 16, 2020.(AP Photo/Raul Mee)</span></div>
<p>Kee said, “I've found it to be really effective in helping me be consistent with things that I really do want to do.”</p>
<p>What Kee did is called habit <strong>stacking</strong>. Writer S.J. Scott created this term for his 2014 book of the same name. The idea behind habit stacking is to attach something you want to start doing to something you already do every day.</p>
<p>A common example is <strong>flossing</strong> your teeth after brushing them. However, you can use habit stacking in many areas of your daily life. Kee, for example, places her <strong>vitamins</strong> next to the coffee machine. This helps her remember to take them every morning.</p>
<p>Exercise experts say habit stacking is especially helpful if you are trying to increase exercise time.</p>
<p>Dana Santas is a movement expert who has trained more than 50 professional sports teams. She combines exercise habits with personal health care. For example, Santas does <strong>push-ups</strong> before every <strong>shower.</strong> And she does leg exercises while brushing her teeth. She says that her electric toothbrush makes a sound every 30 seconds to remind her to brush different teeth. But she uses the reminder to change her exercises. “It's perfect,” she added.</p>
<p>Two minutes of exercise may not get you in shape. But, experts say every little bit helps. Experts at the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention suggest getting 150 minutes of <strong>moderate</strong> activity, like a fast walk, every week. Or you could also get 75 minutes of very energetic<strong> </strong>activity, like jogging, every week. The health experts also suggest two days a week of strength training.</p>
<p>Most people find keeping new habits difficult. And while habit stacking is not a perfect solution, it does help with one barrier -- decision-making.</p>
<p>Gretchen Rubin is the writer of <em>Better Than Before: Mastering the Habits of Our Everyday Lives</em>. She said habit stacking is one of the best ways to start and keep new habits. The technique helps to remove the barrier of deciding when or if to do something.</p>
<p>Rubin shared a story of her college days. To help her stay active, she would only shower if she had exercised that day.</p>
<p>She suggested combining the new, or what she calls “shaky,” behavior with something you have to do or deeply want to do.</p>
<p>“So you have to do the <strong>shaky</strong> habit before you get to the strong habit,” Rubin said. If she wants to listen to a podcast, her strong habit, she must do it while exercising on a running machine. For her, this will strengthen her shaky habit.</p>
<p>And that's the Health &amp; Lifestyle report. I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Albert Stumm reported this story for The Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>habit </strong><em>– n.</em><strong> </strong>a usual manner of behavior or thinking</p>
<p><strong>jumping jacks </strong><em>– n. </em>a conditioning exercise performed from a standing position by jumping to a position with legs spread and arms raised and then to the original position</p>
<p><strong>shower </strong><em>– v. </em>a bath in which water is sprayed on a person; also <em>– n.</em><strong> </strong>a device for providing such a bath</p>
<p><strong>consistently </strong><em>– adv. </em>being unchanging in behavior or beliefs</p>
<p><strong>stack </strong><em>– n. </em>an orderly pile of objects usually one on top of the other; also <em>– v. </em>to arrange in or form a stack</p>
<p><strong>floss</strong> <em>– v. </em>to use dental floss on one's teeth : <strong>dental floss </strong><em>– n.</em> a thread used to clean between the teeth</p>
<p><strong>vitamin </strong><em>– n. </em>any of various substances that are necessary in very small amounts to the nutrition of most animals and some plants, that are important to the control of growth and development by activating and assisting in the function of enzymes, and that are present naturally in many foods or in some cases are produced within the body</p>
<p><strong>push-up </strong><em>– n. </em>a conditioning exercise performed in a prone position by raising and lowering the body with the straightening and bending of the arms while keeping the back straight and supporting the body on the hands and toes</p>
<p><strong>moderate</strong> <em>– adj</em>. avoiding or lacking extremes (as in behavior or temperature)</p>
<p><strong>shaky</strong> <em>– adj. </em>lacking in firmness (as of beliefs or principles)</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Pennsylvania Bakery Is Ready with Election Cookie Poll (2024/10/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/pennsylvania-bakery-is-ready-with-election-cookie-poll.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">30 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>People are driving from hours away to buy cookies at Lochel's Bakery outside of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. And orders for its red and blue cookies are coming in from as far away as the American state of Alaska.</p>
<p>They come to<strong> </strong>buy the 10-centimeter round cookies in blue and white showing the name of the Democratic candidate, Kamala Harris. Or, they want the red and white cookies with the name of the Republican candidate, Donald Trump.</p>
<p>These are not your everyday cookies. At Lochel's Bakery, the sale of each Harris 2024 or Trump 2024 cookie counts as a vote for the candidate. The candidate with the most cookies sold is considered the winner of its “cookie <strong>poll</strong>.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Cookies, with Harris and Trump labels on, are on display at Lochel's Bakery in the town of Hatboro in suburban Philadelphia, Tuesday, Sept. 24, 2024. (AP Photo/Tassanee Vejpongsa)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/db0c0d3f-8bdf-4aac-873c-ed38b7941b19_cx20_cy19_cw79_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Cookies, with Harris and Trump labels on, are on display at Lochel's Bakery in the town of Hatboro in suburban Philadelphia, Tuesday, Sept. 24, 2024. (AP Photo/Tassanee Vejpongsa)
</span></div>
<p>The sale of cookies and the cookie poll began in the 2008 presidential election as a joke between the bakery owners and their <strong>customers</strong>. The cookie poll correctly predicted Barack Obama as the winner in 2008 and 2012 and Trump as the winner in 2016. But in 2020, more customers bought cookies named after Trump, who lost that year's election to Joe Biden.</p>
<p>Kathy Lochel is one of the bakery's owners. She said the cookie poll is meant to be fun. “It's definitely not scientific. It's just a... way... to take the pressure off with what is going on with the election,” Lochel added.</p>
<p>Helene Moran recently bought Trump cookies on her 82nd birthday. Moran said she bought each time Trump ran for election. “He's my sweetheart, I love him so much,” she said.</p>
<p>Lochel said the bakery is selling even more cookies this year than in 2020. “These cookies are being shipped all over the United States right now, so much so that they're on <strong>back order</strong>, so we're about three to four weeks back,” Lochel said.</p>
<p>It helps that Lochel's Bakery is in the moderate and heavily populated <strong>suburbs</strong> of Philadelphia. The bakery is also in the battleground state of Pennsylvania, where support for Trump and Harris is evenly split among voters. Whichever candidate wins more battleground states will likely win this year's election.</p>
<p>The sale of Trump cookies may have increased after he shared a story about the cookie poll on social media. As of September 24, Trump was leading Harris in cookie sales, 12,558 to 889 — a far bigger lead than real election polls of likely voters have found.</p>
<p>Lochel says that while the real election includes attack advertising and name-calling, the cookie-buying public has been much nicer.</p>
<p>“The people that are coming into our store, whether they're buying red or blue cookies, they're friendly, they joke, they laugh, they buy other things,” Lochel said.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith adapted this story for VOA Learning English from reporting from The Associated Press. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>poll </strong><em>-n. </em>a survey in which people are asked their opinion or what they will choose to do</p>
<p><strong>customer </strong><em>-n. </em>a person who buys things from a physical or online store</p>
<p><strong>back order </strong><em>-n. </em>things customers have bought but the seller cannot yet deliver to them</p>
<p><strong>suburb </strong><em>-n. </em>an area, typically with many homes, located immediately outside a city</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>A Century of Changes As Jimmy Carter Turns 100 (2024/10/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/a-century-of-changes-as-jimmy-carter-turns-100.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/><span class="datetime">30 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Former president of the United States Jimmy Carter is turning 100 on October 1.</p>
<p>The 39th president is celebrating the century mark at his home in Plains, Georgia, where he was born in 1924. He is currently in <strong>hospice </strong>care.</p>
<p>Carter's small southern town is much like it was when he was a boy. But America, and the world overall, has seen major changes over his long life.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Former President Jimmy Carter teaches Sunday School class at Maranatha Baptist Church in his hometown, Aug. 23, 2015, in Plains, Ga. (AP Photo/David Goldman, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/af220553-de37-4fd0-bc3e-87fa5f6bb33c_cx0_cy15_cw91_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Former President Jimmy Carter teaches Sunday School class at Maranatha Baptist Church in his hometown, Aug. 23, 2015, in Plains, Ga. (AP Photo/David Goldman, File)</span></div>
<p><strong>Changes everywhere, but not Plains</strong></p>
<p>The U.S. population is almost three times larger than it was in 1924. America grew from about 114 million people to about 330 million today. The world population grew even faster, from 1.9 billion to more than 8.1 billion, during the same period.</p>
<p>That great increase has not reached Plains, Georgia, however. The town of 500 people in the 1920s, now has closer to 600. Much of its local economy revolves around Carter, its most famous son.</p>
<p><strong>Red state, blue state</strong></p>
<p>Jimmy Carter first ran for president in 1976 against then-President Gerald Ford. That election marked the first time the television network NBC started using a red-and-blue electoral map to cover the election results.</p>
<p>The colors have since become a permanent part of the American political language. The color blue represents the Democratic Party and red represents the Republican Party.</p>
<p><strong>Shopping</strong></p>
<p>In 1924, there was no Amazon to order goods online. But Americans could order a build-it-yourself house from a Sears <strong>catalog</strong> for $2,025. That amount was a little below the average worker's yearly earnings.</p>
<p>There was no <strong>superstore</strong> like Walmart. But people could buy bread, milk, and other things at small, local general stores.</p>
<p>Prohibition, the ban on making and drinking alcohol, had been national law for four years when Carter was born. He was nine when it ended.</p>
<p>The former president and his late wife Rosalynn were not known as big drinkers. They usually served <strong>wine</strong> as the single kind of alcoholic drink at White House state dinners, mainly to save money. Other kinds of alcohol would increase the cost of the events.</p>
<p>But Carter's brother Billy was known for his beer drinking. When Carter became president, Billy sold his name to a beer manufacturer to produce Billy Beer. News sources reported that Billy Carter received a $50,000 yearly payment for use of his name from one brewer. That would be about $215,000 in today's economy.</p>
<p><strong>Voting rights </strong></p>
<p>The 19th Amendment that extended voting rights to women went into effect in 1920, four years before Carter's birth. And the Voting Rights Act that widened voting rights to Black Americans was passed in 1965.</p>
<p>Now, Carter is set to vote by mail for Vice President Kamala Harris, says his grandson Jason Carter. He added that his grandfather is <strong>excited</strong> about the chance to see Harris make history.</p>
<p>If elected, Harris would become the first female and the first person of South Asian ancestry to lead the United States.</p>
<p><strong>Immigration and isolationism</strong></p>
<p>Jimmy Carter was born in a period of <strong>isolationism</strong>, protectionism and white Christian nationalism in the U.S.</p>
<p>In 1922, Congress enacted taxes on imports, called tariffs, to help U.S. manufacturers. After stock market losses in 1929, lawmakers added more tariffs to help farmers.</p>
<p>Five months before Carter was born, President Calvin Coolidge signed the Immigration Act of 1924. The law created the U.S. Border Patrol and sharply limited immigration, permitting mostly just Western Europeans to enter. Asians were barred from the country completely.</p>
<p>Congress said the law was meant to “<strong>preserve</strong> the<strong> ideal</strong> of U.S. <strong>homogeneity</strong>.” The militant white supremacist group Ku Klux Klan held large marches in Washington in 1925 and 1926 to gather support.</p>
<p>A century later, Republican presidential candidate Donald Trump is promising to order the largest <strong>deportation</strong> effort in U.S. history if he wins office.</p>
<p>Trump is also calling for tariffs on all goods coming to America.</p>
<p><strong>Other presidents </strong></p>
<p>Carter has lived through 40 percent of U.S. history since the Declaration of Independence in 1776. When Carter took office, just one president, John Adams, had lived to be 90. Since then, Ford, Ronald Reagan, Carter and George H.W. Bush all reached at least 93.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver. </p>
<p><em>Bill Barrow reported this story for The Associated Press. Hai Do adapted the story for Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>hospice</strong> - n. a place that provides care for people who are dying</p>
<p><strong>catalog</strong> - n. a book of list of things that you can buy</p>
<p><strong>wine</strong> - n. an alcoholic drink made from juice of grapes</p>
<p><strong>excited</strong> - adj. enthusiastic and eager</p>
<p><strong>isolationism</strong> - n. a belief that country should not be involved with other countries</p>
<p><strong>preserve</strong> - v. to keep something in its original state</p>
<p><strong>ideal</strong> - n. the idea or standard of excellence</p>
<p><strong>homogeneity</strong> - n. making up of the same kind of people</p>
<p><strong>deportation</strong> - n. forceful removal of non-citizen to leave a country</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Water Sources on Moon More Widespread than Thought (2024/9/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/study-water-sources-on-moon-more-widespread-than-thought.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A new study suggests sources of water on the moon are more widespread than previously thought.</p>
<p>The study was based on new examinations of data collected by India's Chandrayaan-1 spacecraft. It launched in October 2008 and collected data while orbiting the moon for about a year.</p>
<p>Chandrayaan-1 has already provided evidence of water on the moon. In September 2009, scientists published a study based on data from the Indian space mission. The data showed the presence of molecules linked to water, as well as the substance hydroxyl.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this early Monday, Oct. 5, 2020, file photo, a waning moon is seen at the sky over Frankfurt, Germany. (AP Photo/Michael Probst, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/ea29b6fd-92d5-4daf-8385-3c3f941ced79_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this early Monday, Oct. 5, 2020, file photo, a waning moon is seen at the sky over Frankfurt, Germany. (AP Photo/Michael Probst, File)</span></div>
<p>The American space agency NASA describes hydroxyl (OH) as “a molecule made up of one hydrogen atom and one oxygen atom with a free (unpaired) electron.” It notes it is “one of the most reactive gases in the atmosphere” and can help break down other gases in the air.</p>
<p>The 2009 study suggested the water molecules identified by Chandrayaan-1 data were mainly found in the moon's extreme northern and southern areas, known as the poles. Scientists said the data from that study showed most of the water probably existed in large <strong>craters</strong> near the poles where sunlight is blocked.</p>
<p>But new examinations of the data show that water and hydroxyl molecules likely exist over much wider areas of the moon. In addition, the research suggests water is even present in areas of the moon receiving direct sunlight.</p>
<p>The instrument aboard Chandrayaan-1 that captured the molecule data is called the Moon Mineralogy Mapper (M3). NASA built and operated the instrument. The space agency <a class="wsw__a" href="https://nssdc.gsfc.nasa.gov/nmc/experiment/display.action?id=2008-052A-04">describes</a> M3 as an “imaging spectrometer.” A spectrometer is an instrument used to study the chemical <strong>composition</strong> and structures of substances.</p>
<p>On the Chandrayaan-1 mission, the spectrometer aimed to map the mineral composition of materials on the moon's surface. Researchers examined this data and centered their search on areas outside the lunar poles. They found that the sources of water and hydroxyl are believed to be contained in minerals on or just below the moon's surface.</p>
<p>Scientists involved in the research recently reported their results <a class="wsw__a" href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/PSJ/ad5837">in a study</a> published in the <em>Planetary Science Journal</em>.</p>
<p>The research was led by Roger Clark, a senior scientist at the Planetary Science Institute.</p>
<p>In a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.psi.edu/blog/sources-of-water-and-hydroxyl-are-widespread-on-the-moon/">press release</a> announcing the findings, the researchers noted their discovery was made possible by data that the M3 instrument collected. They explained the instrument provides highly detailed data using imaging and infrared technologies.</p>
<p>The M3 instrument, for example, can identify 85 different colors in its examinations of mineral compositions. This compares to normal digital cameras, which generally only record three colors.</p>
<p>The researchers said, “Just like we see different colors from different materials, the infrared spectrometer can see many (infrared) colors to better determine the composition, including the water and hydroxyl."</p>
<p>The team noted the water might have resulted from heating of rocks and soil or from chemical reactions that combined different hydroxyls to produce water, as well as oxygen.</p>
<p>Clark, from the Planetary Science Institute, said both cratering and volcanic activity can bring water-rich materials to the surface. He noted that both are observed in the newly examined data. “We see a lunar surface with complex <strong>geology</strong> with <strong>significant</strong> water in the sub-surface and a surface layer of hydroxyl.”</p>
<p>The discovery, Clark said, can be helpful to future exploration efforts on the moon. “Future astronauts may be able to find water even near the equator by <strong>exploiting</strong> these water-rich areas.”</p>
<p>He added, “Knowing where water is located not only helps to understand lunar geologic history, but also where astronauts may find water in the future.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from the Planetary Science Institute and NASA. </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>crater </strong><em>– n.</em> a hole left in the ground by an object that hits it with a huge force</p>
<p><strong>composition </strong><em>– n. </em>the parts, substances, etc. that something is made up of</p>
<p><strong>geology</strong> <em>– v. </em>the study of rocks and soil and the physical structure of Earth</p>
<p><strong>exploit </strong><em>– v.</em> to use or develop something for your advantage</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Buyers Want Japanese Temples for Tax Breaks (2024/9/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/buyers-want-japanese-temples-for-tax-breaks.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Benmou Suzuki is a religious worker at a 420-year-old <strong>temple</strong> that is not in very good condition.</p>
<p>It is deep in the forest near a small Japanese mountain village. It does not look like a valuable property.</p>
<p>Yet two men recently asked Suzuki if he was interested in selling. He said he thinks they did not want the old, <strong>ornate</strong> building next to a mountain that is considered holy. Instead, they wanted the special tax <strong>status</strong> that comes with running a religious property.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Mikaboyama Fudoson temple is pictured in Fujioka, Gunma Prefecture, Japan September 4, 2024. (REUTERS/Kim Kyung-Hoon)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/c988ac70-330a-4d40-8f72-284281596644_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Mikaboyama Fudoson temple is pictured in Fujioka, Gunma Prefecture, Japan September 4, 2024. (REUTERS/Kim Kyung-Hoon)</span></div>
<p>"There are people out there who want a temple, even a mountain temple like this," said 52-year-old Suzuki.</p>
<p>Japan's population is decreasing and interest in religion is less intense. There are fewer people to support the country's many temples and <strong>shrines</strong>.</p>
<p>Suzuki's Mikaboyama temple, for example, is in a small town, which also has three other Buddhist temples, one Shinto shrine and a Christian church.</p>
<p>Japanese officials say they are seeing more sales of religious properties to buyers who do not continue to run them as religious centers. Officials fear many are buying them to avoid paying taxes or possibly even to hide criminal activity.</p>
<p>Japan's Agency for Cultural Affairs oversees religious places. An official from the agency said, "It's already a sense of crisis for us and the religious community."</p>
<p>The public is unhappy about the sales, too. In Osaka, a temple sold in 2020 was later torn down for a property development. In Kyoto, news reports said a temple was destroyed to make a parking lot.</p>
<p>The owner of an active religious center in Japan is a corporation that pays no taxes. Even non-religious businesses on the property enjoy lower tax rates. The law permits many different activities like restaurants, hair salons and hotels.</p>
<p>The cultural affairs agency said it has increased its efforts to end the legal status of inactive religious corporations to stop sales to non-religious owners. Where there has been damage to a religious place, agency officials visit, warning the religious leaders about selling to such buyers.</p>
<p>It might seem easier for Japan to change its laws for purchasing religious properties. But the agency said the government does not like to change laws related to religion. They do not want to limit religious freedom, which Japan's constitution protects.</p>
<p>Osaka-based property dealer Takao Yamamoto said interest is rising quickly. He said a religious corporation <strong>license</strong> can sell for $210,000. Some religious properties, especially those where burials take place, are advertised for millions of dollars.</p>
<p>"Anyone can buy independent sites as long as you have money...even foreigners can buy them. Recently, a lot of Chinese people are trying to buy them," Yamamoto said.</p>
<p>For his part, Suzuki says he does not plan to sell Mikaboyama temple and is working on ideas to raise money to keep it up. "Temples are places for local people to gather and <strong>forge</strong> connections. We just can't <strong>get rid of</strong> them," he said.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Mariko Katsumura</em> <em>reported this story for</em> <em>Reuters.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>temple</strong> – <em>n</em>. a building for worship, in Japan, belonging to the Buddhist religion</p>
<p><strong>ornate </strong>–<em>n</em>. including many fine details and made in an effort to impress those who see it</p>
<p><strong>status </strong>–<em>n</em>. how a person or property is treated under the law</p>
<p><strong>shrine</strong> – <em>n</em>. in Japan, a place connected with a holy person or event where people go to worship in the Shinto religious tradition</p>
<p><strong>license </strong>–<em>n</em>. usually a document that permits the holder to carry on an activity, use or own something that is subject to government rules</p>
<p><strong>forge</strong> – <em>v</em>. to form or create (something, such as an agreement or relationship) through great effort</p>
<p><strong>get rid of</strong> – <em>phrasal verb</em>. to do something so that you no longer have or are affected or bothered by (something or someone that is unwanted)</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Keep Your Nose to the Grindstone (2024/9/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/keep-your-nose-to-the-grindstone.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Learning a language is difficult. Sometimes it requires a plan and resources. But it also usually requires hard work. People who <strong>persist</strong> with their language goals often get good results. They keep working even through hard times. They <u>keep their nose to the grindstone</u>.</p>
<p>When you <u>keep your nose to the grindstone,</u> you work very hard for a long time at something. You don't give up.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This is an antique grindstone used for sharpening knives. (Adobe Photo by Mannyo/Wirestock Creators)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1f7eda90-3172-4142-8ff6-1fe31c72e71c_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpeg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This is an antique grindstone used for sharpening knives. (Adobe Photo by Mannyo/Wirestock Creators)</span></div>
<p>How do we use this<strong> idiom</strong> in daily life? How did it come to mean <strong>perseverance</strong>? And just what is a grindstone? We answer all these questions on today's show.</p>
<p>First, let's talk about a grindstone. A grindstone is a large stone circular stone with a hole in the middle. An <strong>axle</strong> fits through that hole. When the stone turns quickly on the axle, it can sharpen, shape, or smooth a tool.</p>
<p>And that brings us to the beginnings of this idiom.</p>
<p>On his website Phrase Finder, writer and language researcher Gary Martin suggests two possible beginnings. Both are set in work environments of long ago: a place for milling<strong> </strong>grain and a place for sharpening tools.</p>
<p>Some online sources claim that <u>keeping your nose to the grindstone</u> comes from milling grain. If the stone got too hot while grinding, it could burn the grain. So, workers would have to keep their noses close to the stone and smell for any sign of burning.</p>
<p>However, word expert Martin says that doesn't seem true. He claims that these mills used millstones. So, if this story were true, we would say <u>keep your nose to the millstone.</u> But we don't.</p>
<p>He also notes that the terms “millstone” and “grindstone” were used interchangeably hundreds of years ago. But then, at some point long ago, that stopped. Grain mills used millstones and not grindstones. And <strong>vice versa</strong> – tool sharpening workshops used grindstones and not millstones.</p>
<p>So, let's talk about the explanation set in a tool sharpening workshop. Martin talks about old workshops in his area of England. He says these workshops have <strong>benches</strong> very near to grinding stones. Workers would sit on the benches <strong>hunched over</strong> and work very hard and very long. He goes on to write the following:</p>
<p><em>“They had to pay close attention to their work as a moment too long on the wheel could cause the steel to overheat and be ruined.”</em></p>
<p>Martin guesses that this story is the more likely explanation. Imagine being hunched over your work and working hard at it. That describes <u>having your nose to the grindstone</u>.</p>
<p>In some cases, we also say <u>put your nose to the grindstone</u>. We may say it this way if we give someone advice. For example, “You need to <u>put your nose to the grindstone</u> if you're going to finish this project on time.”</p>
<p>Now let's hear another example.</p>
<p><em>A: Have you seen Marisa lately? She hasn't called or texted in weeks!</em></p>
<p><em>B: I was worried about her too. But the other day, I ran into her co-worker. She said Marisa has her <u>nose to the grindstone</u> trying to finish her year-end report.</em></p>
<p><em>A: Oh I forgot about that! In that case, let's take her some dinner. She never eats when she's busy with work. </em></p>
<p><em>B: Good idea! I'll make my famous pasta and meatballs. </em></p>
<p>If I had to pick an <strong>opposite</strong> of this idiom, it would be this one: All work and no play makes Jack a <strong>dull </strong>boy.</p>
<p>Life can't be all about work. So, if you've been keeping your nose to the grindstone, remember to take a break.</p>
<p>And that's all the time we have this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>.</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>persist</strong> <em>– v.</em> to continue to do something in spite of opposition, warnings, or pleas</p>
<p><strong>idiom</strong> <em>– n. </em>an expression that cannot be understood from the meanings of its separate words but must be learned as a whole</p>
<p><strong>perseverance </strong><em>– n. </em>continued effort to do or achieve something despite difficulties, failure, or opposition</p>
<p><strong>axle </strong><em>– n. </em>a pin, pole, or bar on or with which a wheel revolves</p>
<p><strong>mill </strong><em>– v. </em>Milling transforms grain into flour for food preparation. : <em>– n.</em> A mill is where grain is processed into flour.</p>
<p><strong>vice versa </strong><em>– adv. </em>with the order changed <strong>: </strong>with the relations reversed</p>
<p><strong>bench </strong><em>– n. </em>a long seat for two or more persons</p>
<p><strong>hunch over</strong> <em>phrasal verb </em>to bend one's body into an arch or hump</p>
<p><strong>opposite </strong><em>– adj. </em>as different as possible</p>
<p><strong>dull </strong><em>– adj. </em>mentally slow</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Accuses Visa of Illegally Blocking Competition (2024/9/29) | 美国司法部指控VISA阻止竞争</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/us-accuses-visa-of-illegally-blocking-competition.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>The U.S. Department of Justice (DOJ) has brought a lawsuit against Visa. It is accusing the financial services company of using illegal methods to block competition in the debit card market.<br/>美国司法部对Visa提起诉讼。它指控这家金融服务公司使用非法手段遏制借记卡市场的竞争。</p><p>The lawsuit states the San Francisco-based company penalizes businesses and banks that do not use Visa's own payment processing technology.<br/>诉讼称，这家总部位于旧金山的公司对不使用Visa自有支付处理技术的商家和银行进行处罚。</p><p>The DOJ argues that Visa's anti-competition methods cost individuals and businesses billions of dollars every year. Visa earns money for each purchase, or transaction, processed on its own network.<br/>美国司法部认为，Visa的这种反竞争手段每年给个人和商家造成数十亿美元的损失。Visa通过其自有支付网络上处理的每笔购买或交易赚钱。</p><p>The DOJ estimates about 60 percent of debit transactions in the U.S. take place on Visa's debit network. This adds up to more than $7 billion each year.<br/>美国司法部估计，美国约60%的借记交易发生在Visa的借记网络上。这些处理费用加起来每年超过70亿美元。</p><p>In a statement, Attorney General Merrick Garland said the DOJ found that Visa had unlawfully gained enough power to charge money, or fees, “that far exceed what it could charge in a competitive market.”<br/>司法部长梅里克·加兰在一份声明中表示，司法部发现Visa非法获得足够实力来收取金钱或费用，这“远远超过了它在竞争激烈的市场中可以收取的费用。”</p><p>Garland added that businesses and banks then pass those costs on to consumers. They either raise prices or reduce quality or service. As a result, Visa's business methods affect “not just the price of one thing – but the price of nearly everything.”<br/>加兰德补充说，商家和银行随后将这些成本转嫁给消费者。他们要么提高价格，要么降低质量或服务。因此，Visa的商业方式“不仅影响一件东西的价格，而且影响几乎所有东西的价格”。</p><p>Julie Rottenberg is Visa's chief legal counsel. She said in a statement that the lawsuit does not consider the “ever expanding universe of companies offering new ways to pay for goods and services.”<br/>朱莉·罗滕伯格是Visa的首席法律顾问。她在一份声明中表示，该诉讼没有考虑“为商品和服务提供全新支付方式的公司圈不断扩大”。</p><p>“Today's lawsuit ignores the reality that Visa is just one of many competitors in a debit space that is growing, with entrants who are thriving,” Rottenberg said. She added that the company would strongly defend itself against the “meritless” lawsuit.<br/>罗滕伯格说：“今天的诉讼忽略了这样一个事实，即Visa只是借记卡领域不断增长的的众多竞争对手之一，新的加入者也在蓬勃发展。”她补充说，该公司将对这起“毫无根据”的诉讼进行强有力的辩护。</p><p>The lawsuit was brought in the U.S. District Court for the Southern District of New York. The DOJ argues that the huge number of transactions completed on Visa's network makes it difficult for businesses to use alternative companies.<br/>该诉讼是在纽约南区美国地方法院提起的。美国司法部辩称，Visa网络上完成的大量交易使企业难以使用其他公司。</p><p>The DOJ also accuses Visa of blocking competition by paying to enter into partnership agreements with possible competitors.<br/>美国司法部还指责Visa通过掏钱与可能的竞争对手签订合作协议来阻止竞争。</p><p>In 2020, the DOJ brought legal action to block the company's $5.3 billion purchase of financial technology startup Plaid. It argued the takeover was an attempt to gain control of a possible competitor to Visa. The purchase deal was later cancelled.<br/>2020年，美国司法部提起法律诉讼，阻止该公司以53亿美元收购金融科技初创公司Plaid。美国司法部辩称，此次收购是为了控制Visa可能的竞争对手。这笔收购交易后来被取消。</p><p>Since the pandemic, more people worldwide have been shopping online for goods and services. This has led to higher earnings for Visa because of its fee structure for transactions. In addition, more businesses – including ones like bars, haircutters and coffee shops that mostly use cash – have started accepting credit or debit cards as a form of payment.<br/>自疫情以来，全球越来越多人在网上购买商品和服务。由于其交易费用结构，这也导致Visa的收益更高。此外，越来越多的商家，包括酒吧、理发师和咖啡店等主要使用现金的商家，也已经开始接受信用卡或借记卡作为支付方式。</p><p>Sanjay Sahrani is a financial advisor with investment company KBW based in New York City. He recently told investors in a note that he estimates U.S. debit revenue is at most about 10 percent of Visa's revenue. Sahrani said this means the lawsuit is likely to have only a limited effect on Visa's revenue as a whole. He also noted the lawsuit could last for years if it is not settled and goes to trial.<br/>桑贾伊·萨赫拉尼是总部位于纽约市的KBW投资公司的财务顾问。他最近在一份报告中告诉投资者，他估计美国借记卡收入最多约占Visa收入的10%。萨赫拉尼表示，这意味着该诉讼可能对Visa的整体收入影响有限。他还指出，如果该诉讼未能和解，并进入审判阶段，可能会持续数年。</p><p>Financial records show Visa processed $3.3 trillion in transactions on its network during the three months ending on June 30. This was an increase of 7.4 percent from a year earlier. U.S. payments grew by 5.1 percent, which is a lot faster than U.S. economic growth.<br/>财务记录显示，在截至6月30日的三个月里，Visa在其网络上处理了3.3万亿美元的交易。这比去年同期增长了7.4%。美国的支付增长了5.1%，远远快于美国的经济增长。</p><p>I'm Bryan Lynn.<br/>我是布莱恩·林恩。(21VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Video Game Maker Nintendo to Open a Museum (2024/9/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/video-game-maker-nintendo-to-open-a-museum.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">27 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The Japanese video game company Nintendo is opening a <strong>museum</strong> that will teach visitors about its history.</p>
<p>At the museum, fans of Super Mario, The Legend of Zelda and the Game Boy and Switch devices can learn more about one of the world's most famous game makers.</p>
<p>The museum is in Uji near the company's Kyoto headquarters.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This photo taken on September 24, 2024, shows large console-shaped pillows in the gift shop during a media preview of the new Nintendo Museum, located inside a renovated old factory, in the suburbs of Kyoto. (Photo by Richard A. Brooks / AFP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/792b96ee-adfe-4604-8b60-534cdbf5b75e_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This photo taken on September 24, 2024, shows large console-shaped pillows in the gift shop during a media preview of the new Nintendo Museum, located inside a renovated old factory, in the suburbs of Kyoto. (Photo by Richard A. Brooks / AFP)</span></div>
<p>It will show the many developments of Nintendo, which was founded in 1889. The company began as a maker of "hanafuda" playing cards and has since grown to offer many kinds of electronic games.</p>
<p>Shigeru Miyamoto is an executive fellow at Nintendo and the creator of Super Mario. Miyamoto said the museum was meant to deepen understanding of the company.</p>
<p>"If making products while protecting <strong>concepts</strong> such as family, fun and ease of understanding is rooted in our employees then the new Nintendo will continue to grow," he told reporters recently.</p>
<p>The museum, which opens to the public October 2, is in the place where the company used to make playing cards and was a center for product repairs. On its website,<strong> tickets </strong>to the museum are sold out for two months after the opening.</p>
<p>In addition to showing famous devices such as the Wii console and the handheld Game Boy, visitors will be able to see lesser-known products. These include the Mamaberica baby <strong>stroller</strong> and the Copilas printer.</p>
<p>The museum also offers special experiences. Visitors, for example, will be able to work together to play the video game Super Mario Bros. on an oversized Family Computer controller.</p>
<p>The company's push into mobile gaming has dropped off. But other efforts by Nintendo to grow beyond its main, or core, gaming business have made progress. The company has been opening stores and employing its <strong>characters</strong> in <strong>theme parks</strong> and movies.</p>
<p>The Switch console has been a major success with over 140 million devices in use. But, with sales slowing, investor attention is now on the possibility for a new device.</p>
<p>Nintendo aims to announce details of a possible new device in the current financial year, which ends in March.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Sam Nussey and Irene Wang reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>museum </strong><em>– n.</em> a place where objects are exhibited or shown</p>
<p><strong>concept </strong><em>– n. </em>an abstract or generic idea</p>
<p><strong>ticket<em> </em></strong><em>–n.</em> paper or digital proof that you have paid for entry to a place like a museum, a show, movie or a sporting or music event</p>
<p><strong>stroller </strong><em>– n.</em> a kind of carriage designed as a chair in which a small child may be pushed</p>
<p><strong>character </strong><em>– n.</em> someone who appears in a book, movie, or video game</p>
<p><strong>theme park</strong> –<em>n.</em> an amusement park that has rides, events and goods that are all based on a product like a movie or video game</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Insights and Thoughts (2024/9/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/insights-and-thoughts.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">27 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Alvaro about the usage of the words “insight” and “thought.”</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/db098712-bf1e-4369-94bd-66c94d7af8b2_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>I want to ask you the difference between "insights" and "thoughts."</p>
<p>Best Regards,</p>
<p>Alvaro</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>Thank you for writing to us, Alvaro. I'm happy to answer this question.</p>
<p>“Thoughts” is a more general word than “insights.” A thought can be <strong>specific</strong>, as the following examples show:</p>
<p><em>I think we should go shopping tomorrow. </em></p>
<p><em>I think the dog might be hungry. </em></p>
<p>Thoughts can also be a collection of ideas about a subject. For example, we ask, “What are your thoughts on this?” That can mean we want people to share any ideas that they have about the subject. It can also mean that we want to know a person's opinion.</p>
<p>To have insight means to have a special understanding of something. A person with insight might notice something that most people do not see or understand. A person with insight might find a new solution to a problem. Insight often results from having a lot of experience with a <strong>particular</strong> subject or activity.</p>
<p>We can say that someone has “insight into someone or something.” For example, a good psychologist might have insight into why a person is feeling or behaving in a particular way.</p>
<p>Notice that with the noun “insight,” we often use the <strong>preposition</strong> “into” after it.</p>
<p>With “insight,” we often use the verbs “have” or “gain,” as in the following examples:</p>
<p><em>Their manager has a lot of insight into what the workers need. </em></p>
<p><em>By carefully watching the children's behavior, the researchers gained insight into how children try to solve problems. </em></p>
<p>The adjective form of “insight” is “insightful,” and the adjective form of “thought” is “thoughtful.” To be thoughtful has two meanings. It can mean to be kind or to take care of the needs of others. For example, a thoughtful person may listen carefully to a friend who is upset and then offer to help that person. So, when someone does something nice to help us, we might say:</p>
<p><em>Oh, that is so thoughtful of you. Thanks.</em></p>
<p>“Thoughtful” can also describe someone who has been thinking carefully.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your thoughts about American English? Do you have any insights to share? Or perhaps you simply have a question about particular words. We'd like to hear from you. Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please include where you are from in your email, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>specific </strong>–adj. the exact example of something and not any of other similar things</p>
<p><strong>particular </strong>–adj. the specific thing that is being discussed</p>
<p><strong>preposition </strong>–n. a small word that provides additional information about a noun, such as direction, degree or location</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>South Africa’s ‘Health Train’ Travels to Patients in Need (2024/9/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/south-africa-s-health-train-travels-to-patients-in-need.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In South Africa, a former passenger train now serves as a traveling medical center to provide health services to people in need.</p>
<p>The train is known as Phelophepa. In the Sesotho language, this means “good, clean, health.” It travels across South Africa to provide medical care to a mix of patients for whom usual heath care is unavailable or rare.</p>
<p>The train has been operating since South Africa's government ended its racist system of <strong>apartheid </strong>in the early 1990s. The train carries medical professionals around the country, even to the most rural villages. Officials say the service helps at least 375,000 South Africans each year.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A patient eyes are tested for lenses to be made for a new pair of glasses outside the Phelophepa eye clinic carriage, in Tembisa, east of Johannesburg, South Africa, Thursday, Aug. 22, 2024. (AP Photo/Themba Hadebe)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a7a36a9e-bcf4-46e9-ae80-d520efe75e9a_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A patient eyes are tested for lenses to be made for a new pair of glasses outside the Phelophepa eye clinic carriage, in Tembisa, east of Johannesburg, South Africa, Thursday, Aug. 22, 2024. (AP Photo/Themba Hadebe)</span></div>
<p>The care patients receive is separate from the government's main public health care system. That system serves an estimated 84 percent of the population. But government <strong>insurance</strong> plans are too costly for many people to pay for. South Africa is also dealing with an unemployment rate of more than 32 percent.</p>
<p>The government has taken some steps to help get more of the nation's population covered by public health insurance plans.</p>
<p>One of those came in May, when South African President Cyril Ramaphosa signed a law creating the country's National Health Insurance Act. The law aims to provide financial assistance to millions of South Africans who do not currently have health insurance. The program gets support from private insurers.</p>
<p>However, the National Health Insurance Act has been hotly debated. Critics have said government officials have not yet said how much the program will cost or where that money will come from. Economists have predicted the government will have to raise taxes to finance the law. Critics have urged the government to instead fix the country's public healthcare system.</p>
<p>Thethiwe Mahlangu has used the health train and recently spoke to The Associated Press about her experiences. She said local health clinics in her area – in the township of Tembisa, east of Johannesburg – cannot effectively serve her needs.</p>
<p>“There we are not treated well,” Mahlangu said. “We are made to sit in the sun for long periods. You can sit there from 7 a.m. until around 4 p.m. when the clinic closes.” She noted that when people ask about such issues, the medical workers say they simply need bigger hospitals.</p>
<p>When the train began in 1994, many Black people in South Africa still lived in rural villages with little availability to health centers. The time was a period of great change in South Africa. Today, the trains assist the growing populations of the capital, Pretoria, as well as Johannesburg, the country's economic center.</p>
<p>Shemona Kendiah is the train's manager. She told the AP trains can remain in one place for multiple days to see as many people as possible. Those going to major population centers – like Tembisa, for example – can end up staying up to two weeks. “The major metros are really struggling,” Kendiah said.</p>
<p>Mahlangu's trip resulted in her getting a new pair of glasses. She was among hundreds of people who received health services from the train on its latest stop.</p>
<p>Another patient, Jane Mabuza, got a full health examination as well as services for her teeth. She said she hopes the train will be able to reach many more people in other areas. “Here on the train you never hear that anything has been finished,” Mabuza added.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>apartheid </strong><em>– n. </em>a political system that existed in South Africa's past in which the white minority enjoyed government power over Black people who were made to live separately</p>
<p><strong>insurance</strong> <em>– n. </em>an agreement in which you pay a company to cover necessary costs in case there is an accident that causes damage or injuries</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>California Passed Law to Limit Phone Use in Schools (2024/9/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/california-passed-additional-legislation-to-limit-phone-use-in-schools.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Ashley Thompson</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A new state law will soon require school districts in California to create new rules restricting student smartphone use.</p>
<p>California Governor Gavin Newsom signed the law recently. The legislation makes California the latest state to try to reduce student phone <strong>access. </strong>Florida, Louisiana, Indiana, and several other states have also passed laws aimed at restricting student phone use at school.</p>
<p>The legislation is aimed at reducing <strong>distractions</strong> in the classroom. It is also meant to <strong>address</strong> the mental health effects that social media can have on children.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Student Keiran George uses her cellphone as she steps outside the Ramon C. Cortines School of Visual and Performing Arts High School in downtown Los Angeles on Tuesday, Aug. 13, 2024. (AP Photo/Damian Dovarganes)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/b7a212ba-e624-49ea-99a8-7e3220f09fda_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Student Keiran George uses her cellphone as she steps outside the Ramon C. Cortines School of Visual and Performing Arts High School in downtown Los Angeles on Tuesday, Aug. 13, 2024. (AP Photo/Damian Dovarganes)</span></div>
<p>Newsom said in a statement, “This new law will help students <strong>focus</strong> on <strong>academics</strong>, social development, and the world in front of them, not their screens, when they're in school."</p>
<p>But some critics of such policies worry the rules will make it harder for students to seek help if there is an emergency. Critics also argue that decisions on phone bans should be made by school districts, and not state governments.</p>
<p>The law requires districts to pass rules by July 1, 2026. The rules should limit or ban students from using smartphones on school grounds or while students are under the supervision of school employees.</p>
<p>The new law comes after Newsom signed an earlier law in 2019 permitting school districts to restrict student phone access.</p>
<p>In June, Newsom announced plans to seek more legislation. His announcement came after the U.S. surgeon general called on the United States Congress to require written warning on social media <strong>platforms</strong> describing their effects on young people. Newsom sent letters to districts in August, urging them to limit student device use in school.</p>
<p>Assembly member Josh Hoover represents the city of Folsom. Hoover introduced the bill with a group of lawmakers. Phones are restricted where Hoover's children attend school. He said many of the students do not always like the policy. He said that is in part a sign of how <strong>addictive</strong> phones can be.</p>
<p>Hoover said, "Any time you're talking about interrupting that addiction, it's certainly going to be hard for students sometimes."</p>
<p>Some parents have raised concerns that school cellphone bans could cut parents off from their children if there is an emergency, such as a school shooting.</p>
<p>The 2019 law permitting districts to restrict student phone access makes exceptions for emergencies. The new law does not change that. Some supporters of school phone restrictions say it may be safer to have phones off in an active shooter situation.</p>
<p>ShaKenya Edison is assistant superintendent with the Santa Barbara Unified School District. The district put in place a ban on student phone use in class during the 2023 to 2024 school year. She said teachers have noted that their students are paying closer attention in class since the start of the ban.</p>
<p>Tarik McFall is principal of Sutter Middle School in Folsom. He said that before his school's cellphone ban, students recorded fights, filmed TikTok videos and spent lunchtime looking at their phones.</p>
<p>The ban has “totally changed the culture” of the school, he said. Now, students spend more time talking to one another. “To have them put away, to have them power off...it has been a great thing,” McFall said.</p>
<p>I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Ashley Thompson adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>_________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>access </strong>–v. to get or use something</p>
<p><strong>distraction </strong>–n. something that is unimportant that takes attention away from something else that is more important</p>
<p><strong>address </strong>–v. to deal with in some way</p>
<p><strong>focus </strong>–v. to place one's attention on something</p>
<p><strong>academics </strong>–n. (pl.) things related to school and learning that are not connected to the real world</p>
<p><strong>platform </strong>–n. an online service that provides media material and advertisements and seeks a very large number of users</p>
<p><strong>addictive </strong>–adj. causing a strong, harmful need to regularly use something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Appositives: Renaming Words and Other Terms (2024/9/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/appositives-renaming-words-and-other-terms.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Imagine you want to improve your writing skills. Perhaps you would like to take an English test or use English in a business email.</p>
<p>Today on <em>Everyday Grammar</em>, we will talk about something that could help you: appositives.</p>
<p>We will explain the <strong>grammar</strong> rules behind appositives and demonstrate how to use them in sentences.</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a7714f3d-6c7a-4e53-a5ff-05253b589c8a_w268_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>Let us begin with a few definitions.</p>
<p><strong>Appositive definition</strong></p>
<p>An appositive is a word or group of words that renames something else.</p>
<p>An appositive is often a noun or noun phrase that helps explain or identify another noun or a pronoun.</p>
<p>Take this sentence, for example:</p>
<p><em>My best friend, <u>Ahmed</u>, studies English literature. </em></p>
<p>The subject of the sentence is <em>my best friend</em>. The name <em>Ahmed</em> is an appositive. It adds information to the sentence.</p>
<p>What is important is that the sentence is grammatically correct without the appositive.</p>
<p>So, our example without the appositive would read:</p>
<p><em>My best friend studies English literature. </em></p>
<p><strong>Another example</strong></p>
<p>Now, let us consider a more complex example.</p>
<p>Imagine you are reading a crime novel. Perhaps the book has the following lines.</p>
<p><em>Police questioned the next suspect, <u>the victim's <strong>ex-</strong>wife.</u> </em></p>
<p>In this example, <em>the victim's ex-wife </em>is the appositive. The words give readers more information about <em>the next suspect.</em></p>
<p>If the sentence did not have an appositive, it would have been written this way:</p>
<p><em>Police questioned the next suspect.</em></p>
<p><strong>Appositives can introduce a sentence</strong></p>
<p>Martha Kolln and Robert Funk wrote a famous book on English grammar. In it, they note that if an appositive renames the subject of a sentence, it can <strong>introduce</strong> the same sentence.</p>
<p>Kolln and Funk say the following description, by Michael D. Lemonick and Andrea Dorfman, is a good example of an introductory series of appositives. It is about epithets, or insulting terms, that people used to describe the Vikings of northern Europe.</p>
<p><u>“<em>Ravagers, despoilers, pagans, heathens</em></u><em> – such epithets pretty well <strong>summed up</strong> the Vikings for those who lived in the British Isles during <strong>medieval</strong> times.” </em></p>
<p>The nouns<em> ravagers, despoilers, pagans</em> and <em>heathens</em> are all <em>epithets</em>, the subject of the sentence.</p>
<p>The writers could have left out the list of nouns. Instead, they could have begun the sentence simply with the words <em>epithets such as, </em>or <em>such epithets. </em></p>
<p><strong>Why are appositives important?</strong></p>
<p>You might be asking yourself why this discussion is important.</p>
<p>The reason is this: using appositives correctly is one of the best ways to improve your writing style. Appositives can help writers change the rhythm or order of a sentence. In other words, appositives help make sentences more interesting.</p>
<p>Think back to our first example:</p>
<p><em>My best friend, <u>Ahmed</u>, studies English literature.</em></p>
<p>If you were to write the example as two separate sentences, it might be something like this:</p>
<p><em>My best friend studies English literature. My friend's name is Ahmed.</em></p>
<p>These sentences are grammatically correct. But they are repetitive. In other words, they are less interesting to read.</p>
<p><strong>What can you do?</strong></p>
<p>The next time you are reading, try to find examples of appositives. Ask yourself why the writer might have chosen to use them.</p>
<p>When you <strong>practice</strong> writing in English – perhaps for a test or business purposes – try to use appositives in certain places. They will help make your writing smooth and clear – if you use them correctly!</p>
<p>We will leave you with a famous example. In his book <em>A History of the English-Speaking Peoples, </em>Winston Churchill wrote the following words about Britain's Queen Victoria.</p>
<p><em>High <strong>devotion</strong> to her royal task, domestic <strong>virtues</strong>, evident <strong>sincerity</strong> of nature, a piercing and sometime <strong>disconcerting</strong> truthfulness – all these qualities of the Queen's had long impressed themselves upon the mind of her subjects.</em></p>
<p>Can you identify the appositive? Can you identify the subject of the sentence? Write to us in the Comments Section of our website.</p>
<p>I'm Anne Ball.</p>
<p>And I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>John Russell wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. George Grow was the editor. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>grammar </strong><em>– n.</em> the study of words and their uses and relations in sentences</p>
<p><strong>ex- </strong><em>prefix</em> meaning former</p>
<p><strong>introduce </strong><em>– v.</em> to lead to or present</p>
<p><strong>sum up</strong> – <em>phrasal verb</em> to describe or show the most important parts or qualities of (someone or something) in a brief or simple way</p>
<p><strong>medieval </strong>– <em>adj.</em> of or relating to Europe's Middle Ages</p>
<p><strong>practice</strong> – <em>v.</em> to work at repeatedly so as to become skilled</p>
<p><strong>devotion </strong>–<em> n. </em>a feeling of strong love or loyalty</p>
<p><strong>virtue </strong><em>– n. </em>morally good behavior</p>
<p><strong>sincerity </strong>–<em> n. </em>having or showing true feelings that are expressed in an honest way</p>
<p><strong>disconcerting </strong><em>– adj. </em>unnerving or troubling; concerning</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Find Energy Jets Among the Universe’s Largest Structures (2024/9/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/scientists-find-energy-jets-among-the-universe-s-largest-structures.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">25 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists say they have found the largest <strong>jets </strong>of energy ever observed shooting out of a black hole in a distant galaxy.</p>
<p>The jets extend 23 million light years from end to end. That is about 140 times the width of our Milky Way Galaxy. The galaxy responsible is estimated to be 7.5 billion light years from Earth.</p>
<p>The scientists observed the structures using the Low-Frequency Array, or LOFAR, radio telescope network centered in the Netherlands.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="This undated image provided by Caltech, taken by Europe's LOFAR (LOw Frequency ARray) radio telescope, shows the longest known pair of black hole jets, as reported in the journal Nature. (LOFAR Collaboration/Martijn Oei/Caltech via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/d50af00e-c5a9-4342-81cb-cefac8ae9099_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">This undated image provided by Caltech, taken by Europe's LOFAR (LOw Frequency ARray) radio telescope, shows the longest known pair of black hole jets, as reported in the journal Nature. (LOFAR Collaboration/Martijn Oei/Caltech via AP)</span></div>
<p>Violent, highly energetic events around a black hole in the galaxy are the cause of the jets. A black hole is often the remains of a super-massive star that collapses. It is so massive that even light cannot escape its powerful gravity.</p>
<p>Researchers have named the energy jets Porphyrion after a giant in ancient Greek <strong>mythology</strong>. Porphyrion is 30 percent longer than any other known energy jet.</p>
<p>Martijn Oei of Caltech is an <strong>astrophysicist</strong> and lead writer of the study published in <em>Nature</em>. Oei said, “Jet systems like Porphyrion appear to be among the most energetic <strong>spectacles</strong> that have occurred in the universe since the Big Bang.”</p>
<p>The Big Bang is the event that scientists say marked the beginning of the universe.</p>
<p>Astrophysicist Martin Hardcastle of the University of Hertfordshire in English was also a writer of the study. He explained how scientists believe the jets formed.</p>
<p>“The general understanding is that jets are formed when magnetized material falls onto a <strong>rotating</strong> black hole,” he said.</p>
<p>He said the jets “need to be sustained by a continued infall of matter into the black hole, something on the order of one solar mass (the mass of the sun) a year of material.”</p>
<p>However, although they are huge, the jets cannot be seen in visible light. Scientists used radio telescopes to find them. They start small and grow over time, the scientists say.</p>
<p>“We've known for a while that black holes can <strong>generate</strong> these jets. But what is interesting is that to generate a large structure like this, the jets must stay on for a long time — about a billion years,” Hardcastle said.</p>
<p>The Porphyrion jets reach far beyond their home galaxy. Their total output of energy is equal to trillions of stars like the sun.</p>
<p>Oei said that amount of energy is similar to when two <strong>clusters</strong> of galaxies crash into one another, each containing thousands of galaxies.</p>
<p>Hardcastle said the discovery could increase knowledge of magnetic fields in the universe.</p>
<p>He said: “The fact that it extends so far from its parent black hole means that it may be carrying energy, particles and magnetic fields into the <strong>voids</strong> in the cosmic web...”</p>
<p>Such jets also could heat up gas in interstellar space, suppressing the formation of new stars or could damage planets that could hold life, the researchers said.</p>
<p>Scientists say our Milky Way Galaxy has a black hole at its center, but it does not have a jet, and it is not active.</p>
<p>However, the researchers noted that the most important finding of the study might be that black holes can create some of the largest structures in the universe.</p>
<p>“This means that individual black holes can have a sphere of influence that extends way beyond the galaxy in which they <strong>reside</strong>,” Oei added.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Will Dunham reported this story for Reuters news agency. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>jet </strong><em>–n. </em>a forceful rush of liquid, gas, or vapor especially through a narrow opening</p>
<p><strong>mythology </strong><em>–n.</em> ancient stories of a culture which are often the source of names in astronomy and other sciences</p>
<p><strong>astrophysicist</strong> <em>–n. </em>a scientist who studies stars and their physical and chemical qualities</p>
<p><strong>spectacle</strong> <em>–n.</em> something that is seen that creates wonder and amazement</p>
<p><strong>rotate </strong><em>–v.</em> to turn (around an axis or center)</p>
<p><strong>generate</strong> <em>–v.</em> to create electromagnetic, electric or heat energy</p>
<p><strong>cluster </strong><em>–n.</em> a number of related objects that form a group and which influence each other in some ways</p>
<p><strong>void </strong><em>–n.</em> emptiness</p>
<p><strong>reside </strong><em>–v.</em> to be in, on or at a place</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>New California Laws Aim to Prevent AI Harm during Elections (2024/9/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/new-california-laws-aim-to-prevent-ai-harm-during-elections.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>California recently enacted three legislative measures that ban the use of artificial intelligence (AI) tools to create false images and videos during election campaigns.</p>
<p>The laws – which are among the strongest in the U.S. – aim to reduce the use of AI to produce <strong>fake</strong> materials that could mislead voters during elections. California Governor Gavin Newsom <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.gov.ca.gov/2024/09/17/governor-newsom-signs-bills-to-combat-deepfake-election-content/">signed</a> the bills into law last week.</p>
<p>One of the main goals of the California measures is to fight the use of so-called deepfakes. A deepfake is a piece of video or audio created to make it appear that people in it are saying or doing things that they never said. Deepfakes have already been used in political campaigns around the world.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file photo, California Gov. Gavin Newsom speaks at the opening ceremony for Panda Ridge, the new exhibit at the San Diego Zoo, Aug. 8, 2024, in San Diego. (AP Photo/Derrick Tuskan, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f5ca21b1-8573-4e5c-b11e-f3482889aa3a_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this file photo, California Gov. Gavin Newsom speaks at the opening ceremony for Panda Ridge, the new exhibit at the San Diego Zoo, Aug. 8, 2024, in San Diego. (AP Photo/Derrick Tuskan, File)</span></div>
<p>One of the laws requires large online publishers to either remove or identify content that has been digitally created or changed in an effort to mislead voters during specific election periods.</p>
<p>Another requires any election advertisements that have been created or changed using AI methods to include a message informing the public that the material has been changed.</p>
<p>The third bill bans the publishing of certain kinds of misleading information about campaign activities within 120 days of an election.</p>
<p>All the California measures permit state law enforcement officials to take different forms of action against violators of the laws.</p>
<p>In a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.gov.ca.gov/2024/09/17/governor-newsom-signs-bills-to-combat-deepfake-election-content/">statement</a> issued after he signed the bills, Newsom said the measures were aimed at “safeguarding the <strong>integrity</strong> of elections.” He added, “It's critical that we ensure AI is not deployed to <strong>undermine</strong> the public's trust through disinformation – especially in today's <strong>fraught</strong> political climate.”</p>
<p>State lawmakers in several other U.S. states have passed similar measures in recent years to prevent deepfakes and misinformation during election campaigns. But critics argue that the laws are difficult to enforce and face numerous legal actions aimed at overturning them.</p>
<p>The Associated Press (AP) reports two of the new California measures immediately faced legal action seeking to block the legislation. One of the lawsuits argues that one of the measures <strong>censors</strong> expressions of free speech and permits anyone to take legal action against material they do not agree with.</p>
<p>That lawsuit was brought by an individual who created <strong>parody</strong> videos that received public attention online. This included changed audio of Vice President and Democratic presidential nominee Kamala Harris. At least one of the creator's videos was shared by Elon Musk, who owns the social media service X.</p>
<p>The governor's office told the AP the law does not ban <strong>satire</strong> and parody content. Instead, it requires material changed through AI methods to be clearly identified in videos, audio or images. A spokesman for Newsom, Izzy Gardon, said in a statement, “It's unclear why this conservative activist is suing California.” Gardon added that California's measure is nearly the same as laws passed in other states.</p>
<p>But critics – such as free speech activists and Musk – have called the new laws unconstitutional. They have argued they violate the U.S. Constitution's First Amendment, which protects speech and other personal freedoms.</p>
<p>Ilana Beller is with Public Citizen, a nonprofit group that seeks to protect individual rights. She told the AP she does not know how effective such laws will be in stopping election deepfakes. Beller noted her group closely follows U.S. measures related to deepfakes and none of them have yet been tested in court.</p>
<p>Some technology experts warn that the laws' effectiveness could be limited by the slow process of court actions. Misleading content, including deepfakes, might not be removed before harm has been done, the experts say. Even if it only takes a court a few days to act against such material, candidates and the election process may have already been hurt, Beller said.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters and the California Governor's office. </em></p>
<p><strong>______________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>fake </strong><em>– adj.</em> false or not real</p>
<p><strong>integrity </strong><em>– n. </em>the quality of being honest and having strong moral principles that you refuse to change</p>
<p><strong>undermine</strong> <em>– v. </em>to make someone less confident of make something weaker</p>
<p><strong>fraught </strong><em>– adj.</em> full of danger or difficulties</p>
<p><strong>censor </strong><em>– v. </em>to examine books, documents or films in an attempt to remove part that are offensive or not permitted by rules</p>
<p><strong>parody</strong> <em>– n. </em>a kind of content that copies someone's else's style in a funny way</p>
<p><strong>satire</strong> <em>– n. </em>the use of jokes and humor to criticize people or ideas</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Alcohol-free Beer Becomes More Popular in Germany  (2024/9/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/alcohol-free-beer-becomes-more-popular-in-germany.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The head brewmaster for Weihenstephan, the world's oldest <strong>brewery</strong>, has a secret.</p>
<p>The secret is that he really likes to drink alcohol-free beer.</p>
<p>Tobias Zollo is quick to say that he enjoys real beer more. Still, the expert brewer says he enjoys alcohol-free beer when he is working.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Head Brewmaster Tobias Zollo poses behind non alcoholic beer at the Weihenstephan brewery in Freising, Germany, Friday, Sept. 20, 2024. (AP Photo/Matthias Schrader)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/d9f66d8c-3f43-412d-ada9-beeedfd2e5f4_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Head Brewmaster Tobias Zollo poses behind non alcoholic beer at the Weihenstephan brewery in Freising, Germany, Friday, Sept. 20, 2024. (AP Photo/Matthias Schrader)</span></div>
<p>Alcohol-free beer has the same taste as usual beer but has fewer calories, he said.</p>
<p>The caloric reduction is a result of the brewery's process of evaporating the alcohol.</p>
<p>“You can't drink beer every day — unfortunately,” he joked recently at the Bavarian state brewery in the German town of Freising, located about 31 kilometers north of Munich.</p>
<p>Zollo is not alone in his enjoyment for alcohol-free beer. The drink has been gaining popularity in recent years as interest in the alcoholic version decreases.</p>
<p>Christian <strong>monks</strong> established Weihenstephan as a brewery in 1040. The operation began to produce non-alcoholic wheat beer and lager in the 1990s. Now those non-alcoholic drinks account for 10 percent of its total beer production. The same is true, generally, across Germany's beer industry.</p>
<p>“The people are unfortunately — I have to say that as a brewer — unfortunately drinking less beer,” Zollo said recently. He spoke the day before the start of Oktoberfest, a 16-day celebration held yearly in Munich.</p>
<p>Zollo said that if there is a way to offer a choice that has “the <strong>crisp</strong> and fresh taste from a<strong> typical</strong> Weihenstephan beer, but just as a non-alcoholic version, we want to do that.”</p>
<p>Celebrants can choose that version at all but two of the 18 large tents at the event. The alcohol-free beer will cost the same as an alcoholic beer.</p>
<p>Oktoberfest celebrant Mikael Caselitz of Munich seemed to approve of the drink choices.</p>
<p>“For people who don't like to drink alcohol and want to enjoy the Oktoberfest as well, I think it's a good <strong>option</strong>,” he said.</p>
<p>The 24-year-old continued, “Sometimes people feel like they have more fun with alcohol, which is not a good thing because you can also have fun without alcohol...If you want to come and drink alcohol-free beer, nobody will judge you.”</p>
<p>Oktoberfest began in the early 1800s.</p>
<p>This year marked the first time an alcohol-free beer garden opened in Munich. “Die Null,” which means “the zero” in German, served non-alcoholic beer and other alcohol-free drinks near the city's main train station this summer.</p>
<p>Walter Ko<i></i>776;nig is managing director of the Society of Hop Research. He said researchers have had to create special<strong> hops</strong> for alcohol-free beer. If brewers use the usual hops for alcohol-free beer, the special smell gets lost when the alcohol is reduced during the brewing process.</p>
<p>But alcohol-free beer buyers do not care about that, Ko<i></i>776;nig said recently as he prepared for Oktoberfest. He explained, “They only want to know that what they are tasting is as good as traditional beers with alcohol."</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Stefanie Dazio reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>__________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>brewery</strong> <em>-- n. </em>a place where beer is produced</p>
<p><strong>monk </strong><em>-- n. </em>a man who is a member of a religious order and lives in a monastery</p>
<p><strong>crisp</strong> <em>-- adj.</em> notably sharp and clear</p>
<p><strong>typical<em> </em></strong><em>-- adj.</em> having the essential characteristics of a group</p>
<p><strong>option</strong> <em>-- n.</em> something that may be chosen</p>
<p><strong>hops</strong> <em>-- n.</em> the dried flower clusters of the hemp family used especially to give a bitter flavor to beer</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Colleges Cut Programs Because of Budget Deficits, Fewer Students (2024/9/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/us-colleges-cut-programs-because-of-budget-deficits-fewer-students.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/><span class="datetime">24 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Christina Westman hoped to become a music <strong>therapist</strong> when she came to St. Cloud State University in Minnesota. But that became impossible when the college announced a plan to cut its music department along with 42 other study programs.</p>
<p>The move is part of a wave of program cuts among small and large colleges in the United States. The aim of the cuts is to deal with budget deficits. Causes for the deficits include less government money, rising operational costs and fewer students.</p>
<p>The cuts mean more than reduced budget deficits or job losses. “For me, it's really been <strong>anxiety-ridden</strong>,” said Westman. "It's just the fear of the unknown.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="University student Christina Westman poses at St. Cloud State University, Tuesday, July 30, 2024, in St. Cloud, Minn. (AP Photo/Adam Bettcher)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-f94e-08dcbd48370f_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">University student Christina Westman poses at St. Cloud State University, Tuesday, July 30, 2024, in St. Cloud, Minn. (AP Photo/Adam Bettcher)</span></div>
<p>At St. Cloud State, most students will be able to finish their degrees before the cuts. But Westman is <strong>transferring</strong> to Augsburg University in Minneapolis.</p>
<p><strong>Colleges are holding on</strong></p>
<p>For years, many colleges avoided making cuts, said Larry Lee. He was acting president of St. Cloud State but left last month to lead Blackburn College in Illinois.</p>
<p>The number of students <strong>enrolling</strong> in college dropped during the pandemic. But officials hoped the number would return to levels that existed before the COVID pandemic. They had used federal aid money to ease budget deficits.</p>
<p>“They were holding on, holding on,” Lee said.</p>
<p>The National Student Clearinghouse Research Center said students have begun to return to two-year community colleges. But the numbers for four-year colleges remain lower than expected. Even without growing concerns about the high cost of college and student debt, the population of young adults in the U.S. is shrinking.</p>
<p>Birth rates fell during the Great Recession of 2007 to 2009 and never recovered. Now smaller classes of high school students are preparing to finish and head off to college.</p>
<p>“It's very difficult math to overcome,” said Patrick Lane, a vice president at the Western Interstate Commission for Higher Education.</p>
<p>In addition, the new federal government's financial aid application has created more <strong>confusion</strong>. Millions of students are wondering where to go to college and how to pay for it.</p>
<p>Katharine Meyer is an expert with the Brown Center on Education Policy at the Brookings Institution. She said, “I think a lot of colleges are really concerned they're not going to make their enrollment targets.”</p>
<p>Many colleges like St. Cloud State had already faced budget problems. The university's enrollment rose to around 18,300 students in the autumn of 2020 before steadily falling to about 10,000 students in 2023. Its student population has stopped shrinking. But the budget deficit totaled $32 million over the past two years, forcing the sweeping cuts, Lee said.</p>
<p><strong>Some colleges are closing</strong></p>
<p>Some colleges have taken the more extreme step of closing.</p>
<p>That happened at the 1,000-student Birmingham-Southern College in Alabama, the 900-student Fontbonne University in Missouri, the 350-student Wells College in New York, and the 220-student Goddard College in Vermont.</p>
<p>Cuts, however, are more common. Two of North Carolina's public universities in Asheville and Greensboro plan to cut 14 programs including ancient Mediterranean studies and physics. Arkansas State University announced it was ending nine programs. Three of the 64 colleges in the State University of New York system have also cut programs because of low enrollment and budget problems.</p>
<p>Other schools cutting study programs include West Virginia University, Drake University in Iowa, the University of Nebraska campus in Kearney, North Dakota State University and nearby Dickinson State University.</p>
<p>Experts say it is just the beginning. Schools that are not making cuts now are examining their class offerings. At Pennsylvania State University, officials are looking for similar or under-enrolled programs to cut.</p>
<p><strong>Humanities and small programs affected</strong></p>
<p>The most affected programs are usually smaller ones and those in the humanities, which now have fewer students than 15 years ago.</p>
<p>“It's a humanitarian disaster for all of the <strong>faculty</strong> and <strong>staff</strong> involved, not to mention the students who want to pursue this stuff,” said Bryan Alexander, a Georgetown University senior scholar who has written on higher education. “It's an open question to what extent colleges and universities can cut their way to <strong>sustainability</strong>.”</p>
<p>Terry Vermillion recently retired after 34 years as a music professor at St. Cloud State. He said the cuts are hard to watch after the pandemic.</p>
<p>“We were just unable to really effectively teach music online, so there's a <strong>gap</strong>,” he said. “And, you know, we're just starting to come out of that gap and we're just starting to rebound a little bit. And then the cuts are coming.”</p>
<p>Lilly Rhodes is a music major at St. Cloud State. Rhodes said, “There's no musicians coming in, so when our seniors graduate, they go on, and our <strong>ensembles</strong> just keep getting smaller and smaller.”</p>
<p>“It's a little difficult to keep going if it's like this,” she added.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter Jr.</p>
<p>And I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Heather Hollingsworth reported this story for the Associated Press. Hai Do adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>__________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>therapist</strong><strong> </strong>–n. a person who treats people with medical conditions but is not a doctor and does not use drugs</p>
<p><strong>anxiety-ridden</strong> <em>–adj. </em>filled with nervousness, worry or tension</p>
<p><strong>transfer</strong> <em>–v.</em> to change enrollment from one school to another</p>
<p><strong>enroll</strong> –v. to go through the process of being accepted to a school</p>
<p><strong>confusion</strong> –n. a state of being unsure about something</p>
<p><strong>faculty </strong>–n. the teachers at a school, college or university</p>
<p><strong>staff </strong>–n. employees who are not faculty members</p>
<p><strong>sustainability </strong>–n. the ability to carry on business so that income meets or is greater than costs</p>
<p><strong>gap </strong>–n. something that is missing</p>
<p><strong>ensemble </strong>–n. a small group of musicians who play together</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Federal Bureau of Investigation: Rate of Violent Crimes in US Down in 2023 (2024/9/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/federal-bureau-of-investigation-rate-of-violent-crimes-in-us-down-in-2023.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">24 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p class="MsoBodyText">Violent crime decreased in the United States in 2023, a new report from the Federal Bureau of Investigation says.</p>
<p>The FBI released its report Monday. The report shows violent crime dropped an estimated three percent in 2023 from the year before. Murders dropped almost 12 percent.</p>
<p>Here is what the Associated Press (AP) said about the FBI report:</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - An FBI seal is seen on a wall on Aug. 10, 2022, in Omaha, Neb. Violent crime in the US dropped again in 2023, according to FBI statistics. (AP Photo/Charlie Neibergall, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/6b1f8b33-934e-4814-863d-23a51b656a27_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - An FBI seal is seen on a wall on Aug. 10, 2022, in Omaha, Neb. Violent crime in the US dropped again in 2023, according to FBI statistics. (AP Photo/Charlie Neibergall, File)</span></div>
<p><strong>The numbers</strong></p>
<p>Crime increased sharply during the coronavirus pandemic, with <strong>homicides</strong> increasing by nearly 30 percent in 2020 from the year before. That was the largest one-year increase since the FBI began keeping records. Experts said possible reasons for the rise include the huge <strong>disruption</strong> of the pandemic, gun violence, worries about the economy and intense <strong>stress</strong>.</p>
<p>The FBI data show that, in 2022, violent crime across the U.S. decreased to levels near those before the pandemic. Crime continued to decrease last year from 377 violent crimes per 100,000 people in 2022 to 364 per 100,000 people in 2023. Deputy Assistant Director Brian Griffith of the FBI's Criminal Justice Information Services Division said that rate is a little higher than the 2019 rate.</p>
<p>“Are we looking at crime rates at a return to pre-pandemic levels? I think a reasonable person would look at that and say, ‘Yes, that's what has happened,'” Griffith told the AP.</p>
<p>The largest cities, those with populations of one million or more, recorded the biggest drop in violent crime at almost seven percent. Agencies in communities of 250,000 to almost 500,000 people reported an increase of .3 percent, between 2022 and 2023.</p>
<p>Rape decreased more than nine percent while <strong>aggravated assault</strong> decreased nearly three percent. Overall, property crime decreased two percent, but automobile stealing increased 13 percent. There were about 319 motor vehicle thefts per 100,000 people in 2023. That was the largest increase since 2007.</p>
<p><strong>The FBI's data is not complete</strong></p>
<p>The FBI collects data through its Uniform Crime Reporting Program. Not all law enforcement agencies in the U.S. take part in the reporting. The 2023 report is based on data from more than 16,000 agencies, or more than 85 percent of those agencies in the FBI's program. The agencies included in the report protect almost 316 million people across America. And every agency with at least one million people in its <strong>jurisdiction</strong> provided a full year of data to the FBI, the report said.</p>
<p>“What you're not seeing in that number are a lot of very small agencies," Griffith said.</p>
<p><strong>Another crime report</strong></p>
<p>The FBI's findings are similar to the findings of the independent, nonprofit group, Council on Criminal Justice based in Washington, D.C. Earlier this year, it examined crimes rates across 39 U.S. cities. The group said that most violent crimes are at or below 2019 levels. It said that there were 13 percent fewer homicides across 29 cities that provided data during the first half of 2024 compared to the same period in 2023.</p>
<p>Another Justice Department report, the National Crime Victimization Survey, was released earlier this month. It said that the violent crime victimization rate rose from about 16 per 1,000 people in 2020 to 22.5 last year. The report said that the rate last year was not <strong>statistically</strong> different from the rate in 2019. It said the rate has dropped a lot since the 1990s.</p>
<p>The FBI report and the Crime Victimization Survey use different study methods and collect different kinds of information.</p>
<p>The victimization survey is carried out every year. It questions about 240,000 people. The FBI's data only includes crimes reported to police. The victimization study aims to record crimes that people did not report to police.</p>
<p>The victimization survey does not include data on murder or crimes against children under 12 years old.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>homicide</strong> <em>–n.</em> a killing of one human being by another</p>
<p><strong>disruption</strong> <em>–n.</em> a break or interruption in the normal course or continuation of some activity, process, etc.</p>
<p><strong>stress </strong><em>–n.</em> a physical, chemical, or emotional factor that causes bodily or mental tension</p>
<p><strong>aggravated assault </strong><em>–n. (legal) </em>an attack that is more serious than a simple attack and which is punished more severely</p>
<p><strong>jurisdiction </strong><em>–n. </em>the area in which a court or government agency may lawfully exercise its power</p>
<p><strong>statistically </strong><em>–adv. </em>related to numbers that represent information</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Reservoir in Poland Praised for Blocking major Flooding (2024/9/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/reservoir-in-poland-praised-for-blocking-major-flooding.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">24 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A <strong>reservoir</strong> in Poland built to prevent flooding is being praised for doing its job well after major floodwaters hit the area.</p>
<p>The anti-flood reservoir, called the Lower Raciborz Reservoir, sits on the Oder River. It is near the Polish cities of Opole and Wroclaw.</p>
<p>The project was first imagined in 1997, when the “flood of the century” hit the two cities, causing major damage. Work was completed on the water body in 2020.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This photo provided by the state company Polish Waters shows the Oder River flood waters channeled into the newly-built Lower Raciborz Reservoir in Raciborz, southwestern Poland, Sept. 23, 2024. (Polish Waters via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/d1e47e47-126b-4629-afcb-150a4b0d396c_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This photo provided by the state company Polish Waters shows the Oder River flood waters channeled into the newly-built Lower Raciborz Reservoir in Raciborz, southwestern Poland, Sept. 23, 2024. (Polish Waters via AP)</span></div>
<p>Over the past week, heavy rains have created major floodwaters across central Europe. Officials in Poland have struggled to keep waters from flowing out of the Oder River into nearby communities. The Associated Press reported the flooding across central Europe killed at least 24 people.</p>
<p>But people living in Opole and Wroclaw are now crediting the reservoir with saving the areas from severe flooding and destruction. Locals told the AP that the reservoir successfully flattened a huge wave created by the flooded Oder.</p>
<p>Some people who remembered the 1997 flood disaster watched carefully to see whether the newly finished reservoir would effectively do its job. And it did.</p>
<p>The reservoir's performance led to some public attention on social media. Some individuals gave the water body honorable names. These included “National Hero,” "King of Gold” and "Raciborz Reservoir the Great.” Other social media messages suggested the reservoir should be named after Poland's famous football goalkeeper Wojciech Szczesny.</p>
<p>The anti-flood reservoir was built following <strong>lessons</strong> learned from the severe flooding of 1997. The project took about $520 million to build. Part of the money came from the European Union and World Bank. Two villages had to be resettled to complete the reservoir.</p>
<p>When it opened in 2020, the water body covered 26 square kilometers of wildland. It can hold up to 185 million cubic meters of floodwater.</p>
<p>People living in Opole and Wroclaw said the Oder reached extreme heights. But, they said, the reservoir caught the floodwaters. Water never flowed out into the streets.</p>
<p>Some areas not covered by the reservoir system suffered heavy flooding.</p>
<p>Last week, European Union chief Ursula van der Leyen promised the EU would provide billions of dollars in aid to affected communities in Central Europe. Among other nations suffering severe flood destruction are Austria, the Czech Republic, Hungary and Slovakia.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press and Reuters.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>reservoir </strong><em>– n. </em>a large natural or manmade lake used as a source of water supply</p>
<p><strong>lesson </strong><em>– n. </em>an experience that teaches you something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Ways to Protect Yourself from Injures while Walking Your Dog (2024/9/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/ways-to-protect-yourself-from-injures-while-walking-your-dog.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">23 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Over the past 20 years, injuries related to dog walking have been on the rise among adults and children in the U.S., Johns Hopkins University researchers say.</p>
<p>The most common kinds of injuries include broken bones, <strong>sprains</strong> and head <strong>trauma</strong>.</p>
<p>From 2001 to 2020, the estimated number of adults treated for dog-walking injuries at emergency departments increased from 7,300 to 32,300 a year. That comes from lead researcher Ridge Maxson who spoke to the Associated Press.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Susannah Johnston, of Croton-on-Hudson, N.Y., walks her dog Ellie on Sept. 8, 2024 in Norfolk, Conn. Johnston, a fit yoga instructor and strength trainer, has been injured three times in incidents involving walking her dog. (Vincent Cohan via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a6ae59ed-c46c-424f-972a-94766ab701ad_cx0_cy7_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Susannah Johnston, of Croton-on-Hudson, N.Y., walks her dog Ellie on Sept. 8, 2024 in Norfolk, Conn. Johnston, a fit yoga instructor and strength trainer, has been injured three times in incidents involving walking her dog. (Vincent Cohan via AP)</span></div>
<p>Of those patients, 75 percent were women. Forty-seven percent were adults between ages 40 and 64.</p>
<p>But that information is only for visits to emergency rooms. Maxson said many people might seek treatment at other healthcare centers for their injuries, including at primary care, specialty or urgent care <strong>clinics</strong>.</p>
<p>He noted that dog ownership has become increasingly common in the United States with about half of households having at least one dog.</p>
<p><strong>How to protect yourself </strong></p>
<p>Safe dog walking involves careful attention and, in some cases, special equipment. That can be especially true in bad weather conditions.</p>
<p>However, multitasking — doing several tasks at once — can be dangerous. That includes using your mobile phone while doing something else.</p>
<p>“You can't really afford to<strong> relax</strong> when you walk a powerfully built dog...You have to pay attention,” said Noel Holston, a dog owner in Athens, Georgia.</p>
<p>In the early 2000s, Holston was walking his 30-kilogram dog in a park near his home when a large bird made a noise. His dog did what dogs often do and ran after the bird. That pulled Holston off the sidewalk.</p>
<p>“I stepped into a hole and heard my left ankle snap. The pain was so intense. I almost passed out,” said Holston who is now 76 years old.</p>
<p>Running with a leashed dog is another risk no matter how well trained you think your dog is. The activity is especially dangerous with a dog that is easily surprised or very young. That is what happened to Robert Godosky in New York City.</p>
<p>“My dog...was relatively new to us. He <strong>got spooked</strong> and got in front of me, and I went flying over the dog...I ended up breaking two ribs,” he said.</p>
<p>There are other dangers in rural areas, said Steven Haywood, an emergency room doctor in Corinth, Mississippi.</p>
<p>“Getting struck by vehicles,” he said. “That's definitely the most life-threatening injury when people are walking their dogs.”</p>
<p>Areas like his have many roads without sidewalks or wide shoulders. That is especially dangerous when people wear dark clothes with no reflectors or lights and their animal also does not have such protection.</p>
<p>In addition to lights and reflectors, there are other things that can minimize dog-walking risks.</p>
<p>During snowy or icy weather, wear shoes with good <strong>treads</strong>. Consider wearing shoes with spikes or studs.</p>
<p>Maxson suggests using a non-<strong>retractable</strong> leash of 1.8 to 2.4 meters. “Longer leashes are more likely to get tangled around your legs and cause falls. Retractable leashes can sometimes make your dog more difficult to control.”</p>
<p>They can cause burns when held too close to the body, if they lengthen or retract too quickly.</p>
<p>In San Francisco, dog trainer Shoshi Parks recommends a no-pull harness with a leash clipped to a dog's chest rather than their back. It gives the walker more control and puts less strain on the dog.</p>
<p>Parks suggests holding a leash at your center of gravity, near your torso, hip or thigh. Put your hand through the loop of a leash and hold it a little lower down.</p>
<p>She calls retractable leashes “no go,” meaning you should not use them. They can cause burns when held too close to the body if they lengthen or retract too quickly.</p>
<p><strong>Other ways to protect yourself </strong></p>
<p>For people with problems balancing or moving around, experts suggest seeking help walking a dog, especially in bad weather. Helpers could include a neighbor, an older child or a professional dog walker.</p>
<p>Haywood and Maxson agreed that balance and strength-training exercises, especially for older adults, can help decrease the risk of falls and broken bones.</p>
<p>And they said working with a dog trainer helps not only the dog but the walker, who can learn to read their dog's body language better.</p>
<p>“Even young, healthy, strong people may have difficulty controlling larger breeds that aren't used to walking on a leash. Any exercise to give strength, give balance, is going to help,” Haywood said. “Make sure you can control the dog that you're walking.”</p>
<p>I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p>And I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Leanne Italie reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>__________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>sprain </strong><em>–n. </em>an injury to the tissue that connects bones at joints like the knees, wrists, elbows or ankles</p>
<p><strong>trauma</strong> <em>–n.</em> damage to tissue from force or a blow</p>
<p><strong>clinic </strong><em>–n.</em> a center that provides health care but is not as large as a hospital</p>
<p><strong>relax </strong><em>– v.</em> to make less tense or rigid; to make less severe or stringent</p>
<p><strong>get spooked </strong>–<em> v. (phrasal) </em>to become scared or frightened from something seen or heard</p>
<p><strong>tread </strong><em>– n.</em> the part of a shoe or boot sole that touches the ground</p>
<p><strong>retract </strong><em>– v.</em> to draw back or in</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Cholera Threatens Sudan as Civil War Continues (2024/9/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/cholera-threatens-sudan-as-civil-war-continues.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">23 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Cholera is spreading in Sudan as fighting between the military and a <strong>paramilitary </strong>group goes on past 17 months.</p>
<p>Health officials said the disease has killed at least 388 people and sickened 13,000 in the past two months.</p>
<p>The disease is spreading in areas flooded by recent heavy rainfall. The floods have especially affected eastern Sudan where millions of people displaced by war are seeking shelter.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE -People line up in front of a bakery during a cease-fire in Khartoum, Sudan, May 27, 2023. (AP Photo/Marwan Ali, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/c7c015ef-1dea-412e-b5c2-80483115db30_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE -People line up in front of a bakery during a cease-fire in Khartoum, Sudan, May 27, 2023. (AP Photo/Marwan Ali, File)</span></div>
<p>On Sunday, the Health Ministry said six people had died and about 400 sickened over the weekend. The ministry said the disease has spread to 10 of the country's 18 provinces with the eastern Kassala and al-Qadarif provinces most affected.</p>
<p>Cholera is a bacterial infection that causes diarrhea, leading to severe dehydration. The World Health Organization says it can lead to death within hours if not treated. The bacteria spread mainly through <strong>contaminated</strong> water and food.</p>
<p>In 2017, a major outbreak of the disease in Sudan killed 700 people and sickened about 22,000 in less than two months.</p>
<p>Increasing tension between the Sudanese army and the powerful paramilitary group, Rapid Support Forces, exploded into open warring in April last year.</p>
<p>The fighting wrecked the capital, Khartoum, and other urban areas. It has been marked by <strong>atrocities</strong> including mass rape and ethnic killings that could be considered war crimes and crimes against humanity. The United Nations and international rights groups say this is especially the case in the western area of Darfur, which has a history of violence.</p>
<p>The U.N. said at least 20,000 people have died and tens of thousands have been injured. However, rights groups and activists say the numbers are much higher.</p>
<p>The war also created what might be the world's largest displacement crisis at this time. The International Organization for Migration said more than 13 million people have fled their homes since the fighting began. That number includes over 2.3 million who fled to neighboring countries.</p>
<p>Seasonal floods and cholera have combined to create a major disaster in Sudan. Recent flooding killed at least 225 people and injured about 900 others, the Health Ministry said. The floods destroyed roads, bridges, and other public systems, and destroyed or damaged more than 76,000 houses, the ministry reported.</p>
<p>A group of international experts called the Famine Review Committee said famine had been confirmed in July in the Zamzam camp for displaced people. The camp is about 15 kilometers from North Darfur's capital of al-Fasher. The group said about 25.6 million people — more than half of Sudan's population — could face severe hunger this year.</p>
<p>Fighting is continuing in al-Fasher, the last major city in Darfur that the military still controls. The RSF has been trying to retake it since January.</p>
<p>Last week, the paramilitary force and its allied militias launched a new attack on the city. The military said its forces, aided by rebel groups pushed back the attack and killed hundreds of RSF fighters, including two top commanders.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Samy Magdy reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>paramilitary</strong> <em>–adj.</em> an armed group outside a country's military that is not under its command</p>
<p><strong>contaminated</strong> <em>–adj.</em> containing harmful, infectious or poisonous substances</p>
<p><strong>atrocity </strong><em>–n.</em> a cruel, violent and shocking action</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
