<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>VOA Special English</title>
        <link>https://www.21voa.com/special_english/</link>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <itunes:category>ESL</itunes:category>
        <itunes:author>VOA</itunes:author>
        <description>美国之音（以下称VOA）的英语节目，按播音速度可分为两种：Standard English （标准英语）和 Special English（特别英语）。

Special English 又叫“慢速英语”，是VOA 专为全世界非英语国家初学英语的听众安排的一种简易、规范的英语广播节目。该节目创始于50年代末期，是VOA 的专家们研究如何与世界各地的英语学习者进行交际的产物。它正式开播于1959年10月。当时只面向欧洲和中东，但由于这个节目适合许多国家英语学习者的需要，所以它的广播对象不久就扩大到世界其他地区，并很快在全世界范围内产生了广泛的影响。现在这个节目对欧洲、非洲和拉丁美洲每晚广播一次，对加勒比地区每晚广播一次（星期天除外），对东南亚广播次数最多，每天上午两次，晚上三次。

30多年来，VOA 为了办好Special English节目，进行了大量的调查研究工作，对播音速度、内容及用词范围都作了具体规定，基本上达到了既能为英语学习者提供信息，又不损害英语本身风格的目的，使之成为VOA 独具特色，拥有最大量听众的节目。

美国著名词汇学家S. B. Flexmer 指明了Special English的三条标准，也就是它所“特别”的地方：

1、它是一种由美国人最常用的1500个基本单词为主体构成的美国英语；

2、它用简短、明晰的句子写作和广播；

3、它以每分钟90个单词的速度，即2/3的Standard English（标准英语）速度进行广播。

Special English的节目可分为两大类：一类是新闻节目；一类是专题节目。

1．新闻节目

VOA Special English 的新闻广播向听众提供世界范围内的政治、经济、军事、外交、国际关系、宗教、天气以及各种重大事件和珍闻奇事等各个方面的信息，每天向东南亚地区广播五次，早上两次，晚上三次，每逢半点播出。

Special English新闻节目每次长约十分钟，大都播出十条左右新闻，近一千个单词，每条新闻多为一分钟，但偶尔也有长达两分钟的要闻。除头条新闻外，每条新闻都由一个电头引导，这样显得结构分明，条理清晰，适宜初学英语的人收听。在节目结束之前，播音员常常用三四句话重播其中三条新闻的提要以加深听众对要闻的印象。

Special English新闻中70%左右的内容与同时整点播出的Standard English新闻相同，但相同新闻的先后次序有所变动。每次节目的开头和结尾大同小异，格式比较固定。

2．专题节目（一）

Special English的专题节目（Feature Programs）,从时间上看，可分为两大类：一是每五分钟一次的专题，二是每十五分钟一次的专题。本节先介绍每项五分钟一次的专题材节目。

Special English五分钟一次的专题材节目安排在Special English新闻节目之后和（或）每十五分钟一次的专题材节目之前播出，每星期播七次。根据内容，可分为三个小类，即：Science Report（科学报道），逢星期一、三、五播出，每天播六遍；Agriculture Report（农业报道），逢星期二、四播出，每天播六遍；Words And Their Stories（词语掌故），逢星期六和星期天播出，每天播五遍。这三个专题材各具特色，具有相对的独立性，听众每听完一个节目，都会获得一个完整的印象。

Science Report（科学报道）这一专题材节目每周向听众介绍三篇有关现代科学技术最新发展情况的报道，涉及物理、化学、天文至高无上理、生物、环卫、心理、教育、医学和计算机等方面。适宜理工科大学生和科技工作者收集信息，积累资料，学习科技英语。

Agriculture Report（农业报道） Agriculture Report是为农业科技工作者和生产者安排的一个专题。它专门报道世界各国，特别是美国现代农业生产的最新成文汇报总务科 学家对农业生产某一方面的研究进展，以及他们对影响农业生产的某一自然现象进行分析和研究的近况。此外，它还经常向听众介绍发展中国家家业生产的一些有益经验等内容。

Words And Their Stories（词语掌故）这一专题节目，旨在向学习英语的听众介绍美国英语中生动有趣的词语和惯用法，并从科学研究和通俗词源学的角度来解释它们的含意、产生的背景及其在使用过程中的演变情况等。它通过讲故事的形式讲解每一个词语。这是VOA Special English中的优秀节目之一，是学习美国英语的极好材料。通过收听这一节目，听众不仅能学到娓娓动听的掌故和地道的美国英语，而且能增加美国的社会文化背景知识，历史传统与现状的了解。

VOA 为了更好地办好这个节目，便于听众收听学习，于1978年编辑出版了一本名为Words And Their Stories的书，共收集一百篇故事，作者是Herbert Sutcliffe, Harold Bermen 及VOA 该节目的部分编辑人员。在每次的实际广播中，播音员都以此书为蓝本，再根据需要对原稿进行适当增删。按每周两个故事计算，此书的一百个故事还不能满足一年的播音需要。于是编辑们就是重播部分词语掌故的同时，不断增加许多新的词语掌故，及时将词源学家的最新研究成果和不断增加的新词汇介绍给听众。收听实践证明，初学者在收听过程中必然会遇到许多人名、地名和一些较难的句子，有时甚至在听完之后还很难理解所播词语的确切含义及其汉语意思，为此，听众可参看1983年由中国对外翻译出版公司出版的该书英汉对照本中的有关部分。

3．专题节目（二）

VOA Special English的专题节目，除上节谈的五分钟一次的以外，还有本节要介绍的每十五分钟一次的节目。这类节目共有七个不同的小专题，以星期为单位循环，每天分四次复播出一个专题，但星期日和星期六的两个专题材每晚只播三遍，每次节目约十分钟，继每次五分钟的专题节目之后播出。

这类专题节目的基本结构是，在特定的伴声中先报告当次节目的名称，并扼要介绍其主要内容，然后播送节目正文。最后，在伴乐声中报告节目主持人和撰稿人的姓名，以邀请听众在下周的这个时间继续收听该节目而结束。

People in America（美国人物志） 这是有关美国历史名人的一个专题节目，每逢星期天晚上播出。它向听众介绍在美国历史上产生过重大影响、起过重要作用、作出了突出贡献的科学、文学、政治、或其他各方面的历史人物。节目一般都对他们的生平事迹进行简要的叙述，对其贡献作出评介，类似人物小传。有的重要人物事迹很多，必须用两次或几次的节目时间进行联播。对这样的节目要坚持收听，才会获得完整的印象。

TThis is America（今日美国） This Is America向听众介绍美国人民的生活、学习、工作和娱乐情况，是英语学习者解美国社会的一条渠道。该专题大都一个节目一个整体，每逢星期一晚播出。

Science in the News（科学新闻） 这一专题材主要对新近的科学技术新闻进行综述或摘要广播。向听众介绍世界各国在自然、医学、疾病、原子能、航天等方面的科研动态、成果、突破性进展及存在的困难。涉及当今世界人们普遍关心的重大问题，如核事故、航天飞机爆炸、自然灾害、环境污染和爱滋病等等。每逢星期二播出，每次播一到五条新闻摘要。

Explorations（自然探索） 每逢星期三晚上，听众可以收听到Explorations这一专题节目。该专题既涉及人类遨游太空、探索原子、研究自身、改造自然的现代技术，也报道发展中国家开发新资源，利用新工艺改善人民生活等方面的成就，其侧重点在各种科技实验和简易实用技术方面。该节目一般安排一段时间播一个系列，每次播出一个主题，以便能将某项新技术的研究和应用的全过程介绍给听众，电台还乐意为感兴趣的听众提供所需的文字材料。

The Making of a Nation（建国史话） 这一专题节目向听众介绍美利坚合众国从十三个殖民地区域到现代工业国的孕育、诞生以及形成超级大国的历史过程，并以历史为线索，特定的历史时期为单位，以重大的历史事件为主题材来叙述各个党派、各届总统和政府的历史作用与贡献。这是每个英语学习者都应了解的基本知识。The Making of a Nation每逢星期四播出。这是个系列节目，坚持收听，则有助于系统了解美国的历史概况。

American Mosaic（美国万花筒） American Mosaic是一个radio magazine（广播杂志）节目。该节目题材广泛、内容丰，展示着美国社会文化生活中比较轻松愉快的生活画面；听众收听该节目就如同在阅读一本图文并茂的杂志。它每次有三到五个小节目，涉及音乐、图书、技术和教育等方面的内容。我们既可以从中欣赏到著名歌唱的优秀歌曲，对美国音乐有所了解，又可以获取一些生动有趣的现代美国社会生活知识，随着播音员那亲切悦耳的声音步入美国风景如画的大好河山；同时还能听到世界各地的听众提出的有关英语语方文学等方面的问题和电台的解答。

American Stories（美国故事） 这一专题材节目安排在每星期六晚上播出。这样能使听众在学习和工作之余，得以轻松一下头脑。我们可以通过这一美国文学的“窗口”，接触各种流派、各类名家的文学作品。了解美国英语的时代特色，欣赏、学习美国人民运用语方的技巧，并从那些佳作名篇中获得艺术享受。该节目对短篇故事采取一次播一篇的方式，对中、长篇小说则先进行简写加工，再分几次播出全文。在播出故事正文之前，播音员常常先介绍故事的主要情节。对需要分几次节目时间播出的中长篇，在播第二或以后各部分之前，主持人还先重述已播部分的故事梗概，以唤起听众的回忆，使故事听起来更加连贯。</description>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          <item>
            <title>Sometimes Help Is Just 'A Phone Call Away' (2024/8/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/sometimes-help-is-just-a-phone-call-away.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>On today's show we talk about some expressions that deal with an important device in our lives – our phones.</p>
<p>With a smartphone, we can connect to the world. In fact, we can say smartphones <u>give us the world at our fingertips</u>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - U.S. actress Lindsay Lohan speaks on a telephone during a charity day at BGC Partners in the Canary Wharf business district in London, Britain September 12, 2016. (REUTERS/Toby Melville)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/F381F711-449B-40A3-9172-DEDE13989B93_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - U.S. actress Lindsay Lohan speaks on a telephone during a charity day at BGC Partners in the Canary Wharf business district in London, Britain September 12, 2016. (REUTERS/Toby Melville)</span></div>
<p>Needless to say, we use phones to stay in contact with the people in our lives. We use them to reach out to our friends, family, neighbors, and co-workers.</p>
<p>So, when we tell someone that we are <u>just a phone call away</u>, what we are really telling them is that we are available. We are there for them. We often use this expression to offer help to someone who is in a difficult situation or just in need of a friendly voice.</p>
<p>For example, let's say my friend is having a hard time with an advanced English course. The assignments are difficult, the material is hard to understand, and his teacher has not been answering his emails. I can say to him, “Look, if you ever need help, <u>I'm just a phone call away</u>. Call anytime!”</p>
<p>It's good to be available to some people some of the time.</p>
<p>But maybe not all the time.</p>
<p>We all have someone in our lives who contacts us too much. They may<u> blow up our phones</u> with a flood of calls and text messages. When <u>your phone blows up</u>, someone is trying to contact you repeatedly.</p>
<p>Here's an example. Let's say your neighbor, Jana, is having trouble with another neighbor, Jake. And you are in the middle of it. They are both <u>blowing up your phone</u> with calls and texts about their disagreement. You can tell them, “<u>Hold the phone</u>! Just stop! Talk to each other and work out your problems because I've had enough.”</p>
<p>The expression <u>hold the phone</u> is a way to say “wait” or “stop.” We use it when we hear something surprising or when we have had enough of a situation.</p>
<p>And it doesn't have to be about phone calls or texts. For example, let's say a friend tells me that my favorite singer is coming to town. I can't believe it! So, I can say, “<u>Hold the phone</u>! Are you serious?” It's like saying, "Hold on a minute!"</p>
<p>Now, let's go back to your arguing neighbors, Jana and Jake. Let's say they take your advice. They are willing to work out their problems. They try to call each other but the keep missing each other's calls. First Jana calls Jake, but he isn't available. Then Jake calls her back, but now Jana isn't available. They play <u>phone tag</u> like this for days until they finally speak to each other.</p>
<p><strong>Tag</strong> is a child's game. One person is “it” and must chase and tag, or touch, the other children. So, <u>phone tag</u> is when two people try to contact each other but their calls go unanswered.</p>
<p>At least Jake and Jana are trying to work out their problems. When it comes to keeping relationships happy in the neighborhood, they are not <u>phoning it in</u>.</p>
<p>When we <u>phone it in</u>, we don't try our best at something. We don't give our best efforts. For example, some people who lose interest in their jobs might start <u>phoning it in</u>. They stop trying and do not do their best work.</p>
<p>That's not the case with us here at VOA Learning English. we are not <u>phoning it in</u>. We work hard every day to bring you new learning English content.</p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this Words and Their Stories.</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>_______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>tag</strong> <em>– n.</em> a game in which the player who is it chases others and tries to touch one of them who then becomes it</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Small Farm Animals Are Growing in Popularity (2024/8/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/small-farm-animals-are-growing-in-popularity.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Americans are showing more interest in owning unusually small cows, goats, d<i><i>onkey</i></i>s and other small farm animals.</p>
<p>These animals are <strong>cute</strong>. They require less food and space. And they might even help cut the grass.</p>
<p>People who farm for fun are known as <strong>hobby</strong> farmers. They are looking for easy-to-raise farm animals. Some just like the idea of having a little pig or a small sheep as a pet.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Jamie Campion pets her one of her Southdown Babydoll sheep as it grazes in the backyard Wednesday morning, July 3, 2024. (AP Photo/George Walker IV)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-36fa-08dcbbc8accc_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Jamie Campion pets her one of her Southdown Babydoll sheep as it grazes in the backyard Wednesday morning, July 3, 2024. (AP Photo/George Walker IV)</span></div>
<p>The word for something that is unusually small is <strong>miniature</strong>.</p>
<p>Animal <strong>breeders</strong> say sales of these little farm animals have grown since the COVID-19 pandemic. At that time, more people started raising chickens at home for fun and fresh eggs. Like chickens, <strong>mini</strong> farm animals appeal to beginners who want to try a rural lifestyle.</p>
<p>Brian Gazda has a small farm in the western state of Idaho. He runs a YouTube channel called "Hobby Farm Guys" with two friends. Gazda said a lot of people do not have a large piece of land, but if they have a small area, “they can keep a miniature cow or a few miniature goats."</p>
<p>Martin Fysh works for Tractor Supply Company. He said social media has brought attention to mini farm animals. But Fysh thinks their popularity also shows a natural path among <strong>customers</strong> who started out by raising a few chickens.</p>
<p>"They're seen as part of the extended family," Fysh said.</p>
<p>Some owners of mini farm animals turn their hobbies into money-making activities. They show the animals to visitors, breed animals, and write about their farming experiences.</p>
<p>But newcomers to these activities need to weigh the pros and cons, or the good and bad effects, of hobby farming, Gazda and other hobby farmers said. Among the problems is the rising cost of miniature farm animals. While they are cute, they can also be aggressive.</p>
<p><strong>Mini goats</strong></p>
<p>Brittany Snow is a high school English teacher in Florida who owns several small-sized Nigerian dwarf goats. She dreamed of living on a farm. Her family recently moved to a rural area.</p>
<p>Thirty-two-year-old Snow started with four Nigerian Dwarf goats. Snow expected them to produce milk right away, but she learned that is not the case.</p>
<p>Angelia Alden is a business operations manager for the Miniature Dairy Goat Association. She said many people who buy mini goats sell them after a few years because their care presents problems and costs they did not expect. Rising animal feed costs can be one problem, as is finding farm animal medical care.</p>
<p><strong>Mini cows and d<i><i>onkey</i></i>s</strong></p>
<p>The mini farm animals can also be heavy. Some of the popular miniature animals on social media are cows that can weigh between 220 and 270 kilograms.</p>
<p>Twenty-eight-year-old Allie Sine started her own business breeding and selling mini cows in 2020. Social media videos showing some of her mini cows have gotten millions of views. Last year, she sold about 190 young cows. Each animal sold for between $2,000 and $30,000. "Everything just <strong>skyrocketed</strong>," Sine said.</p>
<p><strong>Mini d<i><i>onkey</i></i>s</strong></p>
<p>Kim Furches owns a farm with her husband, Ken, in West Jefferson, North Carolina. She has found similar success. Furches said they bred mini d<i><i>onkey</i></i>s for about 20 years. Before the pandemic, they would usually sell about eight d<i><i>onkey</i></i>s per year for less than a thousand dollars each. They now sell about 20 per year. The last mini d<i><i>onkey</i></i> sold for $7,500, Furches said.</p>
<p><strong>Sheep follow her around</strong></p>
<p>Earlier this year, Jamie Campion, who is 41, and her husband, Jeff, bought two Southdown Babydoll sheep from a local breeder near their home in Thompson's Station, Tennessee. The animals cost $800 each.</p>
<p>Jamie Campion said the sheep have become good at keeping their grass short. But more often, the sheep give her joy as would other pets. Once she took them for a walk in the snow. "They just followed right behind," she said. "There's a whole sheep and <strong>shepherd</strong> relationship.”</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Haleluya Hadero and Anne D'Inocenzio reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>cute</strong><strong> </strong>– adj. having a pleasing and usually youthful appearance</p>
<p><strong>miniature</strong> – <em>adj</em>. very small</p>
<p><strong>hobby</strong> – <em>n</em>. an activity that a person does for pleasure when not working</p>
<p><strong>breed</strong> – <em>v</em>. to keep and take care of animals or plants in order to produce more animals or plants of a particular kind</p>
<p><strong>mini- </strong>- <em>combining form</em> smaller or shorter than usual or normal</p>
<p><strong>skyrocket</strong> – <em>v</em>. to increase quickly to a very high level or amount</p>
<p><strong>customer </strong>–n. a person or business that pays for goods or services</p>
<p><strong>shepherd</strong> – <em>n</em>. a person whose job is to take care of sheep</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Combine and Integrate (2024/8/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/combine-and-integrate.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Simona in China about the words "combine" and "integrate."</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-30f2-08dcbc7c9511_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>Hi! I have a question. What is the difference between "combine" and "integrate?" Thank you!</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>Thank you for writing to us, Simona. I'm happy to answer this question.</p>
<p>"Combine" and "integrate" are similar in meaning. But, there are some small differences in usage.</p>
<p>The word "combine" is in our Learning English <em><a class="wsw__a" href="https://docs.voanews.eu/en-US-LEARN/2022/06/07/c4dbd6af-5f63-4f28-bc42-0bd175f4e4b4.pdf">Word Book</a></em>. We define it as a verb meaning to mix or bring together.</p>
<p>"Integrate" is not in our <em>Word Book</em>. <em>Merriam-Webster</em>'s dictionary says the word means to unite or form into a whole.</p>
<p>Now, let's look at the prefixes that begin each word. "Combine" begins with the prefix <em>co-</em>, such as in the word "copilot." This prefix means "with."</p>
<p>"Integrate" begins with the prefix <em>inter-</em> but with the letter "r" removed. This means "among" or "between," as in the word "international."</p>
<p>The prefix <em>co-</em> generally gives the sense of joining two or more things together. For example, oxygen combines with hydrogen to make water.<strong> </strong>However, "combine" can also mean to mix things together, such as mixing the <strong>ingredients</strong> in a <strong>recipe</strong>.</p>
<p>"Integrate" can be used that same way. But, it also can mean to add something to one or more other things and mix them so well that they fully unite.</p>
<p>For example, a school might try to integrate healthy foods into its school meals. Or, a jazz group might try to integrate elements of country music into their songs.</p>
<p>Notice that we use the preposition "into" with the word integrate. We say that we "integrate <em>x into y." </em>Here is another example:</p>
<p><em>New technologies can quickly become <u>integrated into our lives</u>. </em></p>
<p>But when we use "combine," we use the preposition "with." We say we "combine <em>x with y," </em>or "combine <em>x and y," </em>as in these examples:</p>
<p><em>The management team is trying to <u>combine youth with experience.</u></em></p>
<p><em>When you <u>combine talent and hard work</u>, you will see positive results. </em></p>
<p>"Integrate" can sometimes give a sense of deeper connection among two or more things than "combine." To see this, consider the word "integral." This word comes from the same root as ‘integrate.'</p>
<p>We say that something is an integral part of something else. This means that the things are deeply connected or important to each other. For example:</p>
<p><em>Bicycles are an <u>integral part of traffic and culture</u> in the Netherlands. </em></p>
<p><em>Fishing is an <u>integral part of the coastal economy</u>. </em></p>
<p>Last, both the words "integral" and "integration" have technical meanings in calculus, a field of mathematics.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, do you have a question about American English? You can ask about many different areas of English, such as speaking, listening, culture, and more. Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.<em> </em></p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><em>_______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>ingredient </strong><em>-n. </em>a food or item that goes into making a meal or dish</p>
<p><strong>recipe </strong><em>-n. </em>a set of directions for making a meal or dish and which includes a list of ingredients</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Propose Idea to Warm Mars (2024/8/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/scientists-propose-idea-to-warm-mars.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The idea of turning Mars into a livable world for humans is a common element of science fiction. But could such an action be done in real life?</p>
<p>Scientists are now proposing a new method to warm up Earth's planetary neighbor. The idea involves putting engineered particles made of iron or aluminum into the atmosphere. The goal is to trap escaping heat and direct sunlight toward the Martian surface.</p>
<p>The proposed idea would be to increase the natural greenhouse effect on Mars and raise its surface temperature by around 28 degrees Celsius over ten years.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This image taken by the Mars Exploration Rover Spirit's camera shows the Martian surface southwest of the rover's landing site. (REUTERS/NASA/JPL/Arizona State University/Cornell University/Handout)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/29242cac-bc73-4a80-aae2-cc620055d86a_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This image taken by the Mars Exploration Rover Spirit's camera shows the Martian surface southwest of the rover's landing site. (REUTERS/NASA/JPL/Arizona State University/Cornell University/Handout)</span></div>
<p>Such a change alone would not make Mars livable for people. But the scientists who developed the idea see it as a possible first step.</p>
<p>Edwin Kite of the University of Chicago helped lead the study that appeared recently in the publication <em>Science Advances</em>.</p>
<p>Kite described the process of terraforming – meaning to change a planet's environment to be more like Earth. "For Mars, warming the planet is a necessary, but insufficient, first step. Previous concepts have focused on releasing greenhouse gases, but these require large amounts of resources that are scarce on Mars," he said.</p>
<p>Kite added that climate modeling suggests the new idea of using engineered particles to warm Mars' atmosphere could work better than previous ideas. Kite explained that the work is important because it presents a possible method that could help future exploration plans.</p>
<p>NASA has sent robotic vehicles to explore the Martian surface and the InSight Lander to study the planet's interior. The U.S. space agency's Artemis program aims to put astronauts in the coming years on the moon's surface for the first time since 1972 in preparation for possible future human missions to Mars.</p>
<p>There are several barriers to human settlements on Mars. They include a lack of breathable oxygen, harmful ultraviolet radiation, salty soil, and dust storms that sometimes cover much of the planet. And Mars' cold temperatures are a serious issue.</p>
<p>The median Martian surface temperature is about minus-65 degrees Celsius. With its thin atmosphere, solar heat on the Martian surface easily escapes into space. The proposal would aim to permit liquid water to exist on the surface of Mars, which has water in the form of ice at its polar areas and its subsurface.</p>
<p>The scientists proposed continuously releasing tiny particles, called nanorods, into the atmosphere at a rate of about 30 liters per second for years.</p>
<p>Samaneh Ansari of Northwestern University in Illinois is the study's lead writer. Ansari said, "The idea is to either ship the material or better yet, ship the manufacturing tool and make the nanorods on the planet since iron and aluminum are abundant on the surface of Mars.”</p>
<p>The researchers are mindful of the possibility of unintended consequences in terraforming another world. Scientists, for instance, are eager to learn whether Mars has held life in the past - or perhaps currently, in the form of subsurface microbes.</p>
<p>Kite suggested that the costs and benefits of releasing nanorods are uncertain. For example, he said if Mars' soil has compounds that are harmful to life from Earth, then the benefit of warming Mars is zero.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Will Dunham reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>fiction </strong><em>– n.</em> an invented story</p>
<p><strong>greenhouse effect</strong> <em>– n.</em> warming of the surface and lower atmosphere of a planet that is caused by conversion of solar radiation into heat</p>
<p><strong>insufficient</strong> <em>– adj.</em> not enough, inadequate</p>
<p><strong>concept </strong>–<em> n.</em> an abstract or generic idea</p>
<p><strong>focus</strong><em> – v.</em> to concentrate attention or effort</p>
<p><strong>median </strong><em>-- n.</em><strong> </strong> the middle value of a range of values</p>
<p><strong>polar</strong> <em>– adj.</em> of or relating to a geographic pole</p>
<p><strong>abundant </strong><em>-- adj. </em>existing or occurring in large amounts</p>
<p><strong>consequence </strong><em>-- n.</em><strong> </strong>something produced by a cause</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Stonehenge's 'Altar Stone' Came from Far Away Scotland (2024/8/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/study-stonehenge-s-altar-stone-came-from-far-away-scotland.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p class="MsoBodyText">Researchers are one step closer to understanding how Britain's ancient circular structure, Stonehenge, was created.</p>
<p>The circle of huge rocks stands in southern England near the tip of northeast Scotland. Its so-called altar stone lies flat in the center. The new study finds that the huge altar stone did not come from nearby Wales as had been thought. The researchers say the rock instead was carried to the site from the more distant Scotland.</p>
<p><em>Nature</em> magazine published the study on Wednesday. The research did not show how the five-meter-long stone was carried to the site. But the scientists said it traveled about 740 kilometers.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Revelers gather at the ancient stone circle Stonehenge to celebrate the Summer Solstice, the longest day of the year, near Salisbury, England, Wednesday, June 21, 2023. (AP Photo/Kin Cheung, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4f74a5ce-9187-480f-b714-6bc5910bb0ab_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Revelers gather at the ancient stone circle Stonehenge to celebrate the Summer Solstice, the longest day of the year, near Salisbury, England, Wednesday, June 21, 2023. (AP Photo/Kin Cheung, File)</span></div>
<p>“It's a surprise that it's come from so far away,” said University of Exeter archaeologist Susan Greaney, who was not involved in the study.</p>
<p>For more than a hundred years, scientists believed that Stonehenge's central sandstone slab — long called the “altar stone" — came from much closer Wales. But a study last year by some of the researchers showed that the stone did not <strong>match </strong>the <strong>geology</strong> of Wales' sandstone formations. The actual source of the stone remained unknown until now.</p>
<p>For the study, the team tested mineral content in pieces of rock that had been collected in past digs. They found a match in the sandstone formations of Orcadian Basin in northeastern Scotland. The area includes parts of the end of the Scottish <strong>peninsula</strong> as well as the Orkney Islands.</p>
<p>“That <strong>geological</strong> ‘fingerprint' isn't repeated in any other area of <strong>sediment</strong> in the U.K.,” said Aberystwyth University geologist Nick Pearce, one of the study writers.</p>
<p>Greaney said the operational complexity of moving the stone so far suggests a high level of planning, cooperation and cultural connection between these two parts of ancient Britain.</p>
<p>Stonehenge went up around 5,000 years ago. Its design creates a kind of “window” that fully frames the sun as it rises on the summer <strong>solstice</strong>. The ancient purpose of the altar stone remains a mystery.</p>
<p>“Stonehenge isn't a settlement site, but a place of ceremony...,” said Heather Sebire, with English Heritage, an aid organization that cares for hundreds of historic British sites and structures. Sebire said that past archaeological digs had not uncovered evidence of daily living at Stonehenge.</p>
<p>Past research has shown cultural connections — such as similarities in <strong>pottery</strong> making — between the area around Stonehenge and Scotland's Orkney Islands. Other stones at Stonehenge came from western Wales.</p>
<p>Britain is home to other ancient stone circles. But, study writer Richard Bevins of Aberystwyth University says, “the thing that's <strong>unique</strong> about Stonehenge is the distance from which the stones have been sourced.”</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Christina Larson reported this story for The Associated Press. Caty Weaver adapted it for Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>match </strong>– <em>v. </em>to make or find the equal or the like of</p>
<p><strong>peninsula </strong>– <em>n. </em>a piece of land nearly surrounded by water or sticking out into the water</p>
<p><strong>geological </strong>– <em>adj. </em>of, relating to, or based on geology, a science that deals with the history of the earth and its life especially as recorded in rocks</p>
<p><strong>sediment </strong>– <em>n. </em>the material from a liquid that settles to the bottom</p>
<p><strong>solstice </strong>– <em>n. </em>either of the two points on the ecliptic at which its distance from the celestial equator is greatest and which is reached by the sun each year about June 21 and December 21</p>
<p><strong>pottery </strong>– <em>n. </em>clayware, especially earthenware as distinguished from porcelain and stoneware and from brick and tile</p>
<p><strong>unique </strong>– <em>adj. </em>being the only one; singular; unlike any other</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Japan’s Megaquake Warning Leads to Worry, Preparation (2024/8/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/japan-s-megaquake-warning-leads-to-worry-and-preparation.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>An agency of Japan's government recently gave its first-ever "megaquake advisory," or warning message.</p>
<p>The Japan Meteorological Agency (JMA) issued the warning after a powerful quake struck on August 8 off the southeastern coast of Japan's main island of Kyushu.</p>
<p>The <strong>magnitude</strong> 7.1 quake caused no deaths or severe damage, but the advisory has led to questions and a sense of worry. Japan is among the countries most hit by earthquakes. Now many citizens are wondering about when the next big quake will hit.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Stone lanterns fall at a shrine following a strong earthquake in Nichinan, Miyazaki prefecture, southern Japan, on Aug. 9, 2024. (Kyodo News via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-ad26-08dcbc8418b3_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Stone lanterns fall at a shrine following a strong earthquake in Nichinan, Miyazaki prefecture, southern Japan, on Aug. 9, 2024. (Kyodo News via AP)</span></div>
<p>The Associated Press recently explained what the advisory means, what people are being told to do:</p>
<p><strong>What is a megaquake advisory?</strong></p>
<p>JMA issued the advisory after deciding that the August 8 quake increased the likelihood of another major quake.</p>
<p>The agency said there is a 70 to 80 percent chance of a magnitude 8 or 9 quake associated with an area called the Nankai Trough within the next 30 years. The JMA said the probability of such an event is now "higher than normal."</p>
<p>Naoshi Hirata is a <strong>seismologist</strong> at the University of Tokyo and head of the JMA's group of experts. He said that the warning was not a prediction that a megaquake will happen at any specific time or place. He urged people to remain careful and prepared.</p>
<p><strong>What is the Nankai Trough?</strong></p>
<p>The <a class="wsw__a" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nankai_megathrust_earthquakes#/media/File:RuptureAreasNankaiMegathrust_2013.png" target="_self">Nankai Trough</a> is an undersea <strong>trench</strong>, or a deep valley on the ocean floor, that runs from the waters just off the southeastern coast of Kyushu, to Suruga Bay in central Japan. It is about 800 kilometers long.</p>
<p>Two large areas of the Earth's surface, the Philippine Sea <strong>Plate</strong> and the Eurasian Plate meet there. The Philippine plate slowly pulls down on the Eurasian plate and causes it to release energy from time to time. The JMA said that could lead to a megaquake and tsunami.</p>
<p>The last Nankai Trough quake was off Shikoku in 1946. The U.S. Geological Survey estimated its magnitude to be 8.3, and more than 1,400 people died.</p>
<p><strong>What is the government doing to prepare?</strong></p>
<p>As a result of the "megaquake advisory," Japanese Prime Minister Fumio Kishida canceled a trip and announced he would lead the government response. Local governments are studying their emergency plans.</p>
<p>Experts and officials have urged people to stay calm and to continue normal life but to prepare for a possible <strong>evacuation</strong>.</p>
<p>JMA experts said on August 12 they have so far found no abnormal activity that would suggest a megaquake.</p>
<p><strong>How are people reacting?</strong></p>
<p>The "megaquake advisory” is filled with scientific terms. It has worried people across the country. Some towns closed beaches and canceled yearly events. This has led to problems for travelers during Japan's Obon holiday week, a time for festivals and fireworks across the nation.</p>
<p>Some stores are running out of emergency supplies, even in areas where there is little risk. In the vacation town of Matsuyama city on the island of Shikoku, hotels and <strong>resorts</strong> studied their evacuation plans and emergency equipment. In another seaside town, Shirahama, outdoor hot springs were closed for a week and a fireworks festival was cancelled.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Mari Yamaguchi reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>magnitude </strong>– <em>n. </em>a number that shows the power of an earthquake</p>
<p><strong>seismologist </strong>–n. a person who studies the movements of the Earth such as earthquakes</p>
<p><strong>trench</strong> – <em>n</em>. a long, narrow hole in the ocean floor</p>
<p><strong>plate</strong> – <em>n</em>. one of the very large sections of the Earth's surface that are believed to move and cause earthquakes where they touch each other</p>
<p><strong>evacuate</strong> <em>– v. </em>to remove (someone) from a dangerous place</p>
<p><strong>resort </strong><em>–n</em>. a place where people can stay on vacation that includes a hotel, restaurants and activities</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Everyday Grammar: Beating Problems with Adverbs (2024/8/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/beating-problems-with-adverbs-everyday-grammar.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Adam Brock</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">15 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>
For VOA Learning English, this is Everyday Grammar.</p>
<p>This week, we're going to talk about some common problems with <strong>adverbs</strong>. Basically, adverbs are words that describe verbs, <strong>adjectives</strong>, and other adverbs. For example, "I ran quickly to the store." The adverb <em>quickly</em> describes the verb <em>run</em>.</p>
<p><strong>What is an adverb?</strong></p>
<div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1da030e9-e522-43e4-ac8d-a160b9a20b57_tv_w100_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>If a word is not easy to <strong>classify</strong> as a noun, verb, or adjective, it is probably an adverb. Some of the most common words in English are adverbs, including <em>up, so, just, then, how, now, also, here,</em> and<em> more.</em></p>
<p>Adverbs usually describe verbs. They express <em>when, how, where, and why</em> an action is done. Many adverbs are easy to find because they have the <em>–ly</em> ending, such as <em>quickly, surely, </em>and<em> certainly</em>. However, many adverbs do not have the <em>–ly</em> ending.</p>
<p>Adverbs can also describe adjectives. For example, "It is really cold today." In this example,<em> really</em> is an adverb that describes the adjective <em>cold</em>.</p>
<p>Adverbs can describe other adverbs. For example, "I will probably never go back." Here, the adverb <em>probably</em> describes the adverb <em>never</em>.</p>
<p><strong>Where do you put the adverb?</strong></p>
<p>Where do adverbs go in a sentence? Well, it depends.</p>
<p>Some adverbs can go almost anywhere in a sentence. Let us look at the adverb<em> sometimes</em>. It can go at the beginning of the sentence as in, "Sometimes, I walk to work." It can go after the subject: "I sometimes walk to work." Or it can go at the end of the sentence: "I walk to work sometimes."</p>
<p>Other adverbs can only go in the middle of a sentence. The adverb <em>probably</em> is an example. "She will <em>probably</em> leave early."</p>
<p>It is incorrect to say, "Probably she will leave early" or "She will leave early probably." Other such adverbs are <em>never, rarely, seldom,</em> and<em> always</em>. These are called <strong>mid-sentence adverbs</strong>. They usually go between the subject and the main verb. Different types of adverbs have different <a class="wsw__a" href="http://dictionary.cambridge.org/us/grammar/british-grammar/adverbs-and-adverb-phrases-position">sentence positions.</a></p>
<p><strong>What's the difference between adverbs and adjectives?</strong></p>
<p>Adjectives describe nouns, while adverbs describe verbs, adjectives, and other adverbs. Take the sentence, "She is careful." The adjective<em> careful</em> is describing the noun <em>she</em>. But if you said, "She walks carefully," the adverb <em>carefully</em> is describing the verb <em>walk</em>.</p>
<p><strong>Do you think this is hard? Hardly!</strong></p>
<p>Native speakers sometimes confuse adverbs and adjectives.</p>
<p>The words <em>hard </em>and<em> hardly</em> are especially difficult. <em>Hard</em> is both an adjective and an adverb. You can say "The bed was <em>hard</em>," using the adjective, which means it is "very firm." You can also say, "I worked <em>hard</em>," using the adverb, which means "with a lot of effort."</p>
<p><em>Hardly</em> is an adverb. A long time ago, it meant "in a hard manner," but its meaning has changed. People used to say "not hardly.” Over time, the word “not” disappeared. Since the 1500s, <em>hardly</em> has meant "almost not" or "barely." For example, "I hardly had time to finish the project." This conflicting meaning of <em>hard</em> and <em>hardly</em> has become the basis for jokes.</p>
<p>Listen to cartoon character Homer Simpson playing with the confusion between <em>hard</em> and <em>hardly</em>. In the scene, Homer's co-workers are replaced with robots.</p>
<p><em>"So you guys are my new co-workers. So working hard or hardly working? (laugh). I said, ‘Working hard or hardly working?' ‘Working hard or hardly working? WORKING HARD OR HARDLY WORKING?' IT'S A SIMPLE QUESTION!"</em></p>
<p>Homer is asking the robots if they are <em>working hard</em> (working with energy) or <em>hardly working</em> (only working a little). The robots, with their exact reasoning, do not understand the <strong>word play</strong> in the question.</p>
<p>We will leave you with a song that uses the adverb <em>softly </em>in an unexpected way. Listen to the Fugees' version of the classic song "Killing Me Softly with His Song."</p>
<p><em>Strumming my pain with his fingers</em></p>
<p><em>Singing my life with his words</em></p>
<p><em>Killing me softly with his song</em></p>
<p><em>Killing me softly with his song</em></p>
<p> </p>
<p>I'm Jonathan Evans.</p>
<p>And I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>See this excellent reference on adjectives and adverbs from <a class="wsw__a" href="https://owl.english.purdue.edu/owl/owlprint/536/" target="_blank">Purdue University's Online Writing Lab</a>. </em></p>
<p><em>Adam Brock wrote and produced this story. Jill Robbins was the editor.</em></p><div id="bottom">
<ins class="adsbygoogle" data-ad-client="ca-pub-3585518775245612" data-ad-format="auto" data-ad-slot="9284795419" data-full-width-responsive="true" style="display:block; text-align:center;"></ins>
<script>(adsbygoogle =window.adsbygoogle ||[]).push({});</script></div>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>adverb </strong>- <em>gramm. term.</em> a word that describes a verb, an adjective, another adverb, or a sentence and that is often used to show time, manner, place, or degree</p>
<p><strong>adjective </strong>- <em>gramm. term. a word that describes a noun or a pronoun</em></p>
<p><strong>classify</strong> – <em>v</em>. to consider (someone or something) as belonging to a particular group</p>
<p><strong>word play</strong> – <em>n</em>. playful or clever use of words<span style="font-size: 9pt;"></span></p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Hottest Oceans in 400 Years Endanger Great Barrier Reef (2024/8/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/study-hottest-oceans-in-400-years-endanger-great-barrier-reef.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">14 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>New research shows that water temperatures in and around Australia's Great Barrier Reef have risen to their warmest in 400 years over the past 10 years. The rising temperatures have put the world's largest reef under threat.</p>
<p>The Great Barrier Reef is the world's largest living ecosystem. It stretches for 2,400 kilometers off the coast of the northern state of Queensland.</p>
<p>A group of scientists at universities across Australia removed core samples from the coral. They examined the samples to measure summer ocean temperatures going back to the year 1618. The scientists combined information from core samples with ship and satellite <strong>data</strong> going back around 100 years.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this photo provided by the Great Barrier Reef Marine Park Authority the Hardy Reef is viewed from the air near the Whitsunday Islands, Australia, June 22, 2014. (Jumbo Aerial Photography/Great Barrier Reef Marine Park Authority via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-6b60-08dcb8a0a3a0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this photo provided by the Great Barrier Reef Marine Park Authority the Hardy Reef is viewed from the air near the Whitsunday Islands, Australia, June 22, 2014. (Jumbo Aerial Photography/Great Barrier Reef Marine Park Authority via AP)</span></div>
<p>The results show that ocean temperatures were unchanged for hundreds of years. But starting in 1900, the ocean temperatures began to rise. The research found that this is the result of human influence.</p>
<p>From 1960 to 2024, the study's writers observed an average yearly warming for January to March of 0.12 degrees Celsius per <strong>decade</strong>.</p>
<p>Since 2016, the reef has experienced five summers of mass coral bleaching. This is when large parts of the reef turn white due to <strong>heat stress</strong>. This also puts the coral at greater risk of death. The mass bleaching events happened during five of the six warmest years in the last four centuries, the study showed.</p>
<p>This research appeared on August 8 in the publication <em>Nature</em>.</p>
<p>"The world is losing one of its<strong> icons</strong>," said Benjamin Henley. He is with the University of Melbourne and is one of the study's co-writers.</p>
<p>"I find that to be an <strong>absolute</strong> tragedy. It's hard to understand how that can happen on our watch in our lifetime. So it's very sad,” Henley added.</p>
<p>The last temperature measurement, from January to March of this year, was the highest on record. Henley added that it was "head and shoulders" above any other year, meaning it was much higher.</p>
<p>Coral reefs are important for many reasons. They protect shorelines from <strong>erosion</strong>. They are home to thousands of kinds of fish. And they are an important part of the <strong>tourism</strong> industry<strong> </strong>in many countries. In Australia, the Great Barrier Reef adds $4.2 billion to the economy each year.</p>
<p>At least 54 countries and areas have experienced mass bleaching of their reefs since February 2023, as climate change warms the ocean's surface waters. That information comes from the U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Alasdair Pal</em> <em>reported this story for Reuters News Agency from Sydney, Australia. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><em>_____________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>e</strong><strong>cosystem</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n</em>. a system made up of an ecological community of living things interacting with their environment especially under natural conditions</p>
<p><strong>data </strong><em>– n</em>. factual information (such as measurements or statistics) used as a basis for reasoning, discussion, or calculation</p>
<p><strong>decade </strong><em>– n.</em> a period of 10 years</p>
<p><strong>heat stress </strong><em>– n</em>. sustained, warmer-than-average ocean temperatures</p>
<p><strong>icon </strong><em>– n. </em>a person or thing widely admired especially for having great influence or significance in a particular sphere</p>
<p><strong>absolute </strong><em>– adj</em>. free from doubt : having no exceptions</p>
<p><strong>erosion </strong><em>– n. </em>the process of wearing away by the action of water, wind, or glacial ice</p>
<p><strong>tourism </strong><em>– n. </em>the practice and business of traveling for recreation</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Tech Tip: Google Wallet Now Creates Digital IDs from Photos (2024/8/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/tech-tip-google-wallet-now-creates-digital-ids-from-photos.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">14 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Google has added a new tool that permits Android users to create digital versions of many kinds of identification (ID) cards and event passes for device <strong>wallets</strong>.</p>
<p>The tool is part of the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://wallet.google/">Google Wallet</a> <strong>app</strong>. It was first announced in May along with other changes to the latest operating system, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://developer.android.com/about/versions/15/get">Android 15</a>. The change <a class="wsw__a" href="https://support.google.com/wallet/answer/12060038#zippy=%2Cadd-items-from-a-photo-us-only">is explained</a> on a Google Wallet help website. The tool is now available for Android users in the United States who have the latest update of Google Wallet.</p>
<p>Digital wallets are designed to permit users to save non-physical versions of credit cards, personal IDs, membership passes and event tickets to their smartphones or other devices. Credit cards in wallets are linked directly to the banks that offer them and can be used to pay for things just like with a physical credit card.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="The Google Wallet logo is on display during a news conference, Thursday, May 26, 2011, in New York. (AP Photo/Mary Altaffer)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-891f-08dcbc7d06db_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">The Google Wallet logo is on display during a news conference, Thursday, May 26, 2011, in New York. (AP Photo/Mary Altaffer)</span></div>
<p>The use of digital wallets has expanded over the years as people depend more on digital IDs and other documents. Supporters say this reduces the need to carry a lot of cards in a physical wallet.</p>
<p>Until now, Google Wallet divided its digital document offerings into <strong>categories</strong>. Examples of these categories would be payment or gift cards, transportation passes for bus, train or air travel as well as official IDs.</p>
<p>Google's new tool is designed to permit device users to easily add many more kinds of documents to its Wallet service. These could include the kinds of passes many people carry in their physical wallets, such as <strong>gym </strong>memberships and medical or <strong>insurance </strong>cards.</p>
<p>These digital versions can be created by the user taking a picture of the physical document or by doing a screen capture of a digital version from a device. Some documents have an electronic <strong>barcode</strong> or QR code that can be entered into the Wallet app.</p>
<p>Google Wallet then uses artificial intelligence (AI) technology to use information from the photo to create a new digital pass.</p>
<p>The process of creating these digital documents is similar to adding new documents to Google Wallet. Users open the app and then click on “Add to Google Wallet (+).” The app then gives users a choice of what kind of card or pass to create. These include groups like “Payment Card,” “Transit Pass” or “ID Card.”</p>
<p>The new Google Wallet has a new category, called “Everything Else.” This offering was created to permit users to make digital copies of just about any card, pass or document they want to keep in their devices.</p>
<p>Google offers additional security steps to users storing official documents on Android devices. These “private passes” <a class="wsw__a" href="https://support.google.com/wallet/answer/13026633?hl=en">can also be added</a> to Google Wallet. Google says data contained in official digital documents is only saved on the device as an extra security measure.</p>
<p>People in some American states can create a digital ID to be used to officially prove their identity. Google <a class="wsw__a" href="https://support.google.com/wallet/answer/12436402?hl=en">explains</a> that this service is currently only available in Arizona, Colorado, Georgia and Maryland</p>
<p>There is a process users must follow to have their digital IDs <strong>verified</strong> by each state. The Transportation Security Administration (TSA) even accepts this form of state ID at <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.tsa.gov/travel/frequently-asked-questions/when-will-phased-digital-id-rollout-start-which-airportsstates">many major U.S. airports</a>.</p>
<p>Online technology website <em>Android Authority</em> recently <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.androidauthority.com/google-wallet-e-passport-support-3444362/">reported</a> Google Wallet will soon be equipped to also create digital versions of American passports. To create this official digital document, users would need to be holders of a U.S. government issued <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.dhs.gov/e-passports">e-Passport</a>.</p>
<p>The online publication said one of its writers discovered the Google Wallet passport is still in development at Google. <em>Android Authority </em>noted that having a passport saved in Google Wallet might remove the need to present an actual passport in some cases. However, the digital version is not designed to replace the physical passport, which the user should continue to carry.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from Google and </em><em>Android Authority.</em></p>
<p><strong>____________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>wallet</strong> <em>– n.</em> a small container used to carry money and credit cards, or a digital version used for the same purpose</p>
<p><strong>app </strong>–<em> n.</em> a computer program that is designed to do one task or set of tasks and is usually aimed at use on mobile devices</p>
<p><strong>category </strong><em>– n.</em> a group of people or things that are similar in some way</p>
<p><strong>gym (gymnasium) </strong>–n. a business where people go to exercise or play sports</p>
<p><strong>insurance</strong> <em>– n. </em>an agreement in which you pay a company to cover necessary costs in case there is an accident that causes damage or injuries</p>
<p><strong>barcode </strong><em>– n. </em>a small, printed pattern of thick and think black lines that is printed on products and documents</p>
<p><strong>verify </strong><em>– v. </em>to prove that something exists or is true</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Van Gogh’s The Starry Night Recreated in Bosnia’s Hills (2024/8/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/van-gogh-s-the-starry-night-recreated-in-bosnia-s-hills.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">14 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In the green hills of central Bosnia and Herzegovina, Halim Zukic has recreated a nature park in the form of one of Vincent van Gogh's most famous paintings, <em>The Starry Night</em>.</p>
<p>Zukic is from the town of Visoko. He decided to create a park after buying some land and a small house in a nearby village 20 years ago. But he had no clear idea of what the park should look like.</p>
<p>Then he saw <strong>tractors</strong> moving among fields of tall grass six years ago. He also saw that the tractors made circular shapes in the earth. This reminded him of similar shapes in Van Gogh's painting.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Still image from drone footage of The Starry Night nature park near Visoko, Bosnia and Herzegovina. Visoko businessman Halim Zukic created the park using 130,000 lavender bushes and other plants. (REUTERS production by Amel Emric, Branko Filipovic, Fedja Grulovic, Hedy Beloucif)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-1387-08dcbba549ca_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Still image from drone footage of The Starry Night nature park near Visoko, Bosnia and Herzegovina. Visoko businessman Halim Zukic created the park using 130,000 lavender bushes and other plants. (REUTERS production by Amel Emric, Branko Filipovic, Fedja Grulovic, Hedy Beloucif)</span></div>
<p>"From that moment, I was no longer <strong>in doubt</strong>," Zukic told Reuters news agency. But his effort took him time, money, and a lot of work.</p>
<p>To match the painting, Zukic brought in 130,000 lavender plants in six colors. Plants known for their <strong>aromas</strong> and medicinal uses were also planted. These include sage, echinacea, wormwood and chamomile. Together, they form colorful circles and help recreate the appearance of Van Gogh's painting.</p>
<p>Zukic also planted more trees and created 13 small lakes using water from the area.</p>
<p>Zukic did the work to form the land into the same shape as the painting by himself. He said recreating the painting has helped him better understand artists and the creative problems they face.</p>
<p>"This is the largest representation of The Starry Night, and the result of 20 years of dreams, of living those dreams to make them real," he said.</p>
<p>The park is 10 hectares in size. Zukic said it will show art programs and <strong>promote</strong> central Bosnia's cultural <strong>heritage</strong>. Zukic also wants the park to offer visitors a place to rest and think.</p>
<p>Van Gogh was born in 1853 in the Netherlands and died in 1890 in France.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Daria Sito-Sucic reported this story for Reuters news agency. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>tractor </strong><em>–n.</em> a vehicle with a strong motor that is used to pull things</p>
<p><strong>in doubt </strong><em>–phrase</em> to be in a state of indecision</p>
<p><strong>aroma </strong><em>–n.</em> a pleasing smell</p>
<p><strong>promote </strong><em>–v.</em> to tell people about something in an effort to make it more popular</p>
<p><strong>heritage </strong><em>–n</em>. the traditions, beliefs and objects that make up the history of a people</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>More US Schools Are Taking Breaks for Meditation (2024/8/14)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/more-us-schools-are-taking-breaks-for-meditation.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/><span class="datetime">13 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A class of third-grade students in the American state of Georgia had just a few days left until summer vacation would begin. And lunchtime was only an hour away.</p>
<p>But the children, who attend Roberta T. Smith Elementary School in the city of Rex, were in no hurry to leave. They were ready for one of their favorite parts of the day.</p>
<p>The children closed their eyes and moved their thumbs from their foreheads down to their hearts. “Listen to the <strong>chimes</strong>,” said the teacher, Kim Franklin. “Remember to breathe.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Aniyah Woods meditates in her classroom at Roberta T. Smith Elementary School, May 14, 2024, in Rex, Georgia. Schools across the U.S. have been introducing yoga, meditation and mindfulness exercises to help students manage stress and emotions. (AP Photo/Sharon Johnson)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-af6f-08dcb7d6d1ca_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Aniyah Woods meditates in her classroom at Roberta T. Smith Elementary School, May 14, 2024, in Rex, Georgia. Schools across the U.S. have been introducing yoga, meditation and mindfulness exercises to help students manage stress and emotions. (AP Photo/Sharon Johnson)</span></div>
<p>Across the country, schools like Smith Elementary have been introducing mental health sessions that include yoga, meditation and mindfulness exercises. Students do these exercises in addition to traditional math, reading and science classes.</p>
<p><strong>Mindfulness alongside math</strong></p>
<p>More American students have faced mental health struggles following the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
<p>In 2023, the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) reported that more than one-third of students were affected by feelings of long-term sadness and hopelessness. The agency suggested schools use mindfulness practices to help students deal with their stress and emotions.</p>
<p>“We know that our teenagers and <strong>adolescents</strong> have really <strong>strained</strong> in their mental health,” CDC Director Dr. Mandy Cohen told The Associated Press. “There are real skills that we can give our teens to make sure that they are <strong>coping</strong> with some big emotions.”</p>
<p><strong>Poor communities need more help</strong></p>
<p>Research has found that school-based mindfulness programs can help, especially in poor communities where students face higher levels of stress.</p>
<p>GreenLight Fund Atlanta helps school systems in the state of Georgia pay for a mindfulness program called Inner Explorer. That is the program used at Smith Elementary, where more than two-thirds of students are Black.</p>
<p>Joli Cooper is GreenLight Fund Atlanta's executive director. Cooper said it was important to the group to support communities of color in the area.</p>
<p>“When you look at the numbers, unfortunately, in Georgia, the number of children of color with suicidal thoughts and success is quite high,” Cooper said. “When you look at the number of psychologists available for these children, there are not enough <strong>psychologists</strong> of color.”</p>
<p>Information from the CDC shows that Black youth have the fastest-growing suicide rate among racial groups. Between 2007 and 2020, the suicide rate among Black children and teens between the ages of 10 to 17 increased by 144 percent.</p>
<p>Nationwide, children in schools that serve mostly students of color have less access to mental health professionals than children in schools that serve mostly white students.</p>
<p>The Inner Explorer program guides students and teachers through five-to-10-minute sessions of breathing, meditation and <strong>reflection</strong> several times a day. The program is used at over 100 school systems across the U.S.</p>
<p>Teachers and administrators say they have noticed a difference in their students since they've added mindfulness into their daily activities.</p>
<p>Nine-year-old Aniyah Woods is a student in Kim Franklin's class at Smith Elementary. Aniyah said the program has helped her “calm down” and “not stress anymore.” She added, “It made me feel peaceful.”</p>
<p>Malachi Smith, also 9, has used his exercises at home. His father helps guide him through meditation.</p>
<p>“You can relax... and when I calm myself down, I realize I am an excellent <strong>scholar</strong>,” Malachi said.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Sharon Johnson reported this story for The Associated Press. Hai Do adapted the story for Learning English.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"> </h2>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>chime</strong> - n. sound made by a set of bells</p>
<p><strong>adolescent</strong> - n. young person</p>
<p><strong>strain</strong> - v. to injure by too much tension</p>
<p><strong>psychologist</strong> - n. a scientist who specializes in the study and treatment of the mind and behavior</p>
<p><strong>reflection</strong> - n. careful thought about something</p>
<p><strong>scholar</strong> - n. an intelligent and well-educated person</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Student Uprising in Bangladesh Part of History of Political Protest (2024/8/14)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/student-uprising-in-bangladesh-part-of-history-of-political-protest.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">13 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Protests in Bangladesh that involved many students have led to the long-time prime minister fleeing the country.</p>
<p>The developments in the South Asian country are among the most recent incidents in which students and other young people played an important part. They have brought down governments or forced them to change policies. Recently, the Associated Press (AP) listed some historic protests:</p>
<p><strong>Bangladesh</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - University students shout slogans during a protest to demand justice for the victims killed in the recent countrywide deadly clashes and ask for their campuses to be opened, in Dhaka, Bangladesh, July 31, 2024. (AP Photo/Rajib Dhar), File)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-02da-08dcbb0605f0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - University students shout slogans during a protest to demand justice for the victims killed in the recent countrywide deadly clashes and ask for their campuses to be opened, in Dhaka, Bangladesh, July 31, 2024. (AP Photo/Rajib Dhar), File)
</span></div>
<p>In Bangladesh, weeks of protests against a system that set aside government jobs for the families of veterans with ruling party ties forced the prime minister from office.</p>
<p>The demonstrations against the <strong>quotas</strong> for government jobs began peacefully last month. Students are said to have led <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_RkLwIPvw">the protests</a> against the system for government jobs. They said it unfairly favored those with ties to the ruling party.</p>
<p>On July 15, student protesters fought with security officials and pro-government activists. Former Prime Minister Sheikh Hasina fled last week after the unrest. It is estimated that nearly 300 people died in the violence including students and police officers.</p>
<p><strong>Gota Go Gama protests in Sri Lanka</strong></p>
<p>As in Bangladesh, young people took part in widespread protests in Sri Lanka in 2022. The protesters blamed President Gotabaya Rajapaksa for the economic collapse of the country and corruption.</p>
<p>In April 2022, university students and other young people occupied an area next to the president's office in the capital Colombo. They demanded that the president and his government resign. They called the camp "Gota Go Gama," or "Gota Go Village," a play on Gotabaya's <strong>nickname</strong> "Gota."</p>
<p>The protest area grew. Gotabaya Rajapaksa held onto power until July, when protesters <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/sri-lankan-president-flees-protesters-storm-pm-s-office-/6657380.html">stormed his official residence</a>. He fled the country and later resigned.</p>
<p><strong>Athens Polytechnic uprising in Greece</strong></p>
<p>In November 1973, students at Athens Polytechnic university rose up against the military dictatorship that ruled Greece for more than six years.</p>
<p>Student protests began peacefully with a strike on November 14 of that year. The students stopped attending classes and occupied the <strong>campus</strong> at the university in Athens. By the next day, thousands from around Athens had joined to support the students and the demonstrations grew. People called for an end to the dictatorship.</p>
<p>On November 17, the military attacked the protestors, killing many students and injuring more than 1,100. After a series of events, Greece, the birthplace of democracy, returned to that form of government in 1974.</p>
<p><strong>Kent State demonstrations in the United States</strong></p>
<p>President Richard Nixon approved attacks on neutral Cambodia in April 1970. That policy was an attempt to close enemy supply lines, but it expanded the conflict. American students had already been protesting the U.S. involvement in Vietnam for years.</p>
<p>On May 4, hundreds of students at Ohio's Kent State University gathered to protest the bombing of Cambodia. Officials called in the Ohio National Guard to break up the protest.</p>
<p>The National Guard used tear gas as they moved forward. For reasons that are still not clear, some National Guard members opened fire on the crowd. Four students were killed, and nine others wounded.</p>
<p>The deaths were a defining moment for a nation divided over the long war, in which more than 58,000 Americans died.</p>
<p>One result was a strike by an estimated 4 million students across the U.S. About 900 colleges and universities closed temporarily. Historians argue that the events helped turn public opinion against the conflict in Southeast Asia.</p>
<p><strong>Soweto Uprising in South Africa</strong></p>
<p>In the struggle against white minority rule in South Africa, an important moment came in 1976 in the Soweto area of Johannesburg.</p>
<p>On June 16, Black students began to protest against being forced to study in Afrikaans, the language of the country's white rulers. The country was ruled under a system of racial separation called apartheid.</p>
<p>People in other areas of South Africa joined protests to express opposition to apartheid. The government's effort to control the uprising led to deaths estimated to be in the hundreds.</p>
<p>Worldwide attention and support for the protesters brought the end of apartheid years later. South Africa held democratic elections in 1994.</p>
<p><strong>Velvet Revolution in Czechoslovakia</strong></p>
<p>In 1989, the Communist governments of Eastern Europe were beginning to fail. After riot police suppressed a student protest in Prague on November 17, widespread demonstrations against the Communist rulers started in what was then known as Czechoslovakia.</p>
<p>On November 20, many others joined the students and an estimated 500,000 took to the streets of Prague.</p>
<p>Because the protests were non-violent, they were called the "Velvet Revolution." They led to the resignation of the Communist Party's leadership on November 28.</p>
<p>By December 10, Czechoslovakia had a new government. On December 29, parliament elected the writer Vaclav Havel, who had spent several years in prison. In 1992, Czechoslovakia peacefully split into two countries, the Czech Republic and Slovakia.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p>And I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>David Rising reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>quota </strong><em>–n.</em> an official limit or number of people who are permitted in a program or similar system</p>
<p><strong>nickname </strong><em>–n.</em> a name that is not someone's official name, but which people use for them</p>
<p><strong>campus </strong><em>–n.</em> the grounds of a school, business or organization</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Banksy Announces Series of New Works (2024/8/14)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/banksy-announces-series-of-new-works.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">13 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The famous street artist known as Banksy recently announced a new painting on another wall along a street in London. The image is of a<strong> rhinoceros</strong> that appears to be climbing on top of a real car parked in front of the mural.</p>
<p>The work is part of a new series of animal-centered murals that Banksy has created in the British capital. The collection includes paintings of elephants, a goat, a wolf, <strong>pelicans</strong> and more.</p>
<p>The secretive artist, who has never confirmed his official identity, has been announcing the new work on his Instagram social media page.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - An artwork by street artist Banksy, the seventh to released this week, depicting fish swimming around a Police Box, is pictured in the City of London, on August 11, 2024. (Photo by HENRY NICHOLLS / AFP) " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/39dc20d5-3d62-4497-9c62-2de3d8fe53ad_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - An artwork by street artist Banksy, the seventh to released this week, depicting fish swimming around a Police Box, is pictured in the City of London, on August 11, 2024. (Photo by HENRY NICHOLLS / AFP) </span></div>
<p>One of the pieces shows a group of the sharp-toothed fish called piranhas. That piece was painted on a police emergency call box near the Central Criminal Court, known as the Old Bailey.</p>
<p>A small crowd of people gathered near that artwork recently, taking photographs as some city workers placed barriers around it. A spokesman for the city government said it is considering how to <strong>preserve</strong> the work.</p>
<p>Another recent work is of pelicans eating fish. The mural was painted above the sign of a fish market in east London. Another Banksy painting appeared on a satellite dish. It showed a wolf, mouth open and head pointed up, as if howling.</p>
<p>However, that artwork did not remain in place long. A video posted online shows three men removing the piece and carrying it away hours after Banksy announced its existence.</p>
<p>Banksy began his career by <strong>spray-painting</strong> buildings in Bristol, England. He has since become one of the world's best-known artists. His work has sold for millions of dollars.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>John Russell adapted this story from an Associated Press report.</em></p>
<p>__________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>rhinoceros</strong><em> – n.</em> a large mammal of Africa and Asia that has one or two upright horns and thick skin with little hair</p>
<p><strong>pelican</strong><em> – n</em>. a kind of large fish-eating bird with a very large bill</p>
<p><strong>preserve </strong><em>– v.</em> to keep safe from harm or damage</p>
<p><strong>spray-paint </strong><em>– v.</em> to paint (something) with paint that is sprayed from a can</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>World's Largest 3D Printed Community Nears Completion (2024/8/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/world-s-largest-3d-printed-community-nears-completion.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Like other <strong>3D printers</strong>, the Vulcan printer puts down <strong>layer</strong> by layer of materials to build an object. However, this printer is more than 13.7 meters wide and prints homes for people to live in.</p>
<p>This summer, the robotic printer from the homebuilder ICON will complete the last of the 100 3D-printed houses in Wolf Ranch, a community about 48 kilometers from Austin, Texas.</p>
<p>ICON began printing the walls of what it says is the world's largest 3D-printed community in November 2022.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A drone image shows 3D-printed homes in the Wolf Ranch community in Georgetown, Texas, June 27, 2024. (REUTERS/Evan Garcia)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e75b838f-4b38-4102-ae01-fc31770c473a_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A drone image shows 3D-printed homes in the Wolf Ranch community in Georgetown, Texas, June 27, 2024. (REUTERS/Evan Garcia)</span></div>
<p>Compared to traditional homebuilding, the company says 3D printing is faster, less costly, requires fewer workers, and reduces waste.</p>
<p>Conner Jenkins, a project leader, said, "It brings a lot of <strong>efficiency</strong> to the trade market... So, when there were maybe five different crews coming in to build a wall system, we now have one crew and one robot."</p>
<p>After concrete powder, water, sand and other additives are mixed together and put into the printer, a device called a nozzle releases the concrete mixture. The process looks like toothpaste being put onto a toothbrush, as the printer builds up the house layer by layer along an exact path.</p>
<p>The three- to four-bedroom homes take about three weeks to finish printing, with the <strong>foundation</strong> and metal roofs put in place with traditional building methods.</p>
<p>Jenkins said the concrete walls are designed to be resistant to water, <strong>mold</strong>, insects and extreme weather.</p>
<p>Lawrence Nourzad, 32, and his girlfriend Angela Hontas, 29, purchased a Wolf Ranch home earlier this summer.</p>
<p>"It feels like a<strong> fortress</strong>," Nourzad said, adding that he was confident the home would hold up to severe weather conditions.</p>
<p>The walls also provide strong<strong> insulation</strong> from the Texas heat, the couple said. The materials keep the inside temperature cool even when the air conditioner is not put on high levels.</p>
<p>There was one other thing the 3D-printed walls seemed to protect against, however: a solid wireless internet connection.</p>
<p>Nourzad said, "Obviously these are really strong, thick walls. And that's what provides a lot of value for us as homeowners and keeps this thing really well-insulated in a Texas summer, but signal doesn't <strong>transfer</strong> through these walls very well."</p>
<p>To deal with this issue, an ICON spokeswoman said most Wolf Ranch homeowners use mesh internet routers. These routers broadcast a signal from several units placed throughout a home, whereas a traditional router sends a signal from one device.</p>
<p>The 3D-printed homes at Wolf Ranch cost from $450,000 to nearly $600,000. Developers said a little more than one quarter of the 100 homes have been sold.</p>
<p>ICON, which 3D-printed its first home in Austin in 2018, hopes to one day take its technology to the Moon.</p>
<p>NASA, as part of its Artemis Moon exploration program, has an agreement for ICON to develop a system capable of building landing pads, shelters, and other structures on the moon's surface.</p>
<p>I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>Evan Garcia reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>3D printer</strong> – n. a device used to manufacture objects by depositing material in layers according to a pattern or model</p>
<p><strong>layer </strong>– n. a quantity of material covering a surface</p>
<p><strong>efficiency</strong> – n. the capability of producing desired results with little or no waste</p>
<p><strong>foundation </strong><em>-- n.</em><strong> </strong>a body or ground upon which something is built up</p>
<p><strong>mold </strong>– n. a growth produced especially on damp or decaying organic matter</p>
<p><strong>fortress</strong> – n. a large and permanent fortification</p>
<p><strong>insulation</strong> – n. special material that prevents transfer of electricity, heat, or sound</p>
<p><strong>transfer</strong> <em>-- v.</em> <strong> </strong>to move or convey from one place or situation to another</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Moon’s Thin Atmosphere Likely Formed by Meteorite Strikes (2024/8/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/study-moon-s-thin-atmosphere-likely-formed-by-meteorite-strikes.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists say new examinations of soil collected on the moon suggest its atmosphere might have been created by repeated <strong>meteorite</strong> strikes.</p>
<p>Researchers studying the moon first used instruments to confirm it had an atmosphere in the early 1970s. The American space agency NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/moon/facts/">explains</a> the moon's atmosphere is “very thin and weak.” It is technically considered an “<strong>exosphere</strong>.”</p>
<p>The newly examined soil was collected by NASA astronauts during America's Apollo program from 1969 to 1972. The trips resulted in astronauts capturing about 382 kilograms of rocks and soil, called samples.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A view of the moon over a mountain in Garmisch-Partenkirchen, Germany, July 19, 2024. (REUTERS/Angelika Warmuth)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-4bdb-08dcb88f0702_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A view of the moon over a mountain in Garmisch-Partenkirchen, Germany, July 19, 2024. (REUTERS/Angelika Warmuth)</span></div>
<p>Instead of attempting to measure the moon's atmosphere in a direct way, investigators looked to the old soil material. They theorized that the soil should contain <strong>residue</strong> material from atoms released into the lunar atmosphere over billions of years.</p>
<p>The research was led by scientists at the University of Chicago and Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT). Their results recently appeared <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.adm7074">in a study</a> in the publication <em>Science Advances</em>. Nicole Nie was the lead writer of the study. She is a planetary scientist at MIT.</p>
<p><strong>Meteorite impacts</strong></p>
<p>Nie said that when meteorites impact, or hit, an object like the moon, they create very high temperatures. Such strikes can heat up the surface by 2,000 to 6,000 degrees Celsius. These extreme temperatures melt and <strong>vaporize</strong> rocks at the surface and release atoms contained in dust and soil into the atmosphere.</p>
<p>Some of the atoms end up being pushed into space, while others remain just above the surface. The researchers said the soil examinations led to the discovery that the moon's atmosphere was formed through a process known as “impact vaporization.”</p>
<p>Nie and her team centered their examinations on two main elements – potassium and rubidium. These substances were chosen because they can easily be vaporized by meteorite hits. The process involved studying the behaviors of different kinds of isotopes found in potassium and rubidium. That study persuaded the team that repeated meteorite strikes formed the atmosphere.</p>
<p>In the past, studies have shown the moon's atmosphere might have been created by either meteor activity or the solar wind. Solar wind describes a continuous flow of charged particles from the sun that spreads across the solar system.</p>
<p>The researchers said the latest study provides new evidence that most of the lunar atmosphere was likely formed by repeated meteorite hits over billions of years. After testing 10 samples of lunar soil, the team concluded that much more of the atmosphere is due to meteor activity than to the solar wind.</p>
<p>“At least 70 percent of the lunar atmosphere is created by these meteorite impacts,” Nie <a class="wsw__a" href="https://news.uchicago.edu/story/new-study-reveals-why-moon-has-very-thin-atmosphere">said</a> in a statement. “A much smaller percentage is created by the solar wind abrasion of the surface,” she added.</p>
<p>Nicolas Dauphas is a professor of geophysical sciences at the University of Chicago. He helped lead the research. Dauphas <a class="wsw__a" href="https://news.uchicago.edu/story/new-study-reveals-why-moon-has-very-thin-atmosphere">said</a>, “It turns out the answer to this longstanding question was right in front of us – <strong>preserved</strong> in lunar soil brought back to Earth by the Apollo missions.”</p>
<p>Nie said understanding such processes can be extremely valuable to planning future missions to the moon, Mars and beyond. “If humans want to move to different planetary bodies someday, we will have to understand what's going on at the surface to be able to prepare.” She added, “Each planetary body is different, and the more we understand about these processes, the more complete picture we'll have.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Reuters, the University of Chicago and MIT reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>meteorite </strong><em>– n.</em> a piece of rock from outer space that has fallen to a planet's surface</p>
<p><strong>exosphere </strong><em>– n. </em>the outermost layer of a planet's atmosphere</p>
<p><strong>residue </strong><em>– n.</em> something that remains after most of a substance has disappeared or been removed</p>
<p><strong>vaporize </strong><em>– v. </em>to turn, or cause something to turn, from a solid or liquid state into a gas</p>
<p><strong>abrasion</strong> <em>– n. </em>the process of rubbing away the surface of something</p>
<p><strong>preserve </strong><em>– v. </em>to keep something the same or prevent it from being damaged or destroyed</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Work, Sleep Well in a Small Place (2024/8/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/work-sleep-well-in-a-small-place.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the Health &amp; Lifestyle report.</p>
<p>Working from home in a small apartment is fine during the day. But when nighttime comes, it may be more difficult to turn off work and get a good night's sleep.</p>
<p>This can be especially difficult in a <strong>studio apartment</strong>. In a studio apartment, the living room, kitchen and sleeping area are all in one room. These kinds of apartments are common in large cities with a high cost of living.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Space-saving Murphy beds, like this one, can be folded into their own frame. And they supply storage. (California Closets via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-c59f-08dca8439a94_cx0_cy15_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Space-saving Murphy beds, like this one, can be folded into their own frame. And they supply storage. (California Closets via AP)</span></div>
<p>With electronics, kitchen items, clothes and books all in one space, it can be hard to create a restful place for sleep.</p>
<p>Kim Cook, a reporter for the Associated Press, asked sleep experts and <strong>interior design</strong> experts for advice on how to work productively and sleep well in a small one-room area.</p>
<p><strong>Be honest about how you live </strong></p>
<p>Everyone needs good sleep to stay healthy.</p>
<p>“The <strong>primary</strong> rule, maybe the only rule of small space design, is people have to be honest about how they really live,” says Olivia Hosken. She is deputy managing editor of House Beautiful.</p>
<p>She adds that when you have limited space, you need furniture that works well in the room.</p>
<p><strong>A good bed is important for good sleep</strong></p>
<p>She suggests spending money on a high-quality bed. Even better is a high-quality sleep sofa that can double as a bed and couch. She does not suggest big tables or chairs that you may not use.</p>
<p>Andrea Morris is an interior designer with Lancaster Place Interiors in Wilmington, North Carolina. For studio apartments, she likes wall beds. These can be folded up next to a wall when not in use.</p>
<p>They are better known as Murphy beds, named after William Murphy. He came up with this idea in 1900 while living in his own studio apartment in San Francisco, California.</p>
<p><strong>Create a sleep area</strong></p>
<p>To separate your sleep area from the rest of the apartment, you can purchase a freestanding screen or room divider. And as much as you can, keep your sleep area strictly for sleeping, experts say.</p>
<p>Jeff Kahn is co-founder of the Chicago-based sleep-research company Rise Science. His company developed a sleep-tracking app called Rise. His suggestion is to “avoid doing work or anything stressful from your bed.” He said that this helps the brain connect your bed with only sleep rather than wakefulness and work.</p>
<p>However, that is not always possible. If you use your bed during the daytime, you can do small things to keep daytime tasks and sleep separate. Lisa Strauss is a <strong>psychologist</strong> and expert in sleep disorders. She suggests using one side of the bed for reading and the other for sleeping. You can also bring out special blankets and pillows used only for sleeping.</p>
<p><strong>Freshen the air. Lower the lights. Cut the noise.</strong></p>
<p>Kahn also suggests keeping a clean, peaceful environment. For starters, he says to make sure the air flow is good.</p>
<p>“Make sure your space is well <strong>ventilated</strong>, and consider an <strong>air</strong> <strong>purifier</strong>,” says Kahn. He adds that this is especially important if you cook and sleep in the same place.</p>
<p>Another interior expert is Mia Ingui. She is editor at Spruce, a home design website. She suggests using calming smells like lavender or chamomile at bedtime, to “set the <strong>tone</strong> for restful sleep.”</p>
<p>Also, be sure that computer, TV, and other electronic screens are turned off. In a small room, these devices are probably a short distance from the bed. Their light at night can affect our internal clocks, or <strong>circadian rhythm</strong>.</p>
<p>Do not forget about the sounds these devices make. If the buzz of nearby devices, appliances, or street sounds keep you awake, consider a noise machine. Ingui likes the Hatch Restore, a “sunrise lamp” that provides soothing sounds and lights up slowly in the morning. You can also buy noise cancelling curtains. These cut down on outside noises.</p>
<p><strong>Keep things clean and organized</strong></p>
<p>Andrea Morris, the home designer, says one thing to avoid when it comes to studio living is leaving beds unmade.</p>
<p>“It's amazing how much better you feel after a hard day entering a space with a made bed,” she said.</p>
<p>At night, she suggests putting away electronics. Side tables with plugs and ports for electronics help you store devices and keep things tidy – or organized and clean. This is another example of choosing furniture that has multiple uses.</p>
<p><strong>Choose multi-use, storable bedding</strong></p>
<p>If it difficult to control your studio apartment's heating and cooling, Ingui recommends choosing materials for bedding that let the skin breathe. Such materials can keep you cool in warm weather and warm in cooler temperatures.</p>
<p>She also suggests buying several pieces of bedding that are easy to store rather than big, <strong>bulky</strong> blankets. Studio apartments often do not have a lot of storage.</p>
<p>With some thoughtful choices, your small space can have the feeling we all want from home life: calm, clean and good for both working and sleeping.</p>
<p>And that's the Health &amp; Lifestyle report.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo. And I'm Mario Ritter Jr.</p>
<p><em>Kim Cook reported this story for The Associated Press from New York City. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>studio apartment </strong><em>– n. </em>a small apartment consisting typically of a main room, kitchenette, and bathroom</p>
<p><strong>interior design </strong><em>– n.</em> the art of decorating and furnishing the interior of a building</p>
<p><strong>primary </strong><em>– adj. </em>of first rank, importance, or value</p>
<p><strong>psychologist </strong><em>– n. </em>a person who specializes in the study of mind and behavior or in the treatment of mental, emotional, and behavioral disorders</p>
<p><strong>ventilated </strong><em>– v. </em>to expose to air and especially to a current of fresh air</p>
<p><strong>air purifier </strong><em>– n. </em>a device that removes contaminating particles (such as dust and pollen) from the air</p>
<p><strong>tone </strong><em>– n. </em>general character or quality</p>
<p><strong>circadian rhythm </strong><em>– n. </em>the natural patterns that take place in your body over the course of each 24-hour cycle.</p>
<p><strong>bulky </strong><em>– adj. </em>large in size or mass</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Andean Glacier Shrinking at Speed Not Seen Before (2024/8/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/study-andean-glacier-shrinking-at-speed-not-seen-before.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A new study finds that the<strong> </strong>glaciers across the Andes in South America are shrinking at a speed not seen before in the history of human civilization.</p>
<p>This discovery surprised scientists. At first, they only planned to study the current conditions of glaciers and how they changed through history.</p>
<p>"We thought this result was <strong>decades</strong> away," said Andrew Gorin. As lead writer of the study, he first thought the results were an accident. But later he and his team confirmed the results with more <strong>samples</strong>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Mountaineers walk past the Iver glacier close to the El Plomo mountain summit, in the Andes mountain range, in the Santiago Metropolitan Region, Chile, April 4, 2024. (REUTERS/Ivan Alvarado)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-2f30-08dcb58c2cc7_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Mountaineers walk past the Iver glacier close to the El Plomo mountain summit, in the Andes mountain range, in the Santiago Metropolitan Region, Chile, April 4, 2024. (REUTERS/Ivan Alvarado)</span></div>
<p>Gorin said that the shrinking of glaciers is happening even faster than experts had thought.</p>
<p>He and a team of scientists carbon-dated bedrock that had been recently <strong>exposed </strong>by shrinking glaciers. They measured beryllium-10 and carbon-14 nuclide <strong>levels</strong> and found that <strong>concentrations</strong> were nearly zero.</p>
<p>He explained that if the rock can “see the sky” it collects these nuclides. He added that the <strong>decay</strong> rate of these nuclides shows that the rock had not been exposed during the Holocene Era. This era dates back 11,700 years but could go back even further.</p>
<p>"I would bet my whole life savings that in fact, these glaciers are smaller than they've been since the last interglacial period," Gorin said. The last interglacial period ended about 115,000 years ago.</p>
<p>The study collected data at four glaciers across the Andes. These glaciers make up 99 percent of the world's tropical glaciers. They are more affected by changing weather because they are regularly at or near freezing point.</p>
<p>"We think this is the <strong>canary in the coal mine</strong>, that this is going to happen everywhere before long and maybe sooner than we thought," Gorin said. (Canary in the coal mine is an expression that warns of danger. Coal miners would use a canary to tell if the oxygen levels in a coal mine were dangerous.)</p>
<p>Researchers published the new study in the journal <em>Science</em> on August 1.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Alexander Villegas reported this story for Reuters with additional reporting by Jake Spring. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;</em></p>
<p><em>_____________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>decade </strong><em>– n.</em><strong> </strong>a period of 10 years</p>
<p><strong>sample </strong><em>– n. </em>a part or thing that shows the quality of the whole or group</p>
<p><strong>expose </strong><em>– v. </em>to submit or make accessible to a particular action or influence</p>
<p><strong>level </strong><em>– n. </em>an amount of something especially in comparison with typical or expected amounts</p>
<p><strong>concentration </strong><em>– n. </em>the amount of an ingredient or part in relation to that of others</p>
<p><strong>decay </strong><em>– v. </em>to decline in health, strength, or vigor</p>
<p><strong>canary in the coal mine </strong>- an expression that warns of danger. Coal miners would use a canary to tell if the oxygen levels in a coal mine were dangerous.</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Spacecraft Problems Could Keep NASA Astronauts at Space Station until February (2024/8/12) | 波音飞船故障可能让美国宇航员滞留到明年2月</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/spacecraft-problems-could-keep-nasa-astronauts-at-space-station-until-february.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>Two American astronauts could remain at the International Space Station (ISS) until February if the spacecraft that transported them cannot be fixed to safely bring them home.<br/>两名美国宇航员可能会在国际空间站滞留到明年2月，如果运送他们的航天器无法修复以便安全带他们回家的话。</p><p>The U.S. space agency NASA said last week it had not yet made return plans for astronauts Butch Wilmore and Suni Williams. The two have been aboard the ISS since June 6.<br/>美国宇航局上周表示，尚未为宇航员布奇·威尔莫尔和苏妮·威廉姆斯制定返回计划。这两人自6月6日以来一直滞留在国际空间站上。</p><p>The American astronauts were expected to stay in space for only a week. But technical issues with the Boeing-built Starliner spacecraft have so far prevented a return trip.<br/>这两名美国宇航员原本预计将在太空停留一周。但是波音公司制造的星际客机航天器发生的技术问题阻碍了回程。</p><p>The trip that carried Wilmore and Williams was a test flight for Starliner that marked the first time the spacecraft successfully carried astronauts to space.<br/>威尔莫尔和威廉姆斯的这趟行程是星际客机的试飞，标志着该航天器首次成功将宇航员送入太空。</p><p>NASA looking for a solution<br/>美国宇航局正在寻找解决方案</p><p>NASA officials held a news conference Wednesday to discuss the ongoing situation with Starliner and the astronauts at the ISS. They said the agency is still working with Boeing to find a solution for the spacecraft's technical difficulties. Investigations have centered on helium leaks and thruster problems with Starliner.<br/>美国宇航局官员周三举行了一场记者会，讨论了星际客机和国际空间站上宇航员的现状。他们表示，该机构仍在与波音公司合作，为航天器的技术难题找到解决方案。调查主要集中在星际客机的氦气泄漏和推进器问题上。</p><p>But if those issues cannot be resolved in the coming weeks, NASA said it could decide to use SpaceX's Crew Dragon spacecraft to bring the astronauts back to Earth. NASA has been using SpaceX's Crew Dragon to regularly carry astronauts and supplies to the ISS since 2020.<br/>但美国宇航局表示，如果这些问题在未来几周内无法解决，它可能会决定使用太空探索科技公司的载人龙飞船将宇航员带回地球。自2020年以来，美国宇航局一直在使用太空探索科技公司的载人龙飞船定期将宇航员和物资运送到国际空间站。</p><p>If NASA decides to use Crew Dragon, it said it would leave two of four seats open during the spacecraft's next planned launch to the ISS in late September. Wilmore and Williams would then make the trip back to Earth with Crew Dragon.<br/>如果美国宇航局决定使用载人龙飞船，它称其将在9月下旬该航天器下一次计划发射到国际空间站期间，将四个座位中的两个留空。威尔莫尔和威廉姆斯随后将与载人龙飞船一起返回地球。</p><p>NASA officials told reporters they had brought in additional experts to examine Starliner's leak issues and thruster failures. At the same time, the space agency is looking more closely at SpaceX as a backup solution to get the astronauts back home.<br/>美国宇航局官员告诉记者，他们已经请来了更多的专家来检查星际客机的泄漏问题和推进器故障。与此同时，航天局正在更密切地关注太空探索科技公司，将其作为让宇航员回家的后备解决方案。</p><p>The agency's space operations mission chief, Ken Bowersox, said NASA's current thinking is that “we could take either path.” He added that during a recent meeting, “We heard from a lot of folks that had concern, and the decision was not clear.” NASA has said a final decision should be made by mid-August.<br/>该机构太空行动任务负责人肯·鲍尔索克斯表示，美国宇航局目前的想法是“我们可以走任何一条路”。他补充说，在最近的一次会议上，“我们听到了很多人的担忧，但决定尚未做出。”美国宇航局表示，最终决定应该会在8月中旬做出。</p><p>Boeing representatives did not take part in the news conference. But the company issued a brief statement Wednesday repeating its position that Starliner could still be fixed to safely transport the astronauts. “We still believe in Starliner's capability and its flight rationale,” Boeing said.<br/>波音公司的代表没有参加这场记者会。但该公司周三发表了一份简短声明，重申其立场，即星际客机仍可以修复以安全运输宇航员。波音公司表示：“我们仍然相信星际客机的能力及其飞行原理。”</p><p>The Boeing statement said if NASA did decide to change Starliner's mission, the company would "take the actions necessary to configure Starliner for an uncrewed return."<br/>波音公司的声明称，如果美国航空航天局决定改变星际客机的任务，该公司将“采取必要行动配置星际客机进行无人返回。”</p><p>Steve Stich is the commercial crew program manager for NASA. He said the agency was not seriously considering launching a separate SpaceX flight to pick up Wilmore and Williams.<br/>史蒂夫·斯蒂克是美国宇航局的商业载人项目经理。他说，该机构并没有开始认真考虑发射单独的龙飞船去接威尔莫尔和威廉姆斯。</p><p>Problems with thruster's seals<br/>推进器密封件存在问题</p><p>Officials said tests run by Boeing and NASA on Earth have reproduced Starliner's thruster problems. This has suggested to engineers a possible issue with the thruster's seals. But Stich noted it was not clear what is causing the seal issues.<br/>官员们表示，波音公司和美国宇航局在地球上进行的测试再现了星际客机的推进器问题。这一操作向工程师们表明了推进器密封件可能存在的问题。但斯蒂克指出，目前尚不清楚是什么导致了密封问题。</p><p>The thrusters are important for permitting Starliner to back away from the ISS during its separation operations. At the same time, engineers are seeking to find the cause of helium leaks in the spacecraft's propulsion system. The first leak happened before the launch, but more appeared during flight.<br/>推进器对于允许星际客机在分离操作期间远离国际空间站非常重要。与此同时，工程师们正在寻找该航天器推进系统中氦气泄漏的原因。第一次泄漏发生在发射之前，但飞行过程中出现了更多的泄漏。</p><p>Boeing has faced repeated delays as it struggles to complete NASA's flight testing process before it can receive approval to start running official trips to the ISS.<br/>波音公司的星际客机项目一再面临延误，因为它在获得批准开始正式前往国际空间站之前，很难完成美国宇航局的飞行测试程序。</p><p>I'm Bryan Lynn.<br/>我是布莱恩·林恩。(21VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>In Warmer Weather, South Korean Farmers Try Growing Bananas (2024/8/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/in-warmer-weather-south-korean-farmers-try-growing-bananas.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Ma Myung-sun had low expectations for the <strong>subtropical</strong> bananas he planted in a community farm in Seoul. He must use a <strong>greenhouse</strong> for part of the year to protect them from South Korea's cold winters.</p>
<p>But warmer temperatures due to climate change have produced a welcome surprise in the form of flowers and fruit.</p>
<p>The land area where subtropical crops are grown in South Korea has increased from about 295 hectares in 2021 to 3,306 hectares in 2023.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="South Korean farmer, Ma Myung-sun, stands next to a banana tree at his community farm in Seoul, South Korea, July 31, 2024. (REUTERS/Minwoo Park)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-4654-08dcb87137b6_cx0_cy16_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">South Korean farmer, Ma Myung-sun, stands next to a banana tree at his community farm in Seoul, South Korea, July 31, 2024. (REUTERS/Minwoo Park)</span></div>
<p>South Korea's state agricultural organization, the Rural Development Administration, reports that there are 67 banana farms in the south. And Ma is among a growing number of farmers experimenting with crops usually grown in a warmer climate.</p>
<p>"I want to try growing other tropical crops too. So, as you can see here, I have planted these papaya trees as well,” Ma said, pointing to a small papaya plant.</p>
<p>Ma opened up part of his family's farm to people from the city in 2006. He is happy about his small success. But he worries about what it means for the climate.</p>
<p>"I feel that the climate crisis has become very serious," said Ma, who has been a farmer for 25 years.</p>
<p>South Korea lies in the <strong>temperate</strong> zone and has four seasons. But its climate appears to be getting warmer and wetter throughout the year.</p>
<p>The Korea Meteorological Administration reports that since 2012, the average yearly temperature has been continually rising. The average temperature last year of 13.7 degrees Celsius was the highest since its records began in 1973.</p>
<p><strong>Plenty of rain</strong></p>
<p>Rainfall during last year's rainy season was 660.2 mm nationwide, nearly two times the 356.7 mm annual average figure.</p>
<p>Kim Kwang-soo is a professor of Agriculture and Life Sciences at Seoul National University. Kim said South Korea's climate conditions were becoming more like subtropical areas, so it is important for farmers to find the right crop varieties for the climate.</p>
<p>Tropical and subtropical fruit are usually <strong>expensive</strong> in South Korea, so shoppers should welcome the less costly local produce.</p>
<p>"My kids love bananas. So, it would be good if we harvest bananas in this country," said Kim Ji-youn, who was purchasing imported bananas in a Seoul supermarket.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Minwoo Park and Dogyun Kim reported this story for Reuters.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>greenhouse</strong> – <em>n</em>. a building or part of a building that has glass walls and a glass roof and that is used for growing plants</p>
<p><strong>subtropical</strong> – <em>adj.</em> relating to or living in an area that is close to tropical parts of the world</p>
<p><strong>temperate</strong> – <em>adj</em>. having temperatures that are not too hot or too cold</p>
<p><strong>expensive</strong> – <em>adj.</em> costing a lot of money</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>One Person's Trash Is Another Person's Treasure (2024/8/11)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/one-person-s-trash-is-another-person-s-treasure.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">10 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p class="paragraph">And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>People around the world share many things in common. But we are also different from each other. Not only do we look, think, and act differently, but we also like different things. Even <strong>identical</strong> <strong>twins</strong> may look the same but are very different individuals.</p>
<p>On today's program, we will look at a few expressions to describe how no person is exactly the same as another.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Iris Hsueh (L) and Ian Ciou have a picture taken on October 14, 2023, at a garbage dump in Puli Township, Taiwan. The bride is serious about the environment and wants to make a statement with her wedding photos. (Photo by Handout/OWEN KANG/AFP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-43d9-08dbe21a7a41_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Iris Hsueh (L) and Ian Ciou have a picture taken on October 14, 2023, at a garbage dump in Puli Township, Taiwan. The bride is serious about the environment and wants to make a statement with her wedding photos. (Photo by Handout/OWEN KANG/AFP)</span></div>
<p>The first expression involves trash and treasure.</p>
<p>When we say <u>one person's trash is another person's treasure</u>,<strong> </strong>we mean that something that one person may consider worthless could be highly prized or valued by someone else.</p>
<p>Let's hear an example of how to use this expression:</p>
<p><em>A: I really don't understand the appeal of Jackson Pollock's paintings. To me, they look like a team of m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s painted them!" </em></p>
<p><em>B: I love Pollock's paintings. I see something new every time I look at them. </em></p>
<p><em>A: Well, I guess it's true what they say, <u>one person's trash is another person's treasure</u>.</em></p>
<p>Now, rubbish and garbage mean the same as trash. But, in this expression, we use trash because the “tr” in <u>trash</u> and <u>treasure</u> makes the expression sound more natural. It just sounds better.</p>
<p>And, sometimes, we use the word "man" in place of "person" such as <u>one man's trash is another man's treasure</u>. Again it is just easier to say.</p>
<p>Another expression with a similar meaning is <u>different strokes for different folks</u>.</p>
<p>This also means that different things appeal to different people. But as a set expression, we do not say “different strokes for different people.” That just doesn't sound right.</p>
<p><u>Different strokes for different folks</u> can also mean that people live in different ways and value different things.</p>
<p>For example, a perfect evening for my friend is to go out and dance all night long. For me, a perfect evening is to stay at home with a book and a cup of tea. Neither is a better way to spend the evening. So, we should not judge. Or in other words, <u>different strokes for different folks</u>.</p>
<p>When we want to say that we are all different and we like different things without judgment, we can also use the following expressions:</p>
<p><u>It takes all kinds to make the world go round.</u></p>
<p><u>It takes all kinds.</u></p>
<p><u>To each his (her) own. </u></p>
<p><u>Whatever floats your boat.</u></p>
<p>They all mean ... whatever makes you happy!</p>
<p>And all of these expressions have the same general meaning: We are all different and <strong>unique</strong>.</p>
<p>And that's the end of this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>. Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>identical twin</strong> <em>– n.</em> either member of a pair of twins that are produced from a single egg and who look exactly alike</p>
<p><strong>unique </strong><em>– adj. </em>being the only one of its kind</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>In So Many Places, Cats Are the Stars (2024/8/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/in-so-many-places-cats-are-the-stars.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From the United States and Britain to Russia and South America, cats often appear in famous public places.</p>
<p>Cat fans say the animals bring value to the places where they live. Cats can add a cute element or reduce the number of rodents. Sometimes, cats even come to define the place they live in.</p>
<p><strong>Cats in the United States </strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Larry the cat, Chief Mouser to the Cabinet Office, poses for the cameras outside 10 Downing Street in London, on March 13, 2024. (AP Photo/Alberto Pezzali, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/6c6dbe98-6b3a-4ac6-acd1-2598f11306b1_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Larry the cat, Chief Mouser to the Cabinet Office, poses for the cameras outside 10 Downing Street in London, on March 13, 2024. (AP Photo/Alberto Pezzali, File)</span></div>
<p>In 2020, a green-eyed cat named Willow appeared at a Joe Biden campaign event in Pennsylvania. The cat jumped onstage and left with soon-to-be first lady Jill, who later wrote a book about the creature.</p>
<p>But the White House is not the only well-known place in the United States to house cats.</p>
<p>The Hemingway Homes and Museum, in Key West, Florida has fifty-nine cats that move freely through the estate. Half of the creatures are related to Hemingway's own six-toed cat, Snow White.</p>
<p>Visitors are kept away from the furniture, but the animals sit on the writer's desk. A large “Cat Bible” shows the family history, or lineage, of the resident cats.</p>
<p>Alexa Morgan of the Hemingway museum said the cats bring extra public interest.</p>
<p>“We have visitors that come here for Hemingway, and then once they see the cats and they love them, then it's like they visit again so they can come back and see the cats,” she said.</p>
<p><strong>Cats in Britain </strong></p>
<p>In Britain, there is Lilibet.</p>
<p>She is a Siberian Forest cat who spends time sitting by the fire at the Lanesborough Hotel in London. Plenty of people visit the hotel just to see the cat, who is named after Queen Elizabeth II, said managing director Stuart Geddes.</p>
<p>Lilibet has special hair known as hypoallergenic fur. That means her hair is not likely to cause problems for people who are sensitive to cat hair. Lilibet is not the only cat living in an important British building.</p>
<p>Hodge sits inside Southwark Cathedral, which was established in 1106. He moves around bringing happiness to visitors and going into the shop for treats.</p>
<p>Not far away, across the Thames River, is Larry, the famous cat of 10 Downing St., the official home of the prime minister of Britain. Larry has stayed longer than most prime ministers — Kier Starmer is his sixth.</p>
<p>Employed as Chief Mouser to the Cabinet Office, Larry pays his way by keeping the prime minister's office and home more cat than mouse.</p>
<p>He has lasted longer than his rival Palmerston, a previous Foreign Office cat who retired to the British countryside in 2020.</p>
<p><strong>Russia and beyond </strong></p>
<p>Cats also live in the Hermitage Museum in Saint Petersburg, Russia.</p>
<p>About 80 cats get to call Catherine the Great's palace home in return for keeping the pest population down. They have their own press officer and volunteer assistants, who keep them publicized, fed, and watered while they walk around Russia's state museum.</p>
<p>In Venezuela, under a banner of Hugo Chavez, an unnamed cat has become well-known to the journalists of Caracas. Often found moving near TV crews at the National Electoral Council, this mysterious animal keeps reporters company as they wait for updates.</p>
<p>Far away in another part of the world, Lule is so beloved at the Day and Night bar in Pristina, Kosovo, that her cat face has become its symbol. Owner Genc Salihu says she is part of the family, and people come just to see and pet Lule.</p>
<p>“She is very much the soul of this place,” he said.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Hilary Fox reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>cute </strong><em>-- adj.</em> attractive or pretty</p>
<p><strong>rodent </strong><em>– n.</em> a small mammal (such as a mouse)</p>
<p><strong>onstage</strong> <em>– adv.</em> on or onto a stage</p>
<p><strong>estate</strong> <em>– n.</em> a property usually with a large house on it</p>
<p><strong>furniture</strong><em> – n.</em> equipment that is necessary or useful (beds, desks, chairs, etc.)</p>
<p><strong>museum</strong><em> –n.</em> a building where interesting and valuable things are collected and shown to the public</p>
<p><strong>treat</strong> <em>–n. </em>a special food to eat</p>
<p><strong>pay (your) way</strong> <em>–idiom </em>to earn your living or pay for staying in the place you live in</p>
<p><strong>palace</strong><em> –n.</em> the home of a king or queen</p>
<p><strong>pest</strong> <em>–n.</em> an unwanted animal, like an insect or rodent, that damages homes or farms</p>
<p><strong>symbol </strong><em>– n</em>. a sign, object or even a person that stands for or suggests another thing such as an idea or a country</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>'Benito Cereno,' by Herman Melville, Part Three (2024/8/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/benito-cereno-by-herman-melville-part-three.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By VOA</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">09 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p><em>We present the last of three parts of the short story "Benito Cereno." It was written by Herman Melville.</em></p>
<p><em>As we told you in earlier parts of our story, rebel slaves seized the ship San Dominick off the coast of Chile. They killed many of its officers and crew. The captain, Benito Cereno, was ordered to sail to Senegal. But first, he was forced to take the ship to the lonely island of Santa Maria, near the southern end of Chile. There, it could safely get water and supplies for the long, dangerous voyage to Africa.</em></p>
<div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f0bfd657-c381-44a2-91f0-38af2c06d6b2_w100_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p><em>At the island, the rebels were surprised and frightened when they found an American ship anchored in the harbor. It also had stopped for water. Many of the rebels wanted to sail away. But their leader, Babo, opposed it. They had little water and food, and could not go far. Babo created a story to keep anyone from suspecting that the Spanish vessel was in the hands of rebels, and that its captain was a prisoner.</em></p>
<p><em>At first, Babo seemed successful. The captain of the American ship, Amasa Delano, visited the San Dominick. He suspected nothing, although surprised by the general disorder on board. He also could not understand the strange behavior of its captain, Benito Cereno. Later incidents, however, began to worry him. Captain Delano grew more and more suspicious. At one time, he even feared that his life might be in danger.</em></p>
<p><em>Twice, he caught the Spanish captain and his servant, Babo, with their heads together, whispering like two conspirators. It made Captain Delano wonder. Were they plotting to kill him and seize his ship? Who were these men, cut throats? Pirates?</em></p>
<p><em>Captian Delano grew nervous. Then, he was happy to see his whale boat off in the distance. It was returning with supplies for the Spanish ship. The sight of his boat calmed him. It made his suspicions and fear quickly disappear. He felt foolish for having had such dark thoughts.</em></p>
<p><em>Now, here is Shep O'Neal with the rest of our story, "Benito Cereno."</em></p>
<p>Captain Delano went down to Captain Cereno's cabin to cheer him up and say goodbye.</p>
<p>“Better and better, Don Benito,” he said as he entered the cabin, “your troubles will soon be over.” The American invited the Spanish captain to come aboard his boat for a cup of coffee.</p>
<p>Cereno's eyes brightened. But then the light in them died. He shook his head and said he could not accept the invitation. Captain Delano was offended. He was about to withdraw when Don Benito rose from his chair and took Delano's hand. The Spaniard's hand shook. And he was too excited to speak. Delano pulled his hand away and turned, climbing back to the deck. His face was troubled.</p>
<p>Captain Delano could not understand Don Benito's actions. One minute the Spaniard was warm and polite. Then -- just as quickly -- cold and hostile. Captain Delano asked himself: Why did he refuse to join me? Why is he so unfriendly?</p>
<p>Captain Delano got to the deck and was about to step down into his boat when he heard his name. To his surprise, Don Benito was calling, coming quickly toward him.</p>
<p>Captain Delano was pleased and turned back to meet him. Don Benito warmly took his hand, with more energy and emotion than he had ever shown. But his excitement seemed too much for him, and he could not speak. Babo then came between the two men and put his arm around Don Benito to support him. Clearly, he wanted to end the meeting between the two captains.</p>
<p>Walking between the two men, Babo went with them to the walkway. Don Benito would not let go of Captain Delano's hand. He held it tightly across the servant's body.</p>
<p>Soon, they were standing by the ship's side, looking down onto the American boat. Its crew turned up their wondering eyes. Captain Delano did not know what to do as he waited for Don Benito to let go of his hand. He wanted to step down into his boat. But Don Benito still firmly held his hand.</p>
<p>Then, in an excited voice the Spaniard said: “I can go no further. Here I must say goodbye. Farewell, my dear, dear Don Amasa. Go! Go!” And he tore his hand loose. “Go, and God protect you better than he did me. Go, Don Amasa, my best friend.”</p>
<p>Captain Delano was deeply moved. He would have stayed for another minute or so, but he caught the eye of Babo. It seemed to say, ‘This is bad for Don Benito's health.' And so he quickly took the short step down into his boat with the continuing farewells of Don Benito, who stood rooted at the ship's side.</p>
<p>Captain Delano sat down in the back of his boat, gave Don Benito a last salute, and ordered his men to push off. The boat began to move. Suddenly, Don Benito sprang over the side and came down at Delano's feet. And he kept shouting toward the Spanish ship. His cries were so wild that no one could understand him.</p>
<p>An American officer asked what does this mean. Captain Delano turned a cold smile upon Captain Cereno and said he neither knew nor cared. It seems, he added, that the Spaniard has taken it into his head to give his people the idea that we want to kidnap him. Or else...and suddenly Captain Delano shouted: “Watch out for your lives!” He saw Babo, the servant, on the rail above, with a <strong>dagger</strong> in his hand. He was ready to jump.</p>
<p>What followed happened so quickly that Captain Delano could not tell one <strong>incident</strong> from another. They all came together in one great blur of violent action and excitement.</p>
<p>As Babo came down, Captain Delano flung Don Benito aside and caught the rebel leader, pulling the dagger from his hand. He pushed Babo firmly down in the bottom of the boat, which now began to pick up speed. Then, Babo, with his one free hand, pulled a second dagger from his clothes and struck at Captain Cereno. Captain Delano knocked it from his hand.</p>
<p>Now, he saw everything clearly: Babo had leaped into the <strong>whale boat </strong>– not to kill him – but to kill Captain Cereno.</p>
<p>For the first time, he understood the mysterious behavior of Don Benito – a prisoner under sentence of death. He looked back at the Spanish ship and got a clear picture of what its captain had escaped.</p>
<p>On board the San Dominick, the shouting rebels were raising their axes and knives in a wild revolt. They stopped some of the Spanish sailors from jumping into the sea. A few, however, jumped, while two or three, who were not quick enough, went hurrying up the top-most wood arms.</p>
<p>Captain Delano signaled to his ship, ordering it to get its guns ready. When the whale boat reached his ship Captain Delano asked for ropes. He tied Babo, and had him pulled up on deck. A small boat was quickly sent out to pick up three Spanish sailors who had jumped from Captain Cereno's ship.</p>
<p>Captain Delano asked Don Benito what guns the rebels had. He answered that they had none that could be used. In the first days of the rebellion, a cabin passenger now dead had destroyed the few guns there were.</p>
<p>The Americans fired six shots at the San Dominick. But the rebel ship moved out of reach. Small boats were armed and lowered. Captain Delano ordered his men into them. And they moved out to capture the rebel ship.</p>
<p>The boats caught up with the San Dominick when it was nearly night. But the moon was rising, and the <strong>gunners</strong> were able to see where they were shooting. The rebels had no bullets. And they could do nothing but yell. Many of the rebels were killed and the San Dominick was captured.</p>
<p>After an investigation, Babo was found guilty of stealing a ship and of murder, and was hanged. Captain Benito Cereno never was well again and he soon died. So, ended the terrible story of the slave revolt aboard the slave ship, the San Dominick.</p>
<p><em>___________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>incident</strong> – <em>n</em>. an event or something that happens</p>
<p><strong>whale boat</strong> - <em>n.</em> a long rowboat with a bow at either end for easy maneuverability, formerly used in whaling</p>
<p><strong>dagger</strong> - <em>n</em>. a sharp pointed knife that is used as a weapon</p>
<p><strong>gunners</strong> - <em>n</em>. a soldier who operates a large gun</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Ego and Arrogance (2024/8/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/ego-and-arrogance.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Ahmed in Egypt about the usage of the words “arrogance” and “ego."</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-0239-08dcb2f616db_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>I'm just asking about the difference between arrogance and ego because I hear actors use them interchangeably in movies.</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>Thank you for writing to us, Ahmed. I'm happy to answer this question.</p>
<p>First, let's explain the word “interchangeably." It describes using two things for the same purpose. For example, when we talk about the weather, the words “cloudy” and “overcast” mean the same thing.</p>
<p>“Ego” and “arrogance” are both nouns and are often interchangeable. The American dictionary publisher <em>Merriam-Webster </em>defines “ego” as having a sense of self-worth and “arrogance” as having a much greater sense of self-worth over others.</p>
<p>“Arrogant” and “egotistical” are the adjective forms of these words. An arrogant or egotistical person thinks he or she is better than other people.</p>
<p>You have heard actors using both terms because they usually mean the same thing. But we have particular ways of using each of these words. Here are some examples of how to use the two words:</p>
<p><em>That actor has such a big <u>ego</u>. He agrees to be in movies only if he gets to play the leading role.</em></p>
<p><em>You can feel her <u>arrogance</u> when she makes all those negative comments about other artists.</em></p>
<p>We sometimes say that a person “has a big ego." But we do not say that a person “has a big arrogance." That is because “arrogance” is a non-count noun.</p>
<p>To have “an inflated ego” is another common way of saying that a person is egotistical.</p>
<p>“Arrogance” is often used with a negative meaning. But “ego,” defined as a sense of self-worth, is neither positive nor negative. For example:</p>
<p><em>The teenage years are important for the development of a <u>healthy ego</u>.</em><em> </em></p>
<p>When a person feels their ego has been affected negatively, we say that person has “a wounded ego.”</p>
<p>And while we can use the expression “a big ego,” we rarely say “a small ego." Instead, we say a person “is not egotistical." Or, we simply say a person is <strong>humble</strong>.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, do you have a question about American English? Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>humble </strong><em>-adj. </em>not too proud, not believing one is better than other people.</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Are Microplastics Harmful? (2024/8/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/are-microplastics-harmful.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Extremely small pieces of plastic called microplastics are in the ocean and the air, as well as in our food and water. Scientific study has discovered microplastics in human body tissues also, including the heart, liver and kidneys.</p>
<p>Some researchers worry that microplastics harm human health, although they say that science has not found clear evidence of that. Still, they say questions remain about the possible health effects of microplastics.</p>
<p>Manufacturers mostly use oil or other petroleum products to make plastic. The material is used to make a huge number of different products: water bottles, car parts, children's playthings, clothing, electronics and more. Heat, weather, and even animal <strong>digestion</strong> break down plastic into smaller and smaller pieces.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A blue piece of microplastic sits on the finger of a researcher with the University of Washington-Tacoma environmental science program, after it was found in debris collected from the Thea Foss Waterway, in Tacoma, Wash., on May 19, 2010. (AP Photo/Ted S. Warren, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-0267-08dcb6f76c29_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A blue piece of microplastic sits on the finger of a researcher with the University of Washington-Tacoma environmental science program, after it was found in debris collected from the Thea Foss Waterway, in Tacoma, Wash., on May 19, 2010. (AP Photo/Ted S. Warren, File)</span></div>
<p>Microplastics can be 5 millimeters long at most or as small as one micrometer. A micrometer is one-one thousandth of a millimeter. Microplastics have been found in salt, sugar, honey, rice and seafood. They have also been found in milk, soil, and drinking water.</p>
<p><strong>Risks to the human body</strong></p>
<p>Researchers disagree about how much plastic people might be breathing in or taking in as food and drink. Still, many studies find evidence of plastics in body tissues.</p>
<p>Tracey Woodruff is a researcher at the University of California at San Francisco. She said, “Microplastics have been measured in pretty much all of the body tissues that have been <strong>evaluated</strong>.”</p>
<p>Scientists are still trying to answer the question of how harmful microplastics might be. In 2022, a World Health Organization report found no clear risk to human health, based on the available evidence.</p>
<p>There is also not clear evidence of widespread public health effects.</p>
<p>However, researchers only recently began to measure plastic levels in the human body and learn about their possible effects. Woodruff of U.C. San Francisco said it makes sense that microplastics are harmful because they contain poisonous chemicals. The researcher was part of an investigative team that examined nearly 2,000 studies about microplastics at the request of California state lawmakers.</p>
<p>Some evidence suggests plastics can increase <strong>inflammation </strong>and other changes in the body. Such changes could increase the risk of heart attack and stroke.</p>
<p><strong>Reducing exposure to microplastics</strong></p>
<p>Researchers say there are ways to reduce possible contact with microplastics.</p>
<p>Take off your shoes before you go into your home. This helps prevent the spread of microplastics inside. Eat foods — especially fresh fruits and vegetables — that you prepare at home. Do not heat foods in plastic containers, Woodruff said. And, she added, use metal or glass water bottles, instead of plastic.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Mike Stobbe wrote this story for The Associated Press. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>digestion </strong><em>-n. </em>the breaking down and absorption of food in the body</p>
<p><strong>evaluate </strong><em>-v. </em>to measure, judge, or analyze</p>
<p><strong>inflammation </strong><em>-n. </em>an increase in size of body tissues that results from infection, injury, or illness</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers Discover Very Small Human Ancestors (2024/8/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/researchers-discover-very-small-human-ancestors.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Twenty years ago on an Indonesian island, scientists discovered ancient bone remains of an early human <strong>species</strong> that stood about one meter tall.</p>
<p>These early humans became popularly known as “hobbits.” The name comes for the small humanlike creatures that appear in books by English writer J.R.R Tolkien.</p>
<p>Now a new study suggests ancestors of the “hobbits” were even shorter.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This photo provided by Yousuke Kaifu shows an arm bone fragment excavated on the Indonesia island of Flores. New research suggests ancestors of an early human species nicknamed “hobbits” were even shorter. (Yousuke Kaifu via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e2a73189-8f51-4449-81e1-55f19e684935_cx0_cy50_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This photo provided by Yousuke Kaifu shows an arm bone fragment excavated on the Indonesia island of Flores. New research suggests ancestors of an early human species nicknamed “hobbits” were even shorter. (Yousuke Kaifu via AP)</span></div>
<p>Yousuke Kaifu of the University of Tokyo was a co-writer of the study. Kaifu said in an email, “We did not expect that we would find smaller individuals from such an old <strong>site</strong>.”</p>
<p>The discoverers of the first hobbit fossils named them after <strong>characters</strong> in the The Lord of the Rings books. The fossils date back to between 60,000 and 100,000 years ago.</p>
<p>Researchers found the new fossils at a place called Mata Menge, about 70 kilometers from the cave where researchers found the first hobbit remains.</p>
<p>In 2016, researchers suspected the earlier relatives could be shorter than the hobbits after studying a jawbone and teeth collected from the new site. Additional examination of a small arm bone piece and teeth suggests the ancestors were 6 centimeters shorter and existed 700,000 years ago.</p>
<p>Dean Falk of Florida State University was not involved with the research. Falk said that the researchers in the study have “convincingly shown that these were very small individuals.”</p>
<p>The findings appeared recently in the publication Nature Communications.</p>
<p>Researchers have debated how the hobbits – named Homo floresiensis after the Indonesian island of Flores – developed to be so small and where they fall in the human evolutionary story. Homo floresiensis are thought to be among the last early human species to die off.</p>
<p>Scientists do not yet know whether the hobbits shrank from an earlier, taller human species called Homo erectus that lived in the area, or from an even more primitive human ancestor. Scientists need more study, and more fossils, to learn the hobbits' place in human evolution, said Matt Tocheri of Canada's Lakehead University.</p>
<p>In an email, Tocheri, who was not involved in the research, wrote, “This question remains unanswered and will continue to be a focus of research for some time to come.”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Adithi Ramakrishnan reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>species</strong><em> – n.</em> a class of individuals having common attributes and designated by a common name</p>
<p><strong>site </strong><em>– n. </em>the place point of an occurrence or event; the spatial location of something</p>
<p><strong>character</strong> <em>– n.</em> someone who appears in a book, play, etc</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Particles in Wildfire Smoke May Increase Dementia Risk (2024/8/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/study-particles-in-wildfire-smoke-may-increase-dementia-risk.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A new study suggests that particles found in wildfire smoke could increase the risk of getting dementia.</p>
<p>Dementia is a progressive brain condition that causes thinking problems and other health issues. There are several forms of dementia, including Alzheimer's disease.</p>
<p>Researchers reported the new findings about wildfire smoke at the recent Alzheimer's Association International Conference in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A plane drops fire retardant on the Park Fire near Forest Ranch, Calif., Sunday, July 28, 2024. (AP Photo/Nic Coury)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-a5ac-08dcb23a0b51_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A plane drops fire retardant on the Park Fire near Forest Ranch, Calif., Sunday, July 28, 2024. (AP Photo/Nic Coury)</span></div>
<p>The study centered on a substance called PM2.5. The substance is known as particulate matter, a mixture of small, solid particles and water droplets found in the air.</p>
<p>PM2.5 particles are about 30 times smaller than a human hair. They can be breathed into the lungs and then move on to the blood stream. Existing evidence shows this kind of pollution – from traffic, factories and fires – can cause or worsen heart disease. The new study finds it could also raise dementia risks.</p>
<p>Claire Sexton is the director of scientific programs for the Alzheimer's Association. She said in a statement the study shows that increasing wildfires, especially in the American west, are “an increasing threat to brain health.” Sexton added that the findings demonstrate “the importance of enacting policies to prevent wildfires and investigating better methods to <strong>address</strong> them.”</p>
<p>Researchers from the University of Washington and the University of Pennsylvania carried out the study. They examined health records of 1.2 million older adults in Southern California between 2009 and 2019. The scientists used air quality <strong>monitoring</strong> and other data to estimate how much PM2.5 was released from wildfire smoke or other ways over three years.</p>
<p>The study found the risk of being <strong>diagnosed</strong> with dementia increased about 21 percent for every 1 microgram increase in the <strong>concentration</strong> of wildfire particles. That compared with a 3 percent increased risk for every 3 microgram increase in non-wildfire particles.</p>
<p>It is not clear why this difference exists. But with wildfires increasing, this issue needs more study, said Alzheimer's Association chief science officer Maria Carrillo. She said it is especially important because the risk of Alzheimer's – the most common form of dementia – is higher for lower-income populations who may have a harder time avoiding unhealthy air.</p>
<p>Carrillo noted that health warnings urge staying indoors when air quality is poor. But she added, “there are a lot of people who don't have the <strong>option</strong> to stay home or they work outside.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_________________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>address</strong><em> - v.</em> to speak about a particular subject or issue</p>
<p><strong>monitor </strong><em>– v.</em> to watch something carefully and record the results</p>
<p><strong>diagnose </strong><em>– v.</em> to say what is wrong with a person who is sick</p>
<p><strong>concentration </strong><em>– n. </em>a large number or amount of something in the same place</p>
<p><strong>option </strong><em>– n. </em>something that may be chosen</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Ecuador’s Galapagos Islands Face Many Threats (2024/8/8)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/ecuador-s-galapagos-islands-face-many-threats.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">07 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The Galapagos, a group of islands in the Eastern Pacific Ocean, are coming under increased pressure.</p>
<p>Observers say climate change and invasive<strong> species </strong>threaten wildlife on and around the islands, which are part of the South American country of Ecuador.</p>
<p>Warming ocean waters affect the food<strong> sources</strong> of many of the sea animals around the Galapagos.</p><div class="contentImage"><img a="" alie="" alt="A whale shark swims through the waters off of Wolf Island, Ecuador, next to Enrique " cruz="" ecuador="" from="" galapagos="" in="" island="" june="" local="" moran="" naturalist="" on="" photo="" quike="" santa="" skowronski="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/2c630d2a-a854-4d87-b3b5-530a96621a88_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg" sunday="" the=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A whale shark swims through the waters off of Wolf Island, Ecuador, next to Enrique "Quike" Moran, a local naturalist from Santa Cruz Island, Ecuador in the Galapagos on Sunday, June 9, 2024. (AP Photo/Alie Skowronski)</span></div>
<p>Marine iguanas are one of many species that are <strong>unique</strong> to the Galapagos. The <strong>reptiles</strong> have a harder time finding the food they prefer - red and green algae. A recent Associated Press (AP) report said sea turtles struggle to <strong>nest </strong>in warmer temperatures. Raising young gets harder as water warms and fewer nutrients are available.</p>
<p>“We have something of everything here – that's why people say the Galapagos is so <strong>diverse</strong> – but we have a small number of each thing,” said Natasha Cabezas, a naturalist guide.</p>
<p><strong>A changing climate </strong></p>
<p>The Galapagos Islands are famous for animals that were studied by Charles Darwin in the 1800s. He developed the theory that living things change over large amounts of time.</p>
<p>The group of islands is where major ocean currents meet — cool water from the south, warm water from the north, and a cold current from the west. In addition to those, there is El Ni<i></i>241;o, the periodic and natural Pacific Ocean warming that affects weather worldwide.</p>
<p>While temperatures depend on the season and other natural climate events, scientists say ocean temperatures have been rising. They blame climate change caused by human activities.</p>
<p>Some scientists say the ocean has reached its warmest level since at least the 1800s within the last 10 years. The U.S. space agency NASA says 2023 was the ocean's warmest year on record.</p>
<p>In the Southern Hemisphere, June is the first month of winter. One of the ocean currents, the Cromwell current, brings sea creatures like whale sharks, hammerheads, and sunfish to the surface. It also provides nutrients for penguins, marine iguanas and sea lions in search of food.</p>
<p>Scientists are studying how the past year's El Ni<i></i>241;o affected those creatures.</p>
<p>El Ni<i></i>241;o can bring food shortages for some species like marine iguanas and sea turtles. Scientists observing the species have noted a decrease in their populations during El Ni<i></i>241;o events.</p>
<p>Marine iguanas were “one of the most affected species from El Ni<i></i>241;o last year and right now they are still recovering,” said Galapagos Conservancy Director Jorge Carrión.</p>
<p><strong>Invasive species </strong></p>
<p>As rising ocean temperatures threaten sea life, on land there is a different problem. Animals — cats, dogs, pigs, goats and cattle, none of them native — are threatening the unique species of the islands.</p>
<p>After the COVID-19 pandemic, many people left dogs and cats they had been taking care of, Cabezas said.</p>
<p>“If you don't take care of them, they become a problem and now it's a <strong>shame</strong> to see dogs everywhere. We have a big problem right now I don't know what we're going to do,” she said.</p>
<p>The non-native animals are a special threat to the giant tortoises of the Galapagos. The tortoises almost disappeared in the 1800s because of hunting. Officials have tried to protect them from humans. It has been illegal to kill a giant tortoise since 1933.</p>
<p>“In one night, a<strong> feral</strong> pig can destroy all nesting sites in an area,” Carrión said. Park rangers try to visit areas with nesting sites once a day and kill pigs when they find them. But the pigs are difficult to find, Carrion said.</p>
<p>Feral cats feed on young marine iguanas, and both pigs and cats compete for food with the tortoises.</p>
<p>Plastic is also a widespread problem in the world's oceans. One recent study reported microplastics in the bellies of Galapagos penguins.</p>
<p>“There are no animals in the Galapagos that do not have microplastics in their food,” Carrión said.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Alie Skowronski reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>species</strong><em> – n.</em> a class of creatures having common attributes and designated by a common name</p>
<p><strong>source</strong><em> –n.</em> the place from which something, such as food, comes</p>
<p><strong>unique</strong><em> – adj.</em> being the only one; being without a like or equal</p>
<p><strong>reptile</strong> <em>–n.</em> an animal with scales that lays eggs and needs sunlight to increase its body temperature to become active</p>
<p><strong>nest</strong> <em>–v.</em> to make a place where eggs can be laid or where young can be raised</p>
<p><strong>diverse </strong><em>–adj.</em> containing many different kinds of things, such as plants and animals</p>
<p><strong>shame</strong> <em>– n.</em> something to be regretted</p>
<p><strong>feral </strong>–<em> adj.</em> having escaped from domestication and become wild</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Judge Rules Google Has Illegal Monopoly over Search (2024/8/8)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/judge-rules-google-has-illegal-monopoly-over-search.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">07 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>An American judge has ruled that Google violates U.S. trade laws by operating its search engine as an illegal <strong>monopoly</strong>.</p>
<p>The ruling accuses Google of paying smartphone makers to ensure that Google's search engine is set as the <strong>default</strong> system on new devices. The U.S. Justice Department brought the <strong>antitrust</strong> case against Google's parent company, Alphabet.</p>
<p>U.S. District Judge Amit Mehta said his decision took into account all evidence and statements presented during the trial, which ended in May. When the first part of the trial ended, it was up to Mehta to decide whether any of Google's operations were illegal.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This file image shows various Google logos displayed on a Google search, Monday, Sept. 11, 2023, in New York. (AP Photo/Richard Drew, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-62fc-08dcb71004ac_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This file image shows various Google logos displayed on a Google search, Monday, Sept. 11, 2023, in New York. (AP Photo/Richard Drew, File)</span></div>
<p>Mehta wrote in his ruling, “Google is a monopolist, and it has acted as one to <strong>maintain</strong> its monopoly." Technology experts have estimated Google enjoys control of about 90 percent of the online search market and about 95 percent of smartphones.</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.bondcap.com/report/pdf/AI_Education.pdf">A recent study</a> by the California-based investment company BOND found that Google's search engine processes an estimated 8.5 billion requests per day worldwide. That result was nearly double the number of daily search requests recorded in 2012. Google's online advertising business helps fuel the majority of Alphabet's $307 billion in yearly <strong>revenue</strong>.</p>
<p>The ruling could open the door for a second trial for the court to establish ways for Google to fix its operations to obey current laws. Some experts say one possible fix could be for Google's current business structure to be broken up. Such changes could greatly reshape the current systems for online advertising.</p>
<p>Alphabet criticized the court's ruling and said it plans to appeal. "This decision recognizes that Google offers the best search engine,” the company said in a statement. It added, however, that the ruling does not permit the company “to make it easily available.</p>
<p>U.S. Attorney General Merrick Garland called the decision "a historic win for the American people.” He noted, "no company, no matter how large or influential” should remain above the law.</p>
<p>White House press secretary Karine Jean-Pierre called the decision a "pro-competition ruling” and “a victory for the American people." She said she believes all people "<strong>deserve</strong> an internet that is free, fair, and open for competition."</p>
<p>In explaining his ruling, Mehta noted Google had paid $26.3 billion in 2021 alone to make sure its search engine was included as the default system on smartphones and browsers.</p>
<p>Such payments, the judge wrote, have permitted Google to keep its strong market share over worldwide internet search. Keeping the default position represents a huge business <strong>advantage</strong> for Google over its competitors, Mehta added.</p>
<p>The judge noted that under the current system, it would be nearly impossible for any other company to secure the same kind of default agreement with smartphone makers. Such a deal would require a company willing “to pay partners upwards of billions of dollars in revenue sharing,” Mehta said.</p>
<p>Discussions in court about how Google's operations should change are set to begin on September 6 in Washington D.C.</p>
<p>The ruling is the first major decision in a series of cases brought against big technology companies in recent years, including Google, Apple, Meta and Amazon. Those cases involve antitrust, privacy and other issues.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters and Agence France-Presse. </em></p>
<p><strong>_________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>monopoly </strong><em>– n.</em> complete control of the entire supply of goods or of a service in a certain area or market</p>
<p><strong>default </strong><em>– n.</em> what exists or usually happens if no changes are made</p>
<p><strong>antitrust </strong><em>– adj. </em>related to efforts to prevent companies from working together to unfairly control prices or create a monopoly</p>
<p><strong>maintain </strong><em>– v.</em> keep something going</p>
<p><strong>revenue </strong><em>– n.</em> income a government or company regularly receives</p>
<p><strong>deserve </strong><em>– v. </em>to earn or be given something because of things you do or qualities you have</p>
<p><strong>dominant </strong><em>– adj.</em> more important or notable than anything else of the same kind</p>
<p><strong>advantage </strong><em>– n. </em>a condition that provides a greater chance of success</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Korean Air Takes Instant Noodles Off the Menu (2024/8/8)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/korean-air-takes-instant-noodles-off-the-menu.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">07 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>For many years, cups of <strong>instant </strong>noodles have been a favorite among Korean Air passengers. However, they will no longer be available for economy-class travelers starting August 15, said a spokesperson for the Seoul-based airline.</p>
<p>Korean Air said its decision was a safety measure to deal with increased <strong>turbulence</strong>, “aimed at preventing burn accidents.” Turbulence, or irregular movements from up and down air currents, can cause the hot cups of noodles to spill.</p>
<p>In addition to regular meals, instant noodles are currently part of Korean Air's self-service food, for economy passengers on long trips. In this week's announcement, the airline added that it will offer other food items for economy travelers. The new offerings include sandwiches, corn dogs, and hot pockets.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Korean Air will no longer offer instant noodles to Economy class passengers starting August 15, 2024, a spokesperson for the Seoul-based airline confirmed. (AP Photo/Lee Jin-man, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-6a7f-08dcb58e454c_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Korean Air will no longer offer instant noodles to Economy class passengers starting August 15, 2024, a spokesperson for the Seoul-based airline confirmed. (AP Photo/Lee Jin-man, File)</span></div>
<p>However, business-class and first-class passengers will still get their noodles. Korean Air told the BBC that the noodles are brought individually to business-class and first-class travelers. This reduces the risk of spills and burns.</p>
<p>Concern about the dangers of serving hot food and liquids on airplanes is not new. Over the years, several airlines have faced legal actions from travelers who say they suffered serious burns after having hot coffee, for example, spilled on them during a <strong>flight</strong>.</p>
<p>In 2019, the European Union's highest court ruled that an airline can be held responsible if a passenger is injured in this way. This is the case even if turbulence or other flight-related reasons did not cause the spill.</p>
<p>But turbulence, of course, still adds to the risk. Flying through unstable air can make balancing something like hot soup or drink much more difficult.</p>
<p>Several turbulence-related injuries have been reported over the years. But most injuries are minor. And airlines have made continuous improvements in reducing the number of in-flight accidents. Those include stopping service when needed or taking extra care when giving out certain drinks.</p>
<p>Still, rough air might be getting harder and harder to avoid. Weather and airline experts note increasing reports of turbulence. They point to the possible effects climate change may have on flying conditions.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Wyatte Grantham-Philips reported this story for the Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><em>_____________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>instant </strong><em>– adj.</em><strong> </strong>premixed or precooked for easy final preparation</p>
<p><strong>turbulence </strong><em>– n. </em>irregular atmospheric motion especially when characterized by up-and-down currents</p>
<p><strong>flight </strong><em>– n. </em>a trip made by or in an airplane or spacecraft</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Severe Drought Returns to the Amazon Earlier Than Expected (2024/8/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/severe-drought-returns-to-the-amazon-earlier-than-expected.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The Amazon <strong>Basin</strong> is facing one of the most severe <strong>droughts</strong> in recent years, the Amazon Cooperation Treaty Organization (or ACTO) said.</p>
<p>As the dry season begins in August, many of its rivers are already at very low levels. And several South American countries are preparing to deal with increasing forest fires, water shortages and higher food prices.</p>
<p>In several rivers in the southwestern Amazon, water levels are the lowest on record for this time of year. August and September are usually the driest months. That is also when most fires happen. The ACTO says the most affected countries so far this year are Bolivia, Peru and Brazil.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Boats sit on the bank of the Acre River, the main water source for the city of Rio Branco, which is facing water shortages amid a drought in Acre state, Brazil, Friday, Aug. 2, 2024. (AP Photo/Marcos Vicentti)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-52de-08dcb56c1f96_cx1_cy11_cw98_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Boats sit on the bank of the Acre River, the main water source for the city of Rio Branco, which is facing water shortages amid a drought in Acre state, Brazil, Friday, Aug. 2, 2024. (AP Photo/Marcos Vicentti)</span></div>
<p>Recently, Brazil's federal water agency declared a water shortage in two major basins, Madeira and Purus. Together, they cover an area nearly the size of Mexico. And in Brazil's Acre state, the drought has already caused water shortages in the city of Rio Branco. In June, neighboring Amazonas state declared a water shortage in 20 of its communities.</p>
<p>The declared shortages came more than two months earlier than last year when most of the Amazon Basin suffered its worst drought on record.</p>
<p>The 2023 drought <strong>isolated</strong> people who depend on water for transportation. Smoke from forest fires made the air in cities unhealthy to breathe. And high water temperatures killed more than 100 river dolphins.</p>
<p>The Madeira River is one of the largest rivers in the Basin. It is also an important waterway for soybeans and fuel. The river's level dropped below three meters near Porto Velho on July 20. In 2023, that happened nearly a month later on August 15.</p>
<p>The low water level means fewer boats could travel the river at night. And two of Brazil's largest hydroelectric plants may halt production, as happened last year.</p>
<p>In the Amazonas town of Envira, nearby rivers have become too <strong>shallow</strong> to travel by boat. Local officials have asked old people and pregnant women to move from communities by the river to the city center. This is because medical help may not be able to reach them.</p>
<p>The low water is also affecting food prices. Farmers who produce cassava flour cannot get it to market. As a result, this important Amazon food has more than doubled in price, local government says.</p>
<p>Another worry is fire. There were around 25,000 fires from January until late July — the highest number for this period in almost twenty years. In the Amazon, fires are mostly human-made. People use the fires to manage fields and clear areas where trees have been cut down.</p>
<p>Drought is not the only weather event affecting areas in Brazil's Acre state. Severe flooding hit 19 of the state's 22 communities last year.</p>
<p>“It's been two years <strong>in a row</strong> of extreme events,” said Julie Messias, Acre's secretary of environment. She added, “The result is that we are facing a threat of food shortage. First, the crops were flooded, and now the planting period is very dry.”</p>
<p>The Amazon is the world's largest river system, carrying 20 percent of the world's river water into the oceans each year.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Fabiano Maisonnave wrote this story for The Associated Press. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>basin </strong><em>-n. </em>the land around a river and the area from which water flows into it</p>
<p><strong>drought </strong><em>-n. </em>an extended period of very dry weather</p>
<p><strong>isolate </strong><em>-v. </em>to keep physically separated and away from other people or things</p>
<p><strong>shallow </strong><em>-adj. </em>not deep</p>
<p><strong>in a row </strong><em>-prep. phrase</em> consecutively</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Algae Blamed for Sickening California Sea Lions (2024/8/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/algae-blamed-for-sickening-california-sea-lions.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A California wildlife organization says it has been rescuing sick sea lions in recent weeks showing signs of <strong>algae</strong> poisoning.</p>
<p>On August 1, the Santa Barbara-based Channel Islands Marine &amp; Wildlife Institute said teams had rescued at least 23 animals. The U.S. Vandenberg Space Force Base recently <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.facebook.com/SLD30/">released photos</a> on social media of sea lions being taken from one of its beaches.</p>
<p>The institute said that since July 26, it had received numerous reports daily of sick lions along a 250-kilometer stretch of coastline in Santa Barbara and Ventura counties.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This photo provided by the Channel Islands Marine &amp; Wildlife Institute (CIMWI) shows a sick sea lion on San Buenaventura State Beach in Ventura, California on July 29, 2024. (Channel Islands Marine &amp; Wildlife Institute via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-54b5-08dcb62de4ca_cx0_cy37_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This photo provided by the Channel Islands Marine &amp; Wildlife Institute (CIMWI) shows a sick sea lion on San Buenaventura State Beach in Ventura, California on July 29, 2024. (Channel Islands Marine &amp; Wildlife Institute via AP)</span></div>
<p>The group said in a statement the sea creatures were found to be suffering from the effects of domoic acid, a poison that can harm the brain and heart. The release of the acid in a large ocean event is known as an algae <strong>bloom</strong>.</p>
<p>The poison is produced by microscopic algae eaten by shellfish or small fish. Those shellfish or fish are often then eaten by sea lions, dolphins or birds. The algae can also sicken humans.</p>
<p>Among the signs of sickness experienced by affected sea lions are unusual head movements, <strong>disorientation</strong>, foaming at the mouth and seizures.</p>
<p>In a message <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.facebook.com/CIMWI">published</a> on Facebook August 4, the institute said the poisoning event was “heating up,” with new cases of sick sea lions still appearing at multiple beaches. It explained that rescue teams first try to get the animals in a net so they can be transported for treatment and then returned to the sea.</p>
<p>The U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) says poisoning events linked to domoic acid are common along the California coast. Experts said the latest poisoning event seems to mostly be affecting adult female sea lions.</p>
<p>Last year, an especially severe poisoning event killed hundreds of sea lions and a number of dolphins during the first weeks of June.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>algae </strong><em>- n.</em> a plant with no stem or leaves that grows in or near water</p>
<p><strong>bloom </strong><em>– v.</em> to become densely populated with microorganisms such as algae</p>
<p><strong>disorient </strong><em>– v. </em>to make someone confused or unsure</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How a Small College Became a Top High-tech University (2024/8/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/how-a-small-college-became-a-top-high-tech-university.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A measure begun 40 years ago by South Dakota lawmakers and state higher education leaders has turned a small rural college into one of the top high-tech universities in the United States.</p>
<p>It began at a time when the future of Dakota State College itself was in question.</p>
<p>In 1984, the South Dakota Board of Regents, which oversees the school, was under pressure to cut its budget. It closed one college and turned it into a prison.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="MadLabs research facility of Dakota State University is a hub for cyber research. (Bart Pfankuch / South Dakota News Watch)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-2ebd-08dcb2212e2d_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">MadLabs research facility of Dakota State University is a hub for cyber research. (Bart Pfankuch / South Dakota News Watch)</span></div>
<p>Soon after, a new law went into effect. The measure put technology at the center of all Dakota State's study programs.</p>
<p>The decision to reinvent a teacher's college founded in 1881 in a rural city of 6,000 people seemed risky. But, at around the same time, Citibank, a major financial services company, decided to headquarter its credit card business in Sioux Falls, a city near the college.</p>
<p>José-Marie Griffiths is the current president of Dakota State University (DSU). The school changed its name from college to university in 1989.</p>
<p>Griffiths said Citibank was looking for computer programmers, and “somebody came up with the idea that, well, we could turn this college that's <strong>fumbling</strong> a little bit into a computer school with software development and engineering.”</p>
<p>Griffiths told <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.sdnewswatch.org/dakota-state-university-madison-cybsersecurity-program-growth/">South Dakota News Watch</a>, “That way, we could supply the needed programmers to the Sioux Falls workforce for Citibank and <strong>ultimately</strong> for others....”</p>
<p><strong>Change was not fully supported at first</strong></p>
<p>Lynette Molstad Gorder was teaching at DSU 40 years ago when the change to a high-tech campus began. She said, at first, some members of the college community were unsure about the change, and its effect on people and programs.</p>
<p>“Later on we looked upon it as a welcome opportunity,” she said. “It was kind of hazy (at first) and then all of a sudden, it just clicked.”</p>
<p>Suddenly, computers replaced pens, pencils and typewriters in classrooms. And later, the move into computer science and then cyber security, she said.</p>
<p>The jump into technology at DSU started with a bachelor's degree in computer science using teaching materials from IBM. The teaching of computer science and software development along with industry partnership laid the groundwork for what was to come, Griffiths said.</p>
<p>With a mix of private and public money, the university expanded the school and its offerings.</p>
<p>In 2004, the National Security Agency named DSU a Center of Academic Excellence in computer security, one of the first in the nation.</p>
<p>The number of students has also risen steadily, from 867 in 1985 to 3,509 in 2023. The university said DSU now offers 44 degrees, including seven master's degrees and four doctoral programs.</p>
<p>In 2017, DSU started Madison Cyber Labs with money from the state and local businesses. It expanded research at the university to include cyber security, machine learning, and artificial intelligence, among others.</p>
<p>The school is now planning an expansion into Sioux Falls itself. The plan includes partnerships with another research center and a cyber academy program for high school students.</p>
<p>DSU is also pushing the state for more money to start a new center for quantum computing.</p>
<p><strong>Opportunities for DSU graduates</strong></p>
<p>Jen Easterly is director of the federal Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency. She was the lead speaker at a DSU cybersecurity event last March.</p>
<p>Easterly said that before she visited Madison, she had been hearing increasing discussion on the national level about the growth and<strong> innovation</strong> taking place at DSU.</p>
<p>She said, “The ideas generated at forums like this are just further proof that it doesn't matter the size of the university. ...”</p>
<p>Alexis Kulm graduated from DSU in December of 2022. She studied cyber operations there.</p>
<p>The 23-year-old said she liked the small-town feel of the college. She took classes in web and network design, computer programming and malware analysis. All of them, she said, helped prepare her for the cyber workplace.</p>
<p>“You get a strong real-world education in your classes,” Kulm said.</p>
<p>Kulm also said she had several job offers after graduating. She chose Sanford Health, a company in Sioux Falls. It has a partnership with the university to increase employment opportunities for DSU graduates.</p>
<p>Kulm is not the only DSU graduate to stay in South Dakota. Jon Waldman and Chad Knutson were in the class of 2006. Soon after graduating, they set up a business together right in Madison. Their 90-employee company SBS CyberSecurity serves the banking industry in 49 states.</p>
<p>Waldman said DSU has “a commitment to innovation” that makes it easy for students to remain on top of the always-changing cyber technology and security industry.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p>And I'm Mario Ritter Jr. </p>
<p><em>Bart Pfankuch reported this story for </em><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.sdnewswatch.org/" target="_blank"><em>South Dakota News Watch</em></a><em> and distributed it through a partnership with The Associated Press. Hai Do adapted the story for VOA Learning English</em><em>.</em></p>
<p><em>______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>fumble</strong> - v. to handle something clumsily or awkwardly</p>
<p><strong>ultimately</strong> - adv. at the end of the process</p>
<p><strong>innovation</strong> - n. new idea, method</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Ancient Egyptian Woman’s Suffering Frozen in Final Scream (2024/8/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/ancient-egyptian-woman-s-suffering-frozen-in-final-scream.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists now have an explanation for the mysterious remains of an ancient Egyptian woman who has her mouth open in what appears to be a <strong>scream</strong>.</p>
<p>Scientists used a special computer aided X-ray, or CT scan, of the woman's body. What they found suggested that the so-called "Screaming Woman" <strong>mummy</strong> may have died in pain and experienced a form of muscular hardening known as a cadaveric <strong>spasm</strong>. This rare kind of spasm happens at the moment of death.</p>
<p>The examination found that the woman was about 48 years old when she died. Cairo University's Sahar Saleem said she had lived with mild <strong>arthritis</strong> of the spine and had lost some teeth.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="The face of the " at="" august="" cairo="" egypt="" egyptian="" handout="" in="" is="" january="" mummy="" museum="" on="" photograph="" released="" reuters="" saleem="" screaming="" seen="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/cb26197c-2c9a-434c-bca9-88d379eca2ed_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg" the="" this="" via="" woman=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">The face of the "Screaming Woman" mummy is seen at the Egyptian Museum in Cairo, Egypt, January 18, 2023 in this handout photograph released on August 2, 2024. (Sahar Saleem/Handout via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>Saleem led the study that appeared recently in the publication Frontiers in Medicine.</p>
<p>The woman's body was well-<strong>preserved</strong> although it had been <strong>embalmed</strong> 3,500 years ago. Embalmers used costly imported materials such as juniper oil and frankincense resin, Saleem added.</p>
<p>The ancient Egyptians considered preservation of the body after death important for securing a good existence in the afterlife. It was a custom to remove the internal organs during the mummification process. But the organ removals had not taken place with this woman.</p>
<p>Saleem said, "In ancient Egypt, the embalmers took care of the dead body, so it would look beautiful for the afterlife.”</p>
<p>She explained that embalmers were interested in closing the mouth of the dead. Embalmers kept the <strong>jaw</strong> in place by tying the jaw to the head. This prevented the normal jaw drop that occurs after death.</p>
<p>But the embalmers were likely not careless with the so-called “Screaming Woman.” They used high quality materials and gave her costly jewelry and a wig, Saleem said.</p>
<p>She added that this evidence "opened the way to other explanations of the widely opened mouth.”</p>
<p>The woman may have died screaming from pain. And the muscles of the face may have become tense to preserve this appearance “at the time of death due to cadaveric spasm," Saleem explained.</p>
<p>She said that the full history of the woman's death is unknown, adding the cause of her facial appearance cannot be known “with certainty."</p>
<p>Cadaveric spasm is a poorly understood condition. It is thought to happen after severe physical or emotional suffering. The <strong>contracted</strong> facial muscles become tense and unmoving immediately following death.</p>
<p>Saleem explained that unlike the stiffening of muscles and joints that happens after death - "cadaveric spasm affects only one group of muscles, not the entire body."</p>
<p>Asked whether the woman may have been embalmed while alive, Saleem added, "I don't believe that this is possible."</p>
<p>Saleem was unable to find out how the woman died.</p>
<p>The "Screaming Woman" was found in the ancient city of Thebes during a scientific search of the burial of a high-ranking official named Senmut in 1935.</p>
<p>The mummy was inside a wooden <strong>coffin</strong> in a room beneath Senmut's family burial area. Her identity is unknown, but her costly jewelry shows her important position.</p>
<p>"She was likely a close family member to be buried and share the family's<strong> eternal </strong>resting place," Saleem said.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Will Dunham reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>scream</strong> <em>–n.</em> to shout in a high voice or high pitch</p>
<p><strong>mummy </strong><em>– n.</em> a body embalmed or treated for burial with preservatives in the manner of the ancient Egyptians</p>
<p><strong>spasm</strong> <em>– n.</em> an involuntary and abnormal muscular contraction</p>
<p><strong>arthritis</strong> <em>– n.</em> inflammation of joints</p>
<p><strong>preserve</strong> <em>– v.</em> to keep free from decay or decomposition</p>
<p><strong>embalm</strong> –<em> v.</em> to treat (a dead body) so as to protect from decay</p>
<p><strong>jaw </strong><em>–n.</em> the bones that form the lower part of the mouth and which hold the lower teeth</p>
<p><strong>contract</strong> <em>–v. </em>to increase in tension and become shorter or smaller</p>
<p><strong>coffin</strong> <em>– n.</em> a box for burying a body</p>
<p><strong>eternal</strong> <em>–adj. </em>lasting forever</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Twice-yearly Injections Cut HIV Infections by 100 Percent (2024/8/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/study-twice-yearly-injections-cut-hiv-infections-by-100-percent.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>A new study has found that the twice-yearly injections of a treatment for AIDS were 100 percent effective in preventing new HIV infections in women.</p>
<p>The U.S. drugmaker Gilead sells the drug treatment under the name Sunlenca. The drug is approved in the United States, Canada, Europe and in other places, but only as a treatment for HIV.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A pharmacist holds a vial of lenacapavir, the new HIV prevention injectable drug, at the Desmond Tutu Health Foundation's Masiphumelele Research Site, in Cape Town, South Africa, July 23, 2024. (AP Photo/Nardus Engelbrecht)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-88d2-08dcb0038d29_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A pharmacist holds a vial of lenacapavir, the new HIV prevention injectable drug, at the Desmond Tutu Health Foundation's Masiphumelele Research Site, in Cape Town, South Africa, July 23, 2024. (AP Photo/Nardus Engelbrecht)</span></div>
<p>The researchers ended the study early because of the surprisingly good results. All the people in the study were then offered the injection, or shot, also known as lenacapavir.</p>
<p>Thandeka Nkosi helped run the Gilead research at the Desmond Tutu Health Foundation in Masiphumelele, South Africa. She said the idea of a twice-a-year shot is “quite revolutionary news.”</p>
<p>About 5,300 young women and girls in South Africa and Uganda took part in the study. Researchers reported that none of the women injected with the treatment became infected with HIV. Among those given daily prevention pills, about two percent became infected with HIV from infected sex partners.</p>
<p>Gilead said it is waiting for results of testing in men before seeking permission<strong> </strong>to use it as protection against HIV.</p>
<p>The <em>New England Journal of Medicine</em> published the results on July 24. Experts also discussed the study at an AIDS conference in Munich, Germany. Gilead paid for the study and some of the researchers are company employees.</p>
<p>There are other ways to prevent HIV infection. These include devices like condoms or drugs taken daily by mouth. However, regular use has been a problem in Africa. In the new study, only about 30 percent of people given Gilead's Truvada or Descovy HIV prevention pills actually took them. That percentage also dropped over time.</p>
<p>Nkosi said the twice-yearly injections give people a choice. She added that injections took away the “<strong>stigma</strong> around taking pills” to prevent HIV.</p>
<p><strong>High cost of the drug</strong></p>
<p>As an HIV treatment, the drug costs more than $40,000 a year in the U.S. Health insurance companies pay part of the cost and patients pay the balance.</p>
<p>People working to stop the spread of AIDS are interested in the Sunlenca shots. But they are concerned that Gilead has not agreed on a lower price for those who need the shots the most.</p>
<p>“Gilead has a tool that could change the <strong>trajectory</strong> of the HIV <strong>epidemic</strong>,” said Winnie Byanyima. She is executive director of the Geneva-based UNAIDS.</p>
<p>She said the U.N. AIDS agency urged Gilead to share Sunlenca's <strong>patent </strong>with a U.N. program. The program's goal is to let <strong>generic </strong>drugmakers manufacture low-cost versions of drugs for poor countries.</p>
<p>Dr. Helen Bygrave of Doctors Without Borders said in a statement that the injections could “reverse the epidemic if it is made available in the countries with the highest rate of new infections.” She urged Gilead to publish a lower price for Sunlenca that all countries could pay.</p>
<p>In other research presented at the AIDS conference, Andrew Hill of the University of Liverpool and others said the drug's price would go down. They estimated that once production of Sunlenca is expanded to treat 10 million people, the price would fall to about $40 per treatment.</p>
<p>He said it was important for health officials to get Sunlenca as soon as possible. “This is about as close as you can get to an HIV vaccine,” Hill said.</p>
<p>Gilead said it would seek a “voluntary <strong>licensing</strong> program.” It said a small number of generic producers would be permitted to make the drug.</p>
<p>In a statement last month, Gilead said it was too early to say how much Sunlenca would cost in poorer countries. Dr. Jared Baeten is a product development official with Gilead. He said the company was already talking to generic drugmakers and understood how “deeply important it is that we move at speed.”</p>
<p>Byanyima said many groups need long-lasting protection from HIV infection. They include women and girls who are victims of violence and <strong>homosexual</strong> men in countries where homosexuality is criminalized.</p>
<p>UNAIDS says that in 2022 46 percent of new HIV infections in the world were in women and girls. In Africa, females are three times more likely to get HIV than males, the U.N. group said.</p>
<p>Recently, UNAIDS released a report on the state of the HIV epidemic. It said that fewer people were infected with HIV in 2023 than at any time since the late 1980s.</p>
<p>The U.N. says HIV infects about 1.3 million people every year and kills more than 600,000, mainly in Africa. While much progress has been made in Africa, HIV infections are rising in Eastern Europe, Latin America, and the Middle East.</p>
<p>And that's the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo. And I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Maria Cheng and Gerald Imray reported this story for The Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;</em></p>
<p><em>_____________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>stigma</strong> –n. something that people feel ashamed about</p>
<p><strong>trajectory </strong>–n. the direction that something is going</p>
<p><strong>epidemic</strong> –n. when an infectious disease spreads over a population in a wide area</p>
<p><strong>patent </strong>–n. protection for the legal owner of a process or product against having intellectual property copies or stolen</p>
<p><strong>generic </strong>–adj. not sold under a brand name; a manufactured product that is not protected by a patent</p>
<p><strong>licensing </strong>–n. the legal process of permitting the production of a product protected by patent law by a company that does not own the patent</p>
<p><strong>homosexual </strong>–adj. the state of being sexually interested in the same sex</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>NASA Rover Captures Rock Showing Possible Signs of Microbial Life (2024/8/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/nasa-rover-captures-rock-showing-possible-signs-of-microbial-life.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A Mars explorer operated by the American space agency NASA has captured a rock that scientists say shows possible signs of ancient microbial life.</p>
<p>NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.jpl.nasa.gov/news/nasas-perseverance-rover-scientists-find-intriguing-mars-rock">said</a> in a recent statement that the Perseverance explorer, or rover, collected the rock on July 21. Scientists working on the Perseverance team <strong>nicknamed</strong> the rock “Cheyava Falls,” after the tallest waterfall in the Grand Canyon.</p>
<p>The rover's exploration area is believed to include a former river valley measuring about 400 meters wide. The valley is thought to have formed by water rushing into Jezero <strong>Crater</strong> billions of years ago. Scientists believe the area around Jezero Crater contained large bodies of water in the distant past.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="NASA's Perseverance rover made several new discoveries the space agency says support existing evidence that ancient microbial life may have lived on Mars when the planet had running water. (Credit: NASA/JPL-Caltech/MSSS Full Image Details)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-f15b-08dcb2614ede_cx2_cy3_cw93_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">NASA's Perseverance rover made several new discoveries the space agency says support existing evidence that ancient microbial life may have lived on Mars when the planet had running water. (Credit: NASA/JPL-Caltech/MSSS Full Image Details)</span></div>
<p>NASA's statement says the rock shows signs of “chemical <strong>signatures</strong> and structures that could possibly have been formed by life billions of years ago...”</p>
<p>NASA team members based their findings on examinations of the rock with imaging equipment and multiple scientific instruments. But they noted that additional research is needed to confirm a history of microbial life.</p>
<p>The examinations did suggest the rock contains “organic compounds,” NASA said. But the statement added, “While such carbon-based molecules are considered the building blocks of life, they also can be formed by non-biological processes.”</p>
<p>Perseverance uses its robotic arm and <strong>drilling</strong> equipment to capture rock and soil <strong>samples</strong> from the Martian surface. So far, it has collected 22 samples. The rover has secured the samples in special containers and they are to be picked up and returned to Earth during a future mission.</p>
<p>Ken Farley is a project scientist with the Perseverance team at Caltech in Pasadena, California. He said, “Cheyava Falls is the most <strong>puzzling</strong>, complex, and potentially important rock yet investigated by Perseverance.”</p>
<p>Farley said unusual color spots and other structural elements in the samples suggest “chemical reactions” that might have given energy to ancient microbial life. But he noted that so far, scientists have not been able to identify exactly how the rock formed.</p>
<p>The team described the rock as containing white <strong>veins</strong> that may have been created by the substance calcium sulfate. Between the veins, examiners found lines of material with a reddish color. These lines suggest the presence of hematite, a common substance found in many rocks on Earth.</p>
<p>David Flannery is an astrobiologist and member of the Perseverance science team from the Queensland University of Technology in Australia. He said that on Earth, these kinds of rock elements are often linked “with the <strong>fossilized</strong> record of microbes living in the subsurface."</p>
<p>The scientists said the new findings strengthen existing evidence that such rocks may have been created or were changed by flowing water on Mars billions of years ago.</p>
<p>Caltech's Farley said the rock sample had already been imaged and examined with lasers, X-ray equipment and other instruments as much as possible in recent weeks. He noted that Perseverance has done as much as it can to examine the newly discovered samples.</p>
<p>Farley added, “To fully understand what really happened in that Martian river valley at Jezero Crater billions of years ago, we'd want to bring the Cheyava Falls sample back to Earth.” That way, he said, “it can be studied with the powerful instruments available in laboratories.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from NASA and Agence-France Presse.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>nickname - </strong><em>n.</em><strong> </strong>a name used informally instead of an official name</p>
<p><strong>crater</strong><em> - n.</em> a hole left in the ground by an object that hits it with a huge force</p>
<p><strong>signature </strong><em>– n.</em> a feature in the appearance or qualities of a natural object</p>
<p><strong>drill </strong><em>– v. </em>to make a hole in a hard substance using a special tool</p>
<p><strong>puzzling </strong><em>– adj.</em> difficult to understand or figure out</p>
<p><strong>vein </strong><em>– n.</em> one of the thin lines found on an object</p>
<p><strong>fossil </strong><em>– n. </em>part of a plant or animal from many years ago that has been preserved in rock</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>African Health Officials Warn of Mpox Spread (2024/8/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/african-health-officials-warn-of-mpox-spread.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">04 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>African health officials say mpox infections on the continent have risen by 160 percent in 2024. They expect the spread to continue, they say, as Africa lacks effective treatments or vaccines for the viral disease.</p>
<p>The Africa Centers for Disease Control and Prevention reports that mpox, also known as m<i><i>onkey</i></i>pox, has been identified in 10 African countries this year.</p>
<p>Burundi and Rwanda both reported the virus for the first time recently.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Vials of single doses of the Jynneos vaccine for m&lt;I&gt;&lt;I&gt;onkey&lt;/I&gt;&lt;/I&gt;pox are seen from a cooler at a vaccinations site on Aug. 29, 2022, in the Brooklyn borough of New York. (AP Photo/Jeenah Moon, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-f50a-08dcb24a7fea_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Vials of single doses of the Jynneos vaccine for m<i><i>onkey</i></i>pox are seen from a cooler at a vaccinations site on Aug. 29, 2022, in the Brooklyn borough of New York. (AP Photo/Jeenah Moon, File)</span></div>
<p>New outbreaks were also declared this week in Kenya and Central African Republic.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, Kenya's Health Ministry said it found mpox in a passenger traveling from Uganda to Rwanda at a border crossing in southern Kenya. In a statement, the ministry said that a single mpox case was enough to require an outbreak declaration.</p>
<p>The Africa CDC has reported more than 14,000 cases of the disease. More than 96 percent of cases and deaths are in the Democratic Republic of the Congo. Earlier this year, scientists reported the appearance of a new form of mpox in a Congolese mining town. They fear it might spread more easily among people. Mpox spreads through close contact with infected people, including sex.</p>
<p>The Africa CDC said the mpox death rate is three percent. It said the rate “has been much higher on the African continent compared to the rest of the world.” During the global mpox emergency in 2022, less than one percent of people infected with the virus died.</p>
<p>The version of mpox in the Democratic Republic of the Congo could kill up to 10 percent of people infected, experts reported. The center noted that both of the mpox cases in Rwanda had been in Congo before testing positive.</p>
<p>A study of patients hospitalized from October to January in eastern Congo suggested that recent genetic changes in the virus were the result of ongoing spread in people.</p>
<p>In earlier mpox outbreaks, patients suffered <strong>lesions</strong> mainly on the chest, hands and feet. The new form of mpox causes less severe <strong>symptoms</strong> and lesions mainly appear on the genitals.</p>
<p>The Africa CDC said nearly 70 percent of cases in Congo are in children younger than 15. That group also represents 85 percent of deaths from the disease. The agency said the number of deaths across the continent has jumped by 19 percent since last year.</p>
<p>The medical aid group Doctors Without Borders called the expanding mpox outbreak “worrying.” It also said the disease has been found in camps for displaced people in Congo's North Kivu area, which shares a border with Rwanda.</p>
<p>Dr. Louis Massing is medical director for Congo at Doctors Without Borders. Massing said, “There is a real risk of explosion, given the huge population movements in and out.”</p>
<p>Mpox outbreaks in the West have been uncommon because of vaccines and treatments. But few treatments have been available in African countries including the Congo.</p>
<p>In May, the WHO said no donors had provided money to fight the spread of mpox.</p>
<p>The Coalition for Epidemic Preparedness Innovations is an aid organization based in Norway. It recently announced the start of an mpox vaccine study in Congo and other African countries. It aims to learn if vaccine treatment given just after infection could prevent severity of the disease.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Jean Fernand Koena and Maria Cheng reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>ravaging </strong><em>–adj.</em> damaging or harming badly</p>
<p><strong>lesions </strong><em>–n. (medical)</em> an area of infected skin that is usually swollen, red, bleeding or releasing fluid</p>
<p><strong>symptoms </strong><em>–n.</em> signs that an infection is present</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Singapore Approves Insects as Food (2024/8/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/singapore-approves-insects-as-food.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Singapore's House of Seafood restaurant is the country's first eatery to offer insects to <strong>customers</strong>.</p>
<p>The change comes after the city state's food <strong>authority</strong> recently approved 16 kinds of insects for humans to eat, including grasshoppers, grubs and mealworms.</p>
<p>Crickets and other insects have long been eaten as street food in Southeast Asia. But the wealthy financial center places heavy safety and cleanliness restrictions on food imports.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Restaurant owner Francis Ng prepares house crickets to add to his insect-based dishes at the House of Seafood restaurant in Singapore on July 16, 2024. (REUTERS/Edgar Su)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/682656eb-ce07-4736-9c9b-aebf5be77f04_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Restaurant owner Francis Ng prepares house crickets to add to his insect-based dishes at the House of Seafood restaurant in Singapore on July 16, 2024. (REUTERS/Edgar Su)</span></div>
<p>Francis Ng is the chief of House of Seafood. He said customers love it when the <strong>dishes</strong> bring attention to the insects. For example, the restaurant offers a tofu dish made to look like bugs are crawling out of it and a dish of rice balls <strong>decorated </strong>with silkworms.</p>
<p>"It looks scarier so customers can film (it) for their Tiktok," said Ng. He added that customers had been calling him regularly to plan a tasting of the dishes.</p>
<p>The restaurant has created a menu with 30 dishes that <strong>feature</strong> insects, which they can sell to the public once their importers are approved by the food authority. For now, Ng is offering free <strong>samples</strong>.</p>
<p>In 2019, Singapore declared it was aiming to produce 30 percent of its nutritional needs by 2030. Currently, around 90 percent of food is imported.</p>
<p>Food security expert Paul Teng said insects could certainly help move towards this goal - if people got over "the <strong>yuck </strong>factor.”</p>
<p>"Most insects are almost all protein," said Teng. Teng added that there needs to be local production to make this new way to get protein less costly.</p>
<p>"Getting people to accept insects in their diet is a <strong>challenge</strong>. But really, it's a normal food <strong>item</strong>. Let's do something about it to prepare the consumer for it," he said. "Me personally, I have no problem eating insects."</p>
<p>The United Nations has said bugs can be a <strong>sustainable</strong> way to get protein to feed the world. The U.N. estimates the global population will reach 9.7 billion by 2050. Extreme weather and conflicts have also increased the interest in insects as high-quality, low-cost nutrition.</p>
<p>In Singapore, all insects approved for human food must be farmed in a controlled environment. The insects cannot be taken from the wild. And they cannot be fed materials like human or animal waste or <strong>rotten</strong> food, the food agency says.</p>
<p>There has been local interest in importing insects, but cost remains an issue for now: Ng said insects make up 10 percent of his costs at the House of Seafood, and they are all imported.</p>
<p>"The price is definitely higher than eggs," he said.</p>
<p>It is too early to tell if insects will become an important part of the Singapore diet or whether demand will decrease as it has for <strong>fake</strong> meat products.</p>
<p>But for now, some diners say they are happy to develop a taste for bugs.</p>
<p>"If they have a higher source of protein, why not? I'll add it to my daily meal and daily food intake," said Bregria Sim, a 23-year-old logistics executive. She added that she would be willing to pay about $30 for the unusual dishes.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Xinghui Kok reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>customer</strong><em> –n.</em> a person or group who buys goods or services</p>
<p><strong>authority</strong> <em>–n. </em>an agency or office that oversees a public service or activity and has the power to make and enforce rules governing it</p>
<p><strong>dish</strong><em> –n.</em> a particular kind of food</p>
<p><strong>decorated</strong> <em>–adj.</em> made to look in a pleasing way</p>
<p><strong>feature</strong> <em>– v. </em> to bring attention to some element of a product or object</p>
<p><strong>sample </strong>–<em> n.</em> a small amount of something that is tested, or tasted, to see if it is good</p>
<p><strong>yuck</strong><em> – interjection</em> used to express strong dislike or displeasure</p>
<p><strong>challenge </strong><em>– n. </em>a task or problem</p>
<p><strong>item</strong><em> –n.</em> one of a group of similar things</p>
<p><strong>sustainable</strong><em> – adj.</em> relating to a method of using a resource so that it is not permanently damaged or used up</p>
<p><strong>rotten</strong> <em>–adj.</em> breaking down, decaying or impossible to eat</p>
<p><strong>fake</strong><em> –adj.</em> having the appearance of the real thing, but not real</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>When Is Two Too Many? When It's a 'Double Whammy'! (2024/8/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/when-is-two-too-many-when-it-s-a-double-whammy.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>On this program, we explore words and expressions in the English language. We give definitions, examples and notes on usage.</p>
<p>Today we talk about a word with an unusual history – <u>whammy</u>. A <u>whammy</u> can be a magical <strong>spell</strong> that brings bad luck. It can also be an attack or a damaging, destructive blow. A blow is an incident or event that hits you hard.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - An art installation dubbed " artist="" at="" by="" china="" double="" ducks="" dutch="" florentijn="" harbour="" hofman="" hong="" in="" is="" june="" kong="" seen="" siu="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1a7f6686-b59c-4b86-953e-7f923c29c73a_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg" tyrone="" victoria=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - An art installation dubbed "Double Ducks" by Dutch artist Florentijn Hofman, is seen at Victoria Harbour, in Hong Kong, China June 9, 2023. (REUTERS/Tyrone Siu)</span></div>
<p>So, one <u>whammy</u> is bad. But what happens when you have two?</p>
<p>That is called a <u>double whammy</u>.</p>
<p>People traditionally say they have been hit with a <u>double whammy</u>!”</p>
<p>The online dictionary Merriam-Webster defines a <u>double whammy</u> as a combination of two usually unfavorable forces, <strong>circumstances</strong>, or effects. Two bad things happen at the same time to make something really unpleasant or difficult.</p>
<p>It can also mean that two bad things happen <strong>consecutively</strong>, or one after the other.</p>
<p>The <strong>origin</strong> of the expression is unclear. Some guess it comes from taking the word “wham” which describes a hard <strong>punch</strong> or blow and adding a -y ending which makes it sound funny.</p>
<p>Others say the <strong>cartoonist</strong> Al Capp popularized the word <u>whammy</u> in his 1950s <strong>comic strip</strong> Li'l Abner. A <strong>character</strong> named Evil-Eye Fleegle could stop someone by simply looking at them. The single <u>whammy</u> was a look with one eye, and the feared <u>double whammy</u> used both eyes.</p>
<p>Now, let's listen to the expression used in a sentence.</p>
<p><em>Today, my friend Jonah lost his job. And then, on the way home, he fell and broke his leg. Talk about a <u>double whammy</u>! It has NOT been his best day. </em></p>
<p>Here is another example of the expression <u>double whammy</u>.</p>
<p><em>On their 3-hour hiking trip, the friends were hit with a<u> double whammy</u>. The first was a bad rainstorm. They were forced to take shelter in a cave. Then they realized the second bad thing. They left all their food and water in the car.</em></p>
<p>There is another English expression that has a similar meaning – <u>a one-two punch</u>. The first punch is a difficult blow to take, but then the second one aims to finish the job. The expression comes from boxing where one punch is quickly followed by another from the other fist, or closed hand.</p>
<p>A boxer using a <u>one-two punch</u> is trying to <strong>knock out</strong> their opponent or to score points.</p>
<p>Both <u>double whammy</u> and <u>one-two punch</u> are informal expressions. <u>One-two punch</u> might be less popular than it once was. But <u>double whammy</u> appears in some surprising places in both American and British English.</p>
<p>And that's Words and Their Stories. Until next time ... I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>Do you have a similar expression in your language? Let us know in the comments. Or send us an email at LearningEnglish@21voa.com.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>spell </strong>–n. magic that used on a person, often to create a bad or damaging effect</p>
<p><strong>circumstance </strong>–n. a situation <strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>consecutively </strong>–adv. taking place one after another in a series</p>
<p><strong>origin </strong>–n. the beginning point of something</p>
<p><strong>punch </strong>–n. the act of striking with a closed hand, or fist</p>
<p><strong>cartoonist </strong>–n. a person who draws simple pictures that tell stories</p>
<p><strong>comic strip </strong>–n. a series of pictures telling, often funny, stories that appears in newspapers or books as a series that continues for a time</p>
<p><strong>character </strong>–n. a person who appears in stories, plays, movies or TV who is not real</p>
<p><strong>knock out </strong>–v. to strike a person so that they lose consciousness or cannot continue</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>In Puerto Rico, Well-known Rapper also Works as a Doctor (2024/8/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/in-puerto-rico-well-known-rapper-also-works-as-a-doctor.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">02 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A popular rapper in Puerto Rico has kept his job as a doctor to help deal with a shortage of medical workers in the United States territory.</p>
<p>Many Puerto Ricans know Dr. Pedro Juan Vázquez by his performing name, PJ Sin Suela. But others are now getting to see his medical skills as he often goes <strong>door-to-door</strong> to serve patients.</p>
<p>The 34-year-old Vázquez recently told The Associated Press (AP) he is still living out his love of music. He also believes he is helping those in need and bringing attention to a health crisis in Puerto Rico.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="Dr. Pedro Juan Vázquez, better known by his stage name PJ Sin Suela, attends to a patient in Loiza, Puerto Rico, Saturday, May 25, 2024. (AP Photo/Alejandro Granadillo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-768e-08dcacb0edef_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">Dr. Pedro Juan Vázquez, better known by his stage name PJ Sin Suela, attends to a patient in Loiza, Puerto Rico, Saturday, May 25, 2024. (AP Photo/Alejandro Granadillo)</span></div>
<p>The U.S. territory is currently facing power outages as well as a shortage of medical professionals. Many doctors and other workers have gone to the U.S. mainland seeking better pay.</p>
<p>A 2023 report by Puerto Rican policy group Center for a New Economy found the territory had lost more than 8,600 doctors out of nearly 18,800 in just over 10 years. The problem is expected to get worse in the coming years.</p>
<p>“We have a huge <strong>exodus</strong> of young people,” Vázquez told the AP. He added, “In Puerto Rico, we have a crisis much bigger than people think.”</p>
<p>Vázquez said he travels from the capital, San Juan, to rural areas of the island at least once a week. During these trips, he seeks to treat communities struggling from the combined effects of hurricanes, earthquakes and a weak economy.</p>
<p>When not working as a doctor, Vázquez produces and performs music that brings attention to issues including social inequality, poverty and gun violence.</p>
<p>In one song, he brings up the territory's problems with violence. “A bullet is flying, lost like a child,” he raps, “the wind <strong>caresses</strong> it, seeks to make news, falling into a skull, without any kind of justice.” The rap song, in English, is called <em>Bullets Cry</em>.</p>
<p>In another song, called <em>We are More</em>, Vázquez comments on the territory's economic problems. He raps, “The debt has been placed before the worker, the one who goes outside under the rain and the sun, public servers, teachers and nurses."</p>
<p>Vázquez has left and returned to the island several times. This is common for many Puerto Ricans, who hold U.S. passports. He does not criticize those who have left Puerto Rico for the U.S. mainland. “You can't judge anybody, everybody has their story,” he said. “I'm <strong>blessed</strong> to have two <strong>careers</strong> that I can do and live off of.”</p>
<p>Vázquez was born in the Bronx area of New York City. But he moved with his family to the town of Ponce, Puerto Rico. Later, he went to Pennsylvania, before returning to Bayamón, Puerto Rico. It was there that Vázquez studied medicine. He became a doctor in 2015.</p>
<p>He became a household name as a rapper for a younger generation in Latin America in 2018. The single that made Vázquez a star was called <em>What Is Your Plan?</em> He worked with Puerto Rican musician Bad Bunny and reggaeton singer Nejo on the song.</p>
<p>When the COVID-19 pandemic hit in 2020, he decided to start working in medicine again. Vázquez worked full-time at a hospital in Ponce for a year. Then, as a general doctor, he treated patients of all ages.</p>
<p>Vázquez noted that some doctors questioned his medical abilities at first, since he had spent years performing as a rapper. But after a short time, he said, “Everybody knew that this wasn't a joke for me, and that I'm really good at what I do.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>door-to-door </strong><em>–idiom</em> to go from house to house in a neighborhood</p>
<p><strong>exodus</strong><em> - n.</em> when a large number of people all leave a place together</p>
<p><strong>caress </strong><em>– v.</em> to touch or stroke lightly or lovingly</p>
<p><strong>blessed </strong>-<strong> </strong><em>adj. </em>of or enjoying happiness</p>
<p><strong>career </strong>–n. the path of a person's work live involving different but usually related jobs or professions</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Spoiled Food and Drink (2024/8/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/spoiled-food-and-drink.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Noura about how to describe food that is no longer safe to eat.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-e47f-08dcb00fd98c_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>Would you please tell us the words we use to describe spoiled food? Now I use only one or two words for all of food types, such as " rotten" or "spoiled." However, in my native language we use different words for different categories like spoiled vegetables, bread, beverages, [and] meat-dishes. I wonder if it is the same in English too.</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>Thank you for writing to us, Noura. I'm happy to answer this question.</p>
<p>Let's begin with the two words you mention, “rotten,” and “spoiled”. We can use both words to talk about food in general. So, we can say either of the following:</p>
<p><em>That food is rotten.</em></p>
<p><em>That food is spoiled.</em></p>
<p>But for some foods, we use “rotten” much more than we use “spoiled.” For example, we can say rotten eggs, rotten tomatoes, rotten apples, rotten vegetables, rotten fruit, and so on. The most common usage of “rotten” is with eggs.</p>
<p>We use “spoiled” mostly when talking about meat or milk.</p>
<p>Another general term for spoiled food or drink is the expression “gone bad”.</p>
<p>Now let's look at some other terms we use with certain foods and drinks.</p>
<p>“Rancid” describes foods that contain fats that have started to go bad. These typically include nuts, seeds, and oils. Fish, meat, and poultry can also become rancid.</p>
<p>We use the word “stale” to describe bread that has become hard and difficult to eat. And “wilted” describes lettuce or other greens that are no longer fresh.</p>
<p>Mold is a kind of very small fungus. It makes food go bad and can be found on fruit, bread and cheese. The adjective we use for mold is “moldy.”</p>
<p>We use the adjective “sour” or the expression “to go sour” to describe milk or cream that has started to spoil. Note that there is also a food called sour cream, which is safe to eat – and quite tasty!</p>
<p>As you can see, a meal with rancid, stale, sour, wilted, moldy, rotten and spoiled food is one to avoid!</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, do you have a question about American English? Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: ‘Super Jupiter’ Planet Takes 100 Years to Orbit Star (2024/8/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/study-super-jupiter-planet-takes-100-years-to-orbit-star.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Astronomers say they have observed a new <strong>exoplanet</strong> that orbits far away from its star although it is a large and massive planet.</p>
<p>An international group of researchers said they learned new things about the planet after examining data from the James Webb Space Telescope. The telescope is operated by the American space agency NASA.</p>
<p>The gas giant, which has been named Epsilon Indi A b, was first <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/exoplanet-catalog/epsilon-indi-a-b/">discovered</a> in 2019. It is also known as a “super Jupiter,” meaning it is similar to Jupiter in our own solar system, but more massive.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This illustration provided by the Max Planck Institute for Astronomy in July 2024 depicts a cold gas giant orbiting a red dwarf. (T. M&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;252;ller (MPIA/HdA) via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-c0ba-08dcafdbe324_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This illustration provided by the Max Planck Institute for Astronomy in July 2024 depicts a cold gas giant orbiting a red dwarf. (T. M<i>&amp;#</i>252;ller (MPIA/HdA) via AP)</span></div>
<p>Scientists estimate the exoplanet's <strong>diameter</strong> is about the same as Jupiter's, but it is about six times more massive. The team said the planet has an atmosphere rich in hydrogen like Jupiter's.</p>
<p>Epsilon Indi A b is estimated to be about 12 light-years away from Earth. A light year is the distance light travels in a year – about 9.5 trillion kilometers.</p>
<p>International researchers led by Germany's Max Planck Institute examined new telescope images of Epsilon Indi A b. They said they learned the massive exoplanet orbits the star Epsilon Indi A, which is part of a three-star system.</p>
<p>The scientists said one surprising discovery was that the exoplanet seems to take at least 100 years to orbit its star and possibly as many as 250 years. The research shows Epsilon Indi A b orbits its star at a distance equal to 15 times the distance from the Earth to our own sun.</p>
<p>The researchers said they were able to “directly” observe the gas giant by using a tool on the James Webb to block the light of the planet's main star. The team was then able to identify the exoplanet as a bright spot of infrared light.</p>
<p>The new findings recently appeared <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07837-8">in a study</a> in the publication <em>Nature</em>.</p>
<p>Scientists estimate the planet and star are about 3.5 billion years old. That is 1 billion years younger than our own solar system.</p>
<p>Elisabeth Matthews is an astrophysicist at the Max Planck Institute for Astronomy. Matthews led the research. She told The Associated Press in an email the exoplanet appears to be older and brighter than had been thought.</p>
<p>The team noted the planet's star is so bright that it can be seen with the unaided eye from the Southern Hemisphere.</p>
<p>But Matthews noted that nothing in the newly collected data suggests that Epsilon Indi A b has the right conditions to support life. “This is a gas giant with no hard surface or liquid water oceans," she said.</p>
<p>Matthews said studying worlds similar to Jupiter can help scientists understand “how these planets <strong>evolve</strong>” over many, many years.</p>
<p>The first exoplanets outside our solar system were confirmed in the early 1990s. NASA's total count today stands at about 5,690. The majority of these exoplanets were identified through the so-called “<strong>transit</strong>” method. This involves repeatedly observing drops in starlight that might happen when a planet partly blocks light from its star.</p>
<p>Land- and spaced-based telescopes also search for new data on exoplanets, especially ones that might be similar to Earth.</p>
<p>NASA launched the James Webb Space Telescope in 2021. It is currently the largest and most powerful astronomical observatory ever placed in space.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>exoplanet </strong><em>- n.</em> a planet of a star that sits outside the solar system</p>
<p><strong>diameter </strong><em>– n.</em> the length of a straight line through the center of an object or space</p>
<p><strong>evolve </strong><em>– v. </em>to develop gradually over time</p>
<p><strong>transit </strong><em>– v. </em>to pass through or across a place, area of country, on the way to someplace else</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Some Plants Grow for a Long Time to Flower Only Once (2024/8/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/some-plants-grow-for-a-long-time-to-flower-only-once.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Some plants, known as flowering annuals, <strong>bloom</strong> without stop before dying at the end of the year or season.</p>
<p>Other flowering plants, known as perennials, return every year. They can bloom all season, with a lot of <strong>blossoms</strong> at first followed by additional flowers from time to time. Sometimes it is a limited show that can last as little as two weeks.</p>
<p>Biennials flower only in their second year before dying.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This May 19, 2018 image provided by the Lady Bird Johnson Wildflower Center shows American columbo (Frasera caroliniensis) flowers in bloom in Hayesville, North Carolina. (Stephanie Brundage/Lady Bird Johnson Wildflower Center via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/94af6fa6-deb3-4b31-9ade-72a96c54b4c5_cx0_cy7_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This May 19, 2018 image provided by the Lady Bird Johnson Wildflower Center shows American columbo (Frasera caroliniensis) flowers in bloom in Hayesville, North Carolina. (Stephanie Brundage/Lady Bird Johnson Wildflower Center via AP)</span></div>
<p><strong>Monocarpic plants</strong></p>
<p>But there is another group of plants called monocarpics. Their name comes from the Greek words for “single,” mono, and “fruit,” carpos. Monocarpics spend their whole lives growing in size only to produce a single bloom before dying.</p>
<p>Some monocarpic plants have a following among a small group of <strong>gardeners</strong>. These gardeners enjoy what can be years of waiting. They often throw parties to show their plant's once-in-a-lifetime bloom to others.</p>
<p>Other growers, however, can be surprised to discover their 30-year-old plant unexpectedly blooming, only to watch it die immediately afterward.</p>
<p>Flowers have a purpose: to ensure the continuation of their species. After their bloom ends, plants produce seeds that grow into new plants.</p>
<p>Monocarpic plants have just one chance at this. So, as you might imagine, the effort is often<strong> spectacular</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Examples of monocarpics</strong></p>
<p>Take the century plant. Rather than living for 100 years, as its name suggests, it has an average lifespan of just 10 to 30 years. It is a desert plant native to Mexico and Texas.</p>
<p>During its life, it grows to 1.8 meters tall before sending up a giant flower stalk that can reach nine meters, often surprising its owners.</p>
<p>A 19-year-old American columbo plant growing at the North Carolina Botanical Garden in Chapel Hill bloomed this spring. The plants are native to the eastern and central United States. They grow quickly for many years before pushing forth flowers that are up to two meters long.</p>
<p>The monocarpic plant group also includes the fishtail palm. It can grow over 15 meters in height. The trees produce flowers with yellow centers when they are between 10 and 20 years old.</p>
<p>The good news is the show of flowers can last up to 5 years, after which only the blooming <strong>trunk </strong>will die, leaving secondary trunks, if present, to take over. However, fishtail palms grown as houseplants are not likely to bloom.</p>
<p>Bamboo is also a monocarpic plant. But it can take more than 100 years for some bamboo <strong>species</strong> to flower, and even then, sometimes their roots push up new plants.</p>
<p>Bananas, too, are monocarpic, but they reproduce by sending up suckers, or small, new plants, from their roots. After their one-and-only fruit crop is harvested, the main plant is cut to ground level, leaving the suckers to take over.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Jessica Damiano reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>bloom </strong><em>– v.</em> to produce or yield flowers <em>—n.</em> a flower</p>
<p><strong>blossom</strong> <em>—n.</em> a flower <em>—v.</em> to produce flowers</p>
<p><strong>gardener</strong> <em>–n.</em> a person who raises and keeps plants for flowers and for food</p>
<p><strong>spectacular </strong>–<em> adj.</em> describes the quality of being unusual, notable, or entertaining</p>
<p><strong>trunk</strong><em> -- n.</em> the main part of a tree apart from limbs and roots</p>
<p><strong>species</strong><em> – n.</em> a category of biological classification ranking immediately below the genus or subgenus</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers: New Blood Tests Help Doctors Identify Alzheimer’s Disease (2024/8/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/researchers-new-blood-tests-help-doctors-identify-alzheimer-s-disease.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>New blood tests could help to identify, or <strong>diagnose</strong>, Alzheimer's disease faster and with more <strong>accuracy</strong>, researchers reported recently. However, some of the tests for the brain-wasting disease appear to work better than others.</p>
<p><strong>New tests, new drugs </strong></p>
<p>Doctors can confirm Alzheimer's in a patient if they find one of the disease's main signs: the development, or buildup, of a sticky protein called beta-amyloid. Currently, doctors use brain imaging or a special test known as a spinal tap to look for beta-amyloid buildup. Brain imaging is hard to get and spinal taps are painful.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A doctor points to PET scan results that are part of a study on Alzheimer's disease at Georgetown University Hospital, on Tuesday, May 19, 2015, in Washington. (AP Photo/Evan Vucci, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a199d0f1-3a06-4cff-81e0-ee533dd240c7_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A doctor points to PET scan results that are part of a study on Alzheimer's disease at Georgetown University Hospital, on Tuesday, May 19, 2015, in Washington. (AP Photo/Evan Vucci, File)</span></div>
<p>Instead, many patients are diagnosed based on their behavior and <strong>cognitive</strong> exams.</p>
<p>Now, labs have begun offering blood tests that can show some signs of Alzheimer's. Scientists are excited about the possibilities that the tests offer.</p>
<p>But the tests are not widely used yet because there is little data to guide doctors about which kind to order and when. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has not officially approved any of them, and few patients have insurance coverage for such tests.</p>
<p>“What tests can we trust?” asked Dr. Suzanne Schindler of Washington University in St. Louis. Schindler is part of a research project examining the tests. While some tests are very accurate, Schindler said, “other tests are not much better than a flip of a coin.”</p>
<p>More than 6 million people in the United States and millions more around the world have Alzheimer's, the most common form of dementia. Its usual signs, or “biomarkers,” are amyloid plaques and abnormal tau protein that leads to tangles that damage <strong>neurons</strong>.</p>
<p>New drugs such as Leqembi and Kisunla can slow the disease a little. The medicines remove amyloid from the brain. But these drugs only work in the early part, or stage, of Alzheimer's progression. Few patients get the costly brain scans and invasive spinal taps that could show early stage Alzheimer's.</p>
<p>Even specialists struggle to tell if Alzheimer's or something else is to blame for a patient's problems.</p>
<p>Schindler said she sometimes has patients “who I am convinced have Alzheimer's disease and I do testing and it's negative.”</p>
<p>A limited number of doctors have carried out blood tests for Alzheimer's in carefully controlled research settings. However, a new study of about 1,200 patients in Sweden shows they also can work in doctors' offices.</p>
<p>The findings suggest the blood tests may be more helpful for general care doctors. They see many more cases of people with memory problems than specialists do. However, general care doctors have fewer diagnostic tools.</p>
<p>In the study, patients who visited either a general care doctor or a specialist for memory problems got an early diagnosis using traditional exams. They gave blood for testing and got confirmatory spinal taps or brain scans.</p>
<p>Blood testing is far more accurate, Lund University researchers reported recently at the Alzheimer's Association International Conference in Philadelphia. They said that the primary care doctors' first diagnosis was 61 percent accurate and the specialists' first diagnosis 73 percent. However, the blood test was 91 percent accurate, their study showed. The Journal of the American Medical Association published the study.</p>
<p><strong>Different biomarkers</strong></p>
<p>Dr. John Hsiao of the National Institute on Aging said the new tests measure different biomarkers in different ways.</p>
<p>Doctors and researchers should only use blood tests proven to have a greater than 90 percent accuracy rate, said Alzheimer's Association chief science officer Maria Carrillo.</p>
<p>Carrillo and Hsiao agreed that the blood tests most likely to provide that accuracy measure what is called p-tau217. Schindler helped lead an unusual direct comparison of several kinds of blood tests that came to the same finding. The Foundation for the National Institutes of Health financed the work.</p>
<p>That kind of test measures a form of tau that <strong>correlates</strong> with how much plaque buildup someone has, Schindler explained. A high level signals a strong likelihood the person has Alzheimer's. A low level strongly suggests Alzheimer's is not the cause of a patient's thinking problems.</p>
<p>Several companies are developing p-tau217 tests.</p>
<p><strong>Who should use blood tests for Alzheimer's? </strong></p>
<p>In the United States, only doctors can order the blood tests from labs. The Alzheimer's Association is working on policy suggestions and several companies plan to seek FDA approval, which would clarify correct use.</p>
<p>For now, Carrillo said doctors should use blood testing only in people with memory problems, after checking the accuracy of the kind they order.</p>
<p>Especially for primary care physicians, “it really has great potential to help them in sorting out who to give a reassuring message and who to send on to memory specialists,” said Dr. Sebastian Palmqvist of Lund University. Palmqvist led the Swedish study with Lund's Dr. Oskar Hansson.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p>And I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Lauran Neergaard reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>diagnose </strong><em>– v.</em> to identify a disease from its signs and symptoms</p>
<p><strong>diagnosis</strong><em> – n.</em> the act of identifying a disease from its signs and symptoms</p>
<p><strong>accuracy</strong> <em>– n.</em> the quality of being precise or correct</p>
<p><strong>cognitive</strong> <em>– adj.</em> of or relating to thinking, reasoning, or remembering</p>
<p><strong>neuron</strong> <em>– n.</em> a cell that is the fundamental functional unit of nervous tissue transmitting and receiving nerve impulses</p>
<p><strong>correlate</strong> <em>– v.</em> to bear mutual relations</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>First Online Child Safety Bill Passes US Senate (2024/8/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/first-online-child-safety-bill-passes-us-senate.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">31 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The U.S. Senate has approved the nation's first major legislation aimed at protecting children from internet harms.</p>
<p>Two bills passed the Senate by a vote of 91-3 on Tuesday. But the measures will also need to be passed by the U.S. House of Representatives to become law. It is currently unclear whether the House will approve the bills in the future.</p>
<p>One bill is known as the Kids Online Safety Act, or KOSA. The other is called the Children's Online Privacy Protection Act (COPPA 2.0).</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE — Isabella Cimato, 17, from left, Arianna Schaden, 14, and Sofia Harrison, 15, check their phones at Roosevelt Field shopping mall in Garden City, N.Y., on July 27, 2015. (AP Photo/Seth Wenig, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-697c-08dcb163b3e2_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE — Isabella Cimato, 17, from left, Arianna Schaden, 14, and Sofia Harrison, 15, check their phones at Roosevelt Field shopping mall in Garden City, N.Y., on July 27, 2015. (AP Photo/Seth Wenig, File)</span></div>
<p><strong>What do the measures do?</strong></p>
<p>The KOSA bill requires technology companies to take steps to provide a “duty of care” to protect young users. This legal term covers a range of steps businesses need to take in an effort to “prevent and <strong>mitigate</strong>” harm to children. Such harms include <strong>bullying</strong> and violence, as well as online information related to suicide, eating disorders and substance and sexual abuse.</p>
<p>The bill known as COPPA 2.0 is designed to increase privacy rules related to children. The bill bans some targeted advertising to kids online. It also bars data collection on children without their knowledge or approval. And it gives parents and young users the ability to remove personal information from social media services.</p>
<p>In addition, the bills would require companies to permit minors to <strong>opt out</strong> of product tools that use activity history to predict and suggest additional content to keep users online for long periods.</p>
<p><strong>How will they be enforced?</strong></p>
<p>The bill empowers state attorney general representatives to enforce most parts of the laws. However, the “duty of care” part cannot be enforced by state attorneys general. That change was made after concerns were raised that some states may seek to block information related to <strong>LGBTQ</strong> issues or reproductive rights.</p>
<p>Wider enforcement will be dealt with by the Federal Trade Commission (FTC), which will help decide what kinds of content is “harmful” to children.</p>
<p><strong>Who supports the measures?</strong></p>
<p>KOSA and COPPA 2.0 are being supported by a wide range of nonprofits, technology <strong>accountability</strong> organizations and parental rights groups. In addition, the bills have been supported by major groups representing American doctors and teachers.</p>
<p>Some well-known technology companies – including Microsoft, X and Snap – have also expressed support. Meta, which owns Facebook, Instagram and WhatsApp, has not publicly expressed strong support or opposition to the measures. Meta has said in the past it is not completely against some government <strong>regulation </strong>of social media.</p>
<p><strong>Who opposes the legislation?</strong></p>
<p>Some technology industry groups and the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) have criticized the measures. They have suggested that differing definitions of what is considered harmful to children could result in minors being blocked from important information. Such information could include LGBTQ issues, reproductive rights or vaccines.</p>
<p>Some changes were made earlier to the legislation in an effort to overcome these concerns, but some critics said those did not go far enough. "They made improvements, but not enough," said Democratic Senator Ron Wyden of Oregon. He was one of three senators who voted against the bills. He recently told reporters, "I still think it is going to harm a lot of LGBTQ kids because of the way it's going to make it difficult for them to get information.”</p>
<p><strong>Can the legislation pass the House?</strong></p>
<p>Josh Golin is executive director of Fairplay, a nonprofit group working to protect children from online marketing and other possible harms. He told The Associated Press before the Senate vote that he is “very hopeful” the bills will eventually be passed by both houses of Congress.</p>
<p>“The reason it has not come to a vote yet is that passing legislation is really hard, particularly when you're trying to regulate one of the, if not the most powerful industry in the world,” Golin said.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters, Agence France-Presse and the European Commission.</em></p>
<p><strong>_________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>mitigate</strong><em> - v.</em> to reduce the harmful effects of something</p>
<p><strong>bully </strong><em>– v.</em> to purposefully frighten someone who is smaller or weaker than you</p>
<p><strong>opt out </strong><em>– v. </em>to choose not to be part of an activity or to stop being part of it</p>
<p><strong>LGBTQ </strong><em>– n. </em>lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, and queer/questioning one's sexual or gender identity</p>
<p><strong>accountable </strong>– <em>adj.</em> being responsible for one's own actions and being able to explain those actions</p>
<p><strong>regulate </strong>–<em> v. </em>to control an activity or process, especially by using rules or laws</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Italy’s Historic Trains Draw Visitors to Less Popular Areas (2024/8/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/italy-s-historic-trains-draw-visitors-to-less-popular-areas.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">31 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>As it moves across central Italy, an old train pulling <strong>carriages</strong> from the 1930s and 1950s crosses the forests of the Majella National Park and the Abruzzo highlands.</p>
<p>Across 100 kilometers, the Park Railway, also known as the Italian Transiberian, travels through valleys and tunnels and over old bridges called viaducts. It offers visitors a view of small, rural and hidden villages in the country.</p>
<p>It was the first of some 1,000 kilometers of rail line to have re-opened under a project by Fondazione FS, part of the state-controlled national rail company.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A passenger travels on board of a vintage train that departed from Sulmona on the way to Palena, Italy July 21, 2024. (REUTERS/Antonio Denti)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/88ef9117-d77a-4fac-98c3-f78d3a9017cb_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A passenger travels on board of a vintage train that departed from Sulmona on the way to Palena, Italy July 21, 2024. (REUTERS/Antonio Denti)</span></div>
<p><strong>“Timeless tracks” </strong></p>
<p>The project called "Timeless <strong>tracks</strong>" aims to take visitors to forgotten parts of Italy instead of the popular cities.</p>
<p>"These are tracks that have lived through different eras, they have carried soldiers to the front, cows to <strong>pasture</strong>... they were mistakenly considered unproductive during the 1960s and 70s but are now once again of value," Luigi Cantamessa, who heads Fondazione FS, told Reuters.</p>
<p><strong>Inspired</strong> by train travel in Switzerland, the project now carries 45,000 visitors a year across its 13 lines. Fondazione FS expects to open two new ones by 2026, both in the southern area of Sicily.</p>
<p>"What were considered to be the dry branches of Italy's train network, have now proved to be the green shoots," Cantamessa added.</p>
<p>Norma Pagiotti is a 28-year-old from Florence, Italy traveling on the train with two friends.</p>
<p>Pagiotti said, "People are used to cities and places, like Florence, that everyone knows.. but then there are other areas that need to be discovered. (This) is the right kind of <strong>tourism</strong> that does not spoil the <strong>authenticity</strong> of places,"</p>
<p>Caterina Quaranta, from southern Italy, used the term “nostalgic," meaning a longing for a past time, to describe riding the train.</p>
<p>“The train reminds me of my youth, I feel a bit nostalgic for the things of the past, which were simpler, now everything is fast, short-lived," Quaranta said.</p>
<p>Laura Colaprete, a local guide, said the trains draw Italians and foreigners, families and children, younger people who get off to hike and ride bicycles, and older people "who have time to spare.”</p>
<p><strong>The trip </strong></p>
<p>After climbing up almost 1,000 meters in<strong> altitude</strong>, the Transiberian's first stop is in Palena, a hill-top town known for its beautiful views over the national park.</p>
<p>Traditional folk music accompanies people getting off the train, with local foods such as lamb skewers and soft pancakes and products by local artisans awaiting them at the station.</p>
<p>"The train helps several small towns around here. This line was a dead line before," said Gino Toppi, 60, as he helped his wife with the food stand in the small station.</p>
<p>Milan's Bocconi University recently estimated that for every dollar spent by passengers on tickets, as much as three more are spent on food, tours and other purchases. The rail ticket costs between $32 and $76.</p>
<p>That helps to support the economy of villages that have long lost population due to the declining birth rate and younger people leaving for the bigger cities.</p>
<p>"There certainly are <strong>benefits</strong>, this is a way to show my products," said Annalisa Cantelmi, an herbalist, or herb grower. "These tourists are slowly discovering these new territories, their traditions and people," she added.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Giulia Segreti reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>carriage</strong> <em>– n.</em> a wheeled vehicle</p>
<p><strong>track</strong> <em>– n.</em> the parallel rails of a railroad</p>
<p><strong>pasture </strong><em>– n.</em> land used for grazing</p>
<p><strong>inspire</strong> <em>– v.</em> to influence, move, or guide</p>
<p><strong>tourism</strong> <em>– n.</em> the practice of traveling for fun</p>
<p><strong>authenticity</strong> <em>– n. </em>not false or imitation; true to one's own personality, spirit, or character</p>
<p><strong>altitude</strong><em> – n.</em> the vertical elevation of an object above a surface (such as sea level or land)</p>
<p><strong>benefit</strong> <em>– n.</em> something that produces good or helpful results or effects</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>In the US, Disasters Strike All Over the Country (2024/8/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/in-the-us-disasters-strike-all-over-the-country.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">31 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>When it comes to disasters in the United States, most people think of major storms and earthquakes that hit coastal areas. But a study from the nonprofit Rebuild by Design and New York University says disasters happen everywhere across the country.</p>
<p>The study looks at information on hundreds of federally declared disasters from 2011 to about 2021. It also examines the $60 billion that the Federal Emergency Management Agency, or FEMA, gave state and local governments.</p>
<p>The study finds that eight of the nine <strong>counties </strong>with the most federally declared disasters since 2011 are in Kentucky. One is in Vermont. These counties have several times the number of disasters as the national average of three in the past 13 years.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Buildings and homes are flooded in the aftermath of Hurricane Laura near Lake Charles, La., on Aug. 27, 2020. (AP Photo/David J. Phillip, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-7d69-08dcafccaab7_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Buildings and homes are flooded in the aftermath of Hurricane Laura near Lake Charles, La., on Aug. 27, 2020. (AP Photo/David J. Phillip, File)</span></div>
<p>A federal disaster is declared when a bad natural event is so costly that local government officials do not believe they can recover. So, the governor of the state asks the president to declare a disaster which frees federal money set aside for this purpose.</p>
<p>Amy Chester is director of Rebuild by Design. She said, “California and Louisiana and I would say now even Texas, Florida, for sure, they soak up all the oxygen when you hear about these giant storms.”</p>
<p>Chester added, “But what you're not hearing about are these storms that are happening all the time, and that's just becoming ...regular to places like Vermont.” Chester also noted Tennessee, Oklahoma, Mississippi, Iowa and Alaska as having a lot of disasters.</p>
<p>“We want to show that climate change is already here,” Chester said of the data, which covers 2011 to 2023. It does not include heat waves, lack of rain or diseases, like COVID-19.</p>
<p>Before she studied the data, Chester said she thought Vermont would be safe from climate change. Instead, it has many disasters.</p>
<p>“It's awful,” Chester said. “It just keeps happening to them.”</p>
<p>Vermont recently flooded again because of heavy rain from Hurricane Beryl.</p>
<p><strong>Disasters in unexpected places</strong></p>
<p>In July 2022, at least 40 people died, and 300 homes were damaged when a flood struck Floyd County in eastern Kentucky. It was the 13th time in 12 years that the federal government declared the rural county a disaster.</p>
<p>Judge Robbie Williams is the administrator of the county with about 35,0000 people. He said, “After that flood, I had 500 homeless people looking at me, ‘Judge what are we going to do'?” Williams added, “It's <strong>overwhelming</strong> and it's just a matter of time before it happens again.”</p>
<p>Then, in 2023, Floyd County was declared a disaster again for the 14th time since 2011. But Floyd County is not the nation's most disaster-<strong>prone</strong> county. Neighboring Johnson County has had 15 disasters declared by FEMA.</p>
<p>Floyd County's government received more than $35 million in FEMA disaster aid since 2011. But that is not a lot of money compared to other counties hit by hurricanes.</p>
<p>Five counties received more than $1 billion in FEMA aid. Three of them are in New York state. They are led by Manhattan's New York County, which got $8.9 billion after being struck by Hurricane Sandy in 2012.</p>
<p>FEMA notes that flooding is the most common disaster in the U.S. Since 2011, FEMA has paid more than $41 billion in aid following hurricanes, the most of any kind of disaster.</p>
<p>Susan Cutter is with the Hazards Vulnerability and Resilience Institute at the University of South Carolina. Cutter said: “What the data tell us is that the frequency and severity of disasters at local-state <strong>scales</strong> is increasing with rural, suburban, and urban places being affected nationwide.” She was not involved in Chester's research. But she added, “More needs to be done.”</p>
<p><strong>Geography and regulations</strong></p>
<p>In Floyd County, Judge Williams said geography and government <strong>regulations</strong> make it tough for the area. The county is in the mountains. People live in the narrow valleys, he said. When it rains, the creeks and rivers overflow.</p>
<p>“We're seeing historic levels of flooding,” Williams said. “It's only getting worse.”</p>
<p>Environmental regulations bar local officials from <strong>dredging</strong> the creeks. <strong>Silt</strong> from the mountains keeps building up, Williams said. Some creeks were about six meters deep but are now shallow enough to walk across, he said.</p>
<p>"The problem is there is nowhere for the rain to go,” Williams said.</p>
<p>Samantha Montano is a professor of emergency <strong>management</strong> at the Massachusetts Maritime Academy. Montano said what is more important is how state and local policies create or reduce the risk of future disasters.</p>
<p>In Floyd County, the local government is using FEMA money to buy the homes of 150 residents to move them out of a flood area, but some do not want to leave, Williams said.</p>
<p>“Until we get those homes out of these flood ways...we're still going to have these issues,” Williams added.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins. And I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Seth Borenstein reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>county</strong> <em>–n.</em> an area in a state that has its own local government</p>
<p><strong>overwhelming</strong> –adj. an amount too big to deal with effectively</p>
<p><strong>scale</strong> <em>–n. </em>a level or size of something in relation to other, similar things that are bigger or smaller</p>
<p><strong>regulation</strong> <em>–n.</em> a rule or law that governs a kind of activity or industry</p>
<p><strong>disaster-prone </strong><em>–adj.</em> likely to have a disaster</p>
<p><strong>dredging </strong><em>–n.</em> the process of removing mud from the bottom of a river or canal to make it deeper so boats can pass</p>
<p><strong>silt </strong><em>–n.</em> dirt that is carried by rivers and streams to lower areas of land</p>
<p><strong>management </strong><em>–n.</em> the effort of overseeing and controlling a business, government office or organization</p>
<p><strong>creek </strong><em>–n.</em> a small stream</p>
<p><strong>shallow</strong> <em>–adj.</em> not deep</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>European Parent Groups Aim to Ban Smartphones for Teens (2024/7/31)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/european-parent-groups-aim-to-ban-smartphones-for-teens.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">30 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>If parents say "no" when a child asks for a smartphone, the response they are likely to hear is, "Everyone has one. Why can't I?"</p>
<p>But what would happen if the child's friends did not have a mobile phone either?</p>
<p>That is the way that some parents in Europe are thinking.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A boy plays with his father's phone outside school in Barcelona, Spain, on June 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Emilio Morenatti)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-7c49-08dca76866aa_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A boy plays with his father's phone outside school in Barcelona, Spain, on June 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Emilio Morenatti)
</span></div>
<p>They are concerned by evidence that smartphone use among young children threatens their safety and mental health. They believe that the more parents join their movement, the more powerful their ideas become.</p>
<p>Parents in Spain, Britain and Ireland are using social media groups on services like WhatsApp and Telegram to talk about their plans. They want to keep smartphones out of schools. But for their plan to work, other parents have to refuse to buy children the devices before — or even into — their teenage years.</p>
<p>Elisabet García Permanyer got involved after she talked with another parent in a Barcelona park. Last year, she started a social media group to share information on the dangers of the internet with families at her children's school.</p>
<p>The group, called "<strong>Adolescence</strong> Free of Mobile Phones," quickly grew and now includes over 10,000 members. The most involved parents are asking other parents to agree not to get their children smartphones until they are 16.</p>
<p>"When I started this, I just hoped I would find four other families who thought like me, but it <strong>took off </strong>and kept growing, growing and growing," García Permanyer said. "My goal was to try to join forces with other parents so we could <strong>push back </strong>the point when smartphones arrive. I said, 'I am going to try so that my kids are not the only ones who don't have one.'"</p>
<p><strong>Spain</strong></p>
<p>Police and public health experts have also been voicing concerns about the kind of materials that children can see on their mobile devices. Spain's government took note of the problem and banned smartphones from elementary schools in January. Now they can only be turned on in secondary school, which starts at age 12, if a teacher deems it necessary for an educational activity.</p>
<p><strong>Britain</strong></p>
<p>In Britain last year, a 16-year-old girl named Brianna Ghey was killed by two teenagers. Her mother demanded that social media on smartphones be limited for children under 16.</p>
<p>Mother Daisy Greenwell, who lives in the area of Suffolk, England, and a friend, Clare Reynolds, set up a social media group called Parents United for a Smartphone-Free Childhood. It grew quickly and an organizer said it now has groups in every British county.</p>
<p><strong>Ireland</strong></p>
<p>In Greystones, Ireland, eight primary school leaders, or principals, wrote to parents, asking them not to buy their students smartphones. Then the parents themselves voluntarily signed written agreements, promising not to let their young children have the devices.</p>
<p>Thirty-eight-year-old Christina Capatina is a Greystones parent of two young daughters. She signed the agreement and said there were almost no smartphones in schools this school year.</p>
<p><strong>Unity is powerful</strong></p>
<p>Studies from Spain, Britain, and Ireland show that by the time children are 12, most have smartphones. In Spain, 25 percent of children have a cellphone by age 10, and almost 50 percent by age 11. At 12, this share rises to 75 percent. British media <strong>regulator</strong> Ofcom said 55 percent of children in Britain owned a smartphone between ages eight and 11, with the figure rising to 97 percent by age 12.</p>
<p>Over recent years, organizations, governments, and parents have been reporting that smartphone use by children is linked to <strong>bullying</strong>, mental health problems and loss of the <strong>focus</strong> necessary for learning. China moved last year to limit children's use of smartphones. France has a ban on smartphones in schools for children aged six to 15.</p>
<p>The possible dangers have produced school bans on smartphones and online safety laws. But those measures do not deal with what children do outside of school with mobile phones. Parents and schools that have pushed for changes in their communities saw that it became possible the moment they understood that they were not alone.</p>
<p>Rachel Harper is principal of St. Patrick's National School in Greystones. Harper wants parents to work with their local school to organize phone bans. She said, "There's a bit more strength that way, in that all the parents in the area are talking about it."</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p>And I'm Mario Ritter.</p>
<p><em>Joseph Wilson and Laurie Kellman reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>adolescence</strong> – <em>n</em>. the period of life when a child develops into an adult</p>
<p><strong>take off</strong> <em>– v. (phrasal) </em>to quickly become very popular</p>
<p><strong>push (something) back</strong> – v. (<em>phrasal) </em>to change (a planned event) to start at a later date or time</p>
<p><strong>bullying <em>–</em></strong><em>n.</em> the act of using threats and force to get others to do what you want them to do</p>
<p><strong>focus</strong> – <em>n. </em>the ability to direct your attention or effort at something specific</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Rising Demand for Cooling Systems in Africa Fuels Environmental Concerns (2024/7/31)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/rising-demand-for-cooling-systems-in-africa-fuels-environmental-concerns.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">30 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Rising demand for cooling systems in Nigeria and other African nations might be making existing pollution problems worse.</p>
<p>Cooling systems use gases called refrigerants. Such gases can affect the atmosphere if they escape. Some of these pollutants have been found to be more harmful than other kinds of <strong>greenhouse gases</strong>.</p>
<p>The Nigerian government has approved restrictions on the release of refrigerant gases into the environment. But enforcement efforts for the laws have been difficult.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A technician positions an R-22 refrigerant on an outdoor air conditioning unit in Lagos, Nigeria, Thursday, July 18, 2024. (AP Photo/Sunday Alamba)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-1223-08dcb09ee993_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A technician positions an R-22 refrigerant on an outdoor air conditioning unit in Lagos, Nigeria, Thursday, July 18, 2024. (AP Photo/Sunday Alamba)</span></div>
<p>Abiodun Ajeigbe leads an air conditioning business for Samsung, West Africa. He told The Associated Press (AP), “Those laws, those rules, nobody enforces them.”</p>
<p>Ajeigbe said one of the biggest problems is a lack of effective education and training about the possible harms of refrigerants. This means many cooling system <strong>installers</strong> might not follow legal requirements when removing old systems or putting new ones in.</p>
<p>Some trained workers do follow environmental rules governing the use of cooling refrigerants. But these kinds of installations cost more.</p>
<p>Industry experts and public records suggest the most common air conditioning systems in Africa use a kind of gas known by the trade name R-22. This refrigerant is said to be less harmful to the environment than older cooling chemicals known as chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs). CFC's have largely been removed from most modern cooling systems. That change was put in motion by the 1987 Montreal Protocol environmental treaty.</p>
<p>A document from the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) says R-22 is considered many times more damaging to the world's climate than carbon dioxide. For example, about one-half kilogram of R-22 is said to equal one ton of carbon dioxide, the most common greenhouse gas.</p>
<p>However, while carbon dioxide can stay in the atmosphere for more than 200 years, R-22 stays for about 12 years. R-22 cooling equipment is not as energy <strong>efficient</strong> as some other systems. And most of the electricity used to power R-22 coolers in Africa requires carbon-based fuels.</p>
<p>Nigeria is planning to ban R-22 refrigerants by January 1, 2030. But without enough enforcement, that target is not likely to be met, Samsung's Ajeigbe told the AP.</p>
<p>Some cooling systems use a group of refrigerants called hydrofluorocarbons (HFCs). These do not harm the <strong>ozone layer</strong> and are more energy efficient. But HFCs are said to be strong greenhouse gases and account for an estimated 2 percent of all human-caused warming in the atmosphere.</p>
<p>One of the most harmful HFCs, called R-410A, is used in the second most common kind of air conditioners in Africa, the AP reported. Sellers and installers of cooling equipment in Nigeria told the news agency that although HFC systems are less damaging to the environment, they are more costly to operate.</p>
<p>The same issues are affecting countries beyond Nigeria. In Ghana, the cooling industry also struggles to get companies and workers to obey current environmental rules.</p>
<p>Environmental officials in Ghana told the AP that “poor servicing practices” for cooling systems are common across the country. This is largely the result of the public choosing lower-trained installers who might not follow recommended <strong>standards</strong>.</p>
<p>In Kenya, demand for cooling systems is also growing as the population grows and electricity becomes more widely available. Cooling systems using R-22 are still common across the country. But the nation's Environmental Management Authority told the AP there have not been any new imports of the systems since 2021.</p>
<p>Workers dealing with cooling systems and refrigerants are required to get a <strong>license</strong>. But several installation workers told the AP that since such requirements are hard to enforce, environmentally unsafe methods are carried out.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>greenhouse gases</strong><em> - n.</em> gases in the Earth's atmosphere that can trap heat</p>
<p><strong>install </strong><em>– v.</em> put a piece of equipment somewhere and make it ready to use</p>
<p><strong>efficient </strong><em>– adj. </em>working well and not wasting time or energy</p>
<p><strong>ozone layer </strong><em>– n. </em>the layer of ozone high above the Earth's surface that prevents much of the ultraviolet radiation from the sun from reaching Earth's surface</p>
<p><strong>standard </strong>–n. an accepted way of doing something that is agreed upon by industry or government officials</p>
<p><strong>license </strong>–n. official permission to do an activity, such as driving a car, that usually involves a document</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
