<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>VOA Special English</title>
        <link>https://www.21voa.com/special_english/</link>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <itunes:category>ESL</itunes:category>
        <itunes:author>VOA</itunes:author>
        <description>美国之音（以下称VOA）的英语节目，按播音速度可分为两种：Standard English （标准英语）和 Special English（特别英语）。

Special English 又叫“慢速英语”，是VOA 专为全世界非英语国家初学英语的听众安排的一种简易、规范的英语广播节目。该节目创始于50年代末期，是VOA 的专家们研究如何与世界各地的英语学习者进行交际的产物。它正式开播于1959年10月。当时只面向欧洲和中东，但由于这个节目适合许多国家英语学习者的需要，所以它的广播对象不久就扩大到世界其他地区，并很快在全世界范围内产生了广泛的影响。现在这个节目对欧洲、非洲和拉丁美洲每晚广播一次，对加勒比地区每晚广播一次（星期天除外），对东南亚广播次数最多，每天上午两次，晚上三次。

30多年来，VOA 为了办好Special English节目，进行了大量的调查研究工作，对播音速度、内容及用词范围都作了具体规定，基本上达到了既能为英语学习者提供信息，又不损害英语本身风格的目的，使之成为VOA 独具特色，拥有最大量听众的节目。

美国著名词汇学家S. B. Flexmer 指明了Special English的三条标准，也就是它所“特别”的地方：

1、它是一种由美国人最常用的1500个基本单词为主体构成的美国英语；

2、它用简短、明晰的句子写作和广播；

3、它以每分钟90个单词的速度，即2/3的Standard English（标准英语）速度进行广播。

Special English的节目可分为两大类：一类是新闻节目；一类是专题节目。

1．新闻节目

VOA Special English 的新闻广播向听众提供世界范围内的政治、经济、军事、外交、国际关系、宗教、天气以及各种重大事件和珍闻奇事等各个方面的信息，每天向东南亚地区广播五次，早上两次，晚上三次，每逢半点播出。

Special English新闻节目每次长约十分钟，大都播出十条左右新闻，近一千个单词，每条新闻多为一分钟，但偶尔也有长达两分钟的要闻。除头条新闻外，每条新闻都由一个电头引导，这样显得结构分明，条理清晰，适宜初学英语的人收听。在节目结束之前，播音员常常用三四句话重播其中三条新闻的提要以加深听众对要闻的印象。

Special English新闻中70%左右的内容与同时整点播出的Standard English新闻相同，但相同新闻的先后次序有所变动。每次节目的开头和结尾大同小异，格式比较固定。

2．专题节目（一）

Special English的专题节目（Feature Programs）,从时间上看，可分为两大类：一是每五分钟一次的专题，二是每十五分钟一次的专题。本节先介绍每项五分钟一次的专题材节目。

Special English五分钟一次的专题材节目安排在Special English新闻节目之后和（或）每十五分钟一次的专题材节目之前播出，每星期播七次。根据内容，可分为三个小类，即：Science Report（科学报道），逢星期一、三、五播出，每天播六遍；Agriculture Report（农业报道），逢星期二、四播出，每天播六遍；Words And Their Stories（词语掌故），逢星期六和星期天播出，每天播五遍。这三个专题材各具特色，具有相对的独立性，听众每听完一个节目，都会获得一个完整的印象。

Science Report（科学报道）这一专题材节目每周向听众介绍三篇有关现代科学技术最新发展情况的报道，涉及物理、化学、天文至高无上理、生物、环卫、心理、教育、医学和计算机等方面。适宜理工科大学生和科技工作者收集信息，积累资料，学习科技英语。

Agriculture Report（农业报道） Agriculture Report是为农业科技工作者和生产者安排的一个专题。它专门报道世界各国，特别是美国现代农业生产的最新成文汇报总务科 学家对农业生产某一方面的研究进展，以及他们对影响农业生产的某一自然现象进行分析和研究的近况。此外，它还经常向听众介绍发展中国家家业生产的一些有益经验等内容。

Words And Their Stories（词语掌故）这一专题节目，旨在向学习英语的听众介绍美国英语中生动有趣的词语和惯用法，并从科学研究和通俗词源学的角度来解释它们的含意、产生的背景及其在使用过程中的演变情况等。它通过讲故事的形式讲解每一个词语。这是VOA Special English中的优秀节目之一，是学习美国英语的极好材料。通过收听这一节目，听众不仅能学到娓娓动听的掌故和地道的美国英语，而且能增加美国的社会文化背景知识，历史传统与现状的了解。

VOA 为了更好地办好这个节目，便于听众收听学习，于1978年编辑出版了一本名为Words And Their Stories的书，共收集一百篇故事，作者是Herbert Sutcliffe, Harold Bermen 及VOA 该节目的部分编辑人员。在每次的实际广播中，播音员都以此书为蓝本，再根据需要对原稿进行适当增删。按每周两个故事计算，此书的一百个故事还不能满足一年的播音需要。于是编辑们就是重播部分词语掌故的同时，不断增加许多新的词语掌故，及时将词源学家的最新研究成果和不断增加的新词汇介绍给听众。收听实践证明，初学者在收听过程中必然会遇到许多人名、地名和一些较难的句子，有时甚至在听完之后还很难理解所播词语的确切含义及其汉语意思，为此，听众可参看1983年由中国对外翻译出版公司出版的该书英汉对照本中的有关部分。

3．专题节目（二）

VOA Special English的专题节目，除上节谈的五分钟一次的以外，还有本节要介绍的每十五分钟一次的节目。这类节目共有七个不同的小专题，以星期为单位循环，每天分四次复播出一个专题，但星期日和星期六的两个专题材每晚只播三遍，每次节目约十分钟，继每次五分钟的专题节目之后播出。

这类专题节目的基本结构是，在特定的伴声中先报告当次节目的名称，并扼要介绍其主要内容，然后播送节目正文。最后，在伴乐声中报告节目主持人和撰稿人的姓名，以邀请听众在下周的这个时间继续收听该节目而结束。

People in America（美国人物志） 这是有关美国历史名人的一个专题节目，每逢星期天晚上播出。它向听众介绍在美国历史上产生过重大影响、起过重要作用、作出了突出贡献的科学、文学、政治、或其他各方面的历史人物。节目一般都对他们的生平事迹进行简要的叙述，对其贡献作出评介，类似人物小传。有的重要人物事迹很多，必须用两次或几次的节目时间进行联播。对这样的节目要坚持收听，才会获得完整的印象。

TThis is America（今日美国） This Is America向听众介绍美国人民的生活、学习、工作和娱乐情况，是英语学习者解美国社会的一条渠道。该专题大都一个节目一个整体，每逢星期一晚播出。

Science in the News（科学新闻） 这一专题材主要对新近的科学技术新闻进行综述或摘要广播。向听众介绍世界各国在自然、医学、疾病、原子能、航天等方面的科研动态、成果、突破性进展及存在的困难。涉及当今世界人们普遍关心的重大问题，如核事故、航天飞机爆炸、自然灾害、环境污染和爱滋病等等。每逢星期二播出，每次播一到五条新闻摘要。

Explorations（自然探索） 每逢星期三晚上，听众可以收听到Explorations这一专题节目。该专题既涉及人类遨游太空、探索原子、研究自身、改造自然的现代技术，也报道发展中国家开发新资源，利用新工艺改善人民生活等方面的成就，其侧重点在各种科技实验和简易实用技术方面。该节目一般安排一段时间播一个系列，每次播出一个主题，以便能将某项新技术的研究和应用的全过程介绍给听众，电台还乐意为感兴趣的听众提供所需的文字材料。

The Making of a Nation（建国史话） 这一专题节目向听众介绍美利坚合众国从十三个殖民地区域到现代工业国的孕育、诞生以及形成超级大国的历史过程，并以历史为线索，特定的历史时期为单位，以重大的历史事件为主题材来叙述各个党派、各届总统和政府的历史作用与贡献。这是每个英语学习者都应了解的基本知识。The Making of a Nation每逢星期四播出。这是个系列节目，坚持收听，则有助于系统了解美国的历史概况。

American Mosaic（美国万花筒） American Mosaic是一个radio magazine（广播杂志）节目。该节目题材广泛、内容丰，展示着美国社会文化生活中比较轻松愉快的生活画面；听众收听该节目就如同在阅读一本图文并茂的杂志。它每次有三到五个小节目，涉及音乐、图书、技术和教育等方面的内容。我们既可以从中欣赏到著名歌唱的优秀歌曲，对美国音乐有所了解，又可以获取一些生动有趣的现代美国社会生活知识，随着播音员那亲切悦耳的声音步入美国风景如画的大好河山；同时还能听到世界各地的听众提出的有关英语语方文学等方面的问题和电台的解答。

American Stories（美国故事） 这一专题材节目安排在每星期六晚上播出。这样能使听众在学习和工作之余，得以轻松一下头脑。我们可以通过这一美国文学的“窗口”，接触各种流派、各类名家的文学作品。了解美国英语的时代特色，欣赏、学习美国人民运用语方的技巧，并从那些佳作名篇中获得艺术享受。该节目对短篇故事采取一次播一篇的方式，对中、长篇小说则先进行简写加工，再分几次播出全文。在播出故事正文之前，播音员常常先介绍故事的主要情节。对需要分几次节目时间播出的中长篇，在播第二或以后各部分之前，主持人还先重述已播部分的故事梗概，以唤起听众的回忆，使故事听起来更加连贯。</description>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          <item>
            <title>Experts Question Boeing's Space Business after Starliner Failures (2024/9/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/experts-question-boeing-s-space-business-after-starliner-failures.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Experts and people in the space industry say NASA's decision to send Boeing's Starliner <strong>capsule</strong> home without astronauts was not unexpected. They also said it follows years of problems with Boeing's space business.</p>
<p>Taking NASA astronauts Butch Wilmore and Suni Williams to the International Space Station (ISS) was supposed to have been a turning point for Starliner. The operation had suffered years of delays and technical problems.</p>
<p>Reuters news agency examined financial securities reports for Boeing and reported on what it had found. Reuters estimated that Starliner has cost Boeing $1.6 billion in cost <strong>overruns</strong> since 2016.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this photo provided by NASA, Boeing's Starliner spacecraft is docked to the Harmony module of the International Space Station on July 3, 2024, seen from a window on the SpaceX Dragon Endeavour spacecraft docked to an adjacent port. (NASA via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/59d789d3-1bdb-487a-a48f-6b50917e3079_cx0_cy0_cw95_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this photo provided by NASA, Boeing's Starliner spacecraft is docked to the Harmony module of the International Space Station on July 3, 2024, seen from a window on the SpaceX Dragon Endeavour spacecraft docked to an adjacent port. (NASA via AP)</span></div>
<p>The Starliner spacecraft was launched from Cape Canaveral, Florida, on June 5. Astronauts Wilmore and Williams were to stay at the ISS for about eight days. But problems with Starliner have extended that NASA <strong>mission</strong> to eight months.</p>
<p>Starliner's <strong>propulsion</strong> system failed, and NASA judged the <strong>thrusters</strong> were not safe to attempt a return to Earth with a crew.</p>
<p>Instead, NASA announced that a SpaceX Crew Dragon capsule<strong> </strong>will return<strong> </strong>Wilmore and Williams to Earth in early 2025. SpaceX, led by Elon Musk, is the other company that NASA has contracted to develop crewed space vehicles. The June mission was meant to be a final test for NASA to approve Starliner for normal spaceflights.</p>
<p><strong>Questions for Boeing and its leadership</strong></p>
<p>Boeing's new leader Kelly Ortberg now must decide whether to continue developing the program or sell it. Ortberg also faces problems from failures by the company's airplane manufacturing business.</p>
<p>NASA administrator Bill Nelson said he spoke to Ortberg recently. Nelson reported that the talk left him completely sure that Starliner would fly astronauts again.</p>
<p>Reuters asked Boeing representatives if the company would stay in the program after Starliner's current operation. A Boeing spokesperson chose not to comment on the question, telling Reuters that the company is centering its attention on getting the spacecraft back safely.</p>
<p>"I am not sure the decision will ultimately be NASA's," said Lori Garver. Garver is a former NASA deputy administrator and a main designer of NASA's Commercial Crew Program.</p>
<p>Ortberg started as Boeing's leader on August 8. He is trying to persuade Boeing workers, investors, airlines and the public that safety problems at the company are now under control.</p>
<p>Experts say Boeing will probably keep Starliner in operation. They say this is partly because Boeing has experienced similar cost overruns in its defense business.</p>
<p>In the future, Starliner could serve customers other than NASA. These could include operators of private space stations meant to replace the ISS after 2030.</p>
<p><strong>NASA faces decisions </strong></p>
<p>NASA considers Boeing an important <strong>backup</strong> to Musk's SpaceX.</p>
<p>Boeing has spent more than half of its $4.5 billion NASA contract, which was given in 2014. Starliner has not yet received certification, or final approval for normal use. The contract includes six Starliner missions after the capsule is certified. Although the contract has a fixed price, NASA increased its value by $300 million.</p>
<p>SpaceX's Crew Dragon was certified in 2020. It has carried out 10 missions for NASA with a crew. The company's first contract was worth $2.6 billion. NASA bought more Crew Dragon missions to take the place of Boeing's delayed missions. As a result, the value of SpaceX's contract rose to $4.9 billion.</p>
<p>Boeing may have to carry out the same astronaut mission to the ISS again in order to get NASA certification for the capsule. The company already had to repeat an uncrewed 2022 mission at a cost of nearly $500 million. It has been five years since Starliner's first uncrewed test failed because of several important software problems.</p>
<p>In 2019, NASA's inspector general's office estimated both companies' cost per mission. It said Crew Dragon's mission price of carrying one astronaut into space was about $55 million while Starliner's cost was $90 million.</p>
<p><strong>Questions about workforce and suppliers</strong></p>
<p>For years, Boeing's space business has been losing skilled employees. Many former employees joined competitors SpaceX and Jeff Bezos' Blue Origin. Ten people who spoke to Reuters and who worked for Boeing's space business said the company's structure made designing spacecraft more complex than it is for SpaceX.</p>
<p>Boeing, in a statement to Reuters, said the company is proud of its Starliner workforce. It also said that it has admitted problems with its workforce and with suppliers when reporting on its earnings to shareholders.</p>
<p>Throughout Starliner's development, the propulsion system and sometimes the software have failed. New problems were found just hours before the spacecraft made its first attempt to launch this summer. Helium gas, used to pressurize the propellant, was leaking through a small opening.</p>
<p>NASA considered the leak low risk. The agency permitted Starliner to launch. But officials said the propulsion system had a "design <strong>vulnerability</strong>" that Boeing must deal with before its next mission.</p>
<p>The Space Launch System, or SLS, is another problem for Boeing's space division. The SLS is expected to be the launch vehicle for America's program to return to the moon. But the program has faced years of delays and is billions of dollars over budget.</p>
<p>NASA's inspector general's August report said there were deep problems with quality control at Boeing. The report added that Boeing's SLS workforce in Michoud, Louisiana, lacks enough "aerospace production experience, training, and <strong>instruction</strong>."</p>
<p>A Boeing representative said the company disagrees with much of the report, "including any suggestion that our Michoud workforce is unqualified."</p>
<p>Unlike Starliner, NASA pays the cost of delays and development problems with SLS. Inspector general reports have repeatedly said that the cost overruns are not fully known because NASA does not account for them correctly.</p>
<p>NASA is trying to give ownership of SLS to Boeing and co-contractor Northrop Grumman to bring the costs down. However, experts say such a deal is unlikely.</p>
<p>Richard Aboulafia is an aerospace business adviser. He said Boeing's other businesses are strong, but he wonders about its space division. He thinks Ortberg will negotiate with NASA to make Starliner workable. However, he is not persuaded that that move is the right one.</p>
<p>"If I were an adviser to Kelly Ortberg, which I'm not, I'd say...for space, well boss, you might want to consider selling it," Aboulafia said.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver. And I'm Mario Ritter.</p>
<p><em>Joey Roulette reported this story for Reuters. Caty Weaver adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>____________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>capsule </strong><em>– n.</em><strong> </strong>a part of a spacecraft that carries astronauts or the most important equipment in the vehicle system</p>
<p><strong>overrun </strong><em>–n.</em><em> </em>a situation when more money is needed to complete a project than had been planned</p>
<p><strong>mission </strong><em>–n.</em> a space flight (or an official task) which as a specific set of goals and requirements</p>
<p><strong>propulsion </strong><em>–n.</em> a system that causes a vehicle to move</p>
<p><strong>thruster </strong><em>–n.</em> a device that helps control a spacecraft in space</p>
<p><strong>backup </strong><em>–n.</em> another choice that can be used if something fails</p>
<p><strong>vulnerability </strong><em>–n.</em> a weakness</p>
<p><strong>instruction </strong><em>–n.</em> things that need to be taught to a person so they can complete a task</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Labor Day in the US (2024/9/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/labor-day-in-the-us.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By VOA</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Labor Day is a national holiday to celebrate workers in the United States. The holiday, on the first Monday of September, is on September 2 this year.</p>
<p>For Americans, the holiday also informally marks the end of summer. The hot days of summer turn to cooler days ahead. Students are returning to school. Many celebrate the holiday with an outdoor <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/tasty-travels-barbecue-american-food-tradition/3949118.html">barbecue</a> or one more weekend at the beach.</p>
<p><strong>Origin of Labor Day</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Iron worker Robert Farula marches up Fifth Ave. carrying an American flag during the Labor Day parade on Sept. 8, 2012, in New York. (AP Photo/Mary Altaffer, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-ce39-08dcc6bf668f_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Iron worker Robert Farula marches up Fifth Ave. carrying an American flag during the Labor Day parade on Sept. 8, 2012, in New York. (AP Photo/Mary Altaffer, File)</span></div>
<p>But Labor Day started with a struggle.</p>
<p>On May 1, 1889, workers demonstrated on the streets of Paris, France. The demonstration led to International Labor Day. Most countries in the world, except the United States and Canada, celebrate Labor Day on the first of May.</p>
<p>The first American Labor Day celebration was held on September 5, 1882, in New York City. About 10,000 workers marched through the streets to show the strength of labor organizations.</p>
<p>For many years after that, American workers used the first Monday in September to demand better working conditions and pay. Several U.S. cities and states began to recognize the day as Labor Day. In 1894, President Grover Cleveland signed a bill into law making it a national holiday.</p>
<p>Music was a part of many Labor Day marches.</p>
<p>One American labor song is called <em>Bread and Roses</em>. It is based on a 1911 poem by James Oppenheim. The poem speaks about the women's labor movement. At that time, conditions in factories, where many women worked, were horrible. A fire at a clothing factory in New York killed 146 people. Most of the victims were immigrant women.</p>
<p><strong>Labor Day activities</strong></p>
<p>For the three-day Labor Day weekend, many Americans head to airports and highways for end-of-summer escapes. They visit beaches, mountains or lakes. Some prepare outdoor cookouts for family and friends.</p>
<p>The <a class="wsw__a" href="https://newsroom.acg.aaa.com/aaas-travel-trends-and-tips-for-labor-day-weekend/">American Automobile Association (AAA) said</a>, “Americans see the extended Labor Day weekend as an <strong>opportunity</strong> to say <strong>farewell</strong> to summer with one final trip.” The group said Labor Day weekend travel in the U.S. went up nine percent compared to last year.</p>
<p>Robert F. Moss is a barbecue expert and historian. He wrote the book <em>Barbecue: The History of an American Institution</em>. Moss said barbecue was already an American tradition when the labor movements developed in the late 19th century. He noted that it was a natural way to celebrate as large groups gathered.</p>
<p>“It still has a lot of that same communal sense, gathering around the grill, eating together,” he told the Associated Press.</p>
<p><strong>Not wearing white after Labor Day</strong></p>
<p>Americans also have a saying that one should not wear white after Labor Day.</p>
<p>That may sound strange, but it is true. Many Americans put away their white clothes on Labor Day and do not wear them again until the following May, after Memorial Day.</p>
<p>One reason for the clothing custom relates to the season. In the U.S., the months between June and September are summer. The weather is usually hot and people wear light-colored clothing to keep cool.</p>
<p>Clothing experts say it likely goes back to the Gilded Age — the same period in the late 1800s that started Labor Day. Wealthy New Yorkers in places such as Newport, Rhode Island, would put away their cool, white clothing at the end of the summer. And they returned to the city with darker, heavier clothes for dirt-packed streets.</p>
<p>After the pandemic, many businesses and people have turned to more relaxed clothing. So the saying, or rule, might not be true anymore.</p>
<p>But you may want to be careful about wearing white to an American-style Labor Day barbecue. The trouble is not fashion – it is <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/ketchup-an-american-condiment-with-an-asian-connection/3961575.html">ketchup</a>. If it spills, the popular red tomato sauce can ruin that nice set of white clothes.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith. And I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Hai Do, Mario Ritter Jr., Kelly Jean Kelly, Jerilyn Watson and Nancy Steinbach contributed to this report. Additional information came from The Associated Press and the AAA.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>opportunity</strong> - n. chance, occasion</p>
<p><strong>farewell</strong> - n. goodbye</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Nigerian Herders Bring Cows to City in Search of Grass (2024/9/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/nigerian-herders-bring-cows-to-city-in-search-of-grass.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Angry drivers <strong>honk</strong> as <strong>cattle</strong> slowly march across and feed on the grass in the middle of the streets. It is a common sight for drivers in Nigeria's capital city Abuja. For the young <strong>herder</strong> guiding them, Ismail Abubakar, it is just another day.</p>
<p>Abubakar did not choose to bring his cattle to the city center. His family is from Katsina State in northern Nigeria, where a changing climate turned <strong>grazing</strong> lands into a desert. He moved to Idu — a rural less developed part of Abuja — many years ago. But it now has a large train station and many homes and businesses.</p>
<p>Herders like Abubakar usually bring their cattle to the wild countryside to graze. But the need for housing, crop farming and climate change are taking away the land and their way of life.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A boy guides cattle on a road in Abuja, Nigeria, Friday, Aug. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Olamikan Gbemiga)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-7903-08dcc779917a_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A boy guides cattle on a road in Abuja, Nigeria, Friday, Aug. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Olamikan Gbemiga)</span></div>
<p>To keep cattle off Abuja's streets, some suggest that herders need to start buying private land and operating like other businesses. But to do that, they would need money and government support.</p>
<p>Baba Ngelzarma is the president of Miyetti Allah Cattle Breeders Association of Nigeria, a herders' support group. He said, "The herders take the cattle wherever they can find green grasses and water at least for the cows to survive, not minding whether it is the city or somebody's land.”</p>
<p>He added that part of the problem is the lack of government support for the industry, such as water, animal care, and price control. The government announced a new ministry to support the industry in July. But it does not have a minister yet.</p>
<p><strong>Fewer places to go</strong></p>
<p>Nigeria is home to over 20 million cows, mostly owned by herders from the Fulani ethnic group. The country has the fourth-largest cattle population in Africa. Its <strong>dairy</strong> market is valued at $1.5 billion. But, the US International Trade Administration says imports meet about 90 percent of local demand.</p>
<p>It shows how poorly organized the industry is, Ngelzarma said, as cows affected by constant moving and poor diets cannot produce milk.</p>
<p>There are four areas surrounding Abuja that have been put aside for cattle grazing. But they are not readily available and have been taken by other crop farmers and illegal settlers, Ngelzarma added.</p>
<p>Without grazing land, herders set up settlements anywhere and stay for as long as they can before land owners claim it or the government builds on it.</p>
<p>Mohammed Abbas is a 67-year-old herder. He has repeatedly had to move over the years. Most of his current settlement in the city's Life Camp neighborhood has been taken over by a newly constructed gas station. The remaining land will soon be claimed by another owner.</p>
<p>Abbas said that he would have to sell all his cows to have enough money to buy land for a settlement. It means that he would have nothing left “to put on the land.”</p>
<p>Hassan Mohammed's family now occupies a piece of land near the Idu train station. Once a large area of grassland, the area has turned into housing and roadways. Despite repeated orders from the owners to leave, Mohammed said that his family would stay put, using the land as their home base while taking their cattle elsewhere each day for grazing.</p>
<p>“Many don't have anywhere to call home, so they just find somewhere to sleep at night with the cattle,” said Mohammed. “But for us, we are not leaving except there is a new place within Abuja.”</p>
<p>Folawiyo Daniel is an Abuja-based housing developer. He said the issue is a failure of urban planning and urged the government to bring back grazing areas in the city for herders.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Taiwo Adebayo reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>honk </strong>– <em>v</em>. <em>of a horn</em>: to make a loud sound</p>
<p><strong>cattle</strong> – <em>n.</em> cows, bulls, or steers that are kept on a farm or ranch for meat or milk</p>
<p><strong>herder</strong> – <em>n</em>. a person who gathers and moves (a group of animals)</p>
<p><strong>graze</strong> – v. <em>of an animal:</em> to eat grass or other plants that are growing in a field, pasture, or the like</p>
<p><strong>dairy</strong> – <em>n.</em> milk or food made from milk (such as ice cream, cheese, or yogurt)</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>An Eye for an Eye (2024/9/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/an-eye-for-an-eye.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo and Mario Ritter</span><br/><span class="datetime">31 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Today we talk to you about expressions dealing with payback, getting even, and <strong>revenge</strong>.</p>
<p>When a person wants to <u>even the <strong>score</strong></u>, that person might have the <strong>proverb</strong> <u>an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth</u> in mind.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This April 12, 2018 photo shows a very close up image of a woman's eye. (AP Photo/Patrick Sison)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-3685-08db70f22800_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This April 12, 2018 photo shows a very close up image of a woman's eye. (AP Photo/Patrick Sison)</span></div>
<p>The <em>Merriam-Webster</em> online dictionary describes it as a “repayment in kind as revenge for an injustice.”</p>
<p>In kind means “in the same way.”</p>
<p>The expression <u>an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth</u> is ancient. It appears in <em>The Bible</em> and in <em>The Code of Hammurabi</em>, a set of laws written by the ancient Babylonian king of that name.</p>
<p><u>An eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth</u> describes a way of thinking. It is the idea that <strong>retaliating </strong>in kind is the best way to deal with a crime or some other offense.</p>
<p>It is the idea that a person who causes someone to suffer should suffer in the same amount and in the same way. For example, if someone did something to hurt you, you would want to hurt them equally.</p>
<p>To remind others of the proverb, people often simply say <u>an eye for an eye.</u></p>
<p>For some people, every second counts when they are looking <u>to settle a score</u>. For others, the revenge method might require patience. Some people wait years or a lifetime to get their revenge.</p>
<p>The way people <u>settle the score</u> can be very different. Some cultures have this expression: <u>Revenge is a dish best served cold</u>. The idea is that <u>settling the score</u> over time without emotion is the best way.</p>
<p>A similar expression is <u>tit</u><u> for tat</u>.</p>
<p><u>Tit for tat</u> is often used to describe diplomatic disagreements between nations. It is hundreds of years old. Both “tit” and “tat” mean the same thing: a “strike” or a “blow.” Experts say the expression changed from <u>tip for tap</u> to its present form after years of sound changes in the English language.</p>
<p><u>Tit for tat</u> <strong>literally</strong> means <u>blow for blow</u>. <em>Merriam-Webster</em> says it is: “An equal return given for some wrong that's been done.”</p>
<p>Now, let's hear two friends use some revenge expressions.</p>
<p><em>A: Did you hear what happened to Tom? Someone <strong>slashed</strong> his tires! It cost him hundreds of dollars to replace the ruined tires. </em></p>
<p><em>B: That sounds awful. Does he know who did it? </em></p>
<p><em>A: He suspects it was his ex-girlfriend, Diana. </em></p>
<p><em>B: Why?</em></p>
<p><em>A: Well, he scratched up the paint on her car last week. I'm still friends with Diana and she told me a security camera caught him doing it. It cost her hundreds of dollars to repaint her car. </em></p>
<p><em>B: Well, it sounds like they're even now. You know, <u>an eye for an eye</u> and all that</em>...</p>
<p>And that's Words and Their Stories. Until next time ...</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo and Mario Ritter wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em><u><i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;_____________________________________________</u></em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>revenge </strong><em>–n.</em> hurting someone because they hurt you first</p>
<p><strong>score </strong><em>–n.</em> an accounting in numbers or some other measure that shows who is winning and who is losing in a competition</p>
<p><strong>proverb </strong><em>–n.</em> a short saying that expresses what people recognize as a truth or important idea</p>
<p><strong>retaliate</strong><em> –v. </em>to strike back against a wrong or attack</p>
<p><strong>literally </strong><em>–adv.</em> formally defined as</p>
<p><strong>slash </strong><em>–v.</em> to use a knife or similar instrument to cut into something and severely damage it</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How to Prevent Jet Lag, Enjoy Travel (2024/8/31)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/how-to-prevent-jet-lag-enjoy-travel.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">30 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Many travelers face a common problem: jet lag.</p>
<p>It is the feeling of tiredness people get when traveling a long distance, resulting in a difference in daylight hours. Nobody wants to miss the fun because they are too tired to enjoy their vacation.</p>
<p>Here are some tips on how to deal with jet lag:</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A holiday traveler looks out at a airplane at Salt Lake City International Airport, in Salt Lake City, July 3, 2024. (AP Photo/Rick Bowmer, File)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-45c7-08dcc2e4ca64_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A holiday traveler looks out at a airplane at Salt Lake City International Airport, in Salt Lake City, July 3, 2024. (AP Photo/Rick Bowmer, File)
</span></div>
<p><strong>What is jet lag?</strong></p>
<p>Scientists define jet lag as the effect on the human body of traveling across <strong>time zones</strong>. Sofia Axelrod studies <strong>circadian</strong> <strong>rhythms</strong> at Rockefeller University in New York. She said a circadian rhythm is like a biological clock programmed into almost every cell in the body.</p>
<p>"The clock is set by the 24-hour light and dark <strong>pattern</strong>," Axelrod said. "Every morning when we wake up, specialized (light) receptor cells in our <strong>retina</strong> receive a daylight signal, which is <strong>transmitted</strong> to the brain and from there, (to) the whole body."</p>
<p>When we travel to another time zone, our eyes do not receive the daylight signal at the usual time. This causes our “internal clocks” to reset. But that process can take a while. During that period, we feel the effects of jet lag.</p>
<p><strong>Is jet lag preventable?</strong></p>
<p>People who travel long distances often want to prevent jet lag. One way has a high cost.</p>
<p>Malcolm von Schantz is a professor who specializes in circadian rhythms at Northumbria University in Newcastle, England. He said that paying a lot for a bigger seat and more space in an airplane can prevent sleep <strong>deprivation</strong>.</p>
<p>He knows most people cannot pay so much to travel. But he said timing your flights can help. For example, he suggests flying from Europe to North America during the day, so that it is evening when passengers land and they can get to sleep.</p>
<p>"If you take the evening flight instead, you'll be woken up at midnight to be served breakfast and land an hour or two later, when both jet lag and sleep deprivation will hit you hard," he said.</p>
<p>Von Schantz also said flying in newer model passenger jets, like the Airbus A350 or Boeing 787 Dreamliner, might help. He said those planes can maintain a more <strong>comfortable</strong> atmosphere inside, causing less tiredness.</p>
<p><strong>What should you do when you arrive?</strong></p>
<p>Experts say being in sunlight is important to resetting your internal body clock. That could mean either avoiding morning sun or seeking it out, depending on where you started.</p>
<p>Getting light in the morning will move your body clock forward, while light exposure in the early evening will delay it. Sleeping for a short time during the day is acceptable, but scientists warn against sleeping for longer periods later in the day. Doing so might make it harder to sleep through the night.</p>
<p><strong>Are there supplements or medicines for jet lag?</strong></p>
<p>The brain naturally produces a chemical <strong>hormone</strong> called melatonin when the body thinks it is night. Taking melatonin as a supplement can be helpful. But it is not available everywhere and, in some countries like Britain and France, you need a doctor's permission.</p>
<p>Von Schantz said that one of the good effects of melatonin is that you can start taking it before you travel, to begin the process of resetting your internal clock.</p>
<p>"If you're in a part of the world where melatonin is available <strong>over the counter</strong>, you can combine the effects of light and melatonin to achieve the advance or delay (in your body clock) that you need," he said.</p>
<p><strong>What can you do to deal with the effects of jet lag?</strong></p>
<p>Russell Foster of Oxford University wrote a book on circadian rhythms. He said business travelers might want to consider arriving a day or two ahead of any important meetings or events. Being jet-lagged can lead to unwise decisions and unpleasant emotions.</p>
<p>Tourists might not need to think as clearly as business travelers, but they should still be careful, he said. He advises tourists to get enough sleep before doing anything that might be risky or that requires a lot of attention, like driving.</p>
<p>Foster said he tries to increase his exposure to light when he arrives at a new place to prevent jet lag. But he also has another method if light does not help: he drinks coffee.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Maria Cheng reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>jet lag</strong><em> – n.</em> a tired and unpleasant feeling that you sometimes get when you travel by airplane to a place that is far away</p>
<p><strong>time zone</strong> – <em>n</em>. any one of the world's 24 divisions that has its own time</p>
<p><strong>circadian rhythm</strong> – <em>n</em>. repeated activity in an organism that happens in 24-hour periods</p>
<p><strong>pattern </strong>–n. a regular or repeated happening</p>
<p><strong>retina</strong> – <em>n</em>. the sensitive tissue at the back of the eye that receives images and sends signals to the brain about what is seen</p>
<p><strong>deprivation</strong> – <em>n</em>. the state of not having something that people need</p>
<p><strong>comfortable </strong>–adj. to feel good and to not feel pain or discomfort</p>
<p><strong>hormone </strong>–n. a chemical produced by the body that influences how the body grows and develops</p>
<p><strong>over the counter</strong> – <em>expression</em>. available for purchase without a special note (called a prescription) from a doctor</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>'The Murders in the Rue Morgue,' by Edgar Allen Poe, Part Three (2024/8/31)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/murders-in-rue-morgue-edgar-allen-poe-part-three.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By The story was originally</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">30 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>
<em>We present the third of five parts of the short story "The Murders in the Rue Morgue," by Edgar Allen Poe. The story was originally adapted and recorded by VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>My <strong>housemate</strong> in Paris, August Dupin, was an interesting young man with a busy, forceful mind. This mind could, it seemed, look right through a man's body into his deepest soul.</p>
<p>After reading in the newspaper about the terrible murder of a woman and her daughter, Dupin was <strong>consumed</strong> with the mystery. He questioned the ability of the Paris police to solve the crime. I told Dupin that it seemed to me that it was not possible to explain the strange details surrounding the killings.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/086fca59-1403-43a6-bd32-4490b048ecf6_w100_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>“No, no. I think you are wrong. A mystery it is, yes. But there must be an answer. There must! Let us go to the house where it happened and see what we can see. I know the head of the police, and he will permit our visit. It will be interesting and give us some pleasure.”</p>
<p>I thought it strange that Dupin thought the activity would give us pleasure. But I said nothing.</p>
<p>It was late in the afternoon when we reached the house on the Rue Morgue. It was easily found, for there were still many persons — in fact, a crowd, standing there looking at it. Before going in, we walked all around it, and Dupin carefully looked at the <strong>neighboring</strong> houses as well. I could not understand the reason for such great care.</p>
<p>Finally, we entered the house. We went up the stairs to the room where the daughter's body was found. Both bodies were in the room now. The police had left the room as they had found it in every other way. I saw nothing beyond what the newspaper had told us.</p>
<p>Dupin looked with great care at everything, at the bodies, the walls, the fireplace, the windows. Then we went home. Dupin said nothing. I could see the cold look in his eyes, which told me that his mind was working, working busily, quickly.</p>
<p>Dupin said nothing about our exploration until the next morning when he suddenly asked me a question.</p>
<p>“Did you not notice something especially strange about what we saw at the house on the Rue Morgue?”</p>
<p>“Nothing more than what we both read in the newspaper, which was unusual indeed. How shall we explain the horrible force, the unusual strength used in these murders? And whose were the voices that were heard? No one was found except the dead women; yet there was no way for anyone to escape. And the wild condition of the room; the body which was found head-down in the chimney; the terrible broken appearance of the body of the old lady, with its head cut off-- these are all so far from what might be expected that the police are standing still; they don't know where to begin.”</p>
<p>“These things are unusual, indeed, but they are not deep mysteries. We should not ask, ‘What has happened?' but ‘What has happened that has never happened before?' In fact, the very things that the police think cannot possibly be explained are the things which will lead me to the answer. Indeed, I believe they have already led me to the answer.”</p>
<p>I was so surprised that I could not say a word. Dupin looked quickly at the door.</p>
<p>“I am now waiting for a person who will know something about these murders, these wild killings. I do not think he did them himself. But I think he will know the killer. I hope I am right about this. If I am, then I expect to find the whole answer, today. I expect the man here — in this room — at any <strong>moment</strong>. It is true that he may not come, but he probably will.”</p>
<p>“But who is this person? How did you find him?”</p>
<p>“I'll tell you. While we wait for this man we do not know — for I have never met him — while we wait, I will tell you how my thoughts went.”</p>
<p>Dupin began to talk. But it did not seem that he was trying to explain to me what he had thought. It seemed that he was talking to himself. He looked not at me, but at the wall.</p>
<p>“It has been fully proved that the voices heard by the neighbors were not the voices of the women who were killed. Someone else was in the room. It is therefore <strong>certain</strong> that the old woman did not first kill her daughter and then kill herself. She would not have been strong enough to put her daughter's body where it was found. And the manner of the old lady's death shows that she could not have caused it herself. A person can kill himself with a knife, yes. But he surely cannot cut his own head almost off, then drop the knife on the floor and jump out the window. It was murder, then, done by some third person — or persons. And the voices heard were the voices of these persons. Let us now think carefully about the things people said about those voices. Did you <strong>notice</strong> anything especially strange in what was told about them?”</p>
<p>“Well, yes. Everybody agreed that the low voice was the voice of a Frenchman, but they could not agree about the high voice.”</p>
<p>“Ah! That was what they said, yes, but that was not what was so strange about what they said. You say you have noticed nothing that makes their stories very different from what might have been expected. Yet there was something. All these persons, as you say, agreed about the low voice, but not about the high hard voice. The strange thing here is that when an Italian, an Englishman, a Spaniard, and a Frenchman tried to tell what the voice was like, each one said it sounded like the voice of a foreigner. How strangely unusual that voice really must have been! Here are four men from four big countries, and not one of them could understand what the voice said; each one gave it a different name.</p>
<p>“Now, I know that there are other countries in the world. You will say that <strong>perhaps</strong> it was the voice of someone from one of those other lands — Russia, perhaps. But remember, not one of these people heard anything that sounded like a separate word.</p>
<p>Here, Dupin turned and looked into my eyes.</p>
<p>“This is what we have learned from the newspaper. I don't know what I have led you to think. But I believe that in this much of the story there are enough facts to lead us in the one and only direction to the right answer. What this answer is, I will not say...not yet. But I want you to keep in mind that this much was enough to tell me what I must look for when we were in that house on the Rue Morgue. And I found it!</p>
<p>“What did I first look for? The path of escape, of course. I mean, we agree the killers were not <strong>ghosts</strong>; they could not move through walls. So, how did they escape?</p>
<p>“At first I saw no way out. It had been necessary for the neighbors to break down the door in order to enter the room. There was no other door. The opening above the fireplace is too narrow for even a child to go through. That leaves only the windows. We must make that exit somehow possible.</p>
<p>“Remember, there are two windows in the room. Both of them, you will remember, are made of two parts; to open the window one must lift up the bottom half. One of these windows is easily seen; the lower part of the other is out of sight behind the big bed. I looked carefully at the first of these windows. It was firmly closed, <strong>fastened</strong>, like the door, on the inside. To keep the window closed, to fasten it, someone had put a strong iron <strong>nail</strong> into the wood at the side of the window in such a way that the window could not be raised. At least it seemed that the nail held the window closed. The nail was easy to see. There it was. And the people who discovered the killings used their greatest strength and could not raise the window. I, too, tried to raise the window and could not.</p>
<p>“I went to the second window and looked behind the bed at the lower half of the window. There was a nail here, too, which held the window closed. Without moving the bed, I tried to open this window also, and again I could not do so. But I did not stop looking for an answer there.”</p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>housemate </strong>– <em>n</em>. a person who lives in the same house with another person but is not a part of that person's family</p>
<p><strong>consume</strong>(<strong>d</strong>) – <em>v.</em> to take all of a person's attention, energy or time</p>
<p><strong>neighboring</strong> – <em>adj.</em> near or next to something or someone</p>
<p><strong>moment</strong> – <em>n.</em> a very short period of time</p>
<p><strong>certain </strong>– <em>adj.</em> used with <em>it</em> to say that something is known to be true or correct</p>
<p><strong>notice</strong> – <em>v</em>. to become aware of something or someone by seeing or hearing it</p>
<p><strong>perhaps</strong> – <em>adv.</em> possibly but not certainly</p>
<p><strong>ghost</strong>(<strong>s</strong>) – <em>n</em>. the soul of a dead person thought of as living in an unseen world or as appearing to living people</p>
<p><strong>fasten</strong>(<strong>ed</strong>) – <em>v</em>. to attach something or join two things or two parts of something especially by using a pin, nail or something else</p>
<p><strong>nail</strong> – <em>n.</em> a long, thin piece of metal that is sharp at one end and flat at the other end and that is used chiefly to attach things to wood</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Learning English Expressions or Idioms (2024/8/31)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/learning-english-expressions-or-idioms.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">30 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we consider expressions, or idioms, and offer some advice for learning them.</p>
<p>An idiom is an expression formed from two or more words. But an idiom's meaning often cannot be understood just by knowing each of the words in it.</p>
<p>Let's look at the following sentence as an example:</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-31a7-08dcc6d1af4a_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p><em>We want our students to think <u>outside the box</u>.</em></p>
<p>Here, the words <u>outside the box</u> form an idiom. If you only heard this one sentence, you might not be sure what it means. But people use idioms in connection to situations. For that reason, they usually say more than one sentence, and this can help you understand the idiom. For example:</p>
<p><em>We want our students to think <u>outside the box</u>. That's why we push them to find creative ways to solve problems. </em></p>
<p>By looking at these two sentences together, it can be easier to understand the meaning of <u>outside the box</u>. It means to think in new or creative ways.</p>
<p>In addition to considering the situation to help you understand the meaning of idioms, here is some other advice:</p>
<ul>
<li>Digital translation tools continue to improve, but you should avoid translating the idioms directly, word-for-word, into your native language.</li>
<li>When you hear a short group of words that seem very unrelated to a subject under discussion, those words will often be an idiom.</li>
<li>Be sure to learn the tone, or feeling, an idiom carries with it. The best way to learn about the tone of idioms is to ask native speakers about them. Native speakers might also be able to tell you if an idiom is commonly or rarely used.</li>
</ul>
<p>When learning English, it will likely be easier for you to understand idioms than to use them in speaking.<em> </em>However, if you can use idioms correctly, that can help deepen your connection to native speakers.</p>
<p>With thousands of idioms in English, there is a lot to learn. But do not <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/words-and-their-stories-boxing-expressions/2510976.html">throw in the towel</a>, in other words, do not give up. Instead, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/7071060.html">knock yourself out</a>, or try hard, and do your best to learn them. And you will feel <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/6665119.html">proud as a peacock</a>!</p>
<p>You can learn all about idioms by following our <em><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/z/987">Words and Their Stories</a></em> program or you can download <em><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/7759089.html">In the Loop</a></em>, a guide to American English Idioms.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, do you have a question about American English? Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>UN Chief Issues Urgent Warning of Danger from Rising Pacific Sea Levels (2024/8/30) | 联合国秘书长就太平洋海面上升风险发出紧急警告</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/un-chief-issues-urgent-warning-of-danger-from-rising-pacific-sea-levels.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>United Nations Secretary-General Antonio Guterres says that rising ocean temperatures present urgent risks for people living in the Pacific Islands.<br/>
联合国秘书长安东尼奥·古特雷斯表示，海洋温度上升给太平洋岛屿居民带来了紧迫的风险。</p>
<p>Guterres made the comment while at the Pacific Islands Forum taking place in Tonga. The country is a collection of about 170 islands in the southwestern Pacific Ocean.<br/>
古特雷斯在汤加举行的太平洋岛屿论坛上发表了上述评论。该国由太平洋西南部约170个岛屿组成。</p>
<p>The U.N. chief said studies suggest the southwestern Pacific faces more extreme sea level rise than other parts of the world. The problem, he added, is linked to sea temperatures in the area that in some cases are three times higher than worldwide levels.<br/>
联合国秘书长表示，研究表明，太平洋西南地区的海平面上升比世界其他地区更为极端。他补充说，这个问题与该地区的海水温度有关，在某些情况下，该地区海水温度是全球水平的三倍。</p>
<p>Warmer temperatures cause water to expand and this can cause sea level rise.<br/>
温度升高会导致水膨胀，这可能会导致海平面上升。</p>
<p>"I am in Tonga to issue a global SOS – Save Our Seas – on rising sea levels," Guterres said.<br/>
古特雷斯说：“我在汤加是为了对海平面上升发出全球SOS——救救我们的海洋。”</p>
<p>The U.N. leader said that rising seas were "amplifying” the number and severity of storms and coastal flooding across the area. He said such flooding can destroy fisheries, damage crops and poison water. “All this puts Pacific Island nations in grave danger," he said.<br/>
这位联合国领导人表示，海平面上升正在“放大”该地区风暴和沿海洪水的发生次数和严重程度。他说，这种洪水会破坏渔业、破坏农作物和污染水。他说，“这些都让太平洋岛国处于严重危险之中。”</p>
<p>A report recently released by the U.N.'s World Meteorological Organization showed ocean temperatures in the southwestern Pacific are increasing at up to three times the worldwide rate.<br/>
联合国世界气象组织最近发布的一份报告显示，太平洋西南地区的海洋温度上升速度是全球的三倍。</p>
<p>Guterres said the Pacific islands are especially at risk because much of their land is “just one to two meters above sea level."<br/>
古特雷斯表示，太平洋岛屿尤其面临风险，因为它们的大部分土地“仅高出海平面一到两米”。</p>
<p>And, he added, "Half the infrastructure is within 500 meters of the sea."<br/>
他补充道，而且“一半的基础设施距离大海不到500米。”</p>
<p>Many scientists blame the planet's rising temperatures on pollution from fossil fuel use. Guterres said the Pacific Islands can expect additional sea level rise of 15 centimeters by 2050 if the pollution levels do not drop.<br/>
许多科学家将地球气温上升归咎于使用化石燃料造成的污染。古特雷斯表示，如果污染水平不下降，到2050年，太平洋岛屿的海平面预计将进一步上升15厘米。</p>
<p>Guterres urged world leaders to greatly increase the level of climate-related investments, especially for at-risk countries, to help fight the problem.<br/>
古特雷斯敦促世界各国领导人大幅提高与气候相关的投资水平，特别是对高风险国家的投资，以帮助应对这一问题。</p>
<p>Delegates to the 2023 U.N. climate change conference approved the establishment of a "loss and damage" fund to help poor nations deal with climate disasters.<br/>
2023年联合国气候变化大会的代表们批准设立一个“损失和损害”基金，以帮助贫困国家应对气候灾害。</p>
<p>"Developed countries must deliver on their finance commitments,” Guterres said. He added that one commitment calls for doubling financing to at least $40 billion a year by 2025.<br/>
古特雷斯说：“发达国家必须履行其财政承诺。”他补充说，其中一项承诺要求到2025年将资金翻一番，达到每年至少400亿美元。</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.<br/>
我是布莱恩·林恩。(21VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Florida’s Snake Hunters (2024/8/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/florida-s-snake-hunters.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>It is after midnight when the windshield <strong>fogs</strong> up on Thomas Aycock's pickup truck. He smiles as he slowly drives through the sawgrass and down dirt roads deep in the Florida Everglades.</p>
<p>His foggy windshield confirms what he knows. When the dew point drops in the middle of the night, it is perfect time for pythons.</p>
<p>“I catch more pythons when that happens,” Aycock said. The retired U.S. Army veteran always takes part in the Florida Python Challenge. The wildlife commission runs the 10-day event. The aim is to get people interested in finding and catching the snakes.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Thomas Aycock, left, and Tom Rahill show off an invasive Burmese python caught earlier, as they wait for sunset to hunt pythons on Aug. 13, 2024, in the Florida Everglades. (AP Photo/Wilfredo Lee)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-cb83-08dcc6adfeef_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Thomas Aycock, left, and Tom Rahill show off an invasive Burmese python caught earlier, as they wait for sunset to hunt pythons on Aug. 13, 2024, in the Florida Everglades. (AP Photo/Wilfredo Lee)</span></div>
<p>There is a reason for the timing of the event. Pythons usually <strong>hatch</strong> from their eggs each August before finding their way into the <strong>swamp</strong>.</p>
<p>Aycock works for the Florida Fish and Wildlife Conservation Commission. He has hunted Burmese pythons in the Everglades for 11 years. Aycok loves snakes. And he loves preserving the Everglades. He understands the “greater ecological issue with these pythons.”</p>
<p>The <strong>invasive</strong> Burmese pythons are doing very well in Florida's <strong>preserved</strong> wetlands. Pythons have no natural <strong>predators</strong>. And they are threatening Florida's <strong>native</strong> snakes and mammals. The United States Geological Survey (USGS) estimates tens of thousands live in South Florida.</p>
<p>The snakes are destroying local wildlife. In one 2012 study, the USGS found that populations of raccoons had declined by 99.3 percent, opossums by 98.9 percent and bobcats by 87.5 percent since the early 2000s. Controlling this hungry snake, scientists say, is a critical goal.</p>
<p>More than 600 hunters took part in this year's challenge. Their goal is to beat last year's top total of 209 pythons killed. The hunter who kills the most wins $10,000.</p>
<p>The competition is designed to create understanding about Florida's python problem. It has succeeded in doing that. The event has drawn famous people and has led to some reality television shows.</p>
<p>But the need for python control remains urgent.</p>
<p>Since 2017, Florida has been paying about 100 <strong>contractors</strong> to catch the snakes year-round. That project is shared by the wildlife agency and the South Florida Water Management District. Through 2023, more than 18,000 pythons have been removed from the wild. Contractors like Aycock have removed about 11,000.</p>
<p>The pay is average. Hunting along backroads pays $13 an hour. Walking through the swamp pays $18 an hour. Contractors also get paid per snake: $50 for the first 1.2 meters in length, plus more for longer snakes.</p>
<p>“You're not going to make a living doing this full-time. There's no way you could do it,” Aycock said.</p>
<p>Florida does not permit hunters to use firearms to kill pythons<strong>.</strong> Catching them is a hands-on exercise.</p>
<p>Aycock goes into the wetlands to check on known hatching spots and grabs at them when he can. But mostly he drives down empty roads at night, shining a strong light into the swamps.</p>
<p>He says these bug-filled drives help his mental health. Sometimes he brings along fellow members of the Swamp Apes, a mental health non-profit organization for veterans. The group catches invasive snakes in the wild, clears overgrown areas, and works toward environmental preservation.</p>
<p>The group's founder, Tom Rahill, is also a snake hunting contractor. He knows the swamp so well that he can smell a python's “musk” odor. He says he can feel when a snake is near.</p>
<p>There is an art to catching a snake, the hunters say. The methods change from hunter to hunter. Some use a snake hook and then jump on them before putting them into bags. Rahill likes using his hands -- if the snake is calm enough.</p>
<p>“Instead of jumping on the snake, you just kind of gently get up to it and then just pick it up,” he said.</p>
<p>But the snakes are not always calm. Sometimes a hunter needs a helper to keep the snake <strong>uncoiled</strong> until it calms down and can be contained to prevent escape.</p>
<p>Once the snakes are caught, the hunters have 24 hours to take them to the wildlife agency. It is illegal for any person other than a <strong>licensed</strong> contractor to transport a live, invasive snake.</p>
<p>Aycock takes them home first to be “humanely killed.”</p>
<p>“That's the part of the job that I really just ... hate,” he said. “I hate having to kill snakes.”</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Stephany Matat reported this story for The Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>fog (up)</strong> <em>– v.</em> when small particles of water floating in the atmosphere are near the ground and on surfaces</p>
<p><strong>hatch</strong> <em>– v. </em>to emerge from an egg, chrysalis, or pupa</p>
<p><strong>swamp </strong><em>– n. </em>wet spongy land often partly covered with water</p>
<p><strong>invasive</strong> <em>– adj. </em>tending to spread especially in a quick or aggressive manner: such as<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>preserved </strong><em>– v. </em>to keep safe from injury, harm, or destruction</p>
<p><strong>predator</strong> <em>– n. </em>an animal that obtains food mostly by killing and eating other animals</p>
<p><strong>native </strong><em>– adj. </em>living or growing naturally in a particular region</p>
<p><strong>contractor </strong><em>– n. </em>a person who contracts to perform work or provide supplies at a certain price or within a certain time</p>
<p><strong>coiled </strong><em>– v. </em>to wind into or lie in loops, rings, or a spiral : <strong>uncoiled </strong><em>– v. </em>to unwind from a coil and become straight</p>
<p><strong>licensed </strong><em>– adj. </em>having permission granted by competent authority to engage in a business or occupation or in an activity otherwise unlawful</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>If You Learn Conditionals, You'll Be Glad You Did! (2024/8/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/if-you-learn-conditionals-you-ll-be-glad-you-did.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Adam Brock</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>
In this week's episode of Everyday Grammar, we are going to talk about <strong>conditionals</strong>. We use conditionals to show that something is true only when something else is true. Conditionals offer endless possibilities for creative and <strong>imaginative</strong> expression.</p>
<p><strong>Present real conditional</strong></p>
<p>The present real conditional is the most <strong>basic</strong> kind of conditional. Basically, <em>when A happens, B happens</em>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/77c20b4b-9201-4f25-a3a2-de2c72878152_tv_w100_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>Here's an example of a present real conditional:</p>
<p>"If it rains, I bring an umbrella."</p>
<p>Conditionals have two parts: the <em>if</em> <strong>clause</strong>: "if it rains," and the <em>result </em>clause: "I bring an umbrella." You could also say "I bring an umbrella if it rains."</p>
<p>Poets and songwriters often use conditionals in their work. Listen for the present real conditional in this song by American songwriter Bob Dylan.</p>
<p>"If you see her, say hello. She might be in Tangier ..."</p>
<p>Notice that the verbs <em>see</em> and <em>say</em> are both in the present <strong>tense</strong> for the present real conditional.</p>
<p><strong>Present unreal conditional</strong></p>
<p>The next conditional that we're going to talk about is the present <strong>unreal</strong> conditional. Use the present unreal conditional to talk about what you would do in an unreal, or imaginary situation: <em>If A happened, B would happen.</em></p>
<p>For example, "If I were you, I would take the job." The key word is <em>would; </em>it makes the conditional unreal<em>. Would </em>can only be used in the <em>result clause</em> of the sentence. Here's an example from American singer Johnny Cash.</p>
<p>"If I were a carpenter<br/>
And you were a lady<br/>
Would you marry me anyway?<br/>
Would you have my baby?"</p>
<p>To form a present unreal conditional, use a simple past verb in the <em>if </em>clause. In the <em>result</em> clause, use <em>would</em> followed by a simple present verb.</p>
<p>Use the verb <em>were</em> for all nouns in the<em> if</em> clause of the sentence. For example, "If she <em>were</em> an animal, she would be a cat." In informal speech, people might say, "If she <em>was </em>an animal, she would be a cat." But you should avoid this in formal writing.</p>
<p><strong>Future real conditional</strong></p>
<p>Now let's talk about the future real conditional: <em>If A happens, B will happen</em>.</p>
<p>To make a future real conditional, use <em>will</em> in the result clause. For example, "If your plane is late, I <em>will </em>wait in the car." Use the future real conditional to talk about possible situations in the future.</p>
<p>Speakers sometimes use the future real conditional to threaten others. Listen to actor Liam Neeson in the 2013 movie "Taken." In this scene of the movie, Neeson's character is on the phone threatening the man who kidnapped his daughter.</p>
<p>"If you let my daughter go now, that'll be the end of it. I will not look for you. I will not pursue you. But if you don't, I will look for you, I will find you, and I will kill you."</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p>This is only a quick introduction to conditionals. In a future episode of Everyday Grammar, we will talk about past and mixed conditionals. Until then, we will leave you with country music stars Johnny Cash and June Carter.</p>
<p>"If you were a carpenter<br/>
And I were a lady<br/>
I'd marry you anyway<br/>
I'd have your baby"</p>
<p></p><p>I'm Jonathan Evans.</p>
<p><em>Adam Brock wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. Jill Robbins and Ashley Thompson were the editors.</em></p>
<p><em>______________________________________________</em></p>
<table cellpadding="3" class="wsw__table"><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" style="width:500px">
<p>REFERENCE – Three common conditionals (incomplete list)</p>
</td></tr><tr></tr><tr><td> </td><td>If clause</td><td>Result clause</td></tr><tr><td>Present Real</td><td>
<p>If you <strong>see </strong>her,</p>
<p><em>Simple present</em></p>
</td><td>
<p><strong>say</strong> hello.</p>
<p><em>Simple present</em></p>
</td></tr><tr><td>Present Unreal</td><td>
<p>If I <strong>were </strong>you,</p>
<p><em>Simple past</em></p>
</td><td>
<p>I <strong>would leave</strong>.</p>
<p><em>Would + simple present</em></p>
</td></tr><tr><td>Future Real</td><td>
<p>If your plane <strong>is </strong>late,</p>
<p><em>Simple present</em></p>
</td><td>
<p>I <strong>will wait</strong> for you.</p>
<p><em>Simple future</em></p>
</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Lesson</h2>
<p><strong>conditional</strong> - <em>n.</em> a word, clause, or sentence that shows that something is true or happens only if something else is true or happens</p>
<p><strong>imaginative</strong> - <em>adj. </em>having or showing an ability to think of new and interesting ideas <strong>:</strong> having or showing imagination</p>
<p><strong>basic</strong> – <em>adj</em>. forming or relating to the first or easiest part of something</p>
<p><strong>clause</strong> - <em>n</em>. <em>grammar</em> <strong>:</strong> a part of a sentence that has its own subject and verb</p>
<p><strong>tense</strong> - <em>n.</em> a form of a verb that is used to show when an action happened</p>
<p><strong>unreal</strong> - <em>adj.</em> not real; not true</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Study Amazon Dolphins in Effort to Prevent Deaths (2024/8/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/scientists-study-amazon-dolphins-in-effort-to-prevent-deaths.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>About 200 freshwater dolphins were found dead in Lake Tefé of the Amazon River in Brazil during a period of severe dry weather last year.</p>
<p>That is why a team of biologists, animal doctors, and fishermen temporarily captured some river dolphins recently to study their health. The researchers hope the findings will help protect the dolphins from another weather disaster.</p>
<p>One of the captured dolphins was a female with her <strong>offspring</strong> nearby. Fishermen were careful not to injure her and kept her close to her offspring to avoid <strong>stressing</strong> the animals.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Field researchers from the Mamirau&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;225; Institute of Sustainable Development check the health of a rare Amazon river dolphin, also known as the pink river dolphin, in Lake Tef&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;233;, Amazonas state, Brazil, August 19, 2024. (REUTERS/Bruno Kelly)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-61ee-08dcc391f9bf_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Field researchers from the Mamirau<i>&amp;#</i>225; Institute of Sustainable Development check the health of a rare Amazon river dolphin, also known as the pink river dolphin, in Lake Tef<i>&amp;#</i>233;, Amazonas state, Brazil, August 19, 2024. (REUTERS/Bruno Kelly)</span></div>
<p>"She relaxed and we could do all the tests. She appeared in good health," said project leader Miriam Marmontel. She is a researcher at the Mamirauá Institute of Sustainable Development based in Tefé, Brazil. The organization planned the temporary capture of up to 20 dolphins.</p>
<p>The team took blood from the animals and performed other medical tests. The work included removing a small amount of fat to see if harmful chemicals were in the dolphin's body. They also put microchips in the animals to follow their movements.</p>
<p>The Solim<i></i>245;es River feeds water into Lake Tefé. Unusually dry weather last year caused water <strong>levels</strong> in the river to drop. As a result, the water became warmer than usual. Thousands of fish also died in the Amazon rivers because of a lack of oxygen in the water.</p>
<p>Many Amazon river dolphins are the color pink. They are found only in the rivers of South America, and they are among only a few kinds of freshwater dolphins still living in the world. Because they reproduce slowly, threats to their environment can more easily reduce their populations.</p>
<p>Marmontel said researchers hope to better understand what caused last year's deaths, so that experts and officials can react faster to the effects of this year's dry weather.</p>
<p>"We aim to learn more about the health of the dolphins at a time when water begins to go down and temperatures start to rise, so we can identify the changes and know whether they are due to higher temperatures or a <strong>toxin</strong> or pollutant in the water," she told Reuters.</p>
<p>The river dolphin research project received financial support from the National Marine Mammal Foundation of California in the United States. That organization's researchers helped examine the dolphins using <strong>ultrasound</strong> technology.</p>
<p>Marmontel said most of the dolphins that died last year were in Lake Tefé. The lake is very close to the Solim<i></i>245;es River.</p>
<p>The lake's waters reached 40.9 degrees Celsius during the 2023 dry season, more than 10 degrees higher than the average for that time of year. The water is now at 30 degrees Celsius, said Ayan Fleischmann. He is a geosciences researcher at the Mamirauá Institute.</p>
<p>Environmental activists have blamed climate change for the severe dry weather that made the river water warmer than normal. However, El Ni<i></i>241;o, the periodic and natural Pacific Ocean warming weather event could also have brought about last year's dry weather in the Amazon.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Bruno Kelly reported this story for Reuters. Andrew Smith adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>offspring </strong><em>-n. </em>an animal or child as related to its parent</p>
<p><strong>stress </strong><em>-v. </em>to cause worry or anxiety</p>
<p><strong>level </strong><em>-n. </em>the height of the surface of a body of water or other substance</p>
<p><strong>toxin </strong><em>-n. </em>a poisonous substance produced by animals, plants, or bacteria</p>
<p><strong>ultrasound </strong><em>-n. </em>sound waves that are used to get images of the inside of a human or animal body</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Humans Show Birds How to Fly South for Winter (2024/8/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/humans-show-birds-how-to-fly-south-for-winter.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Humans hunted and killed almost all northern bald ibis birds by the 17th century. But <strong>breeding</strong> and rewilding efforts over the last 20 years helped grow the bird population.</p>
<p>However, the birds do not know which direction to fly to <strong>migrate</strong> without the guidance of wild-born birds. So, humans are helping the birds learn their migration path.</p>
<p>The northern bald ibis once flew over North Africa, the Arabian Peninsula and much of Europe, including southern Germany's Bavaria. People liked eating the migratory birds, and they disappeared from Europe. A few groups of the birds survived in other places.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This photo provided by Waldrappteam Conservation &amp; Research shows the migration from Northern Bald Ibis, or the Waldrapp, supported by foster parents of the birds in a microlight aircraft. (Waldrappteam Conservation &amp; Research via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-1f07-08dcc6bcee1c_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This photo provided by Waldrappteam Conservation &amp; Research shows the migration from Northern Bald Ibis, or the Waldrapp, supported by foster parents of the birds in a microlight aircraft. (Waldrappteam Conservation &amp; Research via AP)</span></div>
<p>In 2002, a conservation and research group based in Austria stepped in to help. The group is called Waldrappteam; the birds are called Waldrapp in German. Scientists at Waldrappteam raise the birds and teach them how to fly to warmer areas.</p>
<p>Johannes Fritz is a biologist working with the team. He said, "We have to teach them the migration <strong>route</strong>.”</p>
<p>Fritz and the Waldrappteam have increased the number of northern ibis in Central Europe from zero to almost 300 since the start of their project in 2002.</p>
<p>Fritz said the group's work is the first attempt to reintroduce a continentally <strong>extinct</strong> migratory bird species. He said his team found that, when released, the birds raised by humans flew in the wrong direction and died in the winter. The humans have led the birds now for 17 years to places like Tuscany, Italy. Due to climate change, they have had to change the <strong>route</strong> to a winter home. Now they help the birds fly to Andalusia in southern Spain.</p>
<p>To prepare them for travel, the humans begin working with the baby birds, or chicks, when they are just a few days old. The <strong>foster </strong>parent humans want the birds to connect with them so they will trust them along the migration route.</p>
<p>Barbara Steininger is one Waldrappteam foster mother. She said she acts like "their bird mom."</p>
<p>"We feed them, we clean them, we clean their nests. We take good care of them and see that they are healthy birds," she said. "But also we <strong>interact</strong> with them."</p>
<p>Steininger and the other foster parents then sit on the back of a very small aircraft, waving and cheering for the birds as they fly.</p>
<p>Fritz knew his work would be possible because he saw the work of Canadian inventor and naturalist Bill Lishman. Lishman taught Canadian geese to fly alongside his small plane beginning in 1988. He later guided endangered whooping cranes through safe routes.</p>
<p>Fritz's team efforts have worked. The first bird independently migrated back to Bavaria from Tuscany in 2011. The team hopes the Central European population will be more than 350 birds by 2028 and will not need human help to migrate.</p>
<p>This year, the route to Spain is longer than last year's path. Earlier this month from an airfield in upper Bavaria, the team guided 36 birds along one stage through blue skies and a wind from behind them that increased their speed.</p>
<p>The full <strong>journey</strong> to Spain could take up to 50 days. Fritz said the effort is bigger than just the northern bald ibises. He hopes the group's work offers a possibility for helping other threatened migratory <strong>species</strong> to fly.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Bobby Hardy and Stefanie Dazio reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>breeding </strong>– <em>n</em>. the activity of keeping and caring for animals or plants in order to produce more animals or plants of a particular kind</p>
<p><strong>migrate</strong> – <em>v. of a bird or animal</em>. to move from one area to another at different times of the year</p>
<p><strong>extinct</strong> – <em>adj</em>. no longer living</p>
<p><strong>route </strong>– <em>n</em>. a way to get from one place to another place</p>
<p><strong>foster</strong> – <em>v. </em>to provide the care that a parent usually gives to a child; to be or become the foster parent of a child</p>
<p><strong>interact</strong> – <em>v</em>. to talk or do things with others</p>
<p><strong>journey</strong> – <em>n</em>. an act of traveling from one place to another</p>
<p><strong>species</strong> – <em>n.</em> <em>biology. </em> a group of animals or plants that are similar and can produce young animals or plants</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>X Changes AI tool after Pressure to Reduce Misinformation (2024/8/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/x-changes-ai-tool-after-pressure-to-reduce-misinformation.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The social media service X has changed its artificial intelligence (AI) tool after several U.S. states warned that it was spreading election misinformation.</p>
<p>Earlier this month, secretaries of state in five states sent the owner of X, Elon Musk, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.sos.state.mn.us/media/6077/080524-secretaries-letter-to-x.pdf">a letter</a> requesting the change to its Grok AI tool.</p>
<p>X explains on its <a class="wsw__a" href="https://help.x.com/en/using-x/about-grok">Help Center</a> that Grok is designed to be used as an AI search assistant to help users find information online. Such tools are also known as chatbots or generative AI. Grok is only available to paid users of X's Premium and Premium+ services.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FIE - The X logo is shown on a computer screen in Belgrade, Serbia, July 24, 2023. (AP Photo/Darko Vojinovic, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-d2d9-08dcc6e3d6f9_cx17_cy3_cw82_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FIE - The X logo is shown on a computer screen in Belgrade, Serbia, July 24, 2023. (AP Photo/Darko Vojinovic, File)</span></div>
<p>In their letter, the secretaries of state expressed concern that the Grok tool was returning results that included misinformation about the U.S. presidential election process. The officials said that shortly after President Joe Biden ended his run for re-election, the Grok tool provided false information on state ballot requirements.</p>
<p>The misinformation included a statement that the <strong>deadline</strong> had passed in several states to make ballot changes for the nation's presidential election. The secretaries' wrote that the statement was completely false. In all the states identified by Grok, it was still possible for ballot changes to be made, the letter said.</p>
<p>The ballot changes increased in importance when the Democratic Party chose a new nominee, Vice President Kamala Harris, after Biden withdrew.</p>
<p>Former President Donald Trump is the Republican Party's nominee.</p>
<p>The letter recognized that Grok does warn its users that the AI tool might return false information. And it noted that the tool urges users not to depend completely on Grok for news and information.</p>
<p>However, the secretaries of state wrote, the false information about ballot deadlines was “captured and shared repeatedly in multiple posts - reaching millions of people.” In addition, they noted, Grok continued to repeat this false information for more than a week until it was corrected on July 31, 2024.</p>
<p>The secretaries of state requested that Grok instead direct users who enter search requests about election-related questions to an official government-run website for the latest voting information. The request aimed to send Grok users immediately and directly to an official election-related website.</p>
<p>The secretaries recently sent out a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.sos.state.mn.us/about-the-office/news-room/secretaries-of-state-welcome-changes-to-x-s-ai-search-assistant/">press release</a> confirming that Grok had made such a change. Before providing results to search requests about election matters, the tool now offers new user guidance. “For accurate and up-to-date information about the 2024 U.S. Elections, please visit Vote.gov,” Grok now says.</p>
<p>The state secretaries explained that <a class="wsw__a" href="https://vote.gov/">Vote.gov</a> is a politically neutral, “trustworthy” website operated by the U.S. government in partnership with state election officials. The website also receives support from government organizations that seek to prevent internet attacks that can block sites or take them offline.</p>
<p>All elections in the United States are operated by local officials supported and led by a state agency. Experts say because each state sets its own requirements and deadlines, it is important for voters to be connected to the most dependable information available.</p>
<p>Musk bought Twitter in 2022 and later renamed the service X. Activist groups have repeatedly raised concerns about a large increase in hate speech and misinformation appearing on the service after Musk became the owner. Some X critics have also said major employee cuts had left the company with ineffective content <strong>moderation</strong> methods that do not catch misinformation.</p>
<p>In their latest press release, the secretaries of state thanked X for agreeing to the change and said they hope the company will remain open to additional improvements to protect its users. They added, “Elections are a team effort, and we need and welcome any partners who are committed to ensuring free, fair, secure, and <strong>accurate</strong> elections.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters and Agence France-Presse and the Minnesota Secretary of State. </em></p>
<p><strong>_________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>deadline</strong> <em>– n. </em>a date or time by which something must be completed</p>
<p><strong>moderate</strong> <em>– v. </em>to make sure the rules of an internet discussion are not broken</p>
<p><strong>accurate </strong><em>– </em><em>adj. </em>correct or exact</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Colleges Change Rules for Campus Protests (2024/8/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/us-colleges-change-rules-for-campus-protests.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">27 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>As students return to college across the United States, administrators are preparing for new activism against the war in Gaza. Some have <strong>adopted</strong> new rules limiting protests. Last spring, college protests resulted in damage, conflict and arrests at several schools.</p>
<p>The summer break brought most protests to an end. But the results of the damage last spring are still being felt.</p>
<p>At Columbia University in New York City, Minouche Shafik resigned from her position as president earlier this month. In April, Shafik faced strong criticism from lawmakers over her response to protests at Columbia.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Student protesters gather inside their encampment on the Columbia University campus, April 29, 2024, in New York. (AP Photo/Stefan Jeremiah, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-2ec3-08dcc160da1c_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Student protesters gather inside their encampment on the Columbia University campus, April 29, 2024, in New York. (AP Photo/Stefan Jeremiah, File)</span></div>
<p><strong>New measures for campus demonstrations</strong></p>
<p>Some universities are putting new measures in place to avoid what happened at Columbia. The new rules include banning encampments and limiting the duration of demonstrations. They permit protests only in defined areas and restrict campus <strong>access</strong> to those with university identification.</p>
<p>Critics say some of the measures will hurt free speech.</p>
<p>The American Association of University Professors (AAUP) released a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.aaup.org/news/aaup-condemns-wave-administrative-policies-intended-crack-down-peaceful-campus-protest">statement</a> earlier this month condemning “overly restrictive policies” that would harm free expression.</p>
<p>The AAUP said, “Our colleges and universities should <strong>encourage</strong>, not suppress, open and <strong>vigorous</strong> dialogue and debate even on the most deeply held beliefs.”</p>
<p>The University of Pennsylvania has released “temporary guidelines” for student protests. Overnight demonstrations are banned, and the use of loud audio equipment is barred after 5 p.m. on days when classes are being held. Signs, posters, and banners must be removed after two weeks. The university says it remains supportive of freedom of speech and lawful <strong>assembly</strong>.</p>
<p>At Indiana University, protests after 11 p.m. are banned under a new “expressive activities policy” which took effect on August 1. The policy bars “camping” or placing a shelter on campus. Signs require approval from school officials.</p>
<p>The University of South Florida now requires approval for tents, <strong>canopies</strong>, banners, signs and <strong>amplifiers</strong>. “Speech, expression and assembly” rules bar demonstrations after 5 p.m. on weekdays and weekends. Protests are completely banned during the last two weeks of a <strong>semester</strong>.</p>
<p>Risa Lieberwitz is a Cornell University professor of labor and employment law and gives legal advice to the AAUP. Lieberwitz said, “I think right now we are seeing a resurgence of repression on campuses that we haven't seen since the late 1960s.”</p>
<p>However, university officials say free speech cannot interfere with learning. They say the updated rules improve safety on campus.</p>
<p><strong>Why are students protesting?</strong></p>
<p>Tensions at many universities increased after October 7, 2023, when Hamas militants attacked southern Israel. Hamas killed 1,200 people most of whom were civilians. Hamas also took about 250 people hostage. Israel's military operation to answer the attack has continued through the summer.</p>
<p>Many student protesters in the U.S. have promised to continue their activism against the Gaza war. They are fueled by information from Hamas's health ministry that says more than 40,000 people have died in the Gaza conflict.</p>
<p>Much of that tension appeared in the spring on Columbia's campus. On April 30, police with riot shields raided a building that pro-Palestinian protesters had occupied at Columbia. Earlier, police had cleared out a tent camp that protestors had set up.</p>
<p>Similar protests took place on <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/police-clear-protest-camps-at-several-us-colleges/7593871.html">campuses around the country</a>. It is estimated that more than 3,000 people were arrested in connection with the pro-Palestinian protests.</p>
<p>However, many of the students who were arrested during police actions have had their charges dismissed. Some are still waiting to learn what government lawyers decide. Others have faced suspension from school, had their <strong>diplomas</strong> withheld or faced other punishments.</p>
<p>Columbia only recently began permitting people with university identification or registered visitors onto campus. Officials said they wanted to limit possible “<strong>disruptions</strong>” at the start of the new semester.</p>
<p>Shafik of Columbia was among the university leaders who Congress called on in April to explain what was happening. Lawmakers accused her of not doing enough to deal with concerns about anti-Semitism at Columbia. She announced her resignation weeks before classes are to start on September 3.</p>
<p>Other university leaders have also stepped down in recent months.</p>
<p>University of Pennsylvania President Liz Magill resigned in December. She faced pressure after she appeared before Congress and was unable to say whether calls on campus for the genocide of Jewish people would violate school policy.</p>
<p>In January, Harvard University President Claudine Gay resigned after accusations of claiming others' writings as her own and her statement about free speech given to Congress.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p>And I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Nick Perry, Jake Offenhartz and Jocelyn Gecker reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English with additional AP reporting and other sources. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>adopt </strong><em>–v.</em> to accept and put in place</p>
<p><strong>access</strong></p>
<p><strong>encourage</strong> <em>–v.</em> to support and get people to do something</p>
<p><strong>vigorous </strong>–adj. done with energy and willingness</p>
<p><strong>assembly </strong><em>–n.</em> the lawful and peaceful gathering of people in public</p>
<p><strong>canopy </strong><em>–n.</em> a shelter similar to a tent but without sides</p>
<p><strong>amplifier </strong><em>–n</em>. a device that electronically makes a sound louder</p>
<p><strong>semester</strong> <em>–adj. </em>one half of a school year</p>
<p><strong>diploma </strong><em>–n.</em> a document that officially shows that a person has fulfilled requirements for a degree from a school or university</p>
<p><strong>disruption</strong> <em>–n.</em> an event that interferes with normal or necessary activities</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Cambodia Celebrates Return of Long-lost Ancient Cultural Pieces (2024/8/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/cambodia-celebrates-return-of-long-lost-ancient-cultural-pieces.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">27 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Cambodia has celebrated the return of numerous cultural art pieces stolen during the country's civil war period.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Hun Manet recently led a ceremony to welcome the pieces, called artifacts, back to Cambodia. The event took place at the nation's Peace Palace in Phnom Penh. The palace houses the government's official headquarters.</p>
<p>The Cambodian leader said a total of 70 ancient statues had been reunited with the country's people. Most of the pieces are believed to have been stolen during Cambodia's civil war period, from 1967 until 1975.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this photo released by Agence Kampuchea Press (AKP), Cambodian Prime Minister Hun Manet prays with others during a ceremony for the return of artifacts in Peace Palace in Phnom Penh, Cambodia, Thursday, Aug. 22, 2024. (AKP via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-8708-08dcc5f1f260_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this photo released by Agence Kampuchea Press (AKP), Cambodian Prime Minister Hun Manet prays with others during a ceremony for the return of artifacts in Peace Palace in Phnom Penh, Cambodia, Thursday, Aug. 22, 2024. (AKP via AP)</span></div>
<p>At the time, the communist Khmer Rouge ruled Cambodia. It is blamed for the killings of more than 1 million Cambodians during its rule and years of unrest and economic difficulties.</p>
<p>Multiple international efforts over the years have helped Cambodia get back its artistic and archaeological treasures. The stolen artifacts include ancient pieces from Asia as well as artwork lost or stolen in conflict areas such as Syria, Iraq and Nazi-occupied Europe.</p>
<p>“A total of 70 Khmer cultural objects have been returned through a range of different processes,” Cambodia's Ministry of Culture and Fine Arts said in a statement. These included voluntary returns, negotiations, seizures and legal processes.</p>
<p>The statement said the returned artifacts included important Hindu and Buddhist pieces from the 9th-to-14th-century. Among them were “priceless stone statues” representing <strong>mythical</strong> Hindu figures, it added.</p>
<p>Hun Manet said that from 1996 until last month, 1,098 artifacts had been returned to Cambodia. About half were from private collections and half from foreign groups or governments.</p>
<p>Officials said the 70 items presented included 14 that arrived from New York's Metropolitan Museum of Art in early July. The rest, from private collectors, arrived in late July.</p>
<p>The pieces that came from the Metropolitan Museum were bought and trafficked by well-known art dealer Douglas Latchford. He had been <strong>indicted</strong> in 2019 on charges linked to an effort that sought to sell stolen Cambodian artifacts on the international art market. Latchford, who died the following year, had denied any involvement in smuggling.</p>
<p>A statement from the U.S. Embassy in Cambodia said the U.S. government had assisted the country with the return of over 150 ancient cultural pieces. Embassy official Bridgette Walker told ceremony attendees that the United States had long been a dependable partner “for protecting the cultural <strong>heritage</strong> of Cambodia.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>mythical </strong><em>–</em><strong> </strong><em>adj.</em> existing in a myth: an ancient story about gods and brave people, often one that explains historical events</p>
<p><strong>indict</strong> <em>– v. </em>to officially accuse someone of a crime</p>
<p><strong>heritage </strong><em>– n.</em> the buildings, paintings, customs, etc. that are important to a culture or society</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Biggest Diamond in 100 Years Discovered in Botswana (2024/8/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/biggest-diamond-in-100-years-discovered-in-botswana.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">27 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Miners in Botswana recently unearthed what officials say is the second largest diamond in mining history. The country's president Mokgweetsi Masisi presented the large stone to the public at a ceremony last week.</p>
<p>The 2,492-<strong>carat</strong> gem is the biggest diamond to be discovered since 1905. The diamond weighs around a half-kilogram. Masisi was one of the first people to get to hold it.</p>
<p>He expressed surprise at the diamond's heaviness and told the gathering, “I am lucky to have seen it in my time."</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Botswana's President Mokgweetsi Masisi holds a large diamond discovered in Botswana at his office in Gaborone on August 22, 2024. (Photo by Monirul BHUIYAN / AFP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/16dfd8fc-3166-4560-b59a-93b62bd1dea2_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Botswana's President Mokgweetsi Masisi holds a large diamond discovered in Botswana at his office in Gaborone on August 22, 2024. (Photo by Monirul BHUIYAN / AFP)</span></div>
<p>Lucara Diamond, a Canadian mining company, found the stone. Company officials said it was too early to value the gem or decide how it would be sold. A smaller uncut diamond from the same mine in Botswana sold for a record $63 million in 2016.</p>
<p>Naseem Lahri is a director with Lucara's Botswana team. “This is history in the making,” she said of the new find. “I am very proud. It is a product of Botswana.”</p>
<p>Lucara said in a statement last week that the company recovered what it called an “exceptional” diamond from Karowe Mine in central Botswana. Company miners used X-ray technology that is designed to find large, high-value diamonds.</p>
<p>“We are <strong>ecstatic</strong> about the recovery of this <strong>extraordinary</strong> 2,492-carat diamond,” Lucara President and chief William Lamb said in a statement.</p>
<p>The weight would make it the largest diamond found in 119 years.</p>
<p>It also is the second-largest diamond ever mined, after the Cullinan Diamond. That 3,106-carat stone was unearthed in South Africa in 1905. The Cullinan was the source of several famous cut gems, including some among the British Crown Jewels.</p>
<p>Botswana, a country of 2.6 million people in southern Africa, is the second-biggest producer of natural diamonds behind Russia.</p>
<p>The Karowe Mine has produced four other diamonds over 1,000 carats in the last decade.</p>
<p>Before this discovery, the Sewelo diamond, which was found at the Karowe Mine in 2019, was recognized as the second-biggest mined diamond in the world at 1,758 carats. French <strong>fashion</strong> business Louis Vuitton bought the diamond. The sale price was not publicized.</p>
<p>A British jeweler bought the 1,111-carat Lesedi La Rona diamond, also from Botswana's Karowe Mine, for $53 million in 2017. A Karowe diamond named The Constellation is the holder of the record $63 million sales price.</p>
<p>Diamonds form when carbon atoms are pushed close together by intense pressure conditions deep underground. Scientists say most diamonds are at least a billion years old and some of them more than 3 billion years old.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Sello Motseta reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>carat </strong><em>– n. </em>a unit of weight for precious stones that is equal to about 200 milligrams</p>
<p><strong>ecstatic </strong><em>– adj.</em> describes a state of overwhelming emotion</p>
<p><strong>extraordinary </strong>–<em> adj.</em> going beyond what is usual, regular <strong>fashion </strong><em>– n.</em> the prevailing style during a particular time</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Telegram Chief Pavel Durov Arrested in France (2024/8/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/telegram-chief-pavel-durov-arrested-in-france.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The founder and chief executive of the Telegram messaging service, Pavel Durov, was arrested in France over the weekend.</p>
<p>The reports said police detained Durov Saturday night at Le Bourget airport in Paris. Durov holds citizenship in both France and Russia. He landed in France after a flight from Azerbaijan, French broadcasters LCI and TF1 reported.</p>
<p>French media reported on Monday that Durov's arrest was linked to a French investigation that found evidence that Telegram had failed to reduce the spread of illegal material on its service.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This file photo shows Telegram co-founder Pavel Durov, following his meeting with Indonesian Communication and Information Minister Rudiantara in Jakarta, Indonesia on Aug. 1, 2017. (AP Photo/Tatan Syuflana, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-a144-08dcc5fb4c1d_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This file photo shows Telegram co-founder Pavel Durov, following his meeting with Indonesian Communication and Information Minister Rudiantara in Jakarta, Indonesia on Aug. 1, 2017. (AP Photo/Tatan Syuflana, File)</span></div>
<p>French President Emmanuel Macron said the arrest was “in no way a political decision.” He said on the social media service X that France “is deeply committed” to freedom of expression. But he added, “Freedoms are upheld with in a legal <strong>framework</strong>.”</p>
<p>The arrest of the 39-year-old Durov was reportedly sought by a French investigative agency that examines crimes against minors. The French media says officials are investigating crimes including <strong>money</strong> <strong>laundering</strong>, drug trafficking and other offenses.</p>
<p>In a statement issued Monday, Telegram said the company obeys all European Union laws, including the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://commission.europa.eu/strategy-and-policy/priorities-2019-2024/europe-fit-digital-age/digital-services-act_en">Digital Services Act</a>. It added that Telegram's <strong>moderation</strong> methods operate within industry standards and are always being improved.</p>
<p>Durov “has nothing to hide and travels frequently in Europe,” the company said. The statement added, “It is <strong>absurd</strong> to claim that a <strong>platform</strong> or its owner are responsible for abuse of that platform."</p>
<p>Representatives for Durov could not be immediately reached for comment. French law enforcement officials also offered no comment because the investigation is ongoing.</p>
<p>Durov founded Telegram with his brother in reaction to Russian government efforts to crush large pro-democracy protests that took place in Moscow at the end of 2011 and 2012. The demonstrations led the Russian government to introduce new restrictions on internet operations in the country. Durov left Russia in 2014.</p>
<p>Russia's agency that governs technology companies at one time tried to block Telegram but was unsuccessful in fully restricting the service. In March, the government said it was working with Telegram to remove content that violated Russian laws.</p>
<p>The messaging service is currently a popular source of news in Ukraine, The Associated Press (AP) reports. Telegram is reportedly used by both government officials and the media to share information on Ukraine's war with Russia. It has also been used to send missile and air raid warnings to citizens during the conflict.</p>
<p>Western governments have criticized Telegram for having weak moderation policies that are supposed to identify and remove illegal material. Experts say the lack of enforcement makes it easier for individuals to commit crimes such as money laundering and drug trafficking on the service.</p>
<p>David Thiel is a researcher at Stanford University in California. He has investigated the use of online services to carry out child <strong>exploitation</strong>. Thiel told the AP that compared to other messaging services, Telegram is “less secure (and) more <strong>lax</strong>” in identifying and removing illegal content.</p>
<p>In addition, Telegram “appears basically <strong>unresponsive</strong> to law enforcement,” he added. As an example, Thiel said that while the messaging service WhatsApp registered 1.3 million reports of possible child exploitation in 2023, Telegram did not send any.</p>
<p>In a statement to the AP earlier this month, Telegram said it actively works to fight the misuse of its service. The company said it uses a combination of <strong>monitoring</strong> methods and user reports in order to remove banned content. “Each day, millions of pieces of harmful content are removed,” it added.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press, Reuters and Agence France-Presse reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>framework </strong>–n. the supporting structure of something<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>money laundering </strong><em>– n.</em> the crime of moving money that has been obtained illegally through banks and other businesses in order to make it seem like the money operations are legal</p>
<p><strong>moderate</strong> <em>– v. </em>to make sure the rules of an internet discussion are not broken</p>
<p><strong>absurd </strong><em>– adj.</em> unreasonable or outrageous</p>
<p><strong>platform </strong><em>– n.</em> a company or service that permits someone to tell a large number of people about ideas or products</p>
<p><strong>exploit</strong> <em>– v. </em>to use someone or something unfairly for your own advantage</p>
<p><strong>lax </strong><em>– adj.</em> without much care, attention or control</p>
<p><strong>unresponsive </strong><em>– adj. </em>not reacting in a quick or positive way</p>
<p><strong>monitor </strong><em>– v.</em> to carefully watch something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>For Exercising, When and How Should You Stretch? (2024/8/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/for-exercising-when-and-how-should-you-stretch.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>Years ago, the traditional advice was to do some stretching before<em> </em>exercising. Over the years, that advice changed to stretching after<em> </em>exercising. It turns out that both advice can be true. And that can lead to some confusion.</p>
<p>Stretching can help make you more <strong>flexible</strong>.<strong> </strong>The more you stretch, the more you improve the <strong>range of motion</strong> in your joints. This not only feels good, but it also can prevent injury and lead to better physical results.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Panamanian gymnast Hillary Heron stretches as she trains for the Olympics at the No Limits Gymnastics Center in Panama City, Saturday, June 15, 2024, ahead of the Games in Paris. (AP Photo/Matias Delacroix, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-c71c-08dcb7c64554_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Panamanian gymnast Hillary Heron stretches as she trains for the Olympics at the No Limits Gymnastics Center in Panama City, Saturday, June 15, 2024, ahead of the Games in Paris. (AP Photo/Matias Delacroix, File)</span></div>
<p>David Behm researches human body movements at Memorial University of Newfoundland in St. John's, Canada. Speaking with the Associated Press, he offers advice on when to stretch and how to do it safely.</p>
<p><strong>Warm up first</strong></p>
<p>It is almost always good to stretch. However, Behm, says it is better if you warm up first. He suggests light <strong>aerobic</strong> activity such as jogging, walking or cycling for five to 10 minutes.</p>
<p>He suggests to follow that warm-up movement with <strong>static</strong> stretching. This traditional way of stretching involves reaching your body into different positions and holding them for about one minute each.</p>
<p>Then you can do <strong>dynamic</strong> stretching related to specific exercises or activities. This is where you warm up the muscles with repeated movements like leg lifts.</p>
<p><strong>Expand your definition of ‘stretching'</strong></p>
<p>Should you always stretch before exercising? If it is traditional static stretching, not necessarily, Behm says.</p>
<p>The better questions, he says, are, “Should people increase their range of motion? Should people have better flexibility? And that is yes, because it helps prevent injuries. It helps with health. But you don't have to stretch to achieve that.”</p>
<p>Resistance training, for example, can be an effective form of stretching. Doing a chest press increases range of motion in your arm and chest muscles. Whether you use barbells, dumbbells or machines, there is no need to stretch beforehand. However, Behm warns to start with a small amount of weight to warm up and then add more to train.</p>
<p>He adds that you do not need to stretch first if you are going for a short run. Simply start with a slow jog to warm up and then increase the speed.</p>
<p><strong>Don't do it if it hurts</strong></p>
<p>After exercise, light stretching is fine, as long as you do not feel pain, Behm says. Because your muscles will be warm by that point, overdoing it makes you more likely to injure yourself.</p>
<p>Foam rollers can help with muscle recovery and have been shown to increase range of motion as well as stretching.</p>
<p><strong>Do some static stretching before sports</strong></p>
<p>If you're playing a sport, Behm says, static stretching beforehand helps reduce muscle and <strong>tendon</strong> injury.</p>
<p>Sports like gymnastics, ice skating, and golf require a great range of motion. For these activities, he suggests extra stretching specific to those sports.</p>
<p>“If you're going to do an explosive movement, change of direction, <strong>agility</strong>, sprint, any of these explosive activities that involve your muscles and tendons,” he said, “you're going to be stronger if you do static stretching.”</p>
<p>People can especially get in trouble when they go back to a sport they used to play. Stretching can prepare muscles that may be out of shape. Also, he says to stretch both sides of your body equally. Lacking flexibility on one side also can lead to injury.</p>
<p><strong>Sounds simple. Why all the confusion?</strong></p>
<p>Different studies over the years have led to different advice about stretching before exercise. Behm says that is partly because some studies did not consider real-life conditions. Also, some researchers designed studies with high-performance athletes in mind and not regular people.</p>
<p>“If you're Usain Bolt, it makes a difference,” he said. For the rest of us ... not so much.</p>
<p>And that's the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report. I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Albert Stumm reported this story for The Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><em>________________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"> </h2>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>flexible </strong><em>– adj.</em> capable of being bent</p>
<p><strong>range of motion</strong> <em>– n. </em>the extent or limit to which a part of the body can be moved around a joint or a fixed point</p>
<p><strong>aerobic</strong> <em>– adj. </em>of, relating to, or being activity which increases the body's demand for oxygen thereby resulting in marked temporary increase in respiration and heart rate</p>
<p><strong>static </strong><em>– adj. </em>standing or fixed in one place</p>
<p><strong>dynamic </strong><em>– adj. </em>always active, moving or changing</p>
<p><strong>tendon </strong><em>– n. </em>a tough cord or band of dense white connective tissue that links a muscle to some other part (as a bone)</p>
<p><strong>agility </strong><em>– n. </em>the quality or state of being able to move quickly and easily</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Sea Lions Gather on California Beach, People Should Let Them Rest (2024/8/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/sea-lions-gather-on-california-beach-people-should-let-them-rest.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hundreds of California <strong>sea lions </strong>have taken over San Carlos Beach in Monterey, California, causing officials to close the area to people.</p>
<p>Drawn to the animals, people still gather to take photos as they rest and play on the sand and in the water. While sea lions, or eared seals, are often seen at certain beaches up and down the California coast, locals say they have never seen so many of them in Monterey.</p>
<p>Lisa Uttal is a <strong>marine</strong> biologist with the Monterey Bay National Marine Sanctuary. She said it was unclear exactly why the sea lions chose San Carlos Beach, but they may be <strong>attracted</strong> to the food supply in nearby waters. Almost all the seals gathered on the beach were male, she said.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Sea lions congregate at San Carlos Beach while local authorities decided to temporarily close the beach in Monterey, CA. August 22, 2024. (REUTERS/Carlos Barria)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-7775-08dcc3abebbd_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Sea lions congregate at San Carlos Beach while local authorities decided to temporarily close the beach in Monterey, CA. August 22, 2024. (REUTERS/Carlos Barria)</span></div>
<p>Uttal explained that the seals move to the northern coast from Ventura and the Channel Islands. “They are incredibly mobile. They're usually chasing the food.” She noted that the Monterey Bay National Marine Sanctuary has many different kinds of sea life. Uttal expects the sea lions to remain on San Carlos Beach for three to four weeks.</p>
<p>Marge Brigadier is a volunteer with Monterey Bay National Marine Sanctuary's Bay Net program. She said people should not get too close to the sea lions or try to make them move away. The U.S. Marine Mammal Protection Act of 1972 is the law that prevents people from harming them.</p>
<p>"People just need to think about how they would feel if they were resting on their bed taking a <strong>nap</strong> and something big kept coming and chasing them out of the house," Brigadier said.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Dylan Bouscher </em><em>reported this story for </em><em>Reuters</em><em>. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>sea lion</strong> – <em>n. </em>an eared seal occurring mainly on Pacific coasts, the large male of which has a mane on the neck and shoulders.</p>
<p><strong>marine</strong> – <em>adj</em>. of or relating to the sea or the plants and animals that live in the sea</p>
<p><strong>mammal</strong><em> – n.</em> a type of animal that feeds milk to its young and that usually has hair or fur covering most of its skin</p>
<p><strong>attract</strong> – <em>v</em>. to cause (someone) to choose to do or be involved in something</p>
<p><strong>nap</strong> – <em>n</em>. a short period of sleep especially during the day</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>NASA Launches Instrument to Measure World’s Carbon, Methane (2024/8/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/nasa-launches-instrument-to-measure-world-s-carbon-methane.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The American space agency NASA has launched an instrument to measure the world's carbon and methane levels in an effort to help fight climate change.</p>
<p>The instrument is attached to a satellite called Tanager-1. It launched August 16 aboard a SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket from NASA's Vandenberg Space Force Base in California. Ground controllers reported they successfully established communications with the satellite shortly after launch.</p>
<p>A statement from NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.jpl.nasa.gov/news/nasa-designed-greenhouse-gas-detection-instrument-launches">said</a> the satellite is equipped with a gas-seeking instrument powered with “imaging spectrometer technology.” A spectrometer is an instrument used to study the chemical composition and structures of substances.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Smoke rises from a coal-powered steel plant at Hehal village near Ranchi, in the eastern state of Jharkhand, Sept. 26, 2021. (AP Photo/Altaf Qadri, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-87df-08db2f047806_cx0_cy7_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Smoke rises from a coal-powered steel plant at Hehal village near Ranchi, in the eastern state of Jharkhand, Sept. 26, 2021. (AP Photo/Altaf Qadri, File)</span></div>
<p>NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL) developed the imaging spectrometer instrument. The joint project also involved other organizations, including Planet Labs PBC. The private company helped build the Tanager-1 satellite.</p>
<p>Tanager-1 is one of two satellites developed as part of the public-private partnership the Carbon Mapper Coalition. The other satellite has not yet been launched.</p>
<p>The coalition <a class="wsw__a" href="https://carbonmapper.org/">says</a> it aims to support the collection of detailed data on methane and carbon dioxide <strong>emissions</strong> worldwide. The coalition hopes to use the data to drive reductions in methane and carbon pollution. Scientists have linked carbon and methane emissions to warming temperatures on Earth. Many climate experts blame most of the warming on pollution caused by human activities.</p>
<p>NASA says the instrument aboard Tanager-1 measures “hundreds of wavelengths of light that are <strong>reflected</strong> by Earth's surface.” This method permits the instrument to find sources of carbon and methane based on the light wavelengths they show.</p>
<p>The process produces “fingerprints” that the imaging spectrometer can identify, NASA said. This data can be used to provide highly detailed information on where the world's carbon and methane come from. The level of detail is so exact, it can even identify “individual <strong>facilities </strong>and equipment,” the space agency added.</p>
<p>Laurie Leshin is director of the JPL, which is based in Pasadena, California. She said in a statement the imaging spectrometer technology is the product of more than 40 years of development at NASA. Leshin said such detailed emissions data can help policymakers, governments and environmental organizations worldwide.</p>
<p>When fully operational, Tanager-1 will aim to capture data across 130,000 square kilometers of Earth's surface each day. This will permit scientists to identify specific gas clouds releasing carbon dioxide and methane. NASA said the collected data will be publicly available online at the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://data.carbonmapper.org/">Carbon Mapper data portal</a>.</p>
<p>NASA says about half of methane emissions worldwide are caused by human activities. The biggest polluters are called “super <strong>emitters</strong>,” said Carbon Mapper Coalition chief executive Riley Duren. He told the Reuters news agency that super emitters produce more than 100 kilograms of methane per hour. This level of release could add up to 20 to 60 percent of an area's total emissions in some industries, Duren said.</p>
<p>In addition, the agency noted, “There is now 50 percent more carbon dioxide in the atmosphere than there was in 1750, an increase largely due to the <strong>extraction</strong> and burning of coal, oil, and (natural) gas.”</p>
<p>Duren said in a statement the Carbon Mapper Coalition is a good example “of how organizations from different <strong>sectors</strong> are uniting around a common goal of addressing climate change.” He added that having the ability to exactly identify the sources of carbon and methane “can drive significant action around the world to cut emissions now.”</p>
<p>The launch of Tanager-1 came after NASA's February <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/nasa-launches-new-satellite-to-study-oceans-atmosphere/7480106.html">deployment</a> of the PACE satellite. It is designed to closely study the world's oceans and atmosphere. PACE stands for Plankton, Aerosol, Cloud, Ocean Ecosystem. The satellite will spend at least three years studying the environment from an orbit 676 kilometers above the Earth's surface.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from Reuters, NASA and the Carbon Mapper Coalition. </em></p>
<p><strong>____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>emission</strong> <em>– n.</em> the act of sending something out such as a gas, heat, or light</p>
<p><strong>reflect</strong> <em>– n. </em>to send back or bouncer off of something</p>
<p><strong>facility </strong><em>– n.</em> the place where a particular activity happens</p>
<p><strong>emit </strong><em>– v. </em>to send out gas, heat, light etc. into the air</p>
<p><strong>extract </strong><em>– v.</em> to take something out, especially by force</p>
<p><strong>sector </strong><em>– n. </em>one part of a country's economy</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Nuns Trouble Companies with Investment Activism (2024/8/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/us-nuns-trouble-companies-with-investment-activism.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In the American state of Kansas, a group of religious women have been calling on large companies to change the way they do business.</p>
<p>The women are Catholic Benedictine religious workers called nuns. They live together in a <strong>monastery</strong> called Mount Saint Scholastica. The nuns, who call themselves sisters, pray and <strong>chant</strong> three times a day in their small church. Members of the Benedictine Order have followed this way of life for about 1,500 years.</p>
<p>But the sisters also put their money into investments in several companies. This gives them the right to propose changes to company policies at regular shareholder meetings that involve important decisions.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Sister Barbara McCracken looks through prior resolutions filed against various corporations, including Alphabet, Meta, Netflix and Chevron, at the Mount St. Scholastica Benedictine monastery in Atchison, Kan., Tuesday, July 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Jessie Wardarski)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-d02c-08dcc1ea141e_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Sister Barbara McCracken looks through prior resolutions filed against various corporations, including Alphabet, Meta, Netflix and Chevron, at the Mount St. Scholastica Benedictine monastery in Atchison, Kan., Tuesday, July 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Jessie Wardarski)</span></div>
<p>For example, the women asked oil company Chevron to consider more carefully its human rights policies. They asked Amazon to publish how much money the company spends trying to influence government officials. And they proposed that several manufacturers of medical drugs reconsider ownership rights called patents that, they said, increase drug prices. Patents legally protect a company's right to manufacture and sell a product that it developed or owns for a limited time.</p>
<p>“Some of these companies, they just really hate us,” said Sister Barbara McCracken. She leads the nuns' <strong>corporate</strong> responsibility program. She added that, because they are a small group of women, the large companies might consider them like an unwanted insect.</p>
<p>Until the 1990s, the nuns had few investments. That changed as they began to invest money to care for older sisters as the community aged.</p>
<p>They invest what little money they have in corporations that meet their religious <strong>ideals</strong>. But they also invest in some that do not meet their ideal. So, they push those companies to change policies they consider harmful.</p>
<p>Sister Rose Marie Stallbaumer supervised the community's finances for years. She said it was important that the group “invested in a responsible way.” She added that they wanted to make sure their investments did not bring harm to others.</p>
<p>The sisters at St. Scholastica and other Benedictine groups work closely with the Interfaith Center for Corporate Responsibility (ICCR). The ICCR is an organization based in New York City that involves religious groups in organizing to push companies to change their policies.</p>
<p>Tim Smith is a policy advisor for the center. He said the Benedictine nuns have been an important part of ICCR for years. He said that while it can take years to see companies change, the sisters “have the <strong>endurance</strong> of long-distance runners.”</p>
<p>Support for many of the changes the nuns seek has grown over the years. Early on, their resolutions received less than 10 percent support from shareholders. But in some cases, they have received 30 percent or even over 50 percent support.</p>
<p>Pushing companies to change comes naturally to McCracken. She has been a peace activist for many years. “There's not a protest she wouldn't go to,” said Sister Anne Shepard. She said McCracken's past involved anti-war, anti-racism, and <strong>union</strong>-supporting demonstrations.</p>
<p>McCracken entered the Benedictine community in 1961. She calls herself unusual for a person who lives in a monastery because she “hates to miss a party.” She and the other sisters follow the Benedictine rule to “pray and work.”</p>
<p>At the center of much of what they do is the belief that the wealthy have too much, the poor have too little, and more should be shared for the <strong>benefit</strong> of everyone.</p>
<p>“To me, it's a continuation of Catholic social teaching,” McCracken said of their activist investing.</p>
<p>Care for the environment has long been of central importance to Mount St. Scholastica members. Their college's graduates include Wangari Maathai, the Kenyan environmental activist and Nobel Peace Prize winner. Maathai died in 2011.</p>
<p>One of their top concerns is climate change. They use much of their 21 hectares of land for solar panels, community gardens and 18 beehives that produced about 360 kilograms of honey last year.</p>
<p>Their activism has often led to criticisms that they are too politically liberal. They recently received attention after they responded to statements made by Harrison Butker, a professional American football player. Butker had given a speech at nearby Benedictine College—cofounded by the Benedictine nuns. In the speech, he suggested that most of the women there would be more excited to be wives and mothers than anything else.</p>
<p>In a written statement, the sisters expressed concern with the idea “that being a homemaker is the highest calling for a woman.”</p>
<p>The nuns are not married and do not have children. Many of the sisters have <strong>doctoral degrees</strong>. Most have worked in professions. Members of their group include a doctor, a lawyer of Catholic Church law, and a professional violinist.</p>
<p>The sisters received angry phone calls after they released their statement. At the same time, the nuns are strong supporters of the team Butker plays for, the nearby Kansas City Chiefs. They often wear the team's red and gold colors to religious services on days when the team is playing.</p>
<p>Sister Mary Elizabeth Schweiger helped write the nuns' statement. “It came from a very basic understanding of who we are and the values that we hold true,” Schweiger said. “We just thought that voice had to be heard because we believe very much in being inclusive.”</p>
<p>Sister McCracken said that following their religious beliefs brings them into contact with political and economic issues. “It's just the nature of being an active citizen,” she said.</p>
<p>McCracken is nearly 85 years old and cannot be as active as she once was. But pushing companies to change gives her “a sit-down job when you can't go to the streets.”</p>
<p>The members of Mount St. Scholastica do not retire, not really.</p>
<p>“We don't use that word,” McCracken said. She added that if they still have the ability think clearly, “we just keep going, you know?”</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins. And I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Tiffany Stanley reported this story for the Associated Press. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>monastery </strong><em>–n.</em> a place were members of a religious order (usually monks) live</p>
<p><strong>chant </strong><em>–n.</em> words that are repeated, often as part of a religious ritual</p>
<p><strong>corporate </strong><em>–adj.</em> related to a business corporation or to actions taken as a group under organizing rules</p>
<p><strong>ideal </strong><em>–n. </em>an idea that people want to copy or embody</p>
<p><strong>benefit </strong><em>–n.</em> a good result from an action or decision</p>
<p><strong>endurance </strong><em>–n.</em> the ability to continue doing something for a long time</p>
<p><strong>union </strong><em>–n.</em> a labor group that supports workers' causes often in opposition to officials of the companies that employ the workers</p>
<p><strong>doctoral degree </strong><em>–n.</em> the highest degree offered by a university</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Uganda’s Motorcycle Taxis Resist Safety Rules (2024/8/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/uganda-s-motorcycle-taxis-resist-safety-rules.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>For tens of thousands of men in Uganda's capital, driving a motorcycle <strong>taxi</strong> is a way to make a living. For others, the vehicles known as boda-bodas are a necessary but dangerous form of transportation in a disorderly city.</p>
<p>The young men sit on motorcycles in the morning heat. When they see someone who might be a passenger, they start their machines and compete to offer the person a ride.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Drivers of motorcycle taxis, known locally as boda-bodas, ride with passengers on a street in Kampala, Uganda, on July 18, 2024. (AP Photo/Hajarah Nalwadda )" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-d000-08dcc2dce787_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Drivers of motorcycle taxis, known locally as boda-bodas, ride with passengers on a street in Kampala, Uganda, on July 18, 2024. (AP Photo/Hajarah Nalwadda )</span></div>
<p>The motorcycle taxis are everywhere in East African capitals like Nairobi and Kigali. But in Kampala, the numbers are huge. The city of 3 million people has no mass transportation system and a high rate of unemployment. There are around 350,000 boda-bodas. The men driving them come from all parts of Uganda. They say there are no other jobs for them.</p>
<p><strong>Nothing to do</strong></p>
<p>"We just do this one because we have nothing to do," said one driver, Zubairi Idi Nyakuni. "All of us here...they have their degrees, they have their master's (degrees), but they are just here. They have nothing to do."</p>
<p>The city has tried to control them and remove them from the central business area. But it is not easy. The government fears what might happen if they anger a large group of jobless men.</p>
<p>Charles Mpagi is a spokesperson for Tugende, a company based in Kampala that finances boda-boda purchases. He said, "You have quite a large number of people that are young, who can't find jobs...and they do not have <strong>significant</strong> <strong>alternative</strong> income to get into other <strong>enterprises</strong>."</p>
<p>About 76 percent of Uganda's 43 million people are under 35, according to government figures. There are few jobs for them. The central bank reports that just one percent of Ugandan workers make $270 or more in monthly pay.</p>
<p>Uganda's unemployment rate for people between 18 and 30 was 17 percent in 2021 - higher than for other age groups. For young people in urban areas, it was 19 percent.</p>
<p>President Yoweri Museveni has held power since 1986. He has long welcomed the support of boda-boda men, who create a loud presence at his political rallies. Museveni has gifted boda-bodas to supporters and is reducing the three-year licensing fee from nearly $100 to about $35.</p>
<p><strong>'Border, border!'</strong></p>
<p>Motorcycles first appeared on the Uganda-Kenya border during political instability in the 1970s. The term "boda-boda" comes from the way drivers used to shout "border, border" at possible <strong>customers</strong>.</p>
<p>At the time, they were also a way to transport <strong>smugglers</strong> and their <strong>merchandise</strong>. Today, they are everywhere in Uganda, taking children to school, people to offices, the sick to <strong>clinics</strong> and even the dead to their burials.</p>
<p>Each year, police reports say that motorcycle taxis help carry out violent crime. The Ministry of Works and Transport also reports that the number of deadly accidents related to motorcycles across Uganda grew from 621 in 2014 to 1,404 in 2021.</p>
<p>Road safety regulations for motorcycles were first approved in 2004. But traffic police are often unable to make arrests for motorcyclists breaking the law. They fear fights because drivers quickly come to support one another.</p>
<p>Many boda-boda men pay the owner of their vehicle every month. Failure to pay means the boda-boda driver loses his job along with the motorcycle.</p>
<p>Innocent Awita, a boda-boda man who left school in 2008, said there was "too much pressure" to keep his motorcycle. He pays $4 a day and pays for fuel and repairs. Some days are better than others, but Awita said he sometimes goes without enough earnings to make the daily payment.</p>
<p>"I can work for three days without getting anything. But if I get something the next day, that can save my life," he said.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Rodney Muhumuza reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>taxi </strong><em>–n.</em> a vehicle whose driver you pay for transportation service</p>
<p><strong>alternative</strong> – <em>adj</em>. offering or expressing a choice</p>
<p><strong>enterprise</strong> –<em> n. </em>a business organization</p>
<p><strong>customer </strong><em>–n.</em> a person or group who buys goods or services</p>
<p><strong>smuggle</strong> – <em>v</em>. to move (someone or something) from one country into another illegally and secretly</p>
<p><strong>merchandise </strong><em>–n.</em> goods that are for sale to the public</p>
<p><strong>clinic </strong>–n. a small health center that treats minor or simple health problems</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Reaching the 'Tipping Point' (2024/8/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/reaching-the-tipping-point.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">24 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Today we talk about an important time in a movement or experience. It is the moment when something cannot be stopped. There is a <strong>momentum</strong> or force pushing something forward or making it more known or popular.</p>
<p>One term for that kind of moment is <u>tipping point</u>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Some experts say deforestation in the Amazon is reaching a tipping point. This sky view shows deforestation near a forest on the border between Amazonia and Cerrado in Nova Xavantina, Mato Grosso state, Brazil on July 28, 2021. (REUTERS/Amanda Perobelli)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/80650000-c0a8-0242-e8ec-08dabf375251_cx10_cy11_cw89_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Some experts say deforestation in the Amazon is reaching a tipping point. This sky view shows deforestation near a forest on the border between Amazonia and Cerrado in Nova Xavantina, Mato Grosso state, Brazil on July 28, 2021. (REUTERS/Amanda Perobelli)</span></div>
<p>The online dictionary <em>Merriam-Webster</em> defines <u>tipping point</u> as “the critical point in a situation, process, or system beyond which a <strong>significant</strong> and often unstoppable effect or change takes place.”</p>
<p>The<u> tipping point</u> can also be the time at which a change or an effect cannot be stopped.</p>
<p>For example, some scientists believe Earth may have passed the <u>tipping point</u> in global warming. Efforts taken now will not prevent environmental disaster. It is too late to stop the damage. In other words, <u>that ship has sailed</u>. When something reaches a <u>tipping point</u> it is too late to turn back. It is a <u>point of no return</u>.</p>
<p>Here is another definition. The online <em>Cambridge Dictionary</em> defines the <u>tipping point</u> as “a time during an activity or process when an important decision has to be made or when a situation changes completely.”</p>
<p>Used this way, we often say we reach, <strong>approach</strong>, or near a tipping point. Here are some examples:</p>
<p><em>In class, the students' anger toward their teacher reached a <u>tipping point.</u> She had again given them a test on a subject she hadn't taught.</em></p>
<p><em>Prices at the food store are nearing a <u>tipping point</u>. If they go much higher, people will just shop elsewhere. </em></p>
<p>Malcolm Gladwell wrote about the subject in his book <em>Tipping Point</em> published in 2002. He describes <u>tipping point</u> this way: “<u>The tipping point</u> is that magic moment when an idea, <strong>trend</strong>, or social behavior crosses a <strong>threshold</strong>, tips, and spreads like wildfire.”</p>
<p>For example, you could say, “The writer's best-selling second book was the <u>tipping point </u>in her career. Now, everything she publishes is popular!”</p>
<p>And that's the end of this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>.</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>momentum </strong><em>– n.</em><strong> </strong>strength or force gained by motion or by a series of events</p>
<p><strong>significant</strong> <em>– adj. </em>having much importance</p>
<p><strong>approach </strong><em>– v. </em>to draw closer to</p>
<p><strong>trend </strong><em>– n. </em>a current style or preference</p>
<p><strong>threshold </strong><em>– n. </em>the place or point of entering or beginning</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Harlem Celebrates Its Rebirth after 50 Years (2024/8/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/harlem-celebrates-its-rebirth-after-50-years.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">23 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In the 1970s, a lack of community investment resulted in a large number of people leaving Harlem, a well-known New York City neighborhood in northern Manhattan.</p>
<p>Nearly 50,000 people, about a third of the area's population, left to escape violence, crime and poor living conditions. Among those who left was LeeSandra Moore's mother who moved to the state of Virginia. “It was a <strong>scary</strong> time,” said Moore, now 52 and still living in Harlem. “I couldn't blame her for that.”</p>
<p>Those who stayed were mostly poor, Black families. They lived through unrest that followed the 1964 killing of an unarmed Black teenager and the killings of Black leader Malcolm X in 1965 and Rev. Martin Luther King Jr. in 1968.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A man walks past a mural in the Harlem neighborhood of New York, Thursday, Aug. 15, 2024. (AP Photo/Pamela Smith)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-f84f-08dcc20d5b18_cx0_cy7_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A man walks past a mural in the Harlem neighborhood of New York, Thursday, Aug. 15, 2024. (AP Photo/Pamela Smith)</span></div>
<p>News reports described Harlem as a “sinking ship.”</p>
<p>Percy Sutton was president of the local Manhattan government at the time. As the city's highest-<strong>ranking</strong> Black official, he knew Harlem needed a lift and started a <strong>festival</strong> called Harlem Day in 1974.</p>
<p>Sutton called up elected officials. He gathered actors, like Sidney Poitier and Ruby Dee, entertainers, including Tito Puente and Max Roach, and the poet Maya Angelou to celebrate the first Harlem Day. It honored Harlem's history and shows how the neighborhood became known as "Black Mecca” or the center of Black arts, culture and businesses.</p>
<p>“It was such a successful day,” said Lloyd Williams — one of Harlem Day's co-founders and the current president of the Greater Harlem Chamber of Commerce — that it became a week-long yearly event called Harlem Week.</p>
<p><strong>The festival's 50th year</strong></p>
<p>This year, Harlem Week celebrated its 50th anniversary with 18 days filled with free programming.</p>
<p>The celebration included food, Broadway performances, an Apollo Hour, and a tribute to entertainer Harry Belafonte. It offered financial education and career training, and for children, back-to-school backpacks.</p>
<p>One important part of Harlem Week was an effort to deal with Harlem's long-standing health crises. Medical volunteers checked blood pressure and tested for cancer and diabetes. People learned about drug use, HIV/AIDS and healthy aging.</p>
<p>Rev. Al Sharpton leads the National Action Network in Harlem. He said, "Harlem Week has been the <strong>constant</strong> line through the last 50 years of America's most historic Black neighborhood."</p>
<p>Organizers and people say Harlem Week has brought new life to the area. The once-deserted neighborhood is now home to restored buildings, new businesses, and immigrants. The streets are filled with jazz, reggae, R&amp;B, and gospel music traditions.</p>
<p><strong>Big stores vs. small shops</strong></p>
<p>Moore, the Harlem native whose mother moved to Virginia, watched as big national stores moved in. Sometimes they took the place of local shops and made rents go up. "Some of that is okay, but what about the small business where you can get that great sandwich?" she asked. Moore wants people to eat less fast food, so she teaches healthy eating and cooking to young local students.</p>
<p>At Harlem Week, Moore represented GirlTrek, a national movement of Black women supporting health through walking. She said, "I feel like I should have left a long time ago, but something about Harlem draws me back to it."</p>
<p>Moore continued, "Harlem is my beginning. Harlem is my future. Harlem is a huge part of what makes me who I am."</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Ryan Doan-Nguyen reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>scary</strong>- <em>adj</em>. causing fear</p>
<p><strong>rank </strong>– <em>v</em>. to place (someone or something) in a particular position among a group of people or things that are being judged according to quality, ability, size, etc.</p>
<p><strong>festival - </strong><em>n</em>. a special time or event when people gather to celebrate something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Speaking Fluently (2024/8/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/speaking-fluently.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">23 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Aaron Ali in Sudan about how to become a fluent speaker.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-a1c6-08dcc14f4076_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>I have been learning English since 2010, but I can't speak English fluently, even now. Could you tell me how to get my English fluent?</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>Thank you for writing to us, Aaron Ali. I'm happy to answer this question.</p>
<p>To help you reach your goal, consider the following two questions:</p>
<p>1. What is making it difficult for you to become fluent?</p>
<p>2. Are you getting the input and practice with English that you need? Input means the language you listen to and read.</p>
<p>Being fluent does not mean speaking a language without any mistakes. Instead, fluency is the ability to speak without stopping too much. It is also the ability to speak about a large number of issues.</p>
<p>Try to identify what is preventing you from being fluent. Maybe you worry about making grammar mistakes. Maybe pronunciation problems slow you down. Perhaps you simply might not know enough words. Or, you might need more confidence, or belief in yourself. If that is the case, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/how-to-gain-confidence-in-your-english-speaking/5750911.html">our VOA Learning English article linked here</a> gives advice for gaining more confidence in your speaking.</p>
<p><strong>Two things to know</strong></p>
<p>People generally need two things to become fluent. The first thing they need is to know a lot of words and expressions. You should listen to and read English that you can mostly understand but that also helps you learn a few new expressions at a time.</p>
<p>Remember, you can be fluent even if you make many grammar mistakes. But you cannot speak fluently if you do not know enough words and expressions.</p>
<p>The second thing learners need is a lot of practice speaking in different kinds of situations.</p>
<p>Try to find an English-speaking partner and practice often. Online sites can help you find a language partner. You can have a conversation with this person over a mobile phone or computer. And this <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/five-tips-for-great-language-exchanges/5175780.html">VOA Learning English article</a> gives advice for great language exchanges.</p>
<p><strong>Other suggestions</strong></p>
<p>Practice speaking about particular <strong>topics</strong>. For example, if you are interested in health and exercise, learn the words and expressions connected to that topic. Next, try to write about it. Writing can help you organize your ideas and remember vocabulary. Last, practice speaking about the topic, using the special vocabulary you have learned.</p>
<p>Storytelling is another way to practice. It helps you learn expressions and grammatical forms. Tell a story many times. That will help you feel what it is like to speak fluently.</p>
<p>Reading out loud is another way to practice, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/early-literacy-fluency/7155518.html">and the video and article linked here</a> gives advice about doing that.</p>
<p>Finally, our <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/z/6042">How to Pronounce</a> series shows you how to say common phrases quickly and easily.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, do you have a question about American English? Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.<em> </em></p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><em>_______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>topic </strong><em>-n. </em>a subject under consideration or discussion</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Astronomy Group Joins Effort to Establish Time Zone on the Moon (2024/8/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/astronomy-group-joins-effort-to-establish-time-zone-on-the-moon.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>An international group of astronomers has joined efforts seeking to establish a separate time zone for the moon.</p>
<p>The French-based International Astronomical Union (IAU) recently approved a resolution on the matter during the group's General Assembly meeting in Cape Town, South Africa.</p>
<p>The resolution calls on space organizations around the world to cooperate on establishing a <strong>standard </strong>clock for the moon.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="An aircraft passes in front of the moon, with a red glow attributable to smoke particles carried in the upper atmosphere from North American wildfires, a day ahead of the full super moon, as seen from Parliament Hill in London, Britain, August 18, 2024. (REUTERS/Toby Melville)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-2186-08dcc0d71094_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">An aircraft passes in front of the moon, with a red glow attributable to smoke particles carried in the upper atmosphere from North American wildfires, a day ahead of the full super moon, as seen from Parliament Hill in London, Britain, August 18, 2024. (REUTERS/Toby Melville)</span></div>
<p>The moon's orbital movements around Earth make one day on the lunar surface equal to 29.5 Earth days. And because the moon has less gravity compared to Earth, time moves slightly faster there, about 58.7 microseconds quicker each day.</p>
<p>Susan Stewart is an astronomer with the U.S. Naval Observatory. She helped create the resolution at the IAU conference. Stewart told The Associated Press the aim of the measure is quite simple: “To work together to establish (a) standard time.”</p>
<p>Currently, moon operations run on the time of the country that is launching spacecraft. But supporters of creating a separate time zone say this method will have to change; more countries and private space companies are starting to launch their own moon missions.</p>
<p>Last year, the European Space Agency (ESA) pushed for the creation of a lunar clock. And earlier this year, the White House directed the U.S. space agency NASA and other agencies to come up with a timekeeping plan for the moon by the end of 2026.</p>
<p>ESA noted communication and navigation systems built for the moon will perform much better if they use “the same timescale.” In addition, a separate time zone will support “the many other crewed and uncrewed missions” planned for the future, ESA said.</p>
<p>In the past, NASA also considered establishing a separate time zone for the International Space Station (ISS). But the agency decided against it. Instead, the ISS runs on Coordinated Universal Time, or UTC, which is based on time kept by atomic clocks. NASA officials say this system helps ease the time difference between NASA and the Canadian Space Agency, as well as other space partners in Russia, Japan and Europe.</p>
<p>The international team looking at establishing a lunar time zone has said it is still deciding whether a single organization should be chosen to set and keep time on the moon.</p>
<p>Bijunath Patla is a physicist at the U.S. Commerce Department's National Institute of Standards and Technology. He told the AP that astronomers are still deciding on how a lunar clock would work. Patla said, “I think the community has realized that this needs to be done. And this is the beginning.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press and Reuters reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>standard</strong> <em>– n.</em> a particular level of quality that is set for multiple things</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Australia Moves Forward with Major Renewable Energy Project (2024/8/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/australia-moves-forward-with-major-renewable-energy-project.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A plan to build a huge solar farm in Australia is a step closer after the Australian government gave environmental approvals for the $19 billion project recently.</p>
<p>Australian company Sun Cable plans to build a 12,400-hectare solar farm in a remote area of northern Australia. The farm will send electricity to the city of Darwin via an 800-kilometer overhead transmission line. Then the power will be transported to large industrial <strong>customers</strong> in Singapore through a 4,300-kilometer submarine cable.</p>
<p>The Australia-Asia PowerLink project aims to deliver up to 6 gigawatts of green electricity each year. Such a project, Australian Environment Minister Tanya Plibersek suggested, would “help turn Australia into a renewable energy superpower” and<strong> boost</strong> its economy.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - The Williamsdale Solar Farm, shown from the air and located south of Canberra, Australia, on Oct. 15, 2020, has about 30 hectares (74 acres) of solar panels. (Mick Tsikas/AAP Image via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/70d00805-4f3f-4f66-8e55-a2f8a7e34233_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - The Williamsdale Solar Farm, shown from the air and located south of Canberra, Australia, on Oct. 15, 2020, has about 30 hectares (74 acres) of solar panels. (Mick Tsikas/AAP Image via AP)</span></div>
<p>Plibersek said in a written statement, “It will be the largest solar <strong>precinct</strong> in the world...”</p>
<p>The project was first backed by Australian mining businessman Andrew Forrest and Atlassian co-founder Mike Cannon-Brookes. The plans were discussed during a state visit by then-Singapore Prime Minister Lee Hsien Loong and Australian Prime Minister Anthony Albanese as part of a “Green Economy” agreement in 2022.</p>
<p>In January 2023, the project collapsed when Sun Cable was involved in a financing dispute between Forrest and Cannon-Brookes. By May of that year, a group led by Cannon-Brookes' Grok Ventures acquired the company, finalizing the takeover in September 2023.</p>
<p>SunCable Australia's managing director Cameron Garnsworthy said it was pleased to have cleared a major legal issue. He added that the company will now put its efforts into the next stage of planning to work towards "a Final Investment Decision targeted by 2027.”</p>
<p>The company said electricity supply would begin in the early 2030s.</p>
<p>Energy has been a politically charged issue for nearly 20 years in Australia. The country depends on coal and gas as well as money from exporting those fuels to help support its economy.</p>
<p>This dependence on <strong>fossil fuels</strong> has historically made it one of the world's worst <strong>greenhouse gas</strong> emitters on a per capita basis.</p>
<p>Australia's main opposition party in June announced plans to build the country's first nuclear power plants as early as 2035. The announcement ensures the major parties will be divided on how to reduce Australia's greenhouse gas emissions at elections due within a year.</p>
<p>The parties have not gone to an election with the same carbon reduction policies since 2007.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Keiran Smith reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>customer </strong><em>-- n. </em>one that buys a good or service</p>
<p><strong>boost</strong><em> -- v. </em>increase, raise</p>
<p><strong>precinct</strong> <em>-- n.</em> a part of a territory with definite bounds often established for administrative purposes</p>
<p><strong>fossil fuel </strong><em>-- n.</em> a fuel (such as coal, oil, or natural gas) formed in the earth from plant or animal remains</p>
<p><strong>greenhouse gas</strong> <em>-- n.</em> any of various gaseous compounds (such as carbon dioxide or methane) that absorb infrared radiation and trap heat in the atmosphere</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Is It Harris' or Harris's? (2024/8/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/is-it-harris-or-harris-s.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The battle for the White House is set as Vice President Kamala Harris officially accepts the Democratic Party nomination on Thursday to run against former President Donald Trump, the Republican nominee.</p>
<p>However, another fight is just starting among grammar <strong>nerds</strong> over where to put the possessive <strong>apostrophe</strong> after her name. Is it <u>Harris'</u> or <u>Harris's</u>?</p>
<p>Eric Turkewitz, a New York lawyer, called the debate <a class="wsw__a" href="https://x.com/Turkewitz/status/1820814762336227836">“apostrophe hell”</a> on the social media website X. It has since received more than 2 million views.</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-a3ab-08dcc1fcf821_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>The <em>Associated Press Stylebook</em> says, “Use only an apostrophe” for singular proper names ending in the letter “s,” such as Dickens' book, Hercules' labors, or Jesus' life. So, for Harris, it is Harris, followed by an apostrophe, as in “<u>Harris'</u> policy.”</p>
<p>The <em>AP Stylebook</em> is widely used as the <strong>standard</strong> by American news organizations. But not everyone agrees.</p>
<p>Three large U.S. newspapers, <em>The New York Times</em>, <em>The Washington Post,</em> and <em>The Wall Street Journal</em> all use Harris, followed by an apostrophe and the letter “s,” as in “<u>Harris's</u> policy.”</p>
<p>Adding to the <strong>confusion</strong>, they all agree that the singular possessive for Harris' running mate, Minnesota Governor Tim Walz, is <u>Walz's</u>. As for plural possessive, it is <u>Harrises'</u> as in <u>Harrises'</u> family home and <u>Walzes'</u> as in <u>Walzes'</u> cats.</p>
<p>Benjamin Dreyer is a retired <strong>editor</strong> who worked for the publisher Random House. He wrote <em>Dreyer's English: An Utterly Correct Guide to Clarity and Style</em>. He told the AP there is widespread agreement that <u>Walz's</u> is correct. But many flooded him with questions about what to do with the apostrophe after Harris.</p>
<p>Add the apostrophe and the letter “s,” Dryer said. “To set the 's is just simpler, and then you can take your valuable brain cells and apply them to more important things.”</p>
<p><strong>Not so fast!</strong></p>
<p>The American dictionary publisher Merriam-Webster <a class="wsw__a" href="https://x.com/MerriamWebster/status/1820874029202284562">joined the debate</a> with this reminder: “For names that end in an s or z sound, you can either add -'s or just an apostrophe. Going with -'s is the more common choice: the car that belongs to Jones → Jones's car or Jones' car.”</p>
<p>Amanda Barrett is AP's vice president for news standards and inclusion. She said, while the AP style has <strong>evolved</strong> over the years, there are no plans to change the guidance on the possessive apostrophe “s.”</p>
<p>Barrett added, “We do know that the <strong>conversation</strong> is out there and people make different choices when it comes to grammar, and that's all fine. Everyone makes a choice that works best for them.”</p>
<p>Timothy Pulju teaches linguistics at Dartmouth College in New Hampshire. He said that until the 17th or 18th <strong>century</strong>, the possessive of proper names ending in the letter “s” - such as Jesus or Moses - often was simply the name itself with no apostrophe or additional “s.” Eventually, the apostrophe (Jesus' or Moses') was added to mark the possession although the pronunciation remained the same.</p>
<p>“That became kind of the standard that I was taught and <strong>adhere</strong> to, even though <strong>in retrospect</strong>, I don't think it's a great standard,” he said.</p>
<p>Pulju expects most people will use the apostrophe followed by the letter “s” form over time. “As long as people are communicating successfully, we say language is doing what it's supposed to be doing,” he said. “If you can read it whichever way it's written, then it seems like it's working for people...”</p>
<p>Michael Dukakis of Massachusetts was the last U.S. presidential candidate whose name ended with the letter “s.” Dukakis told the AP that he does not remember any similar discussion when he was the Democratic nominee. But he agrees with the AP.</p>
<p>“It sounds to me like it would be s, apostrophe, and that's it,” he said.</p>
<p>If Harris wins in November, she would become the fourth U.S. president with a last name ending in the letter “s” and the first since Rutherford B. Hayes, who was elected in 1876.</p>
<p>The Harris campaign has yet to take a clear position. Press releases issued by the campaign talked about “Harris's positive vision,” and “Harris' seventh trip to Nevada.”</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Holly Ramer reported this story for the Associated Press. Hai Do adapted it for VOA Learning English with additional sources. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>nerd</strong><strong> </strong>–n. people who are very interested in the technical details of a subject that most people cannot relate to</p>
<p><strong>apostrophe</strong> <em>–n. </em>a punctuation mark that has several uses including its use with an “s,” to show the possessive form of a noun</p>
<p><strong>standard</strong> <em>–n.</em> a level of quality or normal practice that is acceptable or desirable</p>
<p><strong>confusion </strong>–n. a state of not understanding or not knowing what to do</p>
<p><strong>editor </strong>–n. a person whose job it is to review written work, make changes and correct mistakes</p>
<p><strong>evolve </strong>–v. to change over time</p>
<p><strong>conversation </strong>–n. a discussion between people that is somewhat informal</p>
<p><strong>century </strong>–n. a period of one hundred years (example: the 1900s are known as the 20<sup>th</sup> century)</p>
<p><strong>adhere </strong>–v. to keep close to</p>
<p><strong>in retrospect </strong>–phrase to look back in time or to think about the past</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Tech Tip: How to Keep Your Chatbot Activity More Private (2024/8/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/tech-tip-how-to-keep-your-chatbot-activity-more-private.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Operators of artificial intelligence (AI) <strong>chatbot</strong> tools have made it clear that users' requests can be saved and used to further develop the AI systems.</p>
<p>But what if a user does not want that? Some tools permit users to request that personal information used in chatbot requests not be saved or used to develop or train AI systems.</p>
<p>Technology experts say it could be too late for users who have already provided information to these tools to have the data removed. But the Associated Press is offering the following advice for users who want to increase their privacy protections.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Barbara Winston uses a computer at her home in Northbrook, Ill., on Sunday, June 30, 2024, several days after taking an introduction to artificial intelligence class at a local senior center. (AP Photo/Teresa Crawford)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-8d2c-08dcc202a29a_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Barbara Winston uses a computer at her home in Northbrook, Ill., on Sunday, June 30, 2024, several days after taking an introduction to artificial intelligence class at a local senior center. (AP Photo/Teresa Crawford)</span></div>
<p><strong>Google Gemini</strong></p>
<p>Google saves chatbot interactions, known as conversations<strong>,</strong> with its Gemini tool. The company says it uses the data to train its machine learning systems. But the company does give users a way to limit the information captured and to remove past conversations.</p>
<p>For users 18 or older, requests are kept for 18 months, although this can be changed in user settings. Human workers are sometimes used by Google to examine some user conversations as part of efforts to improve Gemini's systems. In general, Google warns Gemini users not to enter any sensitive information they do not want human workers to see.</p>
<p>Gemini users can change or “opt-out” of these <strong>default</strong> settings. From the main Gemini website <a class="wsw__a" href="https://gemini.google.com/?hl=en">page</a>, users should find and click on the “Activity” button toward the bottom left of the page. From there, they can click the “Turn off” <strong>button</strong> next to the heading “Gemini Apps Activity.” Users then have the chance to block future conversations from being saved. They can also choose to have all previous conversations removed.</p>
<p>Whether a user chooses to turn their activity off or leave it on, Google notes that all conversations with Gemini are saved for 72 hours to “provide the service and process any <strong>feedback</strong>.”</p>
<p><strong>Meta AI</strong></p>
<p>Meta has an AI chatbot used across its social media services Facebook, WhatsApp and Instagram. The company says its AI models are trained on information shared by users including social media posts and photos. Meta says it does not train its AI systems on private messages sent by users to friends or family.</p>
<p>Not everyone can opt out of this policy. People in the 27-nation European Union and Britain – both of which have strong privacy rules – can. This process can be completed from Meta's main <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.facebook.com/privacy/policy/">Privacy Center</a>. Click “Other Policies and Articles” from the list near the bottom on the left side, then click the part related to AI. Users can then find a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.facebook.com/help/contact/1266025207620918">link</a> to a form to opt out.</p>
<p>People in the United States and other countries without national data privacy laws do not have this ability.</p>
<p>Meta's Privacy Center does link to a form where users can request that their data captured by third parties not be used to "develop and improve AI at Meta.” But the company says these requests are examined before being acted upon and might be rejected based on local laws.</p>
<p><strong>Microsoft Copilot</strong></p>
<p>With Microsoft's Copilot chatbot, personal users cannot opt out of having their data used to develop the company's AI models. The best a user can do is to remove conversations with the chatbot by going to Microsoft account's settings and privacy page. Find the drop-down choice called “Copilot interaction history” or “Copilot activity history” to find the button to remove the history.</p>
<p><strong>OpenAI's ChatGPT</strong></p>
<p>Users of OpenAI's <a class="wsw__a" href="https://chatgpt.com/">ChatGPT</a> service can make privacy changes from the tool's settings page. Find the “data controls” setting and remove the choice called "Improve the model for everyone." If a user does not have an account, they can click on the small question mark at the bottom right of the page. Then click “Settings” to see the same choice to opt out of AI training.</p>
<p>OpenAI explains on its data controls “help page” that when users opt out, their conversations will still appear in the history but will not be used for training. The company says these temporary conversations will be kept for 30 days.</p>
<p><strong>Anthropic's Claude AI</strong></p>
<p>Anthropic is an AI research company based in San Francisco. The company says its <a class="wsw__a" href="https://claude.ai/">Claude AI</a> tool is not trained on personal data. However, users can request permission for specific conversations to be used in training or not. Users can do this by giving the conversation a “thumbs up” or “thumbs down” or by emailing the company.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Google, Meta and other online sources. </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>chatbot </strong>– <em>n.</em> a computer program designed to interact with humans</p>
<p><strong>default</strong> <em>– n. </em>what exists or usually happens if no changes are made</p>
<p><strong>button </strong>– n. an image, or icon, that appears on a computer screen which the user can click to cause software to perform some kind of action</p>
<p><strong>feedback </strong><em>– n. </em>information or statements of opinion about something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What Is Ketamine? (2024/8/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/what-is-ketamine.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>An investigation into the death of American actor Matthew Perry has led to criminal charges against five people. Perry, a star of the popular television series <em>Friends</em>, died suddenly in October. He was 54. Doctors who examined his body after death said Perry died from an <strong>overdose</strong> of the powerful drug ketamine.</p>
<p><strong>So what is ketamine?</strong></p>
<p>Ketamine is a powerful anesthetic. The drug is often used to put people into a deep sleep for medical operations, also called surgery. The treatment is called general anesthesia. A doctor can inject the drug into a muscle or through a liquid flow directly into a patient's veins.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Matthew Perry poses for a portrait on Feb. 17, 2015, in New York. A ketamine overdose killed the American actor on October 28, 2023. He was 54 years old. (Photo by Brian Ach/Invision/AP, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/c5bab48c-c720-4b25-96f8-8f634bd6c285_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Matthew Perry poses for a portrait on Feb. 17, 2015, in New York. A ketamine overdose killed the American actor on October 28, 2023. He was 54 years old. (Photo by Brian Ach/Invision/AP, File)</span></div>
<p>The drug's chemistry is similar to the recreational drug called PCP. Some people use ketamine recreationally for its <strong>euphoric</strong> effects. It can cause <strong>hallucinations</strong> and can affect breathing and the heart.</p>
<p><strong>Ketamine becomes popular</strong></p>
<p>The United States Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approved ketamine for use only for general anesthesia. However, American doctors are free to <strong>prescribe</strong> drugs for treatments other than those approved by the FDA. This is known as off-label use.</p>
<p>Ketamine use has seen a huge, fast rise in recent years as a treatment for pain and mental health disorders, including depression and anxiety.</p>
<p>Perry was using it to treat depression. His usual doctors were treating him with what is called ketamine infusion therapy. However, investigators say the actor turned to other sources when his doctors refused to give him as much as he wanted.</p>
<p>Last week, government lawyers said Perry got ketamine illegally through a group that included two doctors, Perry's assistant and a woman they identified as the “Ketamine Queen.” Perry's assistant injected the actor with ketamine — including several times on the day Perry died.</p>
<p><strong>How else is ketamine being used?</strong></p>
<p>Emergency medical workers also sometimes use ketamine to <strong>sedate</strong> people who appear to be out of control, aggressive or a threat to themselves or others. Some states and agencies around the country have begun to reconsider this use of ketamine because of the drug's health risks.</p>
<p>In 2019, an American court found two emergency medical workers guilty in the overdose killing of a teenager in Colorado. The medical team injected the man with a deadly amount of ketamine during a police operation.</p>
<p>An Associated Press investigation found that, generally, use of ketamine and similar drugs as a policing or security tool has spread quietly across the nation over the last 15 years.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>overdose </strong><em>–n. </em>a lethal or toxic amount (as of a drug)</p>
<p><strong>euphoric </strong><em>–adj.</em> marked by a feeling of great happiness and excitement: characterized by, based on, or producing euphoria</p>
<p><strong>hallucination </strong><em>–n.</em> the awareness of something (as a visual image, a sound, or a smell) that seems to be experienced through one of the senses but is not real, cannot be sensed by someone else, and is usually the result of mental illness or the effect of a drug</p>
<p><strong>prescribe </strong><em>–v.</em> to write or give medical orders, such as for drugs or other treatments</p>
<p><strong>sedate </strong><em>–v </em><strong> </strong>to dose with sedatives, drugs that can make people sleep</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Mongolia Aims to Gain More Foreign Visitors (2024/8/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/mongolia-aims-to-gain-more-foreign-visitors.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Mongolia, with its beautiful land and open spaces, is hoping to get more foreign visitors.</p>
<p>Like most countries, Mongolia's <strong>tourism</strong> industry was hurt by the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
<p>It has launched a “Welcome to MonGOlia” campaign to gain more visitors. The government has added flights and simplified the visa process, offering visa-free visits for many countries.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Tourists take photos near the 40-meter-tall stainless steel statue of Genghis Khan, a national hero who amassed power to become the leader of the Mongols in the early 13th century on the outskirts of Ulaanbaatar, Mongolia on July 1, 2024. (AP Photo/Ng Han Guan)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/da66ae98-df97-420e-ac26-01cbf21a5f4e_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Tourists take photos near the 40-meter-tall stainless steel statue of Genghis Khan, a national hero who amassed power to become the leader of the Mongols in the early 13th century on the outskirts of Ulaanbaatar, Mongolia on July 1, 2024. (AP Photo/Ng Han Guan)</span></div>
<p>At least 437,000 foreign visitors came in the first seven months of this year, up 25 percent over the same period last year.</p>
<p>That total includes increasing numbers from Europe, the United States and Japan. Visitors from South Korea nearly doubled, thanks in part to the fact that the flight between the countries is under four hours.</p>
<p>However, Mongolia's government is still short of its goal of 1 million visitors per year from 2023-2025.</p>
<p>The country has a population of 3.3 million people. About half of them live in the capital, Ulaanbaatar. As a result, there is plenty of open space for <strong>adventure</strong> <strong>tourists</strong> to explore, said Egjimaa Battsooj, who works for a tour company.</p>
<p>The company offers adventures including <strong>horseback</strong> trips and camping trips with the possibility of staying in gers, the traditional homes still used by Mongolia's herders.</p>
<p>There is little chance of running across private property, so few places are off-limits, she said.</p>
<p>“You don't need to open a gate, you don't need to have permission from anyone,” Battsooj said, sitting in front of a map of Mongolia.</p>
<p>“We are kind of like the last truly <strong>nomad </strong>culture on the whole planet,” she added.</p>
<p>Lonely Planet, a travel guide publisher, named Mongolia its top destination in its Best in Travel 2024 report. The pope's visit to Mongolia last year also helped bring attention to the country.</p>
<p>Its <strong>breakdancers </strong>became stars at last year's Asian Games. And some local bands have developed a global following, like The Hu, a band that mixes traditional Mongolian instruments and throat singing with modern rock.</p>
<p>Most people know little about Mongolia. American tourist Michael John said he knew some of the history about Genghis Khan. He had also seen a documentary on eagles used by hunters before deciding to stop in Ulaanbaatar as part of a longer vacation.</p>
<p>“It was a great opportunity to learn more,” the 40-year-old said.</p>
<p>Tourism represented 7.2 percent of Mongolia's <strong>gross domestic product</strong> and 7.6 percent of its employment in 2019 before the industry collapsed because of the COVID-19 pandemic, the World Bank says. But the organization noted chances for “<strong>substantial </strong>growth” for Mongolia, with “diverse nature and <strong>stunning sceneries</strong>” and sports and adventure tourism possibilities.</p>
<p>Mongolia tourism advertisements bring attention to all of those interests. The ads show beautiful frozen lakes in winter, the Northern Lights and events like reindeer sledding and riding, camel racing, and hiking.</p>
<p>Munkhjargal Dayan offers rides on camels, traditional archery and the opportunity to have eagles trained for hunting stand on a visitor's arm.</p>
<p>“We want to show tourists coming from other countries that we have such a way of life in Mongolia,” he said, waiting for tourists by a big statue of Genghis Kahn on the outskirts of Ulaanbaatar.</p>
<p>Outside the lively capital, getting around can be difficult in summer as the land becomes wet. There are limited roads and buildings, a shortage of places to stay, and a lack of skilled labor in some areas.</p>
<p>It is also easy for foreigners to get lost, with few signs in English, said Dutch tourist Jasper Koning. Nevertheless, he said he was thoroughly enjoying his trip.</p>
<p>“The weather is super, the scenery is more than super, it's clean, the people are friendly,” he said.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Olivia Zhang and David Rising reported this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>tourism</strong><em> – n.</em> the practice of traveling for fun</p>
<p><strong>adventure</strong><em> –n.</em> an experience that is exciting</p>
<p><strong>tourist</strong> <em>– n.</em> a person who travels for fun</p>
<p><strong>horseback</strong><em> – adj.</em> on the back of a horse</p>
<p><strong>nomad</strong> <em>– n.</em> a member of a people who move from place to place usually seasonally</p>
<p><strong>breakdancer</strong> <em>– n.</em> a person who breakdances (performs a kind of hip-hop dance)</p>
<p><strong>gross domestic product (GDP)</strong><em> –n. </em>a measure of the size of a country's economy equal to the value of all the goods and services produced in one year</p>
<p><strong>substantial</strong> <em>– adj.</em> considerable in quantity, important</p>
<p><strong>stunning</strong> <em>– adj.</em> impressive especially in beauty or excellence</p>
<p><strong>scenery</strong> <em>– n.</em> a beautiful view or landscape</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>UN: Violence Is Harming Haiti’s Schools (2024/8/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/un-violence-is-harming-haiti-s-schools.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">20 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Schools in Haiti are operating without enough chairs, blackboards, and even <strong>bathrooms</strong>.</p>
<p>Violent criminal groups limit basic government services and deepen poverty while the state education system faces a $23 million deficit.</p>
<p>Yasmine Sherif is the executive director of the U.N. organization Education Cannot Wait. “The country needs help,” Sherif said during her three-day visit to the Caribbean country in July.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Students attend a math class at the Jean Marie Vincent High School in Port-au-Prince, Haiti, on Thursday, July 25, 2024. (AP Photo/Odelyn Joseph)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-e7e8-08dcb8a3d59d_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Students attend a math class at the Jean Marie Vincent High School in Port-au-Prince, Haiti, on Thursday, July 25, 2024. (AP Photo/Odelyn Joseph)</span></div>
<p>Sherif said the organization provided $2.5 million to help nearly 75,000 children in Haiti with money, food and other programs. And she asked the European Union and other countries, including France and the U.S., to help close the educational deficit.</p>
<p>"My main concern is security," she said, noting the effect that violence has had on education.</p>
<p>Criminal groups, called <strong>gangs</strong>, killed or injured more than 2,500 people in the first three months of the year. Violence has seriously affected life in the capital, Port-au-Prince, and elsewhere.</p>
<p>At least 919 schools remain closed in Port-au-Prince and in the central area of Artibonite because of gang violence. The U.N. says that school closures have affected more than 150,000 students.</p>
<p>"Education is part of the solution," Sherif said. "That would end extreme poverty, extreme violence and create political stability and create a reliable workforce."</p>
<p><strong>Gang violence impacts</strong></p>
<p>Gang violence also has left some 580,000 people homeless across Haiti, with many crowding into temporary shelters or taking over schools, causing them to close. Schools that remain open are increasingly forced to take students from others that have closed.</p>
<p>The Jean Marie Vincent School in central Port-au-Prince, for example, has accepted students from 12 other schools.</p>
<p>Charles Luckerno is the head of the Vincent School. He said, "We're not the only ones" facing such serious problems. Luckerno said that when classes end for the day, people left homeless by gang violence enter the school and sleep on its ground.</p>
<p>Although that creates health problems, Luckerno still lets them stay. He said, "We are human. We cannot throw them out."</p>
<p><strong>Not enough chairs</strong></p>
<p>Williamson Bissainthe is a 22-year-old high school student who is preparing to take his final exam to <strong>graduate</strong>. He described the sad state of some schools.</p>
<p>"A lot of schools are missing benches or chairs. Teachers do not show up on time. The hardest part of this is that there are no bathrooms," he said.</p>
<p>Bissainthe added, "I hope that the generation that comes after me doesn't have to go through the same suffering.”</p>
<p>Private schools are out of reach for many in Haiti, a country of more than 11 million people. More than 60 percent of the population earns less than $2 a day.</p>
<p><strong>Homeless students</strong></p>
<p>Among those who have been forced to flee their homes is 20-year-old Megane Dumorcy. She would like to study agriculture, but completing her education has been difficult.</p>
<p>"The insecurity has had a huge <strong>impact</strong> on my life," she said, noting that some students have been forced to leave their backpacks behind as they flee gangs. "The state should find a solution for that. We shouldn't be living in a country where our movement is limited."</p>
<p>She said her school is only half-built and lacks a library, a computer room, a blackboard and chairs. She does research on her phone when needed.</p>
<p>Another blow to Haitian schools came in late 2022. That was the time the U.S. started a program permitting Haitians and people from other countries to enter the country on humanitarian grounds.</p>
<p>"A lot of teachers left," said Frantz Erine, an official at the Jean Marie Vincent School.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Evens Sanon reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>bathroom</strong> – <em>n. </em>a room with a sink and toilet and sometimes a bathtub or shower</p>
<p><strong>gang</strong> – <em>n</em>. a group of criminals</p>
<p><strong>graduate</strong> – <em>v</em>. to earn a degree or diploma from a school, college, or university</p>
<p><strong>impact</strong> – <em>n</em>. a powerful or major influence or effect</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Zimbabwean Officials Train Children to Coexist with Dangerous Wildlife (2024/8/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/zimbabwean-officials-train-children-to-coexist-with-dangerous-wildlife.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">20 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In Zimbabwe, increased wildlife activity near people has put children in rural areas at greater risk of animal attacks while walking to school.</p>
<p>Officials and some parents hope a campaign to teach children how to identify danger could reduce risks.</p>
<p>No deaths have been reported, but student Esther Bote and her friends remain careful.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Esther Bote, 14, walks to school with her friends in a bushy area on the periphery of the Save Valley Conservancy in Zimbabwe, Tuesday, July 9, 2024. " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-9fc7-08dcc06be248_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Esther Bote, 14, walks to school with her friends in a bushy area on the periphery of the Save Valley Conservancy in Zimbabwe, Tuesday, July 9, 2024. </span></div>
<p>“We usually walk in groups to feel safer,” said the fourteen-year-old. The five-kilometer walk to school includes travel through thick forest.</p>
<p>Savé Valley Conservancy, a private group, and Zimbabwe's parks agency run the program for school-age children. It teaches them how to recognize danger signs and how to coexist with wildlife.</p>
<p>Many students, like Esther, are now able to identify the footprints of animals and the sounds they make. They also know how to read the direction of the wind and when and where to seek shelter.</p>
<p>Dingani Masuku of Savé Valley Conservancy said wildlife affects children more than other people. He said children walk to school and often do household jobs like getting water and firewood. Such activity means they are outside often.</p>
<p>Masaku said, “That's why we are targeting schools so that they can know how animals behave, what to do with the animals.”</p>
<p>He added that the campaign is trying to teach children “a sense of ownership,” so they “don't see the animal as an <strong>adversary</strong>, but they see it as something <strong>beneficial</strong> to the community, something which should be respected.”</p>
<p><strong>Education efforts </strong></p>
<p>Recently at Chiyambiro Secondary School, a young woman was teaching children about the dangers of wild animals. The 18-year-old recently left school to become part of a group of young woman <strong>rangers</strong>.</p>
<p>“Don't <strong>approach</strong> an animal. If it's a lion, it's looking for food. That's why it's in the community. It is looking for <strong>cheap</strong>, easy <strong>prey</strong>, and you could be the easy prey.”</p>
<p>Some of the children said they travel up to 15 kilometers to get to school. They said they have to start walking to school before the sun rises when animals such as hyenas are still awake and active.</p>
<p>An official from the national parks agency spoke to the children about why wildlife is important to the community. He said wildlife supports the country's <strong>tourism</strong> industry and leads to job creation, such as the new ranger positions.</p>
<p>Alphonce Chimangaisu is the chair of the school development committee at the Chiyambiro Secondary School. He said parents hope the information campaign will make children safer.</p>
<p>“Some parents have stopped their children from going to school because they don't know what might happen,” he said.</p>
<p>School officials in affected rural areas often must delay the start of the day's classes and end them early. The president of the Amalgamated Rural Teachers Union of Zimbabwe, Obert Masaraure, said school officials are trying to let children walk to and from school during daylight hours. That is when wild animals are less likely to be around.</p>
<p>“We have reports of learners who have completely withdrawn from school fearing for their lives,” Masaraure said. He also noted that teachers who live far from schools are increasingly missing work. He said all these problems are making it more difficult for rural learners to get a “quality education.”</p>
<p>Tinashe Farawo is a Zimbabwe National Parks and Wildlife Management Authority official. He said wild animals are going into communities for food and water because of dry weather conditions, also called drought. The official said the parks agency is pushing for animal behavior and conservation training at schools around the country.</p>
<p>Farawo also said children teach their parents what they have learned. He said the agency has established environmental clubs at many schools to bring attention to the issue.</p>
<p>The official noted that conflicts had gotten worse because of<strong> </strong>drought. He said the parks agency had received between 3,000 and 4,000 emergency calls from communities battling wildlife in three years. In 2018, there were only 900 calls.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver. And I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Farai Mutsaka </em><em>reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>adversary </strong><em>–n.</em> an enemy</p>
<p><strong>beneficial </strong><em>–adj.</em> something that has a good effect or that provides something useful</p>
<p><strong>ranger</strong><em> –n. </em>a person who helps to supervise a forest area</p>
<p><strong>approach </strong><em>–n.</em> to move closer to something; to near<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>cheap</strong> <em>–adj.</em> at a low cost; easy to get</p>
<p><strong>prey </strong><em>–n.</em> an animal that is the object of a hunt</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Reporter Used AI to Create False Quotes for Stories (2024/8/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/us-reporter-used-ai-to-create-false-quotes-for-stories.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>An American newspaper reporter has resigned from his job after it was discovered that he used an artificial intelligence (AI) tool to create false <strong>quotes</strong> for stories.</p>
<p>Aaron Pelczar worked for the <em>Cody Enterprise</em>, a newspaper based in the town of Cody, Wyoming. A reporter from a competing newspaper became suspicious about Pelczar's stories and asked to meet with him. Pelczar admitted to using AI to create parts of stories. He later quit his position with the <em>Enterprise</em>.</p>
<p>The reporter who discovered the AI-assisted stories was CJ Baker. He works for the <em>Powell Tribune</em>, a newspaper in the neighboring town of Powell.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A recent issue of the Cody Enterprise, the Wyoming newspaper where a reporter used artificial intelligence to help write his stories, is seen Tuesday, Aug. 13, 2024, at the Wyoming State Library in Cheyenne. (AP Photo/Mead Gruver)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-5264-08dcbe373062_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A recent issue of the Cody Enterprise, the Wyoming newspaper where a reporter used artificial intelligence to help write his stories, is seen Tuesday, Aug. 13, 2024, at the Wyoming State Library in Cheyenne. (AP Photo/Mead Gruver)</span></div>
<p>Baker told The Associated Press he discovered several writing examples that made him suspicious about Pelczar's work. He said some of the writing sounded unnatural or robotic. But one part of a story stood out as possibly being false. It was contained in a June 26 <strong>article</strong> about comedian Larry the Cable Guy being chosen to lead a local parade.</p>
<p>The story ended with a very unusual line that had nothing to do with the story's subject. Rather, it seemed to provide an explanation of the method it used to build the story. The line read, “This structure ensures that the most critical information is presented first, making it easier for readers to <strong>grasp</strong> the main points quickly.”</p>
<p>Baker, who has been a reporter for more than 15 years, said after reading the story he decided to do additional research on other pieces written by Pelczar. He later decided to set up a meeting with Pelczar to discuss his concerns. He was able to meet with Pelczar and the <strong>editor</strong> of the <em>Enterprise</em>, Chris Bacon.</p>
<p>Baker wrote an article in his own newspaper about his findings. He <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.powelltribune.com/stories/after-getting-caught-fabricating-quotes-cody-reporter-resigns,135514">described</a> his meeting with Pelczar and Bacon as uncomfortable, but friendly. Baker wrote that when asked about suspicions surrounding his work, Pelczar answered, “<strong>Obviously</strong> I've never <strong>intentionally</strong> tried to misquote anybody.”</p>
<p>When asked whether any of the disputed statements in his writings had been by created by an AI tool, Pelczar said, “That could be the case.” Baker said Pelczar then added, “But again, if there are issues I will correct them and issue apologies and say they are misstatements.”</p>
<p>After closely examining Pelczar's articles, Bacon and the publisher of the <em>Enterprise</em> discovered the use of AI and apologized for his actions. <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.codyenterprise.com/news/opinion/article_be57a9e0-58de-11ef-96eb-abf87276a1da.html">In an <strong>editorial</strong></a> published recently, <em>Enterprise</em> Editor Chris Bacon admitted he had “failed to catch” the AI-written copy and false quotes. He added that the mistake had permitted AI “to put words that were never spoken into stories.”</p>
<p>Bacon said the <em>Enterprise</em> discovered at least seven stories that included AI-created quotes. Two of the questioned stories included false quotes from Wyoming <strong>Governor</strong> Mark Gordon.</p>
<p>Bacon said some of the quotes appeared “very believable.” He noted that the people he spoke with during his investigation said the quotes sounded like something they might have said. But they never personally spoke to Pelczar.</p>
<p>Other reporters have had their careers hurt or ended for making up facts or quotes in articles. There are also others who have been accused of <strong>plagiarism</strong>, which involves a reporter publishing the writings of others without giving those reporters credit for the material.</p>
<p>But media experts say the recent incident involving Pelczar demonstrates the possible dangers that exist when reporters and editors depend on AI tools in the news production process.</p>
<p>Megan Barton is publisher of the <em>Cody Enterprise. </em>She wrote an editorial that described AI as “the new, <strong>advanced</strong> form of plagiarism and in the field of media and writing.”</p>
<p>Barton<strong> </strong>noted the newspaper now has a system in place to recognize AI-generated stories and will “have longer <strong>conversations</strong> about how AI-generated stories are not acceptable.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>quote</strong> <em>– n.</em> a written statement of what someone has said</p>
<p><strong>article </strong><em>– n. </em>a piece of writing other than fiction or poetry that forms an independent part of a publication (as a magazine)</p>
<p><strong>grasp </strong><em>– v.</em> to understand something</p>
<p><strong>editor </strong><em>– n. </em>someone who revises and prepares stories or the person who is in charge of a newspaper or other news operation</p>
<p><strong>obvious </strong><em>– adj. </em>easy to see or understand</p>
<p><strong>intentional </strong><em>– adj. </em>something<em> </em>done on purpose</p>
<p><strong>editorial </strong><em>– n.</em> a piece of writing that expresses opinions</p>
<p><strong>plagiarism </strong><em>– n. </em>copying someone else's work or ideas</p>
<p><strong>advanced </strong><em>– adj. </em>having developed or progressed to a late stage</p>
<p><strong>conversation </strong><em>– n. </em>a discussion between two or more people</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>WHO Calls for Donations after Declaring Mpox a 'Health Emergency’ (2024/8/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/who-calls-for-donations-after-declaring-mpox-a-health-emergency.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">19 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The World Health Organization is calling for donations to fight the latest outbreak of the viral disease mpox in Africa.</p>
<p>The U.N. health agency declared mpox in Africa a "public health emergency of international concern" last week.</p>
<p>The director-general of the WHO, Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus, made the announcement after a meeting of the WHO's emergency committee. The move follows a declaration by the Africa Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (Africa CDC). That organization declared mpox a public health emergency in Africa one day earlier.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Christian Musema, a laboratory nurse, takes a sample from a child declared a suspected case of Mpox at the treatment center in Munigi, Democratic Republic of Congo on July 19, 2024. (REUTERS/Arlette Bashizi/File Photo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-56e0-08dcbd1e28bc_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Christian Musema, a laboratory nurse, takes a sample from a child declared a suspected case of Mpox at the treatment center in Munigi, Democratic Republic of Congo on July 19, 2024. (REUTERS/Arlette Bashizi/File Photo)</span></div>
<p>The WHO said there have been more than 14,000 cases and more than 524 deaths in Africa this year. So far, about 96 percent of all cases and deaths have taken place in one country: the Democratic Republic of the Congo. But the WHO and others are concerned that a new version of the viral disease could spread more easily among people.</p>
<p>The Associated Press recently reported some of the information known about the current mpox outbreak.</p>
<p><strong>What is mpox?</strong></p>
<p>Mpox is also known as m<i><i>onkey</i></i>pox. The United States Centers for Disease Control and Prevention <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cdc.gov/poxvirus/mpox/index.html">says</a> the viral disease was first identified by scientists in 1958 when outbreaks of a “pox-like” disease appeared in m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s. Until recently, most human cases involved people in central and West Africa who had contact with infected animals.</p>
<p>In 2022, experts confirmed that the virus could be spread through sex. Outbreaks were reported in more than 70 countries that had not reported the disease before.</p>
<p>Mpox belongs to the same virus family as smallpox. It causes symptoms like high body temperature, <strong>chills</strong> and body pain. People with serious cases can develop <strong>lesions</strong> on the face, hands, chest and sex organs.</p>
<p><strong>What is happening in Africa?</strong></p>
<p>The number of cases has increased sharply in the last few weeks. The Africa CDC said the disease has been identified in at least 13 African countries. Compared to the same period last year, the agency said cases have increased by 160 percent and deaths by 19 percent.</p>
<p>The version of mpox seen in the Democratic Republic of the Congo could kill up to 10 percent of people infected. Unlike earlier mpox outbreaks, where lesions were mostly seen on the chest, hands and feet, the new form of mpox causes less severe <strong>symptoms</strong>. This could make the disease harder to identify.</p>
<p>The WHO said mpox was recently reported for the first time in four East African countries: Burundi, Kenya, Rwanda and Uganda. All of those cases were linked to the Democratic Republic of the Congo. In the Ivory Coast and South Africa, health officials have reported a less dangerous version of mpox than the one that spread in 2022.</p>
<p><strong>The WHO's declaration</strong></p>
<p>The WHO's emergency declaration is meant to get donors to provide money for a campaign against the disease.</p>
<p>African CDC Director General Dr. Jean Kaseya said the agency's declaration of a public emergency was meant “to <strong>mobilize</strong> our <strong>institutions</strong>, our collective will and our resources.”</p>
<p>Michael Marks teaches medicine at the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine. He said, “It is clear that current control <strong>strategies</strong> aren't working and there is a clear need for more resources.”</p>
<p><strong>What is different from 2022?</strong></p>
<p>Most of the cases during the 2022 outbreak of the viral disease were gay and bisexual men. The virus was spread through close contact and sex.</p>
<p>Although similar things are happening in Africa, children under the age of 15 now make up more than 70 percent of mpox cases and 85 percent of deaths in the Democratic Republic of the Congo.</p>
<p>WHO chief Tedros said officials are dealing with several outbreaks and, what he called, “different <strong>modes</strong> of <strong>transmission</strong> and different levels of risk.”</p>
<p>Greg Ramm is with the aid group Save the Children. He said his organization is worried about mpox spreading in crowded refugee camps. He said there were 345,000 children living in unhealthy conditions in the eastern Democratic Republic of the Congo. Ramm added that the country's health system is already “collapsing” because of malnutrition, measles and cholera.</p>
<p>Dr. Boghuma Titanji is an infectious disease expert at Emory University in the American state of Georgia. She said it is unclear why the disease is mostly affecting children in the Democratic Republic of the Congo. She said children might become infected more easily or social conditions like overcrowding or infected parents might explain the problem.</p>
<p><strong>How might mpox be stopped</strong></p>
<p>The AP says in 2022, developed countries stopped the outbreak of mpox with treatments and vaccines. But few vaccines are available in Africa.</p>
<p>Marks said the immunization would likely help — including vaccination against the similar smallpox virus. He said, “We need a large supply of vaccine so that we can vaccinate populations most at risk.” He said that would mean vaccinating children, sex workers and adults in affected areas.</p>
<p>The WHO has already released $1.45 million of emergency money for mpox. But the U.N. agency says $15 million is needed to start efforts to combat the disease.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Maria Cheng and Christina Malkia reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>mode </strong><em>–n.</em> a way that something happens</p>
<p><strong>transmission </strong><em>–n. (medical)</em> the process of spreading or infecting</p>
<p><strong>mobilize</strong> <em>–v. </em>to cause people to take part in an effort or campaign</p>
<p><strong>lesions </strong><em>–n. (medical)</em> an area of infected skin that is usually swollen, red, bleeding or releasing fluid</p>
<p><strong>symptoms </strong><em>–n.</em> signs that an infection is present</p>
<p><strong>institutions</strong> –n. a large organization that has been established for a long time</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Plans to Limit Water Usage from Colorado River (2024/8/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/us-plans-to-limit-water-usage-from-colorado-river.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The U.S. government plans to reduce the amount of Colorado River water several states are permitted to use next year.</p>
<p>The river supplies water to seven Western states, more than 20 Native American tribes, and two states in Mexico.</p>
<p>Those states and the country of Mexico are also considering plans for how to share the water after 2026. That is when many current rules and agreements about the use of Colorado River water will come to an end.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - The Colorado River flows at Horseshoe Bend in the Glen Canyon National Recreation Area, in Page, Arizona, June 8, 2022. (AP Photo/Brittany Peterson, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/019e0000-0aff-0242-027e-08da7f0b429e_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - The Colorado River flows at Horseshoe Bend in the Glen Canyon National Recreation Area, in Page, Arizona, June 8, 2022. (AP Photo/Brittany Peterson, File)</span></div>
<p>The river brings water to millions of hectares of farmland in the American West. Hydroelectric dams on the river produce power. Experts say increased water use, combined with rising temperatures and dry weather, are the reasons for the need to make cuts.</p>
<p>In 2007, following years of dry weather, the U.S. states in the river's <strong>basin </strong>and the federal government agreed to rules to help deal with lower water levels. The states involved were Arizona, Nevada, California, Colorado, New Mexico, Utah and Wyoming.</p>
<p>Those rules <strong>determine</strong> when some of the states must cut their water usage based on levels at Lake Mead. The lake is on the border of Nevada and Arizona. It provides water for hydropower, farming, and other needs.</p>
<p>Because of the need for new rules, states, Native American tribes, and others are forming new plans to deal with even deeper water cuts that might happen in 2026.</p>
<p>The federal government will announce water cuts for 2025 based on levels at Lake Mead. If Lake Mead drops below a level that has been agreed to, Arizona, California, Nevada and Mexico will face cuts. However, California might not face cuts because the current rules give that state special water rights.</p>
<p>Last year, Arizona, California and Nevada agreed to save an extra 3 million <strong>acre-feet</strong> of water in addition to the cuts the federal government had already required. An “acre-foot” is equal to about 1.2 million liters. In return, the U.S. government agreed to pay water <strong>districts</strong> and other users for much of that reduction in water use.</p>
<p>Colorado, New Mexico, Utah and Wyoming are in the river's Upper Basin. Those states have not used all of the water the rules permit them to use. For this reason, they have not yet had to reduce the amount of water they take from the river.</p>
<p>Wet weather in 2023 and efforts to save water by Lower Basin states have increased the level of Lake Mead and Lake Powell. Lake Powell in Utah is another body of water that holds and releases water from the river.</p>
<p>However, experts say higher temperatures will continue to reduce water in the Colorado River in the coming years.</p>
<p>In March, Upper and Lower Basin states, tribes and environmental groups proposed plans to deal with likely water reductions in the future.</p>
<p>Arizona, California and Nevada asked the federal government to include water levels at other <strong>reservoirs</strong> besides Lake Mead and Lake Powell. Their plan says that if the whole system drops below 38 percent of the maximum amount of water it can hold, the Upper Basin and Mexico should share deeper cuts equally with the Lower Basin.</p>
<p>Colorado, New Mexico, Utah and Wyoming want larger and sooner cuts when water is low at Lake Mead and Lake Powell. The cuts would affect California, Arizona and Nevada. Their plan does not call for reductions in how much water Upper Basin states use.</p>
<p>The federal government is expected to propose new rules by December. The rules would consider the different plans and possible steps for the future. Until then, states, tribes and other groups will continue negotiations on water.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith. And I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Suman Naishadham wrote this story for The Associated Press. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>basin </strong>–n. the area drained by a river</p>
<p><strong>determine </strong>–v. to officially decide</p>
<p><strong>acre-feet</strong> –n. a measure of volume used specifically in the United States for large-scale water use which is equal to about 1.2 million liters</p>
<p><strong>district </strong>–n. a special area created by a government for a special purpose</p>
<p><strong>reservoir </strong>–n. a body of water usually formed by a dam that is meant to be used as a water supply</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>New Study Suggests Mars Has Large Underground Ocean (2024/8/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/new-study-suggests-mars-has-large-underground-ocean.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A new study provides evidence that Mars contains a large ocean deep beneath its surface.</p>
<p>The finding is based on data collected by the InSight Lander, a robotic explorer operated by the American space agency NASA. <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/insight/">InSight</a>, which landed in 2018, was designed to capture data from within the planet's <strong>interior</strong>. The lander ended its operations on Mars in late 2022.</p>
<p>For the current study, researchers used <strong>seismic</strong> data collected by InSight. The team examined the data to study Martian quake activity. Seismic activity on Mars happens in the form of “<a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/study-suggests-new-cause-for-strongest-marsquake-ever/7328807.html">marsquakes</a>.” NASA says InSight had recorded more than 1,300 marsquakes.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This file image provided by NASA shows the InSight Mars lander in a selfie photo composite on April 24, 2022, the 1,211th Martian day, or sol, of the mission. (NASA/JPL-Caltech via AP, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-2db0-08dcbd7d6964_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This file image provided by NASA shows the InSight Mars lander in a selfie photo composite on April 24, 2022, the 1,211th Martian day, or sol, of the mission. (NASA/JPL-Caltech via AP, File)</span></div>
<p>The device InSight uses to measure ground movements is called a seismometer. NASA specially designed the lander and its instruments to be extremely sensitive for the Martian environment. The seismic data suggests liquid water exists deep beneath the ground where InSight operated from.</p>
<p>Since water is considered necessary to support life, scientists say the presence of it on Mars leaves open the possibility that some form of life might exist, or existed there in the past.</p>
<p>Numerous past studies have also provided evidence that liquid water could exist on Mars. Scientists have already uncovered evidence that about 3 billion years ago, the surface of Mars likely had an active system of lakes, rivers and oceans</p>
<p>Mars is believed to have lost its surface water as its atmosphere thinned. This likely turned the planet into the dry, dusty world it is today. Scientists have theorized that much of the ancient water escaped out into space or remained buried under the surface.</p>
<p><strong>Water below Martian crust</strong></p>
<p>Vashan Wright is an assistant professor of Geophysics at the University of California San Diego's Scripps Institution of Oceanography. He helped lead the research. Wright told The Associated Press the data suggests liquid water sits between 11 to 20 kilometers down in the Martian <strong>crust</strong>. He added that the water likely moved down from the surface billions of years ago when water is believed to have flowed freely on Mars.</p>
<p>The researchers combined computer models with the seismic data collected by InSight to reach their findings. They said the data showed the water is likely contained in a deep<strong> layer</strong> of igneous rock beneath the Martian surface. Igneous rock is formed from magma, a very hot liquid rock that has cooled.</p>
<p>Wright and his team recently reported their results <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.2409983121">in a study</a> published in <em>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</em>.</p>
<p>In a statement to Reuters news agency, Wright said, "On Earth what we know is where it is wet enough and there are enough sources of energy, there is microbial life very deep in Earth's subsurface." He added that the data suggests "the <strong>ingredients</strong> for life as we know it” may exist in the Martian subsurface.</p>
<p>The researchers said the InSight lander operated around the planet's Elysium Planitia area, near the equator. They believe the area is representative of the rest of Mars. The study suggests enough water exists below the surface to form a planet-wide ocean about 1 to 2 kilometers deep.</p>
<p><strong>Better understanding of Martian water cycles</strong></p>
<p>There is currently no way to confirm the study's suggested existence of liquid water because it sits so far beneath the Martian surface. Such a confirmation would require large <strong>drills</strong> and other specialized equipment.</p>
<p>But Wright <a class="wsw__a" href="https://news.berkeley.edu/2024/08/12/scientists-find-oceans-of-water-on-mars-its-just-too-deep-to-tap/">said</a> in a statement that for now, researchers can use the newly examined data to gain a better understanding of Martian water <strong>cycles</strong>. This can help scientists improve their knowledge about the planet's climate as well as the development of the Martian surface and interior. Wright noted the latest findings could also help guide researchers in where to look for further evidence of possible life forms on Mars.</p>
<p>"I'm <strong>inspired</strong> and I hope the public is also inspired," Wright said about the study results. "Humans can work together to put instruments on a planet... and try to understand what's going on there."</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters, UC Berkeley News and Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>interior </strong><em>– n. </em>the inside part of something</p>
<p><strong>seismic</strong> <em>– adj. </em>relating to or caused by an earthquake</p>
<p><strong>crust </strong><em>– n.</em> a hard, dry layer of the surface of something</p>
<p><strong>layer </strong><em>– n. </em>an amount of something covering a surface</p>
<p><strong>ingredient </strong><em>– n. </em>a part of something that makes it successful</p>
<p><strong>drill </strong><em>– v.</em> to use a tool or machine to make holes in a hard substance</p>
<p><strong>cycle </strong><em>– n. </em>a series of events that happen in a particular order and are often repeated</p>
<p><strong>inspire </strong><em>– v. </em>to make someone feel that they want to do something and can do it</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Six Seconds of Daily Kissing May Help Relationship (2024/8/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/six-seconds-of-daily-kissing-may-help-relationship.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>After 13 years of marriage, Bethany Meola admits that she and her husband can get caught up in their busy lives. They are raising three children and they both have careers.</p>
<p>So, they make sure to take time every day for a six-second kiss.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - US WWII veteran Harold Terens, 100, left, and Jeanne Swerlin, 96, kiss from a window after celebrating their wedding at the town hall of Carentan-les-Marais, in Normandy, France, June 8, 2024. (AP Photo/Jeremias Gonzalez)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-24b4-08dc881916c4_cx11_cy25_cw74_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - US WWII veteran Harold Terens, 100, left, and Jeanne Swerlin, 96, kiss from a window after celebrating their wedding at the town hall of Carentan-les-Marais, in Normandy, France, June 8, 2024. (AP Photo/Jeremias Gonzalez)</span></div>
<p>The six-second kiss is a daily exercise suggested by <strong>couples therapists </strong>John and Julie Gottman. It is as simple as it sounds. They say taking time each day for a six-second kiss can help connect you physically and emotionally with your partner.</p>
<p>“It's kind of a funny thing to put on the to-do list,” Meola said. She first learned of the exercise while studying for a master's degree that centered on marriage and family.</p>
<p>It made a difference, Meola said. “It's long enough to kind of ground you and say, ‘Here's this other person that I love, that I've <strong>committed</strong> to.'”</p>
<p><strong>Why does six seconds matter?</strong></p>
<p>Married in 1987, Julie and John Gottman co-founded the Gottman Institute to teach couples therapy. John Gottman also wrote <em>The Seven Principles for Making Marriage Work</em> and other books.</p>
<p>John Gottman told the Associated Press that six seconds is not just a number. It comes from studying more than 3,000 couples over 30 years. The Gottmans found that a six-second kiss is enough to help release oxytocin.</p>
<p>Oxytocin is a natural substance that is produced by the body. The substance is widely believed to help a mother connect with her newborn baby. The Gottmans say it also builds trust in a relationship by calming down the fear center of the brain. They also used research by neuro-economist Paul Zak. Zak suggests that a 20-second hug creates the same results.</p>
<p>“For the 20-second hug or the six-second kiss, it's one that really feels different. It feels like you've come home,” John Gottman said.</p>
<p>Julie Gottman said a long kiss works best for couples who are committed to each other and who trust each other. Couples who are working through personal or marital issues might not be ready for it.</p>
<p><strong>How to start</strong></p>
<p>But how do you start this type of exercise? Couples have to decide to take time out of their day to put their relationship first. One partner might open the discussion by saying they believe the exercise could bring them closer and it is worth a try.</p>
<p>The experts suggest creating a <strong>ritual</strong>. For example, set aside the same time every day when both are about to leave for work or just before bedtime.</p>
<p>Creating a ritual prevents a relationship from becoming one in which the only thing a couple does together is add things "to their very long list of <strong>tasks</strong>,” John Gottman said. “We want to really <strong>nurture</strong> the <strong>romance.”</strong></p>
<p>Rituals also create a shared sense of purpose, Julie Gottman said. However, she reminds people to enjoy<strong> </strong>it. Do not think of it as something you are supposed to do.</p>
<p>And to the couples who say they cannot find the time? She is direct and honest.</p>
<p>“You really don't have six seconds?” “You know, we're not talking six hours here. We're talking six seconds," she said with a laugh.</p>
<p>And that's the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report. I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Albert Stumm reported this story for The Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;<i></i>173;</em></p>
<p><em>_____________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>couple </strong><em>– n. </em>two persons married, engaged, or otherwise romantically paired</p>
<p><strong>therapist </strong><em>– n.</em><strong> </strong>an individual specializing in the therapeutic medical treatment of impairment, injury, disease, or disorder</p>
<p><strong>committed </strong><em>– adj</em>. having made a pledge or commitment to someone (such as a romantic partner) or something (such as a cause)</p>
<p><strong>ritual </strong><em>– n. </em>an established form for a ceremony</p>
<p><strong>task </strong><em>– n.</em><strong> </strong>a usually assigned piece of work often to be finished within a certain time</p>
<p><strong>nurture</strong> <em>– v. </em>to further the development of</p>
<p><strong>romance </strong><em>– n. </em>a relationship between two people who are in love with each other</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Sometimes Help Is Just 'A Phone Call Away' (2024/8/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/sometimes-help-is-just-a-phone-call-away.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>On today's show we talk about some expressions that deal with an important device in our lives – our phones.</p>
<p>With a smartphone, we can connect to the world. In fact, we can say smartphones <u>give us the world at our fingertips</u>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - U.S. actress Lindsay Lohan speaks on a telephone during a charity day at BGC Partners in the Canary Wharf business district in London, Britain September 12, 2016. (REUTERS/Toby Melville)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/F381F711-449B-40A3-9172-DEDE13989B93_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - U.S. actress Lindsay Lohan speaks on a telephone during a charity day at BGC Partners in the Canary Wharf business district in London, Britain September 12, 2016. (REUTERS/Toby Melville)</span></div>
<p>Needless to say, we use phones to stay in contact with the people in our lives. We use them to reach out to our friends, family, neighbors, and co-workers.</p>
<p>So, when we tell someone that we are <u>just a phone call away</u>, what we are really telling them is that we are available. We are there for them. We often use this expression to offer help to someone who is in a difficult situation or just in need of a friendly voice.</p>
<p>For example, let's say my friend is having a hard time with an advanced English course. The assignments are difficult, the material is hard to understand, and his teacher has not been answering his emails. I can say to him, “Look, if you ever need help, <u>I'm just a phone call away</u>. Call anytime!”</p>
<p>It's good to be available to some people some of the time.</p>
<p>But maybe not all the time.</p>
<p>We all have someone in our lives who contacts us too much. They may<u> blow up our phones</u> with a flood of calls and text messages. When <u>your phone blows up</u>, someone is trying to contact you repeatedly.</p>
<p>Here's an example. Let's say your neighbor, Jana, is having trouble with another neighbor, Jake. And you are in the middle of it. They are both <u>blowing up your phone</u> with calls and texts about their disagreement. You can tell them, “<u>Hold the phone</u>! Just stop! Talk to each other and work out your problems because I've had enough.”</p>
<p>The expression <u>hold the phone</u> is a way to say “wait” or “stop.” We use it when we hear something surprising or when we have had enough of a situation.</p>
<p>And it doesn't have to be about phone calls or texts. For example, let's say a friend tells me that my favorite singer is coming to town. I can't believe it! So, I can say, “<u>Hold the phone</u>! Are you serious?” It's like saying, "Hold on a minute!"</p>
<p>Now, let's go back to your arguing neighbors, Jana and Jake. Let's say they take your advice. They are willing to work out their problems. They try to call each other but the keep missing each other's calls. First Jana calls Jake, but he isn't available. Then Jake calls her back, but now Jana isn't available. They play <u>phone tag</u> like this for days until they finally speak to each other.</p>
<p><strong>Tag</strong> is a child's game. One person is “it” and must chase and tag, or touch, the other children. So, <u>phone tag</u> is when two people try to contact each other but their calls go unanswered.</p>
<p>At least Jake and Jana are trying to work out their problems. When it comes to keeping relationships happy in the neighborhood, they are not <u>phoning it in</u>.</p>
<p>When we <u>phone it in</u>, we don't try our best at something. We don't give our best efforts. For example, some people who lose interest in their jobs might start <u>phoning it in</u>. They stop trying and do not do their best work.</p>
<p>That's not the case with us here at VOA Learning English. we are not <u>phoning it in</u>. We work hard every day to bring you new learning English content.</p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this Words and Their Stories.</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>_______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>tag</strong> <em>– n.</em> a game in which the player who is it chases others and tries to touch one of them who then becomes it</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Small Farm Animals Are Growing in Popularity (2024/8/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/small-farm-animals-are-growing-in-popularity.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Americans are showing more interest in owning unusually small cows, goats, d<i><i>onkey</i></i>s and other small farm animals.</p>
<p>These animals are <strong>cute</strong>. They require less food and space. And they might even help cut the grass.</p>
<p>People who farm for fun are known as <strong>hobby</strong> farmers. They are looking for easy-to-raise farm animals. Some just like the idea of having a little pig or a small sheep as a pet.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Jamie Campion pets her one of her Southdown Babydoll sheep as it grazes in the backyard Wednesday morning, July 3, 2024. (AP Photo/George Walker IV)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-36fa-08dcbbc8accc_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Jamie Campion pets her one of her Southdown Babydoll sheep as it grazes in the backyard Wednesday morning, July 3, 2024. (AP Photo/George Walker IV)</span></div>
<p>The word for something that is unusually small is <strong>miniature</strong>.</p>
<p>Animal <strong>breeders</strong> say sales of these little farm animals have grown since the COVID-19 pandemic. At that time, more people started raising chickens at home for fun and fresh eggs. Like chickens, <strong>mini</strong> farm animals appeal to beginners who want to try a rural lifestyle.</p>
<p>Brian Gazda has a small farm in the western state of Idaho. He runs a YouTube channel called "Hobby Farm Guys" with two friends. Gazda said a lot of people do not have a large piece of land, but if they have a small area, “they can keep a miniature cow or a few miniature goats."</p>
<p>Martin Fysh works for Tractor Supply Company. He said social media has brought attention to mini farm animals. But Fysh thinks their popularity also shows a natural path among <strong>customers</strong> who started out by raising a few chickens.</p>
<p>"They're seen as part of the extended family," Fysh said.</p>
<p>Some owners of mini farm animals turn their hobbies into money-making activities. They show the animals to visitors, breed animals, and write about their farming experiences.</p>
<p>But newcomers to these activities need to weigh the pros and cons, or the good and bad effects, of hobby farming, Gazda and other hobby farmers said. Among the problems is the rising cost of miniature farm animals. While they are cute, they can also be aggressive.</p>
<p><strong>Mini goats</strong></p>
<p>Brittany Snow is a high school English teacher in Florida who owns several small-sized Nigerian dwarf goats. She dreamed of living on a farm. Her family recently moved to a rural area.</p>
<p>Thirty-two-year-old Snow started with four Nigerian Dwarf goats. Snow expected them to produce milk right away, but she learned that is not the case.</p>
<p>Angelia Alden is a business operations manager for the Miniature Dairy Goat Association. She said many people who buy mini goats sell them after a few years because their care presents problems and costs they did not expect. Rising animal feed costs can be one problem, as is finding farm animal medical care.</p>
<p><strong>Mini cows and d<i><i>onkey</i></i>s</strong></p>
<p>The mini farm animals can also be heavy. Some of the popular miniature animals on social media are cows that can weigh between 220 and 270 kilograms.</p>
<p>Twenty-eight-year-old Allie Sine started her own business breeding and selling mini cows in 2020. Social media videos showing some of her mini cows have gotten millions of views. Last year, she sold about 190 young cows. Each animal sold for between $2,000 and $30,000. "Everything just <strong>skyrocketed</strong>," Sine said.</p>
<p><strong>Mini d<i><i>onkey</i></i>s</strong></p>
<p>Kim Furches owns a farm with her husband, Ken, in West Jefferson, North Carolina. She has found similar success. Furches said they bred mini d<i><i>onkey</i></i>s for about 20 years. Before the pandemic, they would usually sell about eight d<i><i>onkey</i></i>s per year for less than a thousand dollars each. They now sell about 20 per year. The last mini d<i><i>onkey</i></i> sold for $7,500, Furches said.</p>
<p><strong>Sheep follow her around</strong></p>
<p>Earlier this year, Jamie Campion, who is 41, and her husband, Jeff, bought two Southdown Babydoll sheep from a local breeder near their home in Thompson's Station, Tennessee. The animals cost $800 each.</p>
<p>Jamie Campion said the sheep have become good at keeping their grass short. But more often, the sheep give her joy as would other pets. Once she took them for a walk in the snow. "They just followed right behind," she said. "There's a whole sheep and <strong>shepherd</strong> relationship.”</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Haleluya Hadero and Anne D'Inocenzio reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>cute</strong><strong> </strong>– adj. having a pleasing and usually youthful appearance</p>
<p><strong>miniature</strong> – <em>adj</em>. very small</p>
<p><strong>hobby</strong> – <em>n</em>. an activity that a person does for pleasure when not working</p>
<p><strong>breed</strong> – <em>v</em>. to keep and take care of animals or plants in order to produce more animals or plants of a particular kind</p>
<p><strong>mini- </strong>- <em>combining form</em> smaller or shorter than usual or normal</p>
<p><strong>skyrocket</strong> – <em>v</em>. to increase quickly to a very high level or amount</p>
<p><strong>customer </strong>–n. a person or business that pays for goods or services</p>
<p><strong>shepherd</strong> – <em>n</em>. a person whose job is to take care of sheep</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Combine and Integrate (2024/8/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/combine-and-integrate.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Simona in China about the words "combine" and "integrate."</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-30f2-08dcbc7c9511_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>Hi! I have a question. What is the difference between "combine" and "integrate?" Thank you!</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>Thank you for writing to us, Simona. I'm happy to answer this question.</p>
<p>"Combine" and "integrate" are similar in meaning. But, there are some small differences in usage.</p>
<p>The word "combine" is in our Learning English <em><a class="wsw__a" href="https://docs.voanews.eu/en-US-LEARN/2022/06/07/c4dbd6af-5f63-4f28-bc42-0bd175f4e4b4.pdf">Word Book</a></em>. We define it as a verb meaning to mix or bring together.</p>
<p>"Integrate" is not in our <em>Word Book</em>. <em>Merriam-Webster</em>'s dictionary says the word means to unite or form into a whole.</p>
<p>Now, let's look at the prefixes that begin each word. "Combine" begins with the prefix <em>co-</em>, such as in the word "copilot." This prefix means "with."</p>
<p>"Integrate" begins with the prefix <em>inter-</em> but with the letter "r" removed. This means "among" or "between," as in the word "international."</p>
<p>The prefix <em>co-</em> generally gives the sense of joining two or more things together. For example, oxygen combines with hydrogen to make water.<strong> </strong>However, "combine" can also mean to mix things together, such as mixing the <strong>ingredients</strong> in a <strong>recipe</strong>.</p>
<p>"Integrate" can be used that same way. But, it also can mean to add something to one or more other things and mix them so well that they fully unite.</p>
<p>For example, a school might try to integrate healthy foods into its school meals. Or, a jazz group might try to integrate elements of country music into their songs.</p>
<p>Notice that we use the preposition "into" with the word integrate. We say that we "integrate <em>x into y." </em>Here is another example:</p>
<p><em>New technologies can quickly become <u>integrated into our lives</u>. </em></p>
<p>But when we use "combine," we use the preposition "with." We say we "combine <em>x with y," </em>or "combine <em>x and y," </em>as in these examples:</p>
<p><em>The management team is trying to <u>combine youth with experience.</u></em></p>
<p><em>When you <u>combine talent and hard work</u>, you will see positive results. </em></p>
<p>"Integrate" can sometimes give a sense of deeper connection among two or more things than "combine." To see this, consider the word "integral." This word comes from the same root as ‘integrate.'</p>
<p>We say that something is an integral part of something else. This means that the things are deeply connected or important to each other. For example:</p>
<p><em>Bicycles are an <u>integral part of traffic and culture</u> in the Netherlands. </em></p>
<p><em>Fishing is an <u>integral part of the coastal economy</u>. </em></p>
<p>Last, both the words "integral" and "integration" have technical meanings in calculus, a field of mathematics.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, do you have a question about American English? You can ask about many different areas of English, such as speaking, listening, culture, and more. Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.<em> </em></p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><em>_______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>ingredient </strong><em>-n. </em>a food or item that goes into making a meal or dish</p>
<p><strong>recipe </strong><em>-n. </em>a set of directions for making a meal or dish and which includes a list of ingredients</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Propose Idea to Warm Mars (2024/8/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/scientists-propose-idea-to-warm-mars.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The idea of turning Mars into a livable world for humans is a common element of science fiction. But could such an action be done in real life?</p>
<p>Scientists are now proposing a new method to warm up Earth's planetary neighbor. The idea involves putting engineered particles made of iron or aluminum into the atmosphere. The goal is to trap escaping heat and direct sunlight toward the Martian surface.</p>
<p>The proposed idea would be to increase the natural greenhouse effect on Mars and raise its surface temperature by around 28 degrees Celsius over ten years.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This image taken by the Mars Exploration Rover Spirit's camera shows the Martian surface southwest of the rover's landing site. (REUTERS/NASA/JPL/Arizona State University/Cornell University/Handout)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/29242cac-bc73-4a80-aae2-cc620055d86a_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This image taken by the Mars Exploration Rover Spirit's camera shows the Martian surface southwest of the rover's landing site. (REUTERS/NASA/JPL/Arizona State University/Cornell University/Handout)</span></div>
<p>Such a change alone would not make Mars livable for people. But the scientists who developed the idea see it as a possible first step.</p>
<p>Edwin Kite of the University of Chicago helped lead the study that appeared recently in the publication <em>Science Advances</em>.</p>
<p>Kite described the process of terraforming – meaning to change a planet's environment to be more like Earth. "For Mars, warming the planet is a necessary, but insufficient, first step. Previous concepts have focused on releasing greenhouse gases, but these require large amounts of resources that are scarce on Mars," he said.</p>
<p>Kite added that climate modeling suggests the new idea of using engineered particles to warm Mars' atmosphere could work better than previous ideas. Kite explained that the work is important because it presents a possible method that could help future exploration plans.</p>
<p>NASA has sent robotic vehicles to explore the Martian surface and the InSight Lander to study the planet's interior. The U.S. space agency's Artemis program aims to put astronauts in the coming years on the moon's surface for the first time since 1972 in preparation for possible future human missions to Mars.</p>
<p>There are several barriers to human settlements on Mars. They include a lack of breathable oxygen, harmful ultraviolet radiation, salty soil, and dust storms that sometimes cover much of the planet. And Mars' cold temperatures are a serious issue.</p>
<p>The median Martian surface temperature is about minus-65 degrees Celsius. With its thin atmosphere, solar heat on the Martian surface easily escapes into space. The proposal would aim to permit liquid water to exist on the surface of Mars, which has water in the form of ice at its polar areas and its subsurface.</p>
<p>The scientists proposed continuously releasing tiny particles, called nanorods, into the atmosphere at a rate of about 30 liters per second for years.</p>
<p>Samaneh Ansari of Northwestern University in Illinois is the study's lead writer. Ansari said, "The idea is to either ship the material or better yet, ship the manufacturing tool and make the nanorods on the planet since iron and aluminum are abundant on the surface of Mars.”</p>
<p>The researchers are mindful of the possibility of unintended consequences in terraforming another world. Scientists, for instance, are eager to learn whether Mars has held life in the past - or perhaps currently, in the form of subsurface microbes.</p>
<p>Kite suggested that the costs and benefits of releasing nanorods are uncertain. For example, he said if Mars' soil has compounds that are harmful to life from Earth, then the benefit of warming Mars is zero.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Will Dunham reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>fiction </strong><em>– n.</em> an invented story</p>
<p><strong>greenhouse effect</strong> <em>– n.</em> warming of the surface and lower atmosphere of a planet that is caused by conversion of solar radiation into heat</p>
<p><strong>insufficient</strong> <em>– adj.</em> not enough, inadequate</p>
<p><strong>concept </strong>–<em> n.</em> an abstract or generic idea</p>
<p><strong>focus</strong><em> – v.</em> to concentrate attention or effort</p>
<p><strong>median </strong><em>-- n.</em><strong> </strong> the middle value of a range of values</p>
<p><strong>polar</strong> <em>– adj.</em> of or relating to a geographic pole</p>
<p><strong>abundant </strong><em>-- adj. </em>existing or occurring in large amounts</p>
<p><strong>consequence </strong><em>-- n.</em><strong> </strong>something produced by a cause</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Stonehenge's 'Altar Stone' Came from Far Away Scotland (2024/8/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/study-stonehenge-s-altar-stone-came-from-far-away-scotland.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p class="MsoBodyText">Researchers are one step closer to understanding how Britain's ancient circular structure, Stonehenge, was created.</p>
<p>The circle of huge rocks stands in southern England near the tip of northeast Scotland. Its so-called altar stone lies flat in the center. The new study finds that the huge altar stone did not come from nearby Wales as had been thought. The researchers say the rock instead was carried to the site from the more distant Scotland.</p>
<p><em>Nature</em> magazine published the study on Wednesday. The research did not show how the five-meter-long stone was carried to the site. But the scientists said it traveled about 740 kilometers.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Revelers gather at the ancient stone circle Stonehenge to celebrate the Summer Solstice, the longest day of the year, near Salisbury, England, Wednesday, June 21, 2023. (AP Photo/Kin Cheung, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4f74a5ce-9187-480f-b714-6bc5910bb0ab_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Revelers gather at the ancient stone circle Stonehenge to celebrate the Summer Solstice, the longest day of the year, near Salisbury, England, Wednesday, June 21, 2023. (AP Photo/Kin Cheung, File)</span></div>
<p>“It's a surprise that it's come from so far away,” said University of Exeter archaeologist Susan Greaney, who was not involved in the study.</p>
<p>For more than a hundred years, scientists believed that Stonehenge's central sandstone slab — long called the “altar stone" — came from much closer Wales. But a study last year by some of the researchers showed that the stone did not <strong>match </strong>the <strong>geology</strong> of Wales' sandstone formations. The actual source of the stone remained unknown until now.</p>
<p>For the study, the team tested mineral content in pieces of rock that had been collected in past digs. They found a match in the sandstone formations of Orcadian Basin in northeastern Scotland. The area includes parts of the end of the Scottish <strong>peninsula</strong> as well as the Orkney Islands.</p>
<p>“That <strong>geological</strong> ‘fingerprint' isn't repeated in any other area of <strong>sediment</strong> in the U.K.,” said Aberystwyth University geologist Nick Pearce, one of the study writers.</p>
<p>Greaney said the operational complexity of moving the stone so far suggests a high level of planning, cooperation and cultural connection between these two parts of ancient Britain.</p>
<p>Stonehenge went up around 5,000 years ago. Its design creates a kind of “window” that fully frames the sun as it rises on the summer <strong>solstice</strong>. The ancient purpose of the altar stone remains a mystery.</p>
<p>“Stonehenge isn't a settlement site, but a place of ceremony...,” said Heather Sebire, with English Heritage, an aid organization that cares for hundreds of historic British sites and structures. Sebire said that past archaeological digs had not uncovered evidence of daily living at Stonehenge.</p>
<p>Past research has shown cultural connections — such as similarities in <strong>pottery</strong> making — between the area around Stonehenge and Scotland's Orkney Islands. Other stones at Stonehenge came from western Wales.</p>
<p>Britain is home to other ancient stone circles. But, study writer Richard Bevins of Aberystwyth University says, “the thing that's <strong>unique</strong> about Stonehenge is the distance from which the stones have been sourced.”</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Christina Larson reported this story for The Associated Press. Caty Weaver adapted it for Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>match </strong>– <em>v. </em>to make or find the equal or the like of</p>
<p><strong>peninsula </strong>– <em>n. </em>a piece of land nearly surrounded by water or sticking out into the water</p>
<p><strong>geological </strong>– <em>adj. </em>of, relating to, or based on geology, a science that deals with the history of the earth and its life especially as recorded in rocks</p>
<p><strong>sediment </strong>– <em>n. </em>the material from a liquid that settles to the bottom</p>
<p><strong>solstice </strong>– <em>n. </em>either of the two points on the ecliptic at which its distance from the celestial equator is greatest and which is reached by the sun each year about June 21 and December 21</p>
<p><strong>pottery </strong>– <em>n. </em>clayware, especially earthenware as distinguished from porcelain and stoneware and from brick and tile</p>
<p><strong>unique </strong>– <em>adj. </em>being the only one; singular; unlike any other</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Japan’s Megaquake Warning Leads to Worry, Preparation (2024/8/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/japan-s-megaquake-warning-leads-to-worry-and-preparation.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>An agency of Japan's government recently gave its first-ever "megaquake advisory," or warning message.</p>
<p>The Japan Meteorological Agency (JMA) issued the warning after a powerful quake struck on August 8 off the southeastern coast of Japan's main island of Kyushu.</p>
<p>The <strong>magnitude</strong> 7.1 quake caused no deaths or severe damage, but the advisory has led to questions and a sense of worry. Japan is among the countries most hit by earthquakes. Now many citizens are wondering about when the next big quake will hit.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Stone lanterns fall at a shrine following a strong earthquake in Nichinan, Miyazaki prefecture, southern Japan, on Aug. 9, 2024. (Kyodo News via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-ad26-08dcbc8418b3_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Stone lanterns fall at a shrine following a strong earthquake in Nichinan, Miyazaki prefecture, southern Japan, on Aug. 9, 2024. (Kyodo News via AP)</span></div>
<p>The Associated Press recently explained what the advisory means, what people are being told to do:</p>
<p><strong>What is a megaquake advisory?</strong></p>
<p>JMA issued the advisory after deciding that the August 8 quake increased the likelihood of another major quake.</p>
<p>The agency said there is a 70 to 80 percent chance of a magnitude 8 or 9 quake associated with an area called the Nankai Trough within the next 30 years. The JMA said the probability of such an event is now "higher than normal."</p>
<p>Naoshi Hirata is a <strong>seismologist</strong> at the University of Tokyo and head of the JMA's group of experts. He said that the warning was not a prediction that a megaquake will happen at any specific time or place. He urged people to remain careful and prepared.</p>
<p><strong>What is the Nankai Trough?</strong></p>
<p>The <a class="wsw__a" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nankai_megathrust_earthquakes#/media/File:RuptureAreasNankaiMegathrust_2013.png" target="_self">Nankai Trough</a> is an undersea <strong>trench</strong>, or a deep valley on the ocean floor, that runs from the waters just off the southeastern coast of Kyushu, to Suruga Bay in central Japan. It is about 800 kilometers long.</p>
<p>Two large areas of the Earth's surface, the Philippine Sea <strong>Plate</strong> and the Eurasian Plate meet there. The Philippine plate slowly pulls down on the Eurasian plate and causes it to release energy from time to time. The JMA said that could lead to a megaquake and tsunami.</p>
<p>The last Nankai Trough quake was off Shikoku in 1946. The U.S. Geological Survey estimated its magnitude to be 8.3, and more than 1,400 people died.</p>
<p><strong>What is the government doing to prepare?</strong></p>
<p>As a result of the "megaquake advisory," Japanese Prime Minister Fumio Kishida canceled a trip and announced he would lead the government response. Local governments are studying their emergency plans.</p>
<p>Experts and officials have urged people to stay calm and to continue normal life but to prepare for a possible <strong>evacuation</strong>.</p>
<p>JMA experts said on August 12 they have so far found no abnormal activity that would suggest a megaquake.</p>
<p><strong>How are people reacting?</strong></p>
<p>The "megaquake advisory” is filled with scientific terms. It has worried people across the country. Some towns closed beaches and canceled yearly events. This has led to problems for travelers during Japan's Obon holiday week, a time for festivals and fireworks across the nation.</p>
<p>Some stores are running out of emergency supplies, even in areas where there is little risk. In the vacation town of Matsuyama city on the island of Shikoku, hotels and <strong>resorts</strong> studied their evacuation plans and emergency equipment. In another seaside town, Shirahama, outdoor hot springs were closed for a week and a fireworks festival was cancelled.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Mari Yamaguchi reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>magnitude </strong>– <em>n. </em>a number that shows the power of an earthquake</p>
<p><strong>seismologist </strong>–n. a person who studies the movements of the Earth such as earthquakes</p>
<p><strong>trench</strong> – <em>n</em>. a long, narrow hole in the ocean floor</p>
<p><strong>plate</strong> – <em>n</em>. one of the very large sections of the Earth's surface that are believed to move and cause earthquakes where they touch each other</p>
<p><strong>evacuate</strong> <em>– v. </em>to remove (someone) from a dangerous place</p>
<p><strong>resort </strong><em>–n</em>. a place where people can stay on vacation that includes a hotel, restaurants and activities</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Everyday Grammar: Beating Problems with Adverbs (2024/8/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/beating-problems-with-adverbs-everyday-grammar.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Adam Brock</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">15 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>
For VOA Learning English, this is Everyday Grammar.</p>
<p>This week, we're going to talk about some common problems with <strong>adverbs</strong>. Basically, adverbs are words that describe verbs, <strong>adjectives</strong>, and other adverbs. For example, "I ran quickly to the store." The adverb <em>quickly</em> describes the verb <em>run</em>.</p>
<p><strong>What is an adverb?</strong></p>
<div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1da030e9-e522-43e4-ac8d-a160b9a20b57_tv_w100_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>If a word is not easy to <strong>classify</strong> as a noun, verb, or adjective, it is probably an adverb. Some of the most common words in English are adverbs, including <em>up, so, just, then, how, now, also, here,</em> and<em> more.</em></p>
<p>Adverbs usually describe verbs. They express <em>when, how, where, and why</em> an action is done. Many adverbs are easy to find because they have the <em>–ly</em> ending, such as <em>quickly, surely, </em>and<em> certainly</em>. However, many adverbs do not have the <em>–ly</em> ending.</p>
<p>Adverbs can also describe adjectives. For example, "It is really cold today." In this example,<em> really</em> is an adverb that describes the adjective <em>cold</em>.</p>
<p>Adverbs can describe other adverbs. For example, "I will probably never go back." Here, the adverb <em>probably</em> describes the adverb <em>never</em>.</p>
<p><strong>Where do you put the adverb?</strong></p>
<p>Where do adverbs go in a sentence? Well, it depends.</p>
<p>Some adverbs can go almost anywhere in a sentence. Let us look at the adverb<em> sometimes</em>. It can go at the beginning of the sentence as in, "Sometimes, I walk to work." It can go after the subject: "I sometimes walk to work." Or it can go at the end of the sentence: "I walk to work sometimes."</p>
<p>Other adverbs can only go in the middle of a sentence. The adverb <em>probably</em> is an example. "She will <em>probably</em> leave early."</p>
<p>It is incorrect to say, "Probably she will leave early" or "She will leave early probably." Other such adverbs are <em>never, rarely, seldom,</em> and<em> always</em>. These are called <strong>mid-sentence adverbs</strong>. They usually go between the subject and the main verb. Different types of adverbs have different <a class="wsw__a" href="http://dictionary.cambridge.org/us/grammar/british-grammar/adverbs-and-adverb-phrases-position">sentence positions.</a></p>
<p><strong>What's the difference between adverbs and adjectives?</strong></p>
<p>Adjectives describe nouns, while adverbs describe verbs, adjectives, and other adverbs. Take the sentence, "She is careful." The adjective<em> careful</em> is describing the noun <em>she</em>. But if you said, "She walks carefully," the adverb <em>carefully</em> is describing the verb <em>walk</em>.</p>
<p><strong>Do you think this is hard? Hardly!</strong></p>
<p>Native speakers sometimes confuse adverbs and adjectives.</p>
<p>The words <em>hard </em>and<em> hardly</em> are especially difficult. <em>Hard</em> is both an adjective and an adverb. You can say "The bed was <em>hard</em>," using the adjective, which means it is "very firm." You can also say, "I worked <em>hard</em>," using the adverb, which means "with a lot of effort."</p>
<p><em>Hardly</em> is an adverb. A long time ago, it meant "in a hard manner," but its meaning has changed. People used to say "not hardly.” Over time, the word “not” disappeared. Since the 1500s, <em>hardly</em> has meant "almost not" or "barely." For example, "I hardly had time to finish the project." This conflicting meaning of <em>hard</em> and <em>hardly</em> has become the basis for jokes.</p>
<p>Listen to cartoon character Homer Simpson playing with the confusion between <em>hard</em> and <em>hardly</em>. In the scene, Homer's co-workers are replaced with robots.</p>
<p><em>"So you guys are my new co-workers. So working hard or hardly working? (laugh). I said, ‘Working hard or hardly working?' ‘Working hard or hardly working? WORKING HARD OR HARDLY WORKING?' IT'S A SIMPLE QUESTION!"</em></p>
<p>Homer is asking the robots if they are <em>working hard</em> (working with energy) or <em>hardly working</em> (only working a little). The robots, with their exact reasoning, do not understand the <strong>word play</strong> in the question.</p>
<p>We will leave you with a song that uses the adverb <em>softly </em>in an unexpected way. Listen to the Fugees' version of the classic song "Killing Me Softly with His Song."</p>
<p><em>Strumming my pain with his fingers</em></p>
<p><em>Singing my life with his words</em></p>
<p><em>Killing me softly with his song</em></p>
<p><em>Killing me softly with his song</em></p>
<p> </p>
<p>I'm Jonathan Evans.</p>
<p>And I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>See this excellent reference on adjectives and adverbs from <a class="wsw__a" href="https://owl.english.purdue.edu/owl/owlprint/536/" target="_blank">Purdue University's Online Writing Lab</a>. </em></p>
<p><em>Adam Brock wrote and produced this story. Jill Robbins was the editor.</em></p><div id="bottom">
<ins class="adsbygoogle" data-ad-client="ca-pub-3585518775245612" data-ad-format="auto" data-ad-slot="9284795419" data-full-width-responsive="true" style="display:block; text-align:center;"></ins>
<script>(adsbygoogle =window.adsbygoogle ||[]).push({});</script></div>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>adverb </strong>- <em>gramm. term.</em> a word that describes a verb, an adjective, another adverb, or a sentence and that is often used to show time, manner, place, or degree</p>
<p><strong>adjective </strong>- <em>gramm. term. a word that describes a noun or a pronoun</em></p>
<p><strong>classify</strong> – <em>v</em>. to consider (someone or something) as belonging to a particular group</p>
<p><strong>word play</strong> – <em>n</em>. playful or clever use of words<span style="font-size: 9pt;"></span></p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Hottest Oceans in 400 Years Endanger Great Barrier Reef (2024/8/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/study-hottest-oceans-in-400-years-endanger-great-barrier-reef.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">14 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>New research shows that water temperatures in and around Australia's Great Barrier Reef have risen to their warmest in 400 years over the past 10 years. The rising temperatures have put the world's largest reef under threat.</p>
<p>The Great Barrier Reef is the world's largest living ecosystem. It stretches for 2,400 kilometers off the coast of the northern state of Queensland.</p>
<p>A group of scientists at universities across Australia removed core samples from the coral. They examined the samples to measure summer ocean temperatures going back to the year 1618. The scientists combined information from core samples with ship and satellite <strong>data</strong> going back around 100 years.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this photo provided by the Great Barrier Reef Marine Park Authority the Hardy Reef is viewed from the air near the Whitsunday Islands, Australia, June 22, 2014. (Jumbo Aerial Photography/Great Barrier Reef Marine Park Authority via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-6b60-08dcb8a0a3a0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this photo provided by the Great Barrier Reef Marine Park Authority the Hardy Reef is viewed from the air near the Whitsunday Islands, Australia, June 22, 2014. (Jumbo Aerial Photography/Great Barrier Reef Marine Park Authority via AP)</span></div>
<p>The results show that ocean temperatures were unchanged for hundreds of years. But starting in 1900, the ocean temperatures began to rise. The research found that this is the result of human influence.</p>
<p>From 1960 to 2024, the study's writers observed an average yearly warming for January to March of 0.12 degrees Celsius per <strong>decade</strong>.</p>
<p>Since 2016, the reef has experienced five summers of mass coral bleaching. This is when large parts of the reef turn white due to <strong>heat stress</strong>. This also puts the coral at greater risk of death. The mass bleaching events happened during five of the six warmest years in the last four centuries, the study showed.</p>
<p>This research appeared on August 8 in the publication <em>Nature</em>.</p>
<p>"The world is losing one of its<strong> icons</strong>," said Benjamin Henley. He is with the University of Melbourne and is one of the study's co-writers.</p>
<p>"I find that to be an <strong>absolute</strong> tragedy. It's hard to understand how that can happen on our watch in our lifetime. So it's very sad,” Henley added.</p>
<p>The last temperature measurement, from January to March of this year, was the highest on record. Henley added that it was "head and shoulders" above any other year, meaning it was much higher.</p>
<p>Coral reefs are important for many reasons. They protect shorelines from <strong>erosion</strong>. They are home to thousands of kinds of fish. And they are an important part of the <strong>tourism</strong> industry<strong> </strong>in many countries. In Australia, the Great Barrier Reef adds $4.2 billion to the economy each year.</p>
<p>At least 54 countries and areas have experienced mass bleaching of their reefs since February 2023, as climate change warms the ocean's surface waters. That information comes from the U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Alasdair Pal</em> <em>reported this story for Reuters News Agency from Sydney, Australia. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><em>_____________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>e</strong><strong>cosystem</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n</em>. a system made up of an ecological community of living things interacting with their environment especially under natural conditions</p>
<p><strong>data </strong><em>– n</em>. factual information (such as measurements or statistics) used as a basis for reasoning, discussion, or calculation</p>
<p><strong>decade </strong><em>– n.</em> a period of 10 years</p>
<p><strong>heat stress </strong><em>– n</em>. sustained, warmer-than-average ocean temperatures</p>
<p><strong>icon </strong><em>– n. </em>a person or thing widely admired especially for having great influence or significance in a particular sphere</p>
<p><strong>absolute </strong><em>– adj</em>. free from doubt : having no exceptions</p>
<p><strong>erosion </strong><em>– n. </em>the process of wearing away by the action of water, wind, or glacial ice</p>
<p><strong>tourism </strong><em>– n. </em>the practice and business of traveling for recreation</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Tech Tip: Google Wallet Now Creates Digital IDs from Photos (2024/8/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/tech-tip-google-wallet-now-creates-digital-ids-from-photos.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">14 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Google has added a new tool that permits Android users to create digital versions of many kinds of identification (ID) cards and event passes for device <strong>wallets</strong>.</p>
<p>The tool is part of the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://wallet.google/">Google Wallet</a> <strong>app</strong>. It was first announced in May along with other changes to the latest operating system, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://developer.android.com/about/versions/15/get">Android 15</a>. The change <a class="wsw__a" href="https://support.google.com/wallet/answer/12060038#zippy=%2Cadd-items-from-a-photo-us-only">is explained</a> on a Google Wallet help website. The tool is now available for Android users in the United States who have the latest update of Google Wallet.</p>
<p>Digital wallets are designed to permit users to save non-physical versions of credit cards, personal IDs, membership passes and event tickets to their smartphones or other devices. Credit cards in wallets are linked directly to the banks that offer them and can be used to pay for things just like with a physical credit card.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="The Google Wallet logo is on display during a news conference, Thursday, May 26, 2011, in New York. (AP Photo/Mary Altaffer)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-891f-08dcbc7d06db_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">The Google Wallet logo is on display during a news conference, Thursday, May 26, 2011, in New York. (AP Photo/Mary Altaffer)</span></div>
<p>The use of digital wallets has expanded over the years as people depend more on digital IDs and other documents. Supporters say this reduces the need to carry a lot of cards in a physical wallet.</p>
<p>Until now, Google Wallet divided its digital document offerings into <strong>categories</strong>. Examples of these categories would be payment or gift cards, transportation passes for bus, train or air travel as well as official IDs.</p>
<p>Google's new tool is designed to permit device users to easily add many more kinds of documents to its Wallet service. These could include the kinds of passes many people carry in their physical wallets, such as <strong>gym </strong>memberships and medical or <strong>insurance </strong>cards.</p>
<p>These digital versions can be created by the user taking a picture of the physical document or by doing a screen capture of a digital version from a device. Some documents have an electronic <strong>barcode</strong> or QR code that can be entered into the Wallet app.</p>
<p>Google Wallet then uses artificial intelligence (AI) technology to use information from the photo to create a new digital pass.</p>
<p>The process of creating these digital documents is similar to adding new documents to Google Wallet. Users open the app and then click on “Add to Google Wallet (+).” The app then gives users a choice of what kind of card or pass to create. These include groups like “Payment Card,” “Transit Pass” or “ID Card.”</p>
<p>The new Google Wallet has a new category, called “Everything Else.” This offering was created to permit users to make digital copies of just about any card, pass or document they want to keep in their devices.</p>
<p>Google offers additional security steps to users storing official documents on Android devices. These “private passes” <a class="wsw__a" href="https://support.google.com/wallet/answer/13026633?hl=en">can also be added</a> to Google Wallet. Google says data contained in official digital documents is only saved on the device as an extra security measure.</p>
<p>People in some American states can create a digital ID to be used to officially prove their identity. Google <a class="wsw__a" href="https://support.google.com/wallet/answer/12436402?hl=en">explains</a> that this service is currently only available in Arizona, Colorado, Georgia and Maryland</p>
<p>There is a process users must follow to have their digital IDs <strong>verified</strong> by each state. The Transportation Security Administration (TSA) even accepts this form of state ID at <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.tsa.gov/travel/frequently-asked-questions/when-will-phased-digital-id-rollout-start-which-airportsstates">many major U.S. airports</a>.</p>
<p>Online technology website <em>Android Authority</em> recently <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.androidauthority.com/google-wallet-e-passport-support-3444362/">reported</a> Google Wallet will soon be equipped to also create digital versions of American passports. To create this official digital document, users would need to be holders of a U.S. government issued <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.dhs.gov/e-passports">e-Passport</a>.</p>
<p>The online publication said one of its writers discovered the Google Wallet passport is still in development at Google. <em>Android Authority </em>noted that having a passport saved in Google Wallet might remove the need to present an actual passport in some cases. However, the digital version is not designed to replace the physical passport, which the user should continue to carry.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from Google and </em><em>Android Authority.</em></p>
<p><strong>____________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>wallet</strong> <em>– n.</em> a small container used to carry money and credit cards, or a digital version used for the same purpose</p>
<p><strong>app </strong>–<em> n.</em> a computer program that is designed to do one task or set of tasks and is usually aimed at use on mobile devices</p>
<p><strong>category </strong><em>– n.</em> a group of people or things that are similar in some way</p>
<p><strong>gym (gymnasium) </strong>–n. a business where people go to exercise or play sports</p>
<p><strong>insurance</strong> <em>– n. </em>an agreement in which you pay a company to cover necessary costs in case there is an accident that causes damage or injuries</p>
<p><strong>barcode </strong><em>– n. </em>a small, printed pattern of thick and think black lines that is printed on products and documents</p>
<p><strong>verify </strong><em>– v. </em>to prove that something exists or is true</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Van Gogh’s The Starry Night Recreated in Bosnia’s Hills (2024/8/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/van-gogh-s-the-starry-night-recreated-in-bosnia-s-hills.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">14 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In the green hills of central Bosnia and Herzegovina, Halim Zukic has recreated a nature park in the form of one of Vincent van Gogh's most famous paintings, <em>The Starry Night</em>.</p>
<p>Zukic is from the town of Visoko. He decided to create a park after buying some land and a small house in a nearby village 20 years ago. But he had no clear idea of what the park should look like.</p>
<p>Then he saw <strong>tractors</strong> moving among fields of tall grass six years ago. He also saw that the tractors made circular shapes in the earth. This reminded him of similar shapes in Van Gogh's painting.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Still image from drone footage of The Starry Night nature park near Visoko, Bosnia and Herzegovina. Visoko businessman Halim Zukic created the park using 130,000 lavender bushes and other plants. (REUTERS production by Amel Emric, Branko Filipovic, Fedja Grulovic, Hedy Beloucif)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-1387-08dcbba549ca_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Still image from drone footage of The Starry Night nature park near Visoko, Bosnia and Herzegovina. Visoko businessman Halim Zukic created the park using 130,000 lavender bushes and other plants. (REUTERS production by Amel Emric, Branko Filipovic, Fedja Grulovic, Hedy Beloucif)</span></div>
<p>"From that moment, I was no longer <strong>in doubt</strong>," Zukic told Reuters news agency. But his effort took him time, money, and a lot of work.</p>
<p>To match the painting, Zukic brought in 130,000 lavender plants in six colors. Plants known for their <strong>aromas</strong> and medicinal uses were also planted. These include sage, echinacea, wormwood and chamomile. Together, they form colorful circles and help recreate the appearance of Van Gogh's painting.</p>
<p>Zukic also planted more trees and created 13 small lakes using water from the area.</p>
<p>Zukic did the work to form the land into the same shape as the painting by himself. He said recreating the painting has helped him better understand artists and the creative problems they face.</p>
<p>"This is the largest representation of The Starry Night, and the result of 20 years of dreams, of living those dreams to make them real," he said.</p>
<p>The park is 10 hectares in size. Zukic said it will show art programs and <strong>promote</strong> central Bosnia's cultural <strong>heritage</strong>. Zukic also wants the park to offer visitors a place to rest and think.</p>
<p>Van Gogh was born in 1853 in the Netherlands and died in 1890 in France.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Daria Sito-Sucic reported this story for Reuters news agency. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>tractor </strong><em>–n.</em> a vehicle with a strong motor that is used to pull things</p>
<p><strong>in doubt </strong><em>–phrase</em> to be in a state of indecision</p>
<p><strong>aroma </strong><em>–n.</em> a pleasing smell</p>
<p><strong>promote </strong><em>–v.</em> to tell people about something in an effort to make it more popular</p>
<p><strong>heritage </strong><em>–n</em>. the traditions, beliefs and objects that make up the history of a people</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
