<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>VOA Special English</title>
        <link>https://www.21voa.com/special_english/</link>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <itunes:category>ESL</itunes:category>
        <itunes:author>VOA</itunes:author>
        <description>美国之音（以下称VOA）的英语节目，按播音速度可分为两种：Standard English （标准英语）和 Special English（特别英语）。

Special English 又叫“慢速英语”，是VOA 专为全世界非英语国家初学英语的听众安排的一种简易、规范的英语广播节目。该节目创始于50年代末期，是VOA 的专家们研究如何与世界各地的英语学习者进行交际的产物。它正式开播于1959年10月。当时只面向欧洲和中东，但由于这个节目适合许多国家英语学习者的需要，所以它的广播对象不久就扩大到世界其他地区，并很快在全世界范围内产生了广泛的影响。现在这个节目对欧洲、非洲和拉丁美洲每晚广播一次，对加勒比地区每晚广播一次（星期天除外），对东南亚广播次数最多，每天上午两次，晚上三次。

30多年来，VOA 为了办好Special English节目，进行了大量的调查研究工作，对播音速度、内容及用词范围都作了具体规定，基本上达到了既能为英语学习者提供信息，又不损害英语本身风格的目的，使之成为VOA 独具特色，拥有最大量听众的节目。

美国著名词汇学家S. B. Flexmer 指明了Special English的三条标准，也就是它所“特别”的地方：

1、它是一种由美国人最常用的1500个基本单词为主体构成的美国英语；

2、它用简短、明晰的句子写作和广播；

3、它以每分钟90个单词的速度，即2/3的Standard English（标准英语）速度进行广播。

Special English的节目可分为两大类：一类是新闻节目；一类是专题节目。

1．新闻节目

VOA Special English 的新闻广播向听众提供世界范围内的政治、经济、军事、外交、国际关系、宗教、天气以及各种重大事件和珍闻奇事等各个方面的信息，每天向东南亚地区广播五次，早上两次，晚上三次，每逢半点播出。

Special English新闻节目每次长约十分钟，大都播出十条左右新闻，近一千个单词，每条新闻多为一分钟，但偶尔也有长达两分钟的要闻。除头条新闻外，每条新闻都由一个电头引导，这样显得结构分明，条理清晰，适宜初学英语的人收听。在节目结束之前，播音员常常用三四句话重播其中三条新闻的提要以加深听众对要闻的印象。

Special English新闻中70%左右的内容与同时整点播出的Standard English新闻相同，但相同新闻的先后次序有所变动。每次节目的开头和结尾大同小异，格式比较固定。

2．专题节目（一）

Special English的专题节目（Feature Programs）,从时间上看，可分为两大类：一是每五分钟一次的专题，二是每十五分钟一次的专题。本节先介绍每项五分钟一次的专题材节目。

Special English五分钟一次的专题材节目安排在Special English新闻节目之后和（或）每十五分钟一次的专题材节目之前播出，每星期播七次。根据内容，可分为三个小类，即：Science Report（科学报道），逢星期一、三、五播出，每天播六遍；Agriculture Report（农业报道），逢星期二、四播出，每天播六遍；Words And Their Stories（词语掌故），逢星期六和星期天播出，每天播五遍。这三个专题材各具特色，具有相对的独立性，听众每听完一个节目，都会获得一个完整的印象。

Science Report（科学报道）这一专题材节目每周向听众介绍三篇有关现代科学技术最新发展情况的报道，涉及物理、化学、天文至高无上理、生物、环卫、心理、教育、医学和计算机等方面。适宜理工科大学生和科技工作者收集信息，积累资料，学习科技英语。

Agriculture Report（农业报道） Agriculture Report是为农业科技工作者和生产者安排的一个专题。它专门报道世界各国，特别是美国现代农业生产的最新成文汇报总务科 学家对农业生产某一方面的研究进展，以及他们对影响农业生产的某一自然现象进行分析和研究的近况。此外，它还经常向听众介绍发展中国家家业生产的一些有益经验等内容。

Words And Their Stories（词语掌故）这一专题节目，旨在向学习英语的听众介绍美国英语中生动有趣的词语和惯用法，并从科学研究和通俗词源学的角度来解释它们的含意、产生的背景及其在使用过程中的演变情况等。它通过讲故事的形式讲解每一个词语。这是VOA Special English中的优秀节目之一，是学习美国英语的极好材料。通过收听这一节目，听众不仅能学到娓娓动听的掌故和地道的美国英语，而且能增加美国的社会文化背景知识，历史传统与现状的了解。

VOA 为了更好地办好这个节目，便于听众收听学习，于1978年编辑出版了一本名为Words And Their Stories的书，共收集一百篇故事，作者是Herbert Sutcliffe, Harold Bermen 及VOA 该节目的部分编辑人员。在每次的实际广播中，播音员都以此书为蓝本，再根据需要对原稿进行适当增删。按每周两个故事计算，此书的一百个故事还不能满足一年的播音需要。于是编辑们就是重播部分词语掌故的同时，不断增加许多新的词语掌故，及时将词源学家的最新研究成果和不断增加的新词汇介绍给听众。收听实践证明，初学者在收听过程中必然会遇到许多人名、地名和一些较难的句子，有时甚至在听完之后还很难理解所播词语的确切含义及其汉语意思，为此，听众可参看1983年由中国对外翻译出版公司出版的该书英汉对照本中的有关部分。

3．专题节目（二）

VOA Special English的专题节目，除上节谈的五分钟一次的以外，还有本节要介绍的每十五分钟一次的节目。这类节目共有七个不同的小专题，以星期为单位循环，每天分四次复播出一个专题，但星期日和星期六的两个专题材每晚只播三遍，每次节目约十分钟，继每次五分钟的专题节目之后播出。

这类专题节目的基本结构是，在特定的伴声中先报告当次节目的名称，并扼要介绍其主要内容，然后播送节目正文。最后，在伴乐声中报告节目主持人和撰稿人的姓名，以邀请听众在下周的这个时间继续收听该节目而结束。

People in America（美国人物志） 这是有关美国历史名人的一个专题节目，每逢星期天晚上播出。它向听众介绍在美国历史上产生过重大影响、起过重要作用、作出了突出贡献的科学、文学、政治、或其他各方面的历史人物。节目一般都对他们的生平事迹进行简要的叙述，对其贡献作出评介，类似人物小传。有的重要人物事迹很多，必须用两次或几次的节目时间进行联播。对这样的节目要坚持收听，才会获得完整的印象。

TThis is America（今日美国） This Is America向听众介绍美国人民的生活、学习、工作和娱乐情况，是英语学习者解美国社会的一条渠道。该专题大都一个节目一个整体，每逢星期一晚播出。

Science in the News（科学新闻） 这一专题材主要对新近的科学技术新闻进行综述或摘要广播。向听众介绍世界各国在自然、医学、疾病、原子能、航天等方面的科研动态、成果、突破性进展及存在的困难。涉及当今世界人们普遍关心的重大问题，如核事故、航天飞机爆炸、自然灾害、环境污染和爱滋病等等。每逢星期二播出，每次播一到五条新闻摘要。

Explorations（自然探索） 每逢星期三晚上，听众可以收听到Explorations这一专题节目。该专题既涉及人类遨游太空、探索原子、研究自身、改造自然的现代技术，也报道发展中国家开发新资源，利用新工艺改善人民生活等方面的成就，其侧重点在各种科技实验和简易实用技术方面。该节目一般安排一段时间播一个系列，每次播出一个主题，以便能将某项新技术的研究和应用的全过程介绍给听众，电台还乐意为感兴趣的听众提供所需的文字材料。

The Making of a Nation（建国史话） 这一专题节目向听众介绍美利坚合众国从十三个殖民地区域到现代工业国的孕育、诞生以及形成超级大国的历史过程，并以历史为线索，特定的历史时期为单位，以重大的历史事件为主题材来叙述各个党派、各届总统和政府的历史作用与贡献。这是每个英语学习者都应了解的基本知识。The Making of a Nation每逢星期四播出。这是个系列节目，坚持收听，则有助于系统了解美国的历史概况。

American Mosaic（美国万花筒） American Mosaic是一个radio magazine（广播杂志）节目。该节目题材广泛、内容丰，展示着美国社会文化生活中比较轻松愉快的生活画面；听众收听该节目就如同在阅读一本图文并茂的杂志。它每次有三到五个小节目，涉及音乐、图书、技术和教育等方面的内容。我们既可以从中欣赏到著名歌唱的优秀歌曲，对美国音乐有所了解，又可以获取一些生动有趣的现代美国社会生活知识，随着播音员那亲切悦耳的声音步入美国风景如画的大好河山；同时还能听到世界各地的听众提出的有关英语语方文学等方面的问题和电台的解答。

American Stories（美国故事） 这一专题材节目安排在每星期六晚上播出。这样能使听众在学习和工作之余，得以轻松一下头脑。我们可以通过这一美国文学的“窗口”，接触各种流派、各类名家的文学作品。了解美国英语的时代特色，欣赏、学习美国人民运用语方的技巧，并从那些佳作名篇中获得艺术享受。该节目对短篇故事采取一次播一篇的方式，对中、长篇小说则先进行简写加工，再分几次播出全文。在播出故事正文之前，播音员常常先介绍故事的主要情节。对需要分几次节目时间播出的中长篇，在播第二或以后各部分之前，主持人还先重述已播部分的故事梗概，以唤起听众的回忆，使故事听起来更加连贯。</description>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          <item>
            <title>Study: ‘Super Jupiter’ Planet Takes 100 Years to Orbit Star (2024/8/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/study-super-jupiter-planet-takes-100-years-to-orbit-star.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Astronomers say they have observed a new <strong>exoplanet</strong> that orbits far away from its star although it is a large and massive planet.</p>
<p>An international group of researchers said they learned new things about the planet after examining data from the James Webb Space Telescope. The telescope is operated by the American space agency NASA.</p>
<p>The gas giant, which has been named Epsilon Indi A b, was first <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/exoplanet-catalog/epsilon-indi-a-b/">discovered</a> in 2019. It is also known as a “super Jupiter,” meaning it is similar to Jupiter in our own solar system, but more massive.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This illustration provided by the Max Planck Institute for Astronomy in July 2024 depicts a cold gas giant orbiting a red dwarf. (T. M&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;252;ller (MPIA/HdA) via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-c0ba-08dcafdbe324_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This illustration provided by the Max Planck Institute for Astronomy in July 2024 depicts a cold gas giant orbiting a red dwarf. (T. M<i>&amp;#</i>252;ller (MPIA/HdA) via AP)</span></div>
<p>Scientists estimate the exoplanet's <strong>diameter</strong> is about the same as Jupiter's, but it is about six times more massive. The team said the planet has an atmosphere rich in hydrogen like Jupiter's.</p>
<p>Epsilon Indi A b is estimated to be about 12 light-years away from Earth. A light year is the distance light travels in a year – about 9.5 trillion kilometers.</p>
<p>International researchers led by Germany's Max Planck Institute examined new telescope images of Epsilon Indi A b. They said they learned the massive exoplanet orbits the star Epsilon Indi A, which is part of a three-star system.</p>
<p>The scientists said one surprising discovery was that the exoplanet seems to take at least 100 years to orbit its star and possibly as many as 250 years. The research shows Epsilon Indi A b orbits its star at a distance equal to 15 times the distance from the Earth to our own sun.</p>
<p>The researchers said they were able to “directly” observe the gas giant by using a tool on the James Webb to block the light of the planet's main star. The team was then able to identify the exoplanet as a bright spot of infrared light.</p>
<p>The new findings recently appeared <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07837-8">in a study</a> in the publication <em>Nature</em>.</p>
<p>Scientists estimate the planet and star are about 3.5 billion years old. That is 1 billion years younger than our own solar system.</p>
<p>Elisabeth Matthews is an astrophysicist at the Max Planck Institute for Astronomy. Matthews led the research. She told The Associated Press in an email the exoplanet appears to be older and brighter than had been thought.</p>
<p>The team noted the planet's star is so bright that it can be seen with the unaided eye from the Southern Hemisphere.</p>
<p>But Matthews noted that nothing in the newly collected data suggests that Epsilon Indi A b has the right conditions to support life. “This is a gas giant with no hard surface or liquid water oceans," she said.</p>
<p>Matthews said studying worlds similar to Jupiter can help scientists understand “how these planets <strong>evolve</strong>” over many, many years.</p>
<p>The first exoplanets outside our solar system were confirmed in the early 1990s. NASA's total count today stands at about 5,690. The majority of these exoplanets were identified through the so-called “<strong>transit</strong>” method. This involves repeatedly observing drops in starlight that might happen when a planet partly blocks light from its star.</p>
<p>Land- and spaced-based telescopes also search for new data on exoplanets, especially ones that might be similar to Earth.</p>
<p>NASA launched the James Webb Space Telescope in 2021. It is currently the largest and most powerful astronomical observatory ever placed in space.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>exoplanet </strong><em>- n.</em> a planet of a star that sits outside the solar system</p>
<p><strong>diameter </strong><em>– n.</em> the length of a straight line through the center of an object or space</p>
<p><strong>evolve </strong><em>– v. </em>to develop gradually over time</p>
<p><strong>transit </strong><em>– v. </em>to pass through or across a place, area of country, on the way to someplace else</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Some Plants Grow for a Long Time to Flower Only Once (2024/8/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/some-plants-grow-for-a-long-time-to-flower-only-once.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Some plants, known as flowering annuals, <strong>bloom</strong> without stop before dying at the end of the year or season.</p>
<p>Other flowering plants, known as perennials, return every year. They can bloom all season, with a lot of <strong>blossoms</strong> at first followed by additional flowers from time to time. Sometimes it is a limited show that can last as little as two weeks.</p>
<p>Biennials flower only in their second year before dying.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This May 19, 2018 image provided by the Lady Bird Johnson Wildflower Center shows American columbo (Frasera caroliniensis) flowers in bloom in Hayesville, North Carolina. (Stephanie Brundage/Lady Bird Johnson Wildflower Center via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/94af6fa6-deb3-4b31-9ade-72a96c54b4c5_cx0_cy7_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This May 19, 2018 image provided by the Lady Bird Johnson Wildflower Center shows American columbo (Frasera caroliniensis) flowers in bloom in Hayesville, North Carolina. (Stephanie Brundage/Lady Bird Johnson Wildflower Center via AP)</span></div>
<p><strong>Monocarpic plants</strong></p>
<p>But there is another group of plants called monocarpics. Their name comes from the Greek words for “single,” mono, and “fruit,” carpos. Monocarpics spend their whole lives growing in size only to produce a single bloom before dying.</p>
<p>Some monocarpic plants have a following among a small group of <strong>gardeners</strong>. These gardeners enjoy what can be years of waiting. They often throw parties to show their plant's once-in-a-lifetime bloom to others.</p>
<p>Other growers, however, can be surprised to discover their 30-year-old plant unexpectedly blooming, only to watch it die immediately afterward.</p>
<p>Flowers have a purpose: to ensure the continuation of their species. After their bloom ends, plants produce seeds that grow into new plants.</p>
<p>Monocarpic plants have just one chance at this. So, as you might imagine, the effort is often<strong> spectacular</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Examples of monocarpics</strong></p>
<p>Take the century plant. Rather than living for 100 years, as its name suggests, it has an average lifespan of just 10 to 30 years. It is a desert plant native to Mexico and Texas.</p>
<p>During its life, it grows to 1.8 meters tall before sending up a giant flower stalk that can reach nine meters, often surprising its owners.</p>
<p>A 19-year-old American columbo plant growing at the North Carolina Botanical Garden in Chapel Hill bloomed this spring. The plants are native to the eastern and central United States. They grow quickly for many years before pushing forth flowers that are up to two meters long.</p>
<p>The monocarpic plant group also includes the fishtail palm. It can grow over 15 meters in height. The trees produce flowers with yellow centers when they are between 10 and 20 years old.</p>
<p>The good news is the show of flowers can last up to 5 years, after which only the blooming <strong>trunk </strong>will die, leaving secondary trunks, if present, to take over. However, fishtail palms grown as houseplants are not likely to bloom.</p>
<p>Bamboo is also a monocarpic plant. But it can take more than 100 years for some bamboo <strong>species</strong> to flower, and even then, sometimes their roots push up new plants.</p>
<p>Bananas, too, are monocarpic, but they reproduce by sending up suckers, or small, new plants, from their roots. After their one-and-only fruit crop is harvested, the main plant is cut to ground level, leaving the suckers to take over.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Jessica Damiano reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>bloom </strong><em>– v.</em> to produce or yield flowers <em>—n.</em> a flower</p>
<p><strong>blossom</strong> <em>—n.</em> a flower <em>—v.</em> to produce flowers</p>
<p><strong>gardener</strong> <em>–n.</em> a person who raises and keeps plants for flowers and for food</p>
<p><strong>spectacular </strong>–<em> adj.</em> describes the quality of being unusual, notable, or entertaining</p>
<p><strong>trunk</strong><em> -- n.</em> the main part of a tree apart from limbs and roots</p>
<p><strong>species</strong><em> – n.</em> a category of biological classification ranking immediately below the genus or subgenus</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers: New Blood Tests Help Doctors Identify Alzheimer’s Disease (2024/8/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202408/researchers-new-blood-tests-help-doctors-identify-alzheimer-s-disease.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 August, 2024</span><br/>
<p>New blood tests could help to identify, or <strong>diagnose</strong>, Alzheimer's disease faster and with more <strong>accuracy</strong>, researchers reported recently. However, some of the tests for the brain-wasting disease appear to work better than others.</p>
<p><strong>New tests, new drugs </strong></p>
<p>Doctors can confirm Alzheimer's in a patient if they find one of the disease's main signs: the development, or buildup, of a sticky protein called beta-amyloid. Currently, doctors use brain imaging or a special test known as a spinal tap to look for beta-amyloid buildup. Brain imaging is hard to get and spinal taps are painful.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A doctor points to PET scan results that are part of a study on Alzheimer's disease at Georgetown University Hospital, on Tuesday, May 19, 2015, in Washington. (AP Photo/Evan Vucci, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a199d0f1-3a06-4cff-81e0-ee533dd240c7_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A doctor points to PET scan results that are part of a study on Alzheimer's disease at Georgetown University Hospital, on Tuesday, May 19, 2015, in Washington. (AP Photo/Evan Vucci, File)</span></div>
<p>Instead, many patients are diagnosed based on their behavior and <strong>cognitive</strong> exams.</p>
<p>Now, labs have begun offering blood tests that can show some signs of Alzheimer's. Scientists are excited about the possibilities that the tests offer.</p>
<p>But the tests are not widely used yet because there is little data to guide doctors about which kind to order and when. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has not officially approved any of them, and few patients have insurance coverage for such tests.</p>
<p>“What tests can we trust?” asked Dr. Suzanne Schindler of Washington University in St. Louis. Schindler is part of a research project examining the tests. While some tests are very accurate, Schindler said, “other tests are not much better than a flip of a coin.”</p>
<p>More than 6 million people in the United States and millions more around the world have Alzheimer's, the most common form of dementia. Its usual signs, or “biomarkers,” are amyloid plaques and abnormal tau protein that leads to tangles that damage <strong>neurons</strong>.</p>
<p>New drugs such as Leqembi and Kisunla can slow the disease a little. The medicines remove amyloid from the brain. But these drugs only work in the early part, or stage, of Alzheimer's progression. Few patients get the costly brain scans and invasive spinal taps that could show early stage Alzheimer's.</p>
<p>Even specialists struggle to tell if Alzheimer's or something else is to blame for a patient's problems.</p>
<p>Schindler said she sometimes has patients “who I am convinced have Alzheimer's disease and I do testing and it's negative.”</p>
<p>A limited number of doctors have carried out blood tests for Alzheimer's in carefully controlled research settings. However, a new study of about 1,200 patients in Sweden shows they also can work in doctors' offices.</p>
<p>The findings suggest the blood tests may be more helpful for general care doctors. They see many more cases of people with memory problems than specialists do. However, general care doctors have fewer diagnostic tools.</p>
<p>In the study, patients who visited either a general care doctor or a specialist for memory problems got an early diagnosis using traditional exams. They gave blood for testing and got confirmatory spinal taps or brain scans.</p>
<p>Blood testing is far more accurate, Lund University researchers reported recently at the Alzheimer's Association International Conference in Philadelphia. They said that the primary care doctors' first diagnosis was 61 percent accurate and the specialists' first diagnosis 73 percent. However, the blood test was 91 percent accurate, their study showed. The Journal of the American Medical Association published the study.</p>
<p><strong>Different biomarkers</strong></p>
<p>Dr. John Hsiao of the National Institute on Aging said the new tests measure different biomarkers in different ways.</p>
<p>Doctors and researchers should only use blood tests proven to have a greater than 90 percent accuracy rate, said Alzheimer's Association chief science officer Maria Carrillo.</p>
<p>Carrillo and Hsiao agreed that the blood tests most likely to provide that accuracy measure what is called p-tau217. Schindler helped lead an unusual direct comparison of several kinds of blood tests that came to the same finding. The Foundation for the National Institutes of Health financed the work.</p>
<p>That kind of test measures a form of tau that <strong>correlates</strong> with how much plaque buildup someone has, Schindler explained. A high level signals a strong likelihood the person has Alzheimer's. A low level strongly suggests Alzheimer's is not the cause of a patient's thinking problems.</p>
<p>Several companies are developing p-tau217 tests.</p>
<p><strong>Who should use blood tests for Alzheimer's? </strong></p>
<p>In the United States, only doctors can order the blood tests from labs. The Alzheimer's Association is working on policy suggestions and several companies plan to seek FDA approval, which would clarify correct use.</p>
<p>For now, Carrillo said doctors should use blood testing only in people with memory problems, after checking the accuracy of the kind they order.</p>
<p>Especially for primary care physicians, “it really has great potential to help them in sorting out who to give a reassuring message and who to send on to memory specialists,” said Dr. Sebastian Palmqvist of Lund University. Palmqvist led the Swedish study with Lund's Dr. Oskar Hansson.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p>And I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Lauran Neergaard reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>diagnose </strong><em>– v.</em> to identify a disease from its signs and symptoms</p>
<p><strong>diagnosis</strong><em> – n.</em> the act of identifying a disease from its signs and symptoms</p>
<p><strong>accuracy</strong> <em>– n.</em> the quality of being precise or correct</p>
<p><strong>cognitive</strong> <em>– adj.</em> of or relating to thinking, reasoning, or remembering</p>
<p><strong>neuron</strong> <em>– n.</em> a cell that is the fundamental functional unit of nervous tissue transmitting and receiving nerve impulses</p>
<p><strong>correlate</strong> <em>– v.</em> to bear mutual relations</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>First Online Child Safety Bill Passes US Senate (2024/8/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/first-online-child-safety-bill-passes-us-senate.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">31 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The U.S. Senate has approved the nation's first major legislation aimed at protecting children from internet harms.</p>
<p>Two bills passed the Senate by a vote of 91-3 on Tuesday. But the measures will also need to be passed by the U.S. House of Representatives to become law. It is currently unclear whether the House will approve the bills in the future.</p>
<p>One bill is known as the Kids Online Safety Act, or KOSA. The other is called the Children's Online Privacy Protection Act (COPPA 2.0).</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE — Isabella Cimato, 17, from left, Arianna Schaden, 14, and Sofia Harrison, 15, check their phones at Roosevelt Field shopping mall in Garden City, N.Y., on July 27, 2015. (AP Photo/Seth Wenig, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-697c-08dcb163b3e2_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE — Isabella Cimato, 17, from left, Arianna Schaden, 14, and Sofia Harrison, 15, check their phones at Roosevelt Field shopping mall in Garden City, N.Y., on July 27, 2015. (AP Photo/Seth Wenig, File)</span></div>
<p><strong>What do the measures do?</strong></p>
<p>The KOSA bill requires technology companies to take steps to provide a “duty of care” to protect young users. This legal term covers a range of steps businesses need to take in an effort to “prevent and <strong>mitigate</strong>” harm to children. Such harms include <strong>bullying</strong> and violence, as well as online information related to suicide, eating disorders and substance and sexual abuse.</p>
<p>The bill known as COPPA 2.0 is designed to increase privacy rules related to children. The bill bans some targeted advertising to kids online. It also bars data collection on children without their knowledge or approval. And it gives parents and young users the ability to remove personal information from social media services.</p>
<p>In addition, the bills would require companies to permit minors to <strong>opt out</strong> of product tools that use activity history to predict and suggest additional content to keep users online for long periods.</p>
<p><strong>How will they be enforced?</strong></p>
<p>The bill empowers state attorney general representatives to enforce most parts of the laws. However, the “duty of care” part cannot be enforced by state attorneys general. That change was made after concerns were raised that some states may seek to block information related to <strong>LGBTQ</strong> issues or reproductive rights.</p>
<p>Wider enforcement will be dealt with by the Federal Trade Commission (FTC), which will help decide what kinds of content is “harmful” to children.</p>
<p><strong>Who supports the measures?</strong></p>
<p>KOSA and COPPA 2.0 are being supported by a wide range of nonprofits, technology <strong>accountability</strong> organizations and parental rights groups. In addition, the bills have been supported by major groups representing American doctors and teachers.</p>
<p>Some well-known technology companies – including Microsoft, X and Snap – have also expressed support. Meta, which owns Facebook, Instagram and WhatsApp, has not publicly expressed strong support or opposition to the measures. Meta has said in the past it is not completely against some government <strong>regulation </strong>of social media.</p>
<p><strong>Who opposes the legislation?</strong></p>
<p>Some technology industry groups and the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) have criticized the measures. They have suggested that differing definitions of what is considered harmful to children could result in minors being blocked from important information. Such information could include LGBTQ issues, reproductive rights or vaccines.</p>
<p>Some changes were made earlier to the legislation in an effort to overcome these concerns, but some critics said those did not go far enough. "They made improvements, but not enough," said Democratic Senator Ron Wyden of Oregon. He was one of three senators who voted against the bills. He recently told reporters, "I still think it is going to harm a lot of LGBTQ kids because of the way it's going to make it difficult for them to get information.”</p>
<p><strong>Can the legislation pass the House?</strong></p>
<p>Josh Golin is executive director of Fairplay, a nonprofit group working to protect children from online marketing and other possible harms. He told The Associated Press before the Senate vote that he is “very hopeful” the bills will eventually be passed by both houses of Congress.</p>
<p>“The reason it has not come to a vote yet is that passing legislation is really hard, particularly when you're trying to regulate one of the, if not the most powerful industry in the world,” Golin said.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters, Agence France-Presse and the European Commission.</em></p>
<p><strong>_________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>mitigate</strong><em> - v.</em> to reduce the harmful effects of something</p>
<p><strong>bully </strong><em>– v.</em> to purposefully frighten someone who is smaller or weaker than you</p>
<p><strong>opt out </strong><em>– v. </em>to choose not to be part of an activity or to stop being part of it</p>
<p><strong>LGBTQ </strong><em>– n. </em>lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, and queer/questioning one's sexual or gender identity</p>
<p><strong>accountable </strong>– <em>adj.</em> being responsible for one's own actions and being able to explain those actions</p>
<p><strong>regulate </strong>–<em> v. </em>to control an activity or process, especially by using rules or laws</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Italy’s Historic Trains Draw Visitors to Less Popular Areas (2024/8/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/italy-s-historic-trains-draw-visitors-to-less-popular-areas.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">31 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>As it moves across central Italy, an old train pulling <strong>carriages</strong> from the 1930s and 1950s crosses the forests of the Majella National Park and the Abruzzo highlands.</p>
<p>Across 100 kilometers, the Park Railway, also known as the Italian Transiberian, travels through valleys and tunnels and over old bridges called viaducts. It offers visitors a view of small, rural and hidden villages in the country.</p>
<p>It was the first of some 1,000 kilometers of rail line to have re-opened under a project by Fondazione FS, part of the state-controlled national rail company.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A passenger travels on board of a vintage train that departed from Sulmona on the way to Palena, Italy July 21, 2024. (REUTERS/Antonio Denti)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/88ef9117-d77a-4fac-98c3-f78d3a9017cb_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A passenger travels on board of a vintage train that departed from Sulmona on the way to Palena, Italy July 21, 2024. (REUTERS/Antonio Denti)</span></div>
<p><strong>“Timeless tracks” </strong></p>
<p>The project called "Timeless <strong>tracks</strong>" aims to take visitors to forgotten parts of Italy instead of the popular cities.</p>
<p>"These are tracks that have lived through different eras, they have carried soldiers to the front, cows to <strong>pasture</strong>... they were mistakenly considered unproductive during the 1960s and 70s but are now once again of value," Luigi Cantamessa, who heads Fondazione FS, told Reuters.</p>
<p><strong>Inspired</strong> by train travel in Switzerland, the project now carries 45,000 visitors a year across its 13 lines. Fondazione FS expects to open two new ones by 2026, both in the southern area of Sicily.</p>
<p>"What were considered to be the dry branches of Italy's train network, have now proved to be the green shoots," Cantamessa added.</p>
<p>Norma Pagiotti is a 28-year-old from Florence, Italy traveling on the train with two friends.</p>
<p>Pagiotti said, "People are used to cities and places, like Florence, that everyone knows.. but then there are other areas that need to be discovered. (This) is the right kind of <strong>tourism</strong> that does not spoil the <strong>authenticity</strong> of places,"</p>
<p>Caterina Quaranta, from southern Italy, used the term “nostalgic," meaning a longing for a past time, to describe riding the train.</p>
<p>“The train reminds me of my youth, I feel a bit nostalgic for the things of the past, which were simpler, now everything is fast, short-lived," Quaranta said.</p>
<p>Laura Colaprete, a local guide, said the trains draw Italians and foreigners, families and children, younger people who get off to hike and ride bicycles, and older people "who have time to spare.”</p>
<p><strong>The trip </strong></p>
<p>After climbing up almost 1,000 meters in<strong> altitude</strong>, the Transiberian's first stop is in Palena, a hill-top town known for its beautiful views over the national park.</p>
<p>Traditional folk music accompanies people getting off the train, with local foods such as lamb skewers and soft pancakes and products by local artisans awaiting them at the station.</p>
<p>"The train helps several small towns around here. This line was a dead line before," said Gino Toppi, 60, as he helped his wife with the food stand in the small station.</p>
<p>Milan's Bocconi University recently estimated that for every dollar spent by passengers on tickets, as much as three more are spent on food, tours and other purchases. The rail ticket costs between $32 and $76.</p>
<p>That helps to support the economy of villages that have long lost population due to the declining birth rate and younger people leaving for the bigger cities.</p>
<p>"There certainly are <strong>benefits</strong>, this is a way to show my products," said Annalisa Cantelmi, an herbalist, or herb grower. "These tourists are slowly discovering these new territories, their traditions and people," she added.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Giulia Segreti reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>carriage</strong> <em>– n.</em> a wheeled vehicle</p>
<p><strong>track</strong> <em>– n.</em> the parallel rails of a railroad</p>
<p><strong>pasture </strong><em>– n.</em> land used for grazing</p>
<p><strong>inspire</strong> <em>– v.</em> to influence, move, or guide</p>
<p><strong>tourism</strong> <em>– n.</em> the practice of traveling for fun</p>
<p><strong>authenticity</strong> <em>– n. </em>not false or imitation; true to one's own personality, spirit, or character</p>
<p><strong>altitude</strong><em> – n.</em> the vertical elevation of an object above a surface (such as sea level or land)</p>
<p><strong>benefit</strong> <em>– n.</em> something that produces good or helpful results or effects</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>In the US, Disasters Strike All Over the Country (2024/8/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/in-the-us-disasters-strike-all-over-the-country.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">31 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>When it comes to disasters in the United States, most people think of major storms and earthquakes that hit coastal areas. But a study from the nonprofit Rebuild by Design and New York University says disasters happen everywhere across the country.</p>
<p>The study looks at information on hundreds of federally declared disasters from 2011 to about 2021. It also examines the $60 billion that the Federal Emergency Management Agency, or FEMA, gave state and local governments.</p>
<p>The study finds that eight of the nine <strong>counties </strong>with the most federally declared disasters since 2011 are in Kentucky. One is in Vermont. These counties have several times the number of disasters as the national average of three in the past 13 years.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Buildings and homes are flooded in the aftermath of Hurricane Laura near Lake Charles, La., on Aug. 27, 2020. (AP Photo/David J. Phillip, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-7d69-08dcafccaab7_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Buildings and homes are flooded in the aftermath of Hurricane Laura near Lake Charles, La., on Aug. 27, 2020. (AP Photo/David J. Phillip, File)</span></div>
<p>A federal disaster is declared when a bad natural event is so costly that local government officials do not believe they can recover. So, the governor of the state asks the president to declare a disaster which frees federal money set aside for this purpose.</p>
<p>Amy Chester is director of Rebuild by Design. She said, “California and Louisiana and I would say now even Texas, Florida, for sure, they soak up all the oxygen when you hear about these giant storms.”</p>
<p>Chester added, “But what you're not hearing about are these storms that are happening all the time, and that's just becoming ...regular to places like Vermont.” Chester also noted Tennessee, Oklahoma, Mississippi, Iowa and Alaska as having a lot of disasters.</p>
<p>“We want to show that climate change is already here,” Chester said of the data, which covers 2011 to 2023. It does not include heat waves, lack of rain or diseases, like COVID-19.</p>
<p>Before she studied the data, Chester said she thought Vermont would be safe from climate change. Instead, it has many disasters.</p>
<p>“It's awful,” Chester said. “It just keeps happening to them.”</p>
<p>Vermont recently flooded again because of heavy rain from Hurricane Beryl.</p>
<p><strong>Disasters in unexpected places</strong></p>
<p>In July 2022, at least 40 people died, and 300 homes were damaged when a flood struck Floyd County in eastern Kentucky. It was the 13th time in 12 years that the federal government declared the rural county a disaster.</p>
<p>Judge Robbie Williams is the administrator of the county with about 35,0000 people. He said, “After that flood, I had 500 homeless people looking at me, ‘Judge what are we going to do'?” Williams added, “It's <strong>overwhelming</strong> and it's just a matter of time before it happens again.”</p>
<p>Then, in 2023, Floyd County was declared a disaster again for the 14th time since 2011. But Floyd County is not the nation's most disaster-<strong>prone</strong> county. Neighboring Johnson County has had 15 disasters declared by FEMA.</p>
<p>Floyd County's government received more than $35 million in FEMA disaster aid since 2011. But that is not a lot of money compared to other counties hit by hurricanes.</p>
<p>Five counties received more than $1 billion in FEMA aid. Three of them are in New York state. They are led by Manhattan's New York County, which got $8.9 billion after being struck by Hurricane Sandy in 2012.</p>
<p>FEMA notes that flooding is the most common disaster in the U.S. Since 2011, FEMA has paid more than $41 billion in aid following hurricanes, the most of any kind of disaster.</p>
<p>Susan Cutter is with the Hazards Vulnerability and Resilience Institute at the University of South Carolina. Cutter said: “What the data tell us is that the frequency and severity of disasters at local-state <strong>scales</strong> is increasing with rural, suburban, and urban places being affected nationwide.” She was not involved in Chester's research. But she added, “More needs to be done.”</p>
<p><strong>Geography and regulations</strong></p>
<p>In Floyd County, Judge Williams said geography and government <strong>regulations</strong> make it tough for the area. The county is in the mountains. People live in the narrow valleys, he said. When it rains, the creeks and rivers overflow.</p>
<p>“We're seeing historic levels of flooding,” Williams said. “It's only getting worse.”</p>
<p>Environmental regulations bar local officials from <strong>dredging</strong> the creeks. <strong>Silt</strong> from the mountains keeps building up, Williams said. Some creeks were about six meters deep but are now shallow enough to walk across, he said.</p>
<p>"The problem is there is nowhere for the rain to go,” Williams said.</p>
<p>Samantha Montano is a professor of emergency <strong>management</strong> at the Massachusetts Maritime Academy. Montano said what is more important is how state and local policies create or reduce the risk of future disasters.</p>
<p>In Floyd County, the local government is using FEMA money to buy the homes of 150 residents to move them out of a flood area, but some do not want to leave, Williams said.</p>
<p>“Until we get those homes out of these flood ways...we're still going to have these issues,” Williams added.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins. And I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Seth Borenstein reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>county</strong> <em>–n.</em> an area in a state that has its own local government</p>
<p><strong>overwhelming</strong> –adj. an amount too big to deal with effectively</p>
<p><strong>scale</strong> <em>–n. </em>a level or size of something in relation to other, similar things that are bigger or smaller</p>
<p><strong>regulation</strong> <em>–n.</em> a rule or law that governs a kind of activity or industry</p>
<p><strong>disaster-prone </strong><em>–adj.</em> likely to have a disaster</p>
<p><strong>dredging </strong><em>–n.</em> the process of removing mud from the bottom of a river or canal to make it deeper so boats can pass</p>
<p><strong>silt </strong><em>–n.</em> dirt that is carried by rivers and streams to lower areas of land</p>
<p><strong>management </strong><em>–n.</em> the effort of overseeing and controlling a business, government office or organization</p>
<p><strong>creek </strong><em>–n.</em> a small stream</p>
<p><strong>shallow</strong> <em>–adj.</em> not deep</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>European Parent Groups Aim to Ban Smartphones for Teens (2024/7/31)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/european-parent-groups-aim-to-ban-smartphones-for-teens.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">30 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>If parents say "no" when a child asks for a smartphone, the response they are likely to hear is, "Everyone has one. Why can't I?"</p>
<p>But what would happen if the child's friends did not have a mobile phone either?</p>
<p>That is the way that some parents in Europe are thinking.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A boy plays with his father's phone outside school in Barcelona, Spain, on June 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Emilio Morenatti)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-7c49-08dca76866aa_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A boy plays with his father's phone outside school in Barcelona, Spain, on June 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Emilio Morenatti)
</span></div>
<p>They are concerned by evidence that smartphone use among young children threatens their safety and mental health. They believe that the more parents join their movement, the more powerful their ideas become.</p>
<p>Parents in Spain, Britain and Ireland are using social media groups on services like WhatsApp and Telegram to talk about their plans. They want to keep smartphones out of schools. But for their plan to work, other parents have to refuse to buy children the devices before — or even into — their teenage years.</p>
<p>Elisabet García Permanyer got involved after she talked with another parent in a Barcelona park. Last year, she started a social media group to share information on the dangers of the internet with families at her children's school.</p>
<p>The group, called "<strong>Adolescence</strong> Free of Mobile Phones," quickly grew and now includes over 10,000 members. The most involved parents are asking other parents to agree not to get their children smartphones until they are 16.</p>
<p>"When I started this, I just hoped I would find four other families who thought like me, but it <strong>took off </strong>and kept growing, growing and growing," García Permanyer said. "My goal was to try to join forces with other parents so we could <strong>push back </strong>the point when smartphones arrive. I said, 'I am going to try so that my kids are not the only ones who don't have one.'"</p>
<p><strong>Spain</strong></p>
<p>Police and public health experts have also been voicing concerns about the kind of materials that children can see on their mobile devices. Spain's government took note of the problem and banned smartphones from elementary schools in January. Now they can only be turned on in secondary school, which starts at age 12, if a teacher deems it necessary for an educational activity.</p>
<p><strong>Britain</strong></p>
<p>In Britain last year, a 16-year-old girl named Brianna Ghey was killed by two teenagers. Her mother demanded that social media on smartphones be limited for children under 16.</p>
<p>Mother Daisy Greenwell, who lives in the area of Suffolk, England, and a friend, Clare Reynolds, set up a social media group called Parents United for a Smartphone-Free Childhood. It grew quickly and an organizer said it now has groups in every British county.</p>
<p><strong>Ireland</strong></p>
<p>In Greystones, Ireland, eight primary school leaders, or principals, wrote to parents, asking them not to buy their students smartphones. Then the parents themselves voluntarily signed written agreements, promising not to let their young children have the devices.</p>
<p>Thirty-eight-year-old Christina Capatina is a Greystones parent of two young daughters. She signed the agreement and said there were almost no smartphones in schools this school year.</p>
<p><strong>Unity is powerful</strong></p>
<p>Studies from Spain, Britain, and Ireland show that by the time children are 12, most have smartphones. In Spain, 25 percent of children have a cellphone by age 10, and almost 50 percent by age 11. At 12, this share rises to 75 percent. British media <strong>regulator</strong> Ofcom said 55 percent of children in Britain owned a smartphone between ages eight and 11, with the figure rising to 97 percent by age 12.</p>
<p>Over recent years, organizations, governments, and parents have been reporting that smartphone use by children is linked to <strong>bullying</strong>, mental health problems and loss of the <strong>focus</strong> necessary for learning. China moved last year to limit children's use of smartphones. France has a ban on smartphones in schools for children aged six to 15.</p>
<p>The possible dangers have produced school bans on smartphones and online safety laws. But those measures do not deal with what children do outside of school with mobile phones. Parents and schools that have pushed for changes in their communities saw that it became possible the moment they understood that they were not alone.</p>
<p>Rachel Harper is principal of St. Patrick's National School in Greystones. Harper wants parents to work with their local school to organize phone bans. She said, "There's a bit more strength that way, in that all the parents in the area are talking about it."</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p>And I'm Mario Ritter.</p>
<p><em>Joseph Wilson and Laurie Kellman reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>adolescence</strong> – <em>n</em>. the period of life when a child develops into an adult</p>
<p><strong>take off</strong> <em>– v. (phrasal) </em>to quickly become very popular</p>
<p><strong>push (something) back</strong> – v. (<em>phrasal) </em>to change (a planned event) to start at a later date or time</p>
<p><strong>bullying <em>–</em></strong><em>n.</em> the act of using threats and force to get others to do what you want them to do</p>
<p><strong>focus</strong> – <em>n. </em>the ability to direct your attention or effort at something specific</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Rising Demand for Cooling Systems in Africa Fuels Environmental Concerns (2024/7/31)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/rising-demand-for-cooling-systems-in-africa-fuels-environmental-concerns.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">30 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Rising demand for cooling systems in Nigeria and other African nations might be making existing pollution problems worse.</p>
<p>Cooling systems use gases called refrigerants. Such gases can affect the atmosphere if they escape. Some of these pollutants have been found to be more harmful than other kinds of <strong>greenhouse gases</strong>.</p>
<p>The Nigerian government has approved restrictions on the release of refrigerant gases into the environment. But enforcement efforts for the laws have been difficult.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A technician positions an R-22 refrigerant on an outdoor air conditioning unit in Lagos, Nigeria, Thursday, July 18, 2024. (AP Photo/Sunday Alamba)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-1223-08dcb09ee993_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A technician positions an R-22 refrigerant on an outdoor air conditioning unit in Lagos, Nigeria, Thursday, July 18, 2024. (AP Photo/Sunday Alamba)</span></div>
<p>Abiodun Ajeigbe leads an air conditioning business for Samsung, West Africa. He told The Associated Press (AP), “Those laws, those rules, nobody enforces them.”</p>
<p>Ajeigbe said one of the biggest problems is a lack of effective education and training about the possible harms of refrigerants. This means many cooling system <strong>installers</strong> might not follow legal requirements when removing old systems or putting new ones in.</p>
<p>Some trained workers do follow environmental rules governing the use of cooling refrigerants. But these kinds of installations cost more.</p>
<p>Industry experts and public records suggest the most common air conditioning systems in Africa use a kind of gas known by the trade name R-22. This refrigerant is said to be less harmful to the environment than older cooling chemicals known as chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs). CFC's have largely been removed from most modern cooling systems. That change was put in motion by the 1987 Montreal Protocol environmental treaty.</p>
<p>A document from the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) says R-22 is considered many times more damaging to the world's climate than carbon dioxide. For example, about one-half kilogram of R-22 is said to equal one ton of carbon dioxide, the most common greenhouse gas.</p>
<p>However, while carbon dioxide can stay in the atmosphere for more than 200 years, R-22 stays for about 12 years. R-22 cooling equipment is not as energy <strong>efficient</strong> as some other systems. And most of the electricity used to power R-22 coolers in Africa requires carbon-based fuels.</p>
<p>Nigeria is planning to ban R-22 refrigerants by January 1, 2030. But without enough enforcement, that target is not likely to be met, Samsung's Ajeigbe told the AP.</p>
<p>Some cooling systems use a group of refrigerants called hydrofluorocarbons (HFCs). These do not harm the <strong>ozone layer</strong> and are more energy efficient. But HFCs are said to be strong greenhouse gases and account for an estimated 2 percent of all human-caused warming in the atmosphere.</p>
<p>One of the most harmful HFCs, called R-410A, is used in the second most common kind of air conditioners in Africa, the AP reported. Sellers and installers of cooling equipment in Nigeria told the news agency that although HFC systems are less damaging to the environment, they are more costly to operate.</p>
<p>The same issues are affecting countries beyond Nigeria. In Ghana, the cooling industry also struggles to get companies and workers to obey current environmental rules.</p>
<p>Environmental officials in Ghana told the AP that “poor servicing practices” for cooling systems are common across the country. This is largely the result of the public choosing lower-trained installers who might not follow recommended <strong>standards</strong>.</p>
<p>In Kenya, demand for cooling systems is also growing as the population grows and electricity becomes more widely available. Cooling systems using R-22 are still common across the country. But the nation's Environmental Management Authority told the AP there have not been any new imports of the systems since 2021.</p>
<p>Workers dealing with cooling systems and refrigerants are required to get a <strong>license</strong>. But several installation workers told the AP that since such requirements are hard to enforce, environmentally unsafe methods are carried out.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>greenhouse gases</strong><em> - n.</em> gases in the Earth's atmosphere that can trap heat</p>
<p><strong>install </strong><em>– v.</em> put a piece of equipment somewhere and make it ready to use</p>
<p><strong>efficient </strong><em>– adj. </em>working well and not wasting time or energy</p>
<p><strong>ozone layer </strong><em>– n. </em>the layer of ozone high above the Earth's surface that prevents much of the ultraviolet radiation from the sun from reaching Earth's surface</p>
<p><strong>standard </strong>–n. an accepted way of doing something that is agreed upon by industry or government officials</p>
<p><strong>license </strong>–n. official permission to do an activity, such as driving a car, that usually involves a document</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Olympic Triathlon Delayed Because of Seine River Water Quality (2024/7/31)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/olympic-triathlon-event-delayed-because-of-seine-river-water-quality.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">30 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The organization supervising the Olympic triathlon event at the Paris Olympics has postponed the event because of water quality in the Seine River.</p>
<p>However, World Triathlon and city officials are hopeful the event, which includes swimming, bicycling, and running, can start on July 31.</p>
<p>World Triathlon is the sport's governing body, overseeing competitions and safety. Its technical and medical team met with the International Olympic Committee, and city and local French government officials. They decided to postpone the event because of water quality.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A ship sails past reproductions of artworks decorating the banks of the River Seineat the 2024 Summer Olympics, Tuesday, July 30, 2024, in Paris, France. (AP Photo/Vadim Ghirda)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-7c4e-08dcb0b7a1f7_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A ship sails past reproductions of artworks decorating the banks of the River Seineat the 2024 Summer Olympics, Tuesday, July 30, 2024, in Paris, France. (AP Photo/Vadim Ghirda)
</span></div>
<p><strong>How does water quality affect health?</strong></p>
<p>Tests in June showed unsafe levels of E. coli bacteria although results in July showed improvement.</p>
<p>Dr. Nicole Iovine is an infectious disease specialist at the University of Florida in Gainesville.<strong> </strong>She said while most kinds of E. coli are not harmful, high numbers can be dangerous. The presence of E. coli is a sign that human and animal waste is in water. The World Triathlon Federation considers E. coli levels higher than 900 colony-forming <strong>units</strong> per 100 milliliters to be unsafe.</p>
<p>Swimming in water with unsafe levels of bacteria can lead to feeling sick to the stomach and intestinal problems. Swimmers are likely to swallow water, which can lead to diarrhea. The bacteria can also infect the <strong>urinary tract</strong> or open cuts.</p>
<p>Iovine said, “The athletes are young, and they're in the best shape of anybody...But that doesn't mean they can't get sick from these things.”</p>
<p>Officials are hoping for sunny weather. The ultraviolet light in sunlight can kill bacteria and higher temperatures bring levels of E. coli and other bacteria in the river water to within safe limits.</p>
<p>French Sports Minister Amélie Oudéa-Castéra told French news media on Monday that officials are “absolutely <strong>serene</strong> about all this.” She said plans put in place to control the bacterial levels in the river have worked, but the weather was beyond their control.</p>
<p><strong>Why is the Seine River polluted?</strong></p>
<p>Swimming in the Seine River has been banned for more than 100 years. But Olympic officials wanted to have the swimming part of the triathlon event in the city's famous waterway. So, Paris officials spent $1.5 billion to clean up the Seine.</p>
<p>Paris is an ancient city. And like many old cities, it has what is known as a combined <strong>sewer</strong> system. That means the city's wastewater and storm water flow through the same pipes. When heavy rainfall happens, the pipes carry the extra “storm water” along with wastewater into the river instead of a sewage treatment center. As a result, untreated human waste goes directly into the river after heavy rains.</p>
<p>Iovine said bacteria, viruses and parasites get into the water through human waste. But other things too.</p>
<p>“It's also wildlife — rodents, for example. When it rains a lot, all of that from those animals can end up in the Seine,” she said.</p>
<p>To prevent the wastewater overflow, Paris officials built a huge <strong>basin</strong> next to the Austerlitz train station. It is supposed to capture extra rainwater to keep waste from flowing into the river. They also rebuilt parts of the sewer system and improved water treatment centers. However, heavy rain can still overwhelm the system.</p>
<p>The rain that took place during the weekend of the Olympic opening ceremonies filled the basin by 20 percent. So, officials said the pollution was likely coming from wastewater <strong>upstream</strong>.</p>
<p>If the water quality does not improve, officials are considering holding the event on August 2.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Pat Graham, Kate Brumback, and Devna Bose reported for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted them for VOA Learning English with additional AP material. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>unit </strong>–n. one amount of something</p>
<p><strong>urinary tract</strong> <em>–n. (medical) </em>the tubes that carry liquid waste from the kidneys out of the body</p>
<p><strong>serene</strong> <em>–adj.</em> peaceful and untroubled</p>
<p><strong>sewer </strong>–n. pipes used to carry wastewater</p>
<p><strong>basin </strong>–n. an area or container that holds water</p>
<p><strong>upstream </strong>–adj. the part of a river or stream that is closer to the source (opposite: downstream)</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Heat Can Be Good or Bad for Your Garden (2024/7/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/heat-can-be-good-or-bad-for-your-garden.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">29 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Summer brings very high temperatures to many parts of the United States. That can be both good news and bad news for <strong>gardens</strong> and gardeners.</p>
<p>Jessica Damiano writes about gardening for the Associated Press. She keeps a garden in New York, where summer temperatures can reach 32 degrees Celsius.</p>
<p>Recently, Damiano repeated a difficult truth for gardeners: weather has a lot to do with success, but it is out of our control.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image shows a nearly 6-foot tall tomato plant growing on Long Island, N.Y. on July 9, 2024. (Jessica Damiano via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-389f-08dca2a4ff28_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image shows a nearly 6-foot tall tomato plant growing on Long Island, N.Y. on July 9, 2024. (Jessica Damiano via AP)</span></div>
<p>There are measures that plant lovers can take to ease the effects of hot summer weather. One measure is to spread a thick layer of <strong>mulch</strong> over plant roots. This can help keep plant roots cool and will preserve water, or moisture, in the soil. When watering plants, use a lot of water and let it <strong>soak</strong> deep into the ground. You can water your garden less often if you provide a few deep soaks regularly. Light watering causes roots to spread near the surface of the soil.</p>
<p>If there is too much sun for young plants, don't be afraid to give them shade. Damiano said she has been known to place an umbrella on the ground to protect <strong>tender</strong> plants from the sun.</p>
<p><strong>The good news about heat</strong></p>
<p>Heat is not all bad for a garden. Some plants love heat. Damiano grows a kind of tomato called Big Boy. The plant, she says, has grown quickly in the summer heat. Zucchini, a form of squash, also does well.</p>
<p>Heat can also keep harmful insects away. Cabbage, onion and corn <strong>maggots</strong> prefer cooler weather and struggle in the heat. So do cutworms, which can be especially destructive to gardens.</p>
<p>Damiano says some of her <strong>perennial</strong> flowering plants have bloomed two weeks earlier than usual. For this reason, she decided to add late-blooming plants to her garden to ensure a good crop of flowers.</p>
<p>She reported that her hydrangea plants have never looked better. She has 12 of them, and they are blooming well. However, Damiano said that might not be the result of hot weather this summer. Instead, unusually heavy rains late last summer and fall may have helped <strong>buds</strong> to form. A smaller number of those buds were damaged by the <strong>mild</strong> winter weather. The result is a lot of blooms.</p>
<p><strong>And the downside</strong></p>
<p>Some plants suffer in the heat, including impatiens. The small flowers are not doing well.</p>
<p>But what Damiano dislikes are the creatures that become more active and numerous when temperatures rise.</p>
<p>Mosquitos are most active at sunrise and sunset, but they can bite at any time. Although heat theoretically slows their activity, hot conditions can help mosquitoes spread.</p>
<p>Damiano advises to prevent water from collecting in places around the garden or to put something called Bti in wet areas where mosquitos might lay eggs. Bti is a kind of bacteria that produces a substance poisonous to young mosquitos and a few other flying insects. It is natural, and the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) says it is safe for people and most other insects and animals as well.</p>
<p>Ticks present another problem. The creatures bite people and spread disease. Cold weather kills them, but they do well in hot weather. Normally found in the eastern U.S. and on the Pacific coast, ticks appear to be spreading to new areas. The EPA even said, “Climate change has <strong>contributed</strong> to the expanded <strong>range</strong> of ticks.”</p>
<p>Wearing long sleeves and pants and using special chemicals to keep ticks away can help protect against their bites.</p>
<p>Earwigs also like heat and humidity. They can make holes in plant leaves, Damiano said. But the “pincher bugs” also eat aphids, which are enemies of the garden. So are thrips and spider mites.</p>
<p>In addition to insects, heat and humidity are good conditions for slugs. These creatures have soft slimy bodies, and they eat plants.</p>
<p>Luckily, there are easy ways to control these garden problems. One is to spray soapy water onto soft-bodied insects like aphids, spider mites, thrips and whiteflies.</p>
<p>As for slugs, salt will kill them but is not good for garden soil. They do not like sharp surfaces, however, so adding crushed eggshells can be an effective control method. The eggshells break down and nourish the plants over time.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Jessica Damiano wrote this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>garden</strong><strong> </strong><em>–n. </em>a place where plants are raised for their beauty or as food</p>
<p><strong>mulch</strong> <em>–n.</em> usually organic material that is in small pieces and is used to cover the ground to prevent drying and enrich the soil</p>
<p><strong>soak </strong><em>–v.</em> to get very wet</p>
<p><strong>tender </strong><em>–adj.</em> very soft</p>
<p><strong>maggot </strong><em>–n.</em> the larval stage of flies and similar insects</p>
<p><strong>perennial </strong><em>–adj.</em> lasting for many years</p>
<p><strong>bud </strong><em>–n.</em> a growth on a plant from which a new branch or fruit will grow</p>
<p><strong>mild </strong><em>–adj.</em> not strong or sharp</p>
<p><strong>contribute </strong><em>–v.</em> to be involved in the cause of some outcome</p>
<p><strong>range </strong><em>–n.</em> the area where something is found or where it lives</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Research Farm Raises Pigs to Produce Organs for Humans (2024/7/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/us-research-farm-raises-pigs-to-produce-organs-for-humans.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists are raising pigs to produce human organs at a specialized research farm in the American state of Virginia.</p>
<p>A medical company called Revivicor runs the farm in the rural community of Blacksburg. The area is surrounded by the Blue Ridge Mountains. Workers at the farm follow intense measures in an effort to prevent infection and disease spread.</p>
<p>About 300 pigs of different ages live on the research farm. Some animals raised there have already provided the first genetically changed pig organs ever <strong>transplanted</strong> into humans.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A pig stands in a pen at the Revivicor research farm near Blacksburg, Va., on May 29, 2024, where organs are retrieved for animal-to-human transplant experiments. (AP Photo/Shelby Lum)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-78e8-08dcaa98599d_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A pig stands in a pen at the Revivicor research farm near Blacksburg, Va., on May 29, 2024, where organs are retrieved for animal-to-human transplant experiments. (AP Photo/Shelby Lum)</span></div>
<p>Individuals working at the center must undergo a series of safeguards aimed at preventing infections in the organs grown for people.</p>
<p>Matthew VonEsch is an executive with United Therapeutics, the parent company of Revivicor. He told The Associated Press the research farm was designed with the goal of protecting the pigs “against <strong>contamination</strong> from the environment and from people.”</p>
<p>David Ayares is the founder and chief scientific officer of Revivicor. He described the farmed pigs to the AP as “<strong>precious</strong> animals” because of their ability to help save human lives.</p>
<p>The research farm looks very different from a traditional animal farm. This is because of the strong security and cleanliness measures needed. It was built to meet U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) safety requirements.</p>
<p>For example, pigs living at the farm only drink water that is highly <strong>filtered</strong>. All food also gets disinfected.</p>
<p>Revivicor's farm aims to produce human organs that can be used in scientific experiments or actual transplants.</p>
<p>There is currently a great need in the U.S. for organ transplants. Thousands of people are waiting for a donor organ. But experts say there will never be enough human donors to fill that need.</p>
<p>Using animal-grown organs for human transplants is one possible way to deal with the shortage.</p>
<p>Scientists use genetic engineering methods to grow organs in animals. These organs behave more like human ones than animal ones, which reduces the chances that the body will reject the animal organs. Teams have been working for many years to grow more humanlike organs in pigs.</p>
<p>So far in the United States, four “<strong>compassionate</strong> use” transplants have happened. These cases involved last-minute experiments to transplant pig organs into humans who faced life-threatening conditions. Two transplants involved hearts and two involved kidneys. Revivicor provided both of the hearts and one of the kidneys.</p>
<p>All four patients died within a few months. Still, experts say each transplant offered the possibility for valuable, real-life research. The goal is to one day attempt to put pig organs into human transplant patients who are not quite as sick.</p>
<p>Revivicor's Ayares said the company is aiming to produce organs in the pigs that closely meet the size and needs of each patient. The idea is that such organs will perform better than human-donated organs because they are younger and free of disease.</p>
<p>Ayares added that transplant doctors who have received organs from Revivicor's farm say, “Oh my god, that's the most beautiful kidney I've ever seen.” He said the reaction is the same when they get “a pink healthy happy heart from a young animal.”</p>
<p>Officials at Revivicor say the biggest difficulties they face include overcoming the rejection of pig organs in humans and preventing animals from carrying unknown infection risks. Scientists try to deal with the rejection issue by employing different engineering methods to make the pig organs as humanlike as possible.</p>
<p>Genetic changes are made to the pig eggs that Revivicor receives. The engineered eggs are then <strong>nurtured</strong> in the lab with the hope of producing a healthy embryo. The embryos are then taken to the research farm to be put inside living pigs.</p>
<p>It is expected to take years of experimentation to prove whether animal organ transplants will work long-term in human patients. But if the efforts succeed, United Therapeutics plans to open additional research farms to produce up to 2,000 organs a year.</p>
<p>Ayares said the efforts are currently at a point where several studies have suggested “there's no immediate rejection” of the genetically engineered pig organs. He added, “The next two or three years are going to be super exciting.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>transplant</strong><em> – v.</em> to perform a medical operation in which an organ or other part that has been removed from the body of one person is put into the body of another person</p>
<p><strong>contaminate </strong><em>– n.</em> to make something dirty or poisonous</p>
<p><strong>precious </strong><em>– adj. </em>very important or valuable</p>
<p><strong>filter </strong><em>– v.</em> to pass a liquid or gas through a piece of equipment in order to remove solid pieces or other substances</p>
<p><strong>compassionate </strong><em>– adj. </em>showing compassion: a feeling of sympathy for others who are suffering</p>
<p><strong>nurture </strong><em>– v. </em>to care for or encourage the growth of something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>A Shared Video Raises Concerns about AI and Politics (2024/7/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/a-shared-video-raises-concerns-about-ai-and-politics.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">29 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A video shared on the social media service X is raising concerns about the power of artificial intelligence (AI) to mislead voters, with American elections about three months away.</p>
<p>The video causing concern shows U.S. Vice President Kamala Harris saying things she did not say. Harris is the likely Democratic Party presidential nominee. The video was changed using AI tools.</p>
<p>The video gained widespread attention after tech billionaire Elon Musk shared it on X last week. Musk did not write in his posting that the video was a parody. A parody is any work that <strong>imitates</strong> someone or something, with the purpose of being funny.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Tesla and SpaceX CEO Elon Musk addresses the European Jewish Association's conference in Krakow, Poland, Jan. 22, 2024." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-d89a-08dcaff0bf5e_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Tesla and SpaceX CEO Elon Musk addresses the European Jewish Association's conference in Krakow, Poland, Jan. 22, 2024.</span></div>
<p>People who saw the video thought it had the appearance of a real political advertisement created by the Harris campaign. But the video's <strong>audio</strong> has another voice that sounds like Harris but is not.</p>
<p>Harris began her presidential campaign after U.S. President Joe Biden said he would no longer seek reelection. Biden had already gained enough delegates in primary elections to be the party's candidate.</p>
<p>In the video shared by Musk, the voice that sounds like Harris says, “I, Kamala Harris, am you Democrat candidate for president...” It says Harris is a “<strong>diversity</strong> hire” because she is a woman and is not white. It also says she does not know the “first thing about running the country.” The video uses real “Harris for President” images. It also contains real video of things Harris has said in the past.</p>
<p>Mia Ehrenberg is a Harris campaign spokesperson. Ehrenberg wrote in an email to the Associated Press (AP): “We believe the American people want the real freedom, opportunity and security Vice President Harris is offering; not the fake <strong>manipulated</strong> lies of Elon Musk and Donald Trump.”</p>
<p>The widely shared video is an example of how AI-generated images, video and audio have been used to make fun of people or to mislead the public. AI-generated materials have increasingly targeted politics.</p>
<p>High-quality AI tools are now easier to find and use. Some people say there are not enough federal rules to control their use. Currently, states and social media services set rules for using AI for political purposes.</p>
<p>The fake video of Harris raises questions about how people should deal with videos that have been changed when they are parodies or <strong>satire</strong>.</p>
<p>A YouTube user known as Mr Reagan first shared the video. That user wrote on both YouTube and on X that the video was manipulated and that it was a parody.</p>
<p>Chris Kohls, the YouTube user known as Mr Reagan, pointed an AP reporter to another YouTube video he made early Monday in answer to the reaction of the parody video. In the new video, Kohls confirmed he used AI to make the fake ad and argued that it was clearly a parody.</p>
<p>However, Musk shared the parody ad by writing, “This is amazing.” He also included a “laughing” <strong>emoji</strong>. He did not clearly state that the video is a parody.</p>
<p>More than 123 million people have seen the video through Musk.</p>
<p>Musk's X social media service has a <strong>feature</strong> called “community notes.” It permits users to add <strong>context</strong> to messages that might be misleading. Some people using the feature have suggested that Musk's message should have said that the video was a parody. They say it might have violated X's policies, which bar “out-of-context media that may deceive or <strong>confuse</strong> people and lead to harm.”</p>
<p>The X policy makes exceptions for <strong>memes</strong> and satire, as long as such postings do not cause “significant confusion...”</p>
<p>The United States Congress has not passed a law on AI and politics. But federal agencies have made efforts to do so. The National Conference of State Legislatures says more than one-third of American states have passed their own laws <strong>regulating</strong> the use of AI in campaigns and elections.</p>
<p>The U.S. elections will take place on November 5.</p>
<p>I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>Ali Swenson reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>parody </strong>–n. any artistic work that imitates the style or behavior of another person with the purpose of being funny</p>
<p><strong>diversity</strong> <em>–n. </em>the condition of including many different kinds of things</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_Wgj54Mu9"><strong>manipulated</strong></a> <em>–adj.</em> changed in some way for a specific purpose</p>
<p><strong>satire </strong>–n. a way of using humor to show that someone or something is foolish</p>
<p><strong>feature </strong>–n. a quality, part or ability of a product that is worth noting</p>
<p><strong>context </strong>–n. the additional information necessary to understand a piece of writing, video, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_2alUJ6IZ">sound</a> or an image</p>
<p><strong>confuse </strong>–v. to use language or images to prevent people from understanding something<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>meme </strong>–n. an image that spreads quickly and becomes popular with certain people</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: New Evidence Suggests Earth-like Exoplanet May Hold Liquid Ocean (2024/7/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/study-new-evidence-suggests-earth-like-exoplanet-may-hold-liquid-ocean.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Researchers say new telescope observations suggest an Earth-like planet outside our solar system may hold a large liquid ocean.</p>
<p>The exoplanet is known as LHS 1140 b. Astronomers believe it sits about 48 light years away from Earth. A light year is the distance light travels in a year – about 9.5 trillion kilometers.</p>
<p>The research – led by astronomers at the University of Montreal in Canada – shows the possibility the exoplanet might hold the right conditions to support some form of life. A <a class="wsw__a" href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ad5afa">study</a> explaining the findings recently appeared in <em>The Astrophysical Journal Letters</em>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="New research led by the University of Montreal suggests exoplanet LHS 1140 b may contain a liquid ocean. This illustration depicts the exoplanet (left), Jupiter's moon Europa (center) and Earth (right). (B.Gougeon/University of Montreal)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-b1bc-08dcad92d46e_cx1_cy0_cw98_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">New research led by the University of Montreal suggests exoplanet LHS 1140 b may contain a liquid ocean. This illustration depicts the exoplanet (left), Jupiter's moon Europa (center) and Earth (right). (B.Gougeon/University of Montreal)</span></div>
<p>The study is based on observations collected in December 2023 by the James Webb Space Telescope. The American space agency NASA operates the orbiting observatory.</p>
<p>Researchers combined the information from the James Webb with existing data to make new estimates for the exoplanet's mass and size. These suggest that LHS 1140 b is “a promising super-Earth ice or water world,” the University of Montreal <a class="wsw__a" href="https://exoplanetes.umontreal.ca/en/astronomers-find-surprising-ice-world-in-the-habitable-zone-with-webb-data/">said</a> in a statement.</p>
<p>Some past studies had suggested the exoplanet might be a gas giant, also known as a mini-Neptune. But the researchers said the new study provides evidence that LHS 1140 b is more likely a super-Earth, a rocky planet bigger than Earth.</p>
<p>The new research supports a NASA-led study from October 2023 that <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/science-research/planetary-science/astrobiology/nasa-some-icy-exoplanets-may-have-habitable-oceans-and-geysers/">suggested</a> at least 17 observed exoplanets could hold oceans of liquid water. That study noted that sometimes water from these oceans likely breaks through large pieces of ice to form <strong>geysers</strong>.</p>
<p>Scientists had already identified LHS 1140 b as being within its star's “<strong>habitable</strong> zone.” Exoplanets found within this zone are believed to have temperatures that would permit water to exist in liquid form.</p>
<p>Measurements made by the James Webb data suggest the exoplanet “is less dense” than expected for a rocky, Earth-like body. The researchers estimated that 10 to 20 percent of LHS 1140 b's mass might be made up of water. The possibility of a large liquid ocean would be found on the side of the planet always facing the star that it orbits.</p>
<p>The new data collected by the James Webb showed the exoplanet might also have a nitrogen-rich atmosphere. This differs from earlier research that suggested a possible atmosphere that was mostly hydrogen.</p>
<p>Charles Cadieux is a doctoral student at the University of Montreal's Trottier Institute for Research on Exoplanets. He was the lead writer of the study.</p>
<p>Cadieux said in a statement, “Of all currently known temperate exoplanets, LHS 1140 b could well be our <strong>best bet</strong> to one day indirectly confirm liquid water on the surface of an <strong>alien</strong> world beyond our solar system.” He noted that if the study's findings can be confirmed, the data would represent “a major <strong>milestone</strong>” in the search for exoplanets that could possibly support life.</p>
<p>René Doyon is a project scientist at the University of Montreal. He helped lead the research. He <a class="wsw__a" href="https://exoplanetes.umontreal.ca/en/astronomers-find-surprising-ice-world-in-the-habitable-zone-with-webb-data/">said</a> more observations will be needed to confirm the current study's findings. “The current <strong>hint </strong>of a nitrogen-rich atmosphere <strong>begs</strong> for confirmation with more data,” Doyon said.</p>
<p>He estimated that at least one more year of observations will be needed “to confirm that LHS 1140 b has an atmosphere.”</p>
<p>The process of confirming whether carbon dioxide is present in the atmosphere and liquid water exists on the surface would likely require several years of observations, Doyon noted.</p>
<p>Ryan MacDonald is a NASA Sagan Fellow in the University of Michigan's Department of Astronomy who helped examine the James Webb data. He <a class="wsw__a" href="https://exoplanetes.umontreal.ca/en/astronomers-find-surprising-ice-world-in-the-habitable-zone-with-webb-data/">said</a>, “This is the first time we have ever seen a hint of an atmosphere on a habitable zone rocky or ice-rich exoplanet.”</p>
<p>With further data collection and investigation, MacDonald noted there is a good possibility “we might just have found evidence of air on this world.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from the University of Montreal, the University of Michigan and NASA. </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>geyser</strong><em> - n.</em> a hole in the ground from which hot water and steam come out</p>
<p><strong>habitable </strong><em>– adj.</em> able to support life</p>
<p><strong>best bet </strong><em>– idiom. </em>the action that is most likely to be successful</p>
<p><strong>alien </strong><em>– n. </em>relating to creatures from another planet</p>
<p><strong>milestone </strong><em>– n.</em> an important event in the development or history of something</p>
<p><strong>hint </strong><em>– n. </em>to suggest or indicate something in an indirect way</p>
<p><strong>beg </strong><em>– v. </em>to make a very strong and urgent request</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Insect Hurts Tunisia's Prickly Pear Industry (2024/7/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/insect-hurts-tunisia-s-prickly-pear-industry.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A small insect is hurting Tunisia's prickly pears, an important source of money for the North African country's economy.</p>
<p>Bassem Sahnoun, a farmer struggling to deal with the insect problem, used the term “insomnia,” meaning an inability to sleep, to describe the issue.</p>
<p>"Our biggest fear, which has caused me insomnia, is the fear of the cochineal insect that threatens our harvest," he said.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A view shows a prickly pear plantation infested with cochineal insects, in Sfax, Tunisia July 19, 2024. (REUTERS/Jihed Abidellaoui)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/c2411c63-98fe-4fd0-a3ae-02c4d574a276_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A view shows a prickly pear plantation infested with cochineal insects, in Sfax, Tunisia July 19, 2024. (REUTERS/Jihed Abidellaoui)</span></div>
<p>The insect is known to some as the prickly pear cochineal. Farmers and experts say it has damaged large areas and caused concerns about its economic effects since it was first discovered in the country in 2021.</p>
<p>The bug gets the<strong> sap</strong> from cactus pads, causing yellowing and eventual death of the plants.</p>
<p>Agricultural expert Faouzi Zayani inspected dying prickly pear trees. He said, "The cochineal insect affects the prickly pear tree. As you can see, the trees are dying, and consequently, we are losing the <strong>essence</strong> of things, which is the <strong>cultivation</strong> of prickly pears.”</p>
<p>Zayani said the insect was first discovered in Mexico. "It was present there, and they treated it and had prevention methods," he added. "Then it spread to Morocco in 2015. This insect also came to Tunisia in October 2021 in the city of Mahdia."</p>
<p>Zayani estimates that prickly pears represent about 12 percent of Tunisia's agricultural land, making it second only to olive trees in agricultural wealth.</p>
<p>The pears cover approximately 600,000 hectares and are an important source of money for thousands of people, particularly women who harvest and sell the fruit.</p>
<p>Sahnoun told Reuters, “This is our livelihood, it requires a lot of labor, and it's not just the farmer who <strong>benefits</strong> from it.”</p>
<p>The Tunisian government and international organizations are now taking steps to try to help deal with the insect's effects.</p>
<p>The Food and Agriculture Organization started a $500,000 emergency project to introduce biological control methods such as ladybugs, which are hunters of the insect.</p>
<p>The Tunisian Ministry of Agriculture is promoting <strong>sustainable</strong> control measures, including changes in agricultural methods, <strong>pruning</strong>, and cleaning in production areas.</p>
<p>"We must have a sustainable solution for the cochineal insect. This situation should not continue in this way," said Naima Mahfoudhi, an official at the ministry of agriculture.</p>
<p>At his farm, Sahnoun takes measures to clean and protect his healthy prickly pear trees. But it will be a difficult job if the crisis continues and keeps drying up prickly pear trees.</p>
<p>"It starts at the bottom of the tree," he said.</p>
<p>Selma Jridi, who owns prickly pear trees, says the problem is out of her control. She said, "God's will <strong>prevails</strong>, this is God's judgment... “</p>
<p>I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>Jihed Abidellaoui reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>sap</strong> <em>– n.</em> the fluid part of a plant</p>
<p><strong>essence</strong> <em>– n.</em> the individual, real, or ultimate nature of a thing</p>
<p><strong>cultivation</strong><em>– n.</em> the act of preparing for the raising of crops; the act of helping plants grow</p>
<p><strong>benefit</strong><em> – v.</em> to receive help or an advantage</p>
<p><strong>sustainable</strong> <em>-- adj.</em> Of or relating to a method of harvesting or using a resource so that the resource is not permanently damaged</p>
<p><strong>prune</strong><em> – v.</em> to cut off or cut back parts of a plant <strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>prevail</strong> <em>-- v.</em> to be or continue in use; to gain ascendancy through strength</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>In Tokyo, Brewer Uses Unusual Methods to Make Japan’s Sake (2024/7/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/in-tokyo-brewer-uses-unusual-methods-to-make-japan-s-sake.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A small space in Tokyo houses a container of <strong>fermenting sake</strong>.</p>
<p>The bacteria in the 670-litre container will take more than two weeks to turn the rice and water inside into Japan's traditional alcoholic drink.</p>
<p>But the bacteria are not only alive, they are listening too, said<strong> brewer</strong> Yoshimi Terasawa.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Yoshimi Terasawa, chief brewer at Tokyo Port Brewing, sprinkles the spores of koji fungus over cooled steamed rice as a part of brewing sake, a traditional rice wine, at the brewery in Tokyo, Japan July 9, 2024. (REUTERS/Kim Kyung-Hoon)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/be62b8c7-0eab-4d5e-94ba-a7facaeec365_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Yoshimi Terasawa, chief brewer at Tokyo Port Brewing, sprinkles the spores of koji fungus over cooled steamed rice as a part of brewing sake, a traditional rice wine, at the brewery in Tokyo, Japan July 9, 2024. (REUTERS/Kim Kyung-Hoon)</span></div>
<p>He suggested the kind of music coming from a loudspeaker below the tank determines how the drink will taste.</p>
<p>"The micro-organisms inside are activated by the <strong>vibrations</strong>, and the taste changes," said the 63-year-old chief brewer of Tokyo Port Brewing.</p>
<p>Music is among the unusual methods Terasawa is using at the only sake brewery in the heart of the capital city.</p>
<p>Fit into a narrow building, the small operation employs methods that promise to help the environment.</p>
<p>The brewery employs special machinery and processes that use less energy and labor than a traditional brewery in the countryside.</p>
<p>"Making sake on this kind of smaller scale makes it easier to keep the production environment constant," Terasawa said. He has 45 years of experience in the industry.</p>
<p>The company produces about 30 kiloliters of sake each year. That is enough to fill almost 42,000 720-ml bottles.</p>
<p>But changing tastes and Japan's aging population have reduced demand.</p>
<p>The government says the number of sake breweries has decreased two-thirds from its high point in the 1970s to just over 1,100 now.</p>
<p>More than half of sake breweries are not making a profit.</p>
<p>Other difficulties that sake breweries face include a shortage of workers as brewers retire, increased fuel costs and problems with the rice supply.</p>
<p>Terasawa said his small brewery offers an example of how to deal with those difficulties.</p>
<p>The process starts on the fourth floor, where he and an employee steam the rice for 70 minutes.</p>
<p>Then they let gravity move the rice through openings in the floors and ceilings to a <strong>mold-application</strong> room on the third floor. Fermentation, using <strong>tap water</strong>, takes place on the second level. Finally, the sake is put into bottles at ground level.</p>
<p>"In the future, small breweries like this will have a great deal of <strong>merit</strong>," Terasawa added.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Rocky Swift and Kyung Hoon Kim reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>ferment</strong><em> – v.</em> to undergo fermentation (the anaerobic breakdown of an energy-rich compound (such as a carbohydrate to carbon dioxide and alcohol) by the action of microorganisms (such as bacteria or yeast)</p>
<p><strong>sake</strong> <em>– n. </em>a Japanese alcoholic beverage of fermented rice</p>
<p><strong>brewer </strong>–<em> n.</em> a person who creates (or brews) alcoholic drinks</p>
<p><strong>vibration </strong><em>– n.</em> a quivering or trembling motion</p>
<p><strong>mold </strong><em>– n.</em> a growth produced especially on damp or decaying organic matter</p>
<p><strong>application</strong> <em>– n.</em> an act of administering or laying one thing on another</p>
<p><strong>tap water</strong> <em>–n</em>. water that comes from ordinary pipes and is not treated in any special way</p>
<p><strong>merit</strong> <em>–n.</em> value or worth</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Let's Talk about 'Going South' (2024/7/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/let-s-talk-about-going-south.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">27 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Today, we talk about those times when things do not go as planned. All the planning in the world does not guarantee that your plans will happen the way you had planned.</p>
<p>Things can happen that are outside of your control. To talk about those times when things go <strong>awry</strong>, American English has two directional expressions: <u>go south</u> and <u>go sideways</u>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Passengers crowd the international flights departure area of Rome's Fiumicino airport, July 19, 2024. Many flights were delayed or canceled due to the worldwide internet outage. This unexpected event caused many trips to " borgia="" go="" gregorio="" photo="" south.="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-5457-08dcacc51d98_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Passengers crowd the international flights departure area of Rome's Fiumicino airport, July 19, 2024. Many flights were delayed or canceled due to the worldwide internet outage. This unexpected event caused many trips to "go south." (AP Photo/Gregorio Borgia)</span></div>
<p><strong>To go south</strong></p>
<p>Let's start with <u>go south</u>. If something <u>goes south</u>, it stops working or falls apart. It can also mean that something decreases in value or loses quality. We often use it to describe a situation where everything has gone wrong.</p>
<p>If your career <u>goes south</u>, you need to look for a new job. If your new computer <u>goes south</u>, it stops working. If a relationship <u>goes south</u>, the two people are heading toward a <strong>breakup</strong>.</p>
<p>And if a trip <u>goes south</u>, one bad thing after another happens. You miss your plane, your passport gets stolen, and the hotel loses your <strong>reservation</strong>. That makes for a vacation that has <u>gone south</u>.</p>
<p>Now, let's hear two friends use this expression.</p>
<p><em>A: So, how is your friend's new bakery doing? She opened it earlier this year, right?</em></p>
<p><em>B: She did. But then she ran into trouble. Her investor pulled out. And then her head baker quit. So, her business <u>went south</u> pretty quickly after that. </em></p>
<p><em>A: Oh, I'm sorry to hear that. But I'm not surprised. You need a lot of money up front to start a business. And for a bakery ... you definitely need a baker.</em></p>
<p><em>B: Well it didn't help that another bakery with lower prices opened down the street. Her business was bound to <u>go south</u> after that. </em></p>
<p><strong>To go sidesways</strong></p>
<p><strong>Sideways </strong>is another direction you don't want your projects or efforts to go. As a direction word, sideways means to go to either side – not forward or backward.</p>
<p>As an <strong>idiomatic</strong> expression, to <u>go sideways</u> also means things do not go as planned. But this expression can be used a little differently from <u>going south</u>. Often when things <u>go sideways</u>, they go wrong in strange ways. In other words, things get <strong>weird</strong>.</p>
<p>Sometimes you want things to <u>go sideways</u>. For example, a good story often <u>goes sideways</u>. You think it's going to go in one direction but then there is a <strong>plot twist</strong>. Situations change and the story goes in an unexpected direction. Used this way, <u>going sideways</u> is a good thing.</p>
<p>But what about on a family camping trip? Let's hear this expression used in that situation.</p>
<p><em>A: How was your family camping trip? </em></p>
<p><em>B: It was okay. But some really strange things happened. Nature things...</em></p>
<p><em>A: Tell me more. What happened?</em></p>
<p><em>B: Well, the first night a raccoon stole all my food. The second night while I slept, spiders spun webs all over my tent while I slept. And then on the third day while I was swimming in the lake, a fish bit me!</em></p>
<p><em>A: That IS a lot of weird nature stuff. I didn't even know fish could bite.</em></p>
<p><em>B: Me neither! But I guess on a camping trip that's <u>gone sideways</u> ... anything is possible!</em></p>
<p>And that's the end of this Words and Their Stories.</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>awry </strong><em>-adv. </em>off the correct or expected course</p>
<p><strong>breakup </strong><em>-n. </em>to end a romance</p>
<p><strong>reservation </strong><em>-n. </em>an arrangement to have something (as a motel room or a seat on a plane) held for one's use</p>
<p><strong>sideways </strong><em>-adj. or -adv. </em>from one side viewed the stage sideways : with one side forward turn sideways : to one side</p>
<p><strong>idiomatic </strong><em>-adj. </em>of, relating to, or conforming to <strong>idiom</strong> <em>-n. </em>an expression that cannot be understood from the meanings of its separate words but must be learned as a whole</p>
<p><strong>weird</strong> <em>-adj. </em>very unusual or strange</p>
<p><strong>plot twist </strong><em>– n. </em>a writing device that introduces a big change in the direction or expected outcome of the plot in a story</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>New French Stamps Smell Like Baguettes (2024/7/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/new-french-stamps-smell-like-baguettes.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">26 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Visitors to Paris for the Olympics can now send a smell of France home with their picture <strong>postcards</strong> and letters.</p>
<p>The smell comes from a special stamp showing the country's famous bread called <strong>baguette</strong>. The sweet smell, however, may remind you of a French <strong>bakery</strong> more than an actual baguette.</p>
<p>The stamp was released in May for the day of Saint-Honoré, the <strong>saint</strong> of bakers. Postal worker Clarisse Briend said the baguette makes people think of France. And she hopes visitors will pick up the stamps along with other official Paris 2024 postcards and stamps. The stamp sells for more than $2 at area post offices.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="Visitors to Paris for the Olympics may pick up some unusual stamps. If you rub the stamp, you can smell the freshly baked bread that is famous in France." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-6476-08dcabf5f6b4_tv_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">Visitors to Paris for the Olympics may pick up some unusual stamps. If you rub the stamp, you can smell the freshly baked bread that is famous in France.</span></div>
<p>Pia Sch<i></i>246;ndienst is a German visitor coming from the Netherlands with her family. She bought the stamps and said she could not smell anything, but her son could smell a chocolate <strong>croissant</strong>.</p>
<p>"You just have to rub the stamp here like this with your nails," Clarisse Briend said. "You can smell the bread, the baguette."</p>
<p>At the Léonie Bakery in Paris, baker Yasin Robin smelled the stamp and said, “It smells like flan,” a dessert but not the baguette itself. Chief baker Harlem Gbodialo said he could smell something sweet on the stamp while the shop manager Jeanne Barrère compared it to vanilla.</p>
<p>Regardless, Gbodialo added that the bakery expects to have many visitors at their shop near the Champs <i></i>201;lysées. “On top of that the Olympic Games are going to start next week, so it'll boost our influence in terms of clients, and also the weather's been nicer lately, so all the <strong>factors</strong> are coming together to have a great period of Olympic Games, a great party for everyone,” he added.</p>
<p>Eating baguettes is not as popular as it once was, but France still makes around 16 million per day - or nearly 6 billion a year. One story explains that Napoleon Bonaparte's bakers created the long shape to make it easier for his troops to carry.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Elena Rodriguez, Nathan Frandino, and Helena Williams reported this story for Reuters. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>postcard </strong><em>– n. </em>a card on which a message may be sent by mail without an envelope and that often has a picture on one side</p>
<p><strong>baguette</strong> – n. a long, thin loaf of bread</p>
<p><strong>bakery</strong> – <em>n</em>. a place where bread, cakes, cookies, and other baked foods are made or sold</p>
<p><strong>boost </strong>– <em>v.</em> increase</p>
<p><strong>croissant</strong> – <em>n.</em> a type of roll that has a curved shape and that is usually eaten at breakfast</p>
<p><strong>factor </strong>– n. something that helps produce or influence a result; one of the things that cause something to happen</p>
<p><strong>saint</strong> – <em>n</em>. a person who is officially recognized by the Christian church as being very holy because of the way he or she lived</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Methodology, Strategy, Plan (2024/7/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/methodology-strategy-plan.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Bassam in Yemen about the usage of three words connected with project management.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-3609-08dcabe8a7c5_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>In project management, we face three confused terms: “methodology”, “strategy”, and “plan”. Could [you] please help me to know how [to] differentiate among them and use each one in a correct way?</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>Thank you for writing to us, Bassam. I'm happy to answer this question.</p>
<p>The main difference between these words is how general or <strong>specific </strong>they are. “Plan” usually has the most general meaning, “strategy” tends to be more specific, and “methodology” is the most specific.</p>
<p>In its most general sense, “plan” means the same thing as “goal.” For example, a company may have a “plan,” or “goal,” to expand its business into more countries. And the company's “strategy” is the specific steps it takes to reach that goal.</p>
<p>However, we sometimes use “strategy” in a general way. We could say the company's “strategy” is to expand its business into more countries. But when we use “strategy” in this general sense, we tend to express the reasons for the “strategy.” So, we might say:</p>
<p><em>The company hopes its <u>strategy</u> to expand into more countries will <u>lower production costs</u>.</em></p>
<p>Note that “plan” can sometimes be specific. For example, if police need to catch a criminal, they can list the things they need to do to catch that person. The police can call this list their “plan.”</p>
<p>Now let's look at the most specific term, “methodology.” This word often <strong>refers</strong> <strong>to</strong> the details of how people do research. For example, when scientists write research papers, they include a <strong>section</strong> called “methods,” or “methodology.” This section explains exactly how the scientists did their experiments or other research.</p>
<p>Project management methodology can differ depending on the goals or kind of research needed. For example, marketing researchers study what kind of products people want to buy, while companies study manufacturing costs to help them set prices.</p>
<p>So, it is important to remember that the words “plan” and “strategy” can be general or specific. And “methodology” is the specific method we use to help our “strategy” or “plan” be successful.</p>
<p>We hope today's lesson is helpful, Bassam.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, do you have a question about American English? Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>specific </strong><em>-adj. </em>exact or particular</p>
<p><strong>refer to </strong><em>-v. </em>relate to or point to the meaning or details of something</p>
<p><strong>section </strong><em>-n. </em>a part of a whole</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Indonesia's Nickel Mining Hurting Forests (2024/7/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/indonesia-s-nickel-mining-hurting-forests.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">25 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Indonesia aims to be the world's top nickel supplier. But its efforts to produce nickel have seriously harmed the country's forests, nonprofit groups say.</p>
<p><strong>Natural resources </strong></p>
<p>Indonesia is the world's third most rainforest-covered country, home to giant forest flowers and rare wild animals such as orangutans and elephants.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="A boat cruises past the Indonesia Weda Bay Industrial Park in Central Halmahera, North Maluku province, Indonesia, Saturday, June 8, 2024. Indonesia has been building out a vast industry for nickel. (AP Photo/Achmad Ibrahim)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f44029b7-d80f-4f12-89eb-d8db859fcfbf_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">A boat cruises past the Indonesia Weda Bay Industrial Park in Central Halmahera, North Maluku province, Indonesia, Saturday, June 8, 2024. Indonesia has been building out a vast industry for nickel. (AP Photo/Achmad Ibrahim)</span></div>
<p>Indonesia also has the largest reserves of nickel in the world. The metal lies in <strong>shallow</strong> <strong>deposits</strong> in the rain forest. Mining it is easy when the rainforest is cut down.</p>
<p>Until recently, Indonesia mostly sold its nickel deposits in untreated form. It did not have factories to process the metal. Unprocessed nickel sells for less than the processed product.</p>
<p>Ten years ago, Indonesian officials decided the country should stop selling its resources at such a low cost. Instead, officials said Indonesia would process the metal so it would sell at a higher price. This would result in more job openings, also, officials said.</p>
<p>A large nickel-processing project began. Indonesian President Joko Widodo pushed the project further by building nickel factories, or smelters, near electric vehicle battery factories. In addition to the new nickel plants, coal power plants were built also to serve the new industrial sites.</p>
<p><strong>Forest loss </strong></p>
<p>More than 740,000 square kilometers of Indonesian rainforest have been logged, burned or degraded, since 1950, reports the non-profit research group Global Forest Watch.</p>
<p>But at the sites where developers are building these smelters, the surrounding forest disappears twice as fast, a new study by the Indonesian nonprofit Auriga says.</p>
<p>The new study of rainforest loss, based on government data, shows deforestation rose from an average of 33 square kilometers around each nickel processing plant, or smelter, to 63 square kilometers.</p>
<p>Indonesia plans to build as many as 22 new plants. If plans go through deforestation will likely greatly increase.</p>
<p>“The damage to the environment is <strong>devastating</strong>,” said Timer Manurung of Auriga. “...Rivers are polluted, <strong>mangroves</strong> are cut to develop smelter areas, coastal areas and coral are being damaged by the smelters.”</p>
<p>The waste from coal power plants is another problem, he said. The Associated Press verified the methodology used in the Auriga report.</p>
<p><strong>Effects </strong></p>
<p>The area of Weda Bay is now one of the world's largest nickel production centers. Smelters and coal-fired power plants burn to process nickel ore into material for <strong>batteries</strong> and steel.</p>
<p>The village of Lelilef Sawai is now surrounded by the Weda Bay Industrial Park. There, the deforestation and its effects are clear. Local farmer Librek Loha remains in Lelilef Sawai, refusing to sell the land he has taken care of for forty years. Now orange dust often covers his plants and clean water is often lacking. The plants also grow more slowly, he said.</p>
<p>From his land, he can hear building sounds and see bright orange material flow into the sea. Research shows landslides are far more likely in deforested areas.</p>
<p>Max Sigoro, 54, is a traditional hunter and farmer. Bright lights and noise from construction scare the deer he used to hunt at night. He says he has lost nearly all the means he had to earn a living since the industrial park's growth.</p>
<p>PT Indonesia Weda Bay officials declined to speak to the Associated Press.</p>
<p>The company says it has planted more than 10 square kilometers of new trees. It says it plays an active part in supporting the living standards of local people, offering economic development. And, the industrial zone meets all environmental standards, PT Indonesia Weda Bay says.</p>
<p>The company also says it works to protect water and has launched coral and mangrove planting programs.</p>
<p>The Weda Bay project is just one of the industrial parks criticized by locals nearby. An industrial park on the island of Borneo and other projects in North Maluku are also under community protests.</p>
<p>Perhaps related to these public objections, European companies may be losing interest in nickel from Indonesia.</p>
<p>In recent weeks, the French mining company Eramet and German chemical giant BASF announced they were canceling plans to build a $2.6 billion nickel plant in Indonesia.</p>
<p>Indonesia has been seeking to work more with Tesla, which uses twice as much metal in its total production of batteries than the next highest auto competitor. The amount of nickel Tesla used in 2023 was up a third over the year before. Only 13 percent came from Indonesia last year. But Tesla's 2023 impact report noted Indonesia 18 times and warned the country's nickel will be very important.</p>
<p>Tesla did not answer an AP email requesting information about its use of nickel from Indonesia and deforestation.</p>
<p>Questions to Indonesia's Ministry of Environment and Forestry, Coordinating Ministry of Maritime and Investment Affairs and Ministry of Energy and Natural Resources also went unanswered.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p>And I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>Victoria Milko, Ed Davey, and Camille Fassett reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>shallow</strong> <em>– adj.</em> having little depth</p>
<p><strong>deposit </strong><em>– n.</em> a natural accumulation of something (ore, oil, etc.)</p>
<p><strong>battery</strong> <em>– n.</em> a cell that gives electricity</p>
<p><strong>devastating</strong> <em>– adj.</em> causing great damage or harm</p>
<p><strong>mangrove</strong> <em>– n.</em> tropical maritime trees or shrubs that send out many roots and form dense masses</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Learn about US Presidential Campaigns (2024/7/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/learn-about-us-presidential-campaigns.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Every four years, the United States holds an election for the president in November. This lesson aims to help teachers and learners understand the political processes and expressions used during the election campaign.</p>
<p><strong>The political parties</strong></p>
<p>Let us begin with the expression, political party. In elections, parties organize candidates who share party members' ideas about how government should operate. They try to win elections to gain and keep political power.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Images representing the Republican Party and the Democratic Party in the United States." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-253f-08dc81a74f05_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpeg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Images representing the Republican Party and the Democratic Party in the United States.</span></div>
<p>There are two major political parties in the U.S. They are the Democratic Party and the Republican Party. There are other small political parties at the national level. These include the Libertarian and Green parties.</p>
<p><strong>Primaries and caucuses</strong></p>
<p>Each of the U.S. states and territories holds votes early in the election year. In many states and territories, these votes are called <strong>primaries</strong>. You may know the word “primary” as an adjective meaning “happening or coming first” as in “primary school.” When speaking of elections, it is a noun, but it has a similar meaning – it is the first election in a voting process that takes place over one year.</p>
<p>You might also hear the term <strong>caucus</strong>. A caucus is also a kind of election, but it is held privately by the party and usually does not involve state election officials or equipment. The Iowa caucus was for a long time the first presidential contest during an election year.</p>
<p>In a primary or a caucus, voters choose the party's candidates for local and state offices as well as for national offices. The candidates who get the most votes become the candidates for the election in the fall.</p>
<p>Primaries can be “open” or “closed.” Anyone can take part in an open primary election — even members of another party. Only registered party members can vote in a closed primary.</p>
<p><strong>Delegates</strong></p>
<p>In some states, voters choose delegates in the primaries.<strong> </strong>State party organizations have different rules for choosing them. Delegates are people who will attend their party's convention, or general meeting.</p>
<p>When a delegate is elected to choose a particular candidate, we say the delegate is <strong>pledged</strong> to the candidate. To pledge is to promise something.</p>
<p><strong>Conventions</strong></p>
<p>Each party holds a national convention – a large meeting where the delegates officially <strong>nominate</strong> the candidate that the party supports for the presidential election. The verb “nominate” means to officially choose someone as a candidate for a position. You will hear some other forms of the word in election news.</p>
<p><strong>Nomination</strong></p>
<p>To describe the process of having the delegates choose a candidate, we use the noun form, “nomination.” At the convention, the candidate who gains the majority of delegates is called the “nominee.” The nominee gives a speech to accept the nomination.</p>
<p><strong>The party platform</strong></p>
<p>The party platform is a statement of the ideology of the party and its candidate. At the party convention, the organizing committee shares its platform. The platform is a statement of the policies that the party hopes to put in place during its candidate's term in office.</p>
<p><strong>The campaign trail</strong></p>
<p>Presidential candidates travel the country speaking to voters at a series of events called <strong>rallies</strong>. Reporters use the expression “campaign trail” to describe these events. This is a <strong>metaphor</strong> for progressing along a path toward a goal. The election campaign is sometimes called a “race,” another metaphor comparing the election campaign to a sporting competition.</p>
<p><strong>Debates</strong></p>
<p>Part of the campaign process is for the candidates to debate each other. These are televised events where a reporter asks questions that interest the public and gives each candidate a limited time to answer them. The form of the political debates is not the same as traditional <strong>academic</strong> debates, where teams compete under clear rules and time limits.</p>
<p><strong>Donors</strong></p>
<p>Presidential candidates and others who run for public office must find money to pay for those rallies, television advertising, and campaign workers. A common way to pay for a campaign is to ask for money. People who give to a candidate are donors. The Federal Election Commission makes rules about how much, when, and how donations can be made.</p>
<p><strong>Polls and the Polls</strong></p>
<p>Researchers get the opinions of voters in an effort to guess, or predict, the results of an upcoming election. They do this with <strong>polls</strong>, or public opinion studies. This word has two meanings in the elections. One is where a researcher might ask you about your party affiliation and which candidate you plan to support in a telephone call. Your party affiliation is the party you are registered with or that you support.</p>
<p>The other meaning of “poll” is the place where you go to vote on election day. We can also use “polling place.” Schools, religious centers and public buildings can be polling places. In them, voters <strong>cast </strong>their ballot secretly. That means they fill out their ballot without pressure from others in the room and turn in their ballot to be counted by poll workers.</p>
<p>In the last two election years of 2020 and 2022, people could send in their ballots by mail. But polling places remain important for processing and counting ballots.</p>
<p><strong>Privacy and politics</strong></p>
<p>Now that you have some of the expressions used to talk about the presidential campaign, you should use them with some care. It is not normal to ask someone what party he or she is a member of although many people will offer that information freely.</p>
<p>In some situations, such as among close friends, you will hear Americans talk about the candidates and voice their opinions openly. But when talking with a new <strong>acquaintance</strong> or a stranger, it is best to avoid asking about political affiliation.</p>
<p>Also, know that some workplaces have rules against political activity, and, in government, most political activity is not legal although people often share their opinions.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins. And I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Jill Robbins wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><em>_________________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>primary</strong> – <em>n.</em> an election in which members of the same political party run against each other for the chance to be in the general election</p>
<p><strong>caucus </strong><em>–n.</em> a political party meeting used to decide candidates and often delegates that is private and only open to party members</p>
<p><strong>pledge </strong>– <em>v</em>.<strong> </strong> to formally promise to give or do (something)</p>
<p><strong>platform</strong> – <em>n</em>. the official beliefs and goals of a political party</p>
<p><strong>sustainable</strong> – <em>adj</em>. involving methods that do not completely use up or destroy natural resources</p>
<p><strong>rally</strong> – <em>n. </em>a public meeting to support or oppose someone or something</p>
<p><strong>metaphor </strong><em>–n.</em> a word or term that means one thing that is used to represent a different thing usually because of a similarity</p>
<p><strong>academic </strong><em>–adj.</em> related to school or schooling</p>
<p><strong>poll </strong>–<em> n. </em>an activity in which several or many people are asked a question or a series of questions to provide information about what people think about something; a place for voting</p>
<p><strong>affiliation</strong> – <em>n.</em> the state of belonging to a particular religious or political group</p>
<p><strong>cast</strong> –<em> v. </em>to formally make (a vote)</p>
<p><strong>acquaintance</strong> – <em>n</em>. someone who is known but who is not a close friend</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Some Cubans Are Turning to Electric Bikes, Vehicles (2024/7/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/cubans-are-turning-to-electric-bikes-vehicles.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Cuba's capital, Havana, is famous for its colorful <strong>vintage</strong> cars. They fill the streets and are often popular subjects for visitors' photographs.</p>
<p>But these days, Cubans are just as likely to be found traveling around town quickly and quietly on electric scooters made with Chinese parts.</p>
<p>"Electric motorcycles are solving a lot of problems in Cuba, they are already used for almost everything," said Omar Cortina. He is a Cuban hotel worker who recently purchased his first electric vehicle -- a lime-green scooter powered by a lithium battery.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A view of the Caribbean Electric Vehicles (VEDCA) factory in Havana, Cuba, July 15, 2024. (REUTERS/Alexandre Meneghini)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-09a2-08dcab64d88b_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A view of the Caribbean Electric Vehicles (VEDCA) factory in Havana, Cuba, July 15, 2024. (REUTERS/Alexandre Meneghini)</span></div>
<p>Until recently, Cuba's roads had changed little in the years since former leader Fidel Castro's 1959 revolution. Old cars with old <strong>exhaust</strong> systems drove along uneven roads.</p>
<p>Today, electric vehicles are an increasingly common transportation choice. Between 2020 and 2022, Cuba-based companies produced more than 23,000 electric vehicles. That number comes from official government sources.</p>
<p><strong>Fuel is hard to find and expensive </strong></p>
<p>Fuel for <strong>combustion</strong>-powered engines has been hard to find for years in Cuba. People would wait in fuel lines for hours and sometimes even days.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, the price for gasoline increased to five times the usual price. That means a usual 40-liter tank of gas costs more than a state-worker's average monthly earnings. For most Cubans, that made purchasing gasoline nearly impossible.</p>
<p><strong>Public transportation is hardly any better</strong></p>
<p>But costly fuel is not the only problem.</p>
<p>There are fewer buses in Havana than there were in the past. This year, half the bus routes to points outside the capital were cut, state-run news agencies in Cuba report. Fuel and parts to repair old buses are also harder to find.</p>
<p>All these <strong>factors </strong>have helped to increase the demand for electric vehicles. Products from newly formed companies like Caribbean Electric Vehicles (Vedca) are helping to fill that demand.</p>
<p>Vedca is a <strong>joint venture</strong> between Chinese investor Tianjin Dongxing Industrial and Cuban state bicycle manufacturer Minerva. It has produced more than 2,000 scooters, bikes, and mini-tricycle trucks in Cuba with Chinese parts.</p>
<p>Juilo Oscar Perez is the company's director. Perez told reporters that electric vehicles are not just giving people another way of getting around. They are also solving fuel-related problems.</p>
<p>The company, Perez said, has also begun testing a new electric tractor and experimenting with other electric-powered heavy machinery.</p>
<p>Other small Cuban companies also sell electric bikes. Some bikes are basic while others are more costly. The government also recently began permitting imports of much costlier electric vehicles.</p>
<p>Imports of automobiles from the neighboring United States have risen to $24.6 million so far in 2024, the U.S.-Cuba Trade and Economic Council said. There is a growing number of Cubans who want more <strong>luxurious</strong> electric and <strong>hybrid </strong>automobiles, including Teslas.</p>
<p>But the number of Cubans who can pay for such vehicles is still small. For Omar Cortina, the hotel worker, just being able to get back and forth from work is enough of a selling-point.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Alien Fernandez reported this story for Reuters. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>vintage </strong><em>– adj. </em>dating from the past : old</p>
<p><strong>exhaust </strong><em>– n. </em>a system of pipes through which exhaust escapes</p>
<p><strong>internal combustion engines </strong><em>– n. </em>a heat engine in which the combustion that generates the heat takes place inside the engine proper instead of in a furnace</p>
<p><strong>factor </strong><em>– n.</em><strong> </strong>something that contributes to the production of a result</p>
<p><strong>joint venture </strong><em>– n. </em>a commercial enterprise undertaken jointly by two or more parties which otherwise retain their distinct identities</p>
<p><strong>upscale </strong><em>– adj. </em>relating to, being, or appealing to affluent consumers also :<strong> </strong>of a superior quality</p>
<p><strong>luxurious </strong><em>– adj.</em> characterized by opulence, sumptuousness, or rich abundance</p>
<p><strong>hybrid </strong><em>– adj. </em>a vehicle that uses both an internal combustion engine and one or more electric motors to power it.</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Businesses Recover from Major Worldwide Tech Outage (2024/7/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/businesses-recover-from-major-worldwide-tech-outage.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">24 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A major computer system outage affected a wide range of businesses around the world beginning late last week. But the cause of the outage was quickly identified and fixes were deployed to bring most businesses back online.</p>
<p>The problems were linked to a software <strong>update</strong> provided by cybersecurity company CrowdStrike. The outage affected computers using Microsoft's Windows operating system. The incident caused major flight delays and cancellations. It also affected banking, health care, media and other businesses.</p>
<p>Computers affected by the outage showed what is known in the technology industry as the “blue screen of death.” This warning tool is designed to inform Windows users that there is a problem and to block further activity to prevent wider system damage.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A technician works on an information display near United Airlines gates at Chicago O'Hare International Airport in Chicago, Friday, July 19, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-5837-08dcabf3cb29_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A technician works on an information display near United Airlines gates at Chicago O'Hare International Airport in Chicago, Friday, July 19, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster)</span></div>
<p>Officials at Texas-based CrowdStrike were quick to admit a software update containing a programming mistake was sent to <strong>customers</strong> and caused the outage. Once the problem was identified and a fix deployed, CrowdStrike said it centered on assisting customers to get systems back up as soon as possible.</p>
<p>Technology experts noted one issue with the latest outage was that the problematic software update could not be corrected <strong>remotely</strong>. Instead, individual machines had to be fixed, with bad files removed by technology workers.</p>
<p>CrowdStrike's main business is to provide solutions to help companies prevent internet attacks. However, company leaders made clear that the latest outage was only related to the software update and not part of any cybersecurity attack.</p>
<p>CrowdStrike continued to <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.crowdstrike.com/falcon-content-update-remediation-and-guidance-hub/">inform the public</a> about its latest correction efforts and <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Bn5eRUaMZXk">provided guidance</a> for some businesses to attempt to deal with the issue themselves.</p>
<p><strong>Disruptions around the world</strong></p>
<p>The outage <strong>disrupted</strong> operations at airlines, banks, hospitals and organizations around the world.</p>
<p>Among U.S. airlines, Delta officials said Monday it was forced to cancel more than 4,000 flights since the outage began last Friday. But other major carriers, including American Airlines and United, reported they had largely ended any flight disruptions.</p>
<p>Delta chief Ed Bastian apologized to the airline's customers for the continuing delays and cancellations. He said the company was working around the clock to fix all affected systems. Delta said about 60 percent of its main systems run on Microsoft Windows and therefore were left inoperable by the outage.</p>
<p>Some technology experts expressed concern that such outages can be extremely disruptive because the systems built to run most of the world's computers are provided by only a small number of companies.</p>
<p>Gregory Falco is an assistant professor of engineering at Cornell University in New York. He studies internet security issues. Falco told The Associated Press it is a problem that so many computers worldwide depend on the same technologies and providers. “We rely on very few companies, and everybody uses the same folks, so everyone goes down at the same time,” Falco said.</p>
<p>CrowdStrike is one of the largest cybersecurity service providers, especially in transportation, health care, banking and media. This is the reason it affected so many businesses in those industries. An <strong>irony</strong> of the outage was that companies normally look to CrowdStrike's tools to help prevent internet attacks that could bring their systems down and cause costly disruptions.</p>
<p>Falco noted that while fears of such a widespread outage have long existed, he thinks too few providers are becoming “even more <strong>entrenched</strong>” with certain technologies. "We like to think that we have a lot of players available. But at the end of the day, the biggest companies use all the same stuff.”</p>
<p>Richard Stiennon is a cybersecurity expert who has followed industry developments for 24 years. He told the AP he sees the software issue as a historic mistake by CrowdStrike. “This is easily the worst <strong>faux pas</strong>, technical faux pas or <strong>glitch</strong> of any security software provider ever,” Stiennon said.</p>
<p>He added that while the problem had an easy technical fix, it could still have lasting effects for some companies. This is because the outage required hands-on efforts to fix each affected computer and this can severely disrupt business operations.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters and CrowdStrike. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>update</strong><em> - n.</em> to add new information to an existing thing</p>
<p><strong>customer</strong><em> – n.</em> a person who buys goods or services</p>
<p><strong>remote </strong><em>– adv. </em>happening from far away</p>
<p><strong>disruption </strong><em>– n.</em> to interrupt something and stop it from continuing as it should</p>
<p><strong>irony </strong><em>– adj. </em>a situation in which the opposite happens than what was expected</p>
<p><strong>entrenched </strong><em>– adj. </em>ideas or things that have existed for a long time</p>
<p><strong>faux pas </strong><em>– n. </em>words or behavior that represent a social mistake or something not polite</p>
<p><strong>glitch </strong><em>– n. </em>a small problem or issue that prevents something from being successful or working as well as it should</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Climate Agency Again Reports Hottest Day Record on Earth (2024/7/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/climate-agency-again-reports-hottest-day-record-on-earth.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">24 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The European climate change service Copernicus said Monday broke the world's hottest day record that was just set a day earlier.</p>
<p>The European Union's Copernicus Climate Change Service said the daily global average temperature reached 17.15 degrees Celsius on Monday. Earlier <a class="wsw__a" href="https://nam10.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fpulse.climate.copernicus.eu%2F&amp;data=05%7C02%7Cmritter%40VOANews.COM%7C8ae53aa7ab624dfca32408dcabebe8ae%7Cba99e87c673541c2b1c1354eee3a8659%7C0%7C0%7C638574276940114952%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=2tj5diOprdzp%2B20db%2Br6YpouWVN0x2KmOXU%2B5x%2B1oOA%3D&amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" title="Original URL: https://pulse.climate.copernicus.eu/. Click or tap if you trust this link.">satellite data</a> published by Copernicus on Wednesday showed that Monday's temperature broke the previous day's record by 0.06 degrees Celsius.</p>
<p>Countries around the world from Japan to Bolivia to the United States are said to be having hot conditions.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - The setting sun illuminates the clouds over the Rocky Mountains after a third straight day of record-breaking heat Sunday, July 14, 2024, in Denver. (AP Photo/David Zalubowski)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-f00e-08dcabf81b4b_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - The setting sun illuminates the clouds over the Rocky Mountains after a third straight day of record-breaking heat Sunday, July 14, 2024, in Denver. (AP Photo/David Zalubowski)</span></div>
<p>Climate scientists say the world is now as warm as it was 125,000 years ago. They blame human-caused climate change for the warm temperatures.</p>
<p>Scientists cannot be certain that Monday was the hottest day in more than 100,000 years since data does not go back that far. But average temperatures have not been this high since long before humans developed agriculture, the Associated Press reports.</p>
<p>The temperature rise in recent years supports what climate scientists predicted would happen if humans kept burning oil, natural gas, and coal at an increasing rate.</p>
<p>Roxy Mathew Koll is a climate scientist at the Indian Institute of Tropical Meteorology in western India. Koll said, “We are in an age where weather and climate records are <strong>frequently</strong> stretched beyond our <strong>tolerance</strong> levels, resulting in <strong>insurmountable</strong> loss of lives and livelihood.”</p>
<p>Copernicus' early data shows the global average temperature on Monday, July 22, was 17.15 degrees Celsius. Before last summer, the previous recorded hottest day was in 2016 when the average temperature reached 16.8 degrees Celsius.</p>
<p>The European agency said what caused this week's high temperatures was a warmer-than-usual Antarctic winter. The same thing happened last year when a record was set in early July.</p>
<p>Copernicus records go back to 1940. Other global measurements by the United States and British governments go back to 1880. Many scientists also consider tree growth rings and ice samples. They say that information suggests that last year's record high temperatures were the hottest in about 120,000 years.</p>
<p>Now, temperatures reported in the first six months of 2024 have broken the earlier records.</p>
<p>Without human-caused climate change, scientists say that extreme temperature records would not be broken nearly as often.</p>
<p>Former head of U.N. climate negotiations Christiana Figueres said “We all <strong>scorch</strong> and <strong>fry</strong>” if the world does not immediately change course.</p>
<p>“One third of global electricity can be produced by solar and wind alone, but targeted national policies have to enable that transformation,” she said.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Seth Borenstein and Sibi Arasu reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>frequently </strong><em>–adv</em>. taking place often</p>
<p><strong>tolerance </strong><em>–n.</em> the ability to survive or withstand some event or pressure</p>
<p><strong>insurmountable </strong><em>–adj.</em> impossible to recover from</p>
<p><strong>sample</strong> <em>–n.</em> an amount of something that is taken for study usually in a laboratory</p>
<p><strong>scorch</strong> <em>–v. </em>to burn with a flame or high heat</p>
<p><strong>fry</strong><em> –v.</em> to cook using hot oil</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Athletes Have High Hopes for Paris Olympics, Cultural Activities (2024/7/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/athletes-have-high-hopes-for-paris-olympics-cultural-activities.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">24 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Paris is a popular place for visitors because of its food, art, and history. The city itself is likely to be central to the experience of the Olympic Games.</p>
<p>The athletes going to France have been making long lists of things they want to try, see and eat.</p>
<p>“I'm excited to just explore and just take in everything Paris has to offer, because me and my friends, we look at things and we get<strong> inspired</strong>,” said<strong> breaker </strong>Jeffrey Louis, also known as b-boy Jeffro.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Passengers in the back of a taxi film themselves as they leave the Eiffel Tower decorated with the Olympic rings ahead of the 2024 Summer Olympics, Wednesday, July 17, 2024, in Paris. (AP Photo/David Goldman, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/fef1eed7-5f26-466b-b8d0-7ae11831f6dc_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Passengers in the back of a taxi film themselves as they leave the Eiffel Tower decorated with the Olympic rings ahead of the 2024 Summer Olympics, Wednesday, July 17, 2024, in Paris. (AP Photo/David Goldman, File)</span></div>
<p>He added, “There's a lot of things that we want to try and just explore.”</p>
<p>Some athletes want to ride to the top of Gustave Eiffel's creation from the 1880s, the Eiffel Tower, maybe even dine at its restaurant. The Louvre Museum, with Leonardo da Vinci's painting, the Mona Lisa, the famous Venus de Milo statue, and many other objects are high on many lists of things to see.</p>
<p>Notre Dame Cathedral also is popular although repair work after a 2019 fire will not be completed until after the Summer Games.</p>
<p>“Such a big city. A beautiful city,” diver Andrew Capobianco said.</p>
<p>Athletes are also excited to try the food and drinks.</p>
<p>“Eat as many <strong>crepes </strong>as you can if you're in Paris,” track and field Paralympian Noelle Malkamaki said.</p>
<p>“Looking forward to <strong>macaroons</strong>, pastries, bread,” sitting volleyball Paralympian Nicky Nieves said.</p>
<p>Others are excited about coffee, meats, and sweet desserts such as crème br<i></i>251;lée. And some hope to drink the wines — from the Loire Valley, Bordeaux or Champagne.</p>
<p>There are those, such as breaker Sunny Choi or rower Michelle Sechser, who know they will need to wait to enjoy some of the food and drink.</p>
<p>“We do have weight-class restrictions; we have to weigh in two hours before a race,” Sechser said. “So, after racing's done, I'm most excited to get out and explore the Parisian food and really enjoy some French meals.”</p>
<p><strong>Canoe</strong> and <strong>kayak </strong>star Evy Leibfarth, the first American woman to qualify in three whitewater boating events at an Olympics, looks at the situation differently.</p>
<p>She makes sure to fill herself with foods that help with athletic performance. But she also does not want to deny herself too much.</p>
<p>“If I'm going to be thinking about my<strong> croissant</strong> the whole time I'm paddling, I may as well just eat it, you know? So, it's all about balance,” said Leibfarth, a 20-year-old from North Carolina. “It's just making sure that I'm getting the right amount of protein and the right amount of carbs before a race, while also balancing in the things that I want to eat.”</p>
<p>As she looked forward to her fifth trip to Paris, Leibfarth offered some words to Olympians headed for the first time to the City of Light — which is another name for Paris.</p>
<p>“Don't be afraid to just drop the recommendations and everything and just walk around and find things to do because that's the best I've done.”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Howard Fendrich and Eddie Pells reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted this story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>inspired </strong><em>– adj</em>. very clever or good; to be or become outstanding</p>
<p><strong>breaker</strong> <em>– n.</em> someone who breakdances</p>
<p><strong>crepe </strong><em>– n.</em> a small thin pancake</p>
<p><strong>macaroon</strong> <em>– n.</em> a kind of cookie made of egg, sugar, and almonds or coconut</p>
<p><strong>canoe<em> </em></strong><em>–n</em>. a light narrow boat with two sharp ends</p>
<p><strong>kayak </strong><em>– n.</em> a light narrow boat often has a closed top except for an opening in which the paddler sits</p>
<p><strong>croissant</strong> <em>– n.</em> a flaky, rich roll that comes in the shape of a crescent</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Groups Warn of Conflict Between Loggers, Tribe in Peru (2024/7/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/groups-warn-of-conflict-between-loggers-tribe-in-peru.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">23 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>An <strong>advocacy </strong>group for Indigenous peoples has released images of a <strong>reclusive </strong>Peruvian Amazon tribe's members searching for food outside of their usual area.</p>
<p>The group calls the pictures evidence that industrial tree cutting operations are “dangerously close” to the tribe's territory. The industry is also known as logging.</p>
<p>The group, Survival International, said the photographs and video it posted recently show members of the Mashco Piro looking for food near the community of Monte Salvado, on the Las Piedras River in Madre de Dios.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This June 2024 photo provided by Survival International shows members of the Mashco Piro along the Las Piedras River in the Peruvian Amazon near the community of Monte Salvado, in Madre de Dios province, Peru. (Survival International via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/ddcd5f24-caec-4240-ae69-8620452f17eb_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This June 2024 photo provided by Survival International shows members of the Mashco Piro along the Las Piedras River in the Peruvian Amazon near the community of Monte Salvado, in Madre de Dios province, Peru. (Survival International via AP)</span></div>
<p>Several logging companies hold timber agreements inside territory the tribe lives in, Survival International says. The group has long worked to protect what it says is the largest “uncontacted” tribe in the world. The nearness of logging operations raises fears of conflict between loggers and tribal members, as well as the possibility that loggers could bring dangerous diseases to the Mashco Piro, the group said.</p>
<p>Two loggers, one of whom died, were shot with <strong>arrows</strong> while fishing in 2022 in a reported fight with tribal members.</p>
<p>Cesar Ipenza is a lawyer who specializes in environmental law in Peru. He is not connected with Survival International.</p>
<p>Ipenza said the new images are evidence of a “worrying situation because we do not know exactly what is the reason for their departure (from the rainforest) to the beaches.”</p>
<p>Isolated Indigenous tribes may travel in August to collect turtle eggs to eat, he said.</p>
<p>“But we also see with great concern that some illegal activity may be taking place in the areas where they live and lead them to leave and be under pressure,” he said. “We cannot deny the presence of a logging <strong>concession</strong> kilometers away from where they live.”</p>
<p>Survival International called for the Forest Stewardship Council (FSC), a group that confirms <strong>sustainable</strong> forestry, to remove its approval of the operations of one of those companies, Peru-based Canales Tahuamanu. The FSC responded in a statement that it would do “a comprehensive review” of the company's operations to ensure it is protecting the rights of Indigenous peoples.</p>
<p>Canales Tahuamanu, also known as Catahua, has said in the past that it is operating with official permission. The company did not immediately answer a message seeking comment on its operations and the tribe.</p>
<p>A 2023 report by the United Nations' special reporter on the rights of Indigenous peoples said Peru's government had recognized in 2016 that the Mashco Piro and other isolated tribes were using territories that had been opened to logging.</p>
<p>The report expressed concern that the territory of Indigenous peoples had not been marked out “despite reasonable evidence of their presence since 1999.”</p>
<p>Survival International said the photos were taken June 26-27 and show about 53 male Mashco Piro on the beach. The group estimated as many as 100 to 150 tribal members would have been in the area with women and children nearby.</p>
<p>“It is very unusual that you see such a large group together,” Survival International researcher Teresa Mayo said in a talk with the Associated Press.</p>
<p>Ipenza, the lawyer, said Indigenous people usually move in smaller groups, and a larger group might be a “situation of alarm” even in the case of legal logging.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Steven Grattan reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>advocacy</strong> <em>– n.</em> the act or process of supporting a cause</p>
<p><strong>reclusive</strong> <em>– adj.</em> withdrawn or separate from society</p>
<p><strong>arrow</strong> <em>– n.</em> a sharp object with a slender shaft that is shot from a bow</p>
<p><strong>sustainable</strong> <em>– adj.</em> of or relating to a method of using a resource so that the resource is not permanently damaged</p>
<p><strong>concession</strong> <em>– n.</em> a grant of land or property in return for services or for a particular use</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers in Brazil Say Rain Uncovered Fossil of Old Dinosaur (2024/7/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/researchers-in-brazil-say-rain-uncovered-fossil-of-old-dinosaur.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">23 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists in Brazil say heavy rains helped them discover a <strong>fossil </strong>they believe came from one of the world's oldest dinosaurs.</p>
<p>Researchers found the fossil in May in Brazil's southern state of Rio Grande do Sul. They said the fossilized bones make up nearly a complete dinosaur skeleton.</p>
<p>A leader of the team, <strong>paleontologist</strong> Rodrigo Temp Müller, said the fossil is believed to be about 233 million years old. It was discovered next to a body of water in the area of Sao Joao do Polesine.</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-9525-08dc96c58dc8_cx0_cy3_cw0_w100_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>Müller is with Brazil's Federal University of Santa Maria in Rio Grande do Sul. He said heavy rains in the area had helped speed up the natural process of <strong>erosion</strong> that led to the discovery. Fossils are more likely to get <strong>exposed</strong> after rains because water washes away the dirt that covers them.</p>
<p>Details of the discovery have not yet been confirmed by other scientists or published in any scientific publications.</p>
<p>The researchers believe the dinosaur lived during the Triassic Period. The first dinosaurs are thought to have appeared at that time after Earth's largest mass <strong>extinction</strong> event about 252 million years ago. During the Triassic Period, all continents were part of a single land mass called Pangea.</p>
<p>The team thinks the dinosaur belonged to a group known as Herrerasauridae. A document received by The Associated Press explains this family of creatures once lived on land that now makes up present-day Brazil and Argentina. The document said the size of the bones suggests the dinosaur would have been around 2.5 meters long.</p>
<p>After about four days of <strong>excavation</strong> work, researchers transported a large piece of rock containing the fossil back to their laboratory. There, they carried out tests.</p>
<p>At first, Müller said he thought the team had only collected “a few <strong>isolated</strong> bones.” But after detailed testing, the researchers said they had almost a complete skeleton.</p>
<p>Müller told the AP his team was “very excited and surprised” by the discovery. He said the new find might be the second most complete skeleton found for this kind of dinosaur.</p>
<p>The researchers are carrying out studies to see whether the fossil belongs to an already-known <strong>species</strong> or a new kind. The effort is expected to take several months.</p>
<p>Brazil's Rio Grande do Sul state reported record rainfall earlier this year. Officials said the rain caused widespread flooding in May that led to at least 182 deaths. Some weather experts say climate change makes extreme weather events more likely. They say the burning of oil, gas and coal affects the climate.</p>
<p>Müller said other fossils appeared after the heavy rains. He noted these finds had launched a race against time to rescue the materials before they are ruined. For example, team members in the field said they had observed what appeared to be a leg bone and a pelvis bone. But they said these were in danger of being destroyed because of the rain.</p>
<p>Müller hopes the new discovery can help further explain the <strong>origins</strong> of dinosaurs. “Having new fossils that are so well <strong>preserved</strong> certainly helps us better understand this topic that is still much debated,” he said.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>fossil </strong><em>–</em><em> n.</em> something (such as a leaf, skeleton, or footprint) that is from a plant or animal which lived in ancient times and that you can be seen in rocks</p>
<p><strong>paleontologist </strong><em>– n.</em> a person who studies fossils as a way of getting information about the history of life on Earth</p>
<p><strong>erode </strong><em>– v. </em>to slowly decay over time</p>
<p><strong>extinction </strong><em>– n. </em>a situation in which something no longer exists</p>
<p><strong>excavate </strong><em>– v.</em> to remove earth covering very old objects buried in the ground in order to discover things about the past</p>
<p><strong>isolated </strong><em>– adj. </em>not near to other places</p>
<p><strong>species </strong><em>– n. </em>a group of animals or plants that are similar and can produce young animals or plants</p>
<p><strong>expose </strong><em>– v.</em> to remove what is covering something so that it can be seen</p>
<p><strong>origin </strong><em>– n. </em>where something begins or comes from</p>
<p><strong>preserve </strong><em>– v. </em>to keep something from decaying, being damaged or destroyed</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US States Push for Cell Phone Ban in High Schools (2024/7/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/us-states-push-for-cell-phone-ban-in-high-schools.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">23 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>More American states are pushing for cell phone restrictions in high schools. The move comes as teachers say it is a major problem in the classroom.</p>
<p>In July, Virginia became the latest in a growing number of U.S. states to restrict cell phone use in public schools. The state's governor, Glenn Youngkin, issued an executive order to establish guidance and policies for local school systems to follow by January.</p>
<p>Youngkin's order said, “Studies <strong>indicate</strong> that students who use their phones during class learn less and <strong>achieve</strong> lower grades.” It also <strong>cited</strong> an “alarming mental health crisis” among young people driven by the use of cell phones and social media.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A student places her cellphone into a phone holder as she enters class at Delta High School, Friday, Feb. 23, 2024, in Delta, Utah. (AP Photo/Rick Bowmer)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-0926-08dca5cbd3b3_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">FILE - A student places her cellphone into a phone holder as she enters class at Delta High School, Friday, Feb. 23, 2024, in Delta, Utah. (AP Photo/Rick Bowmer)</span></div>
<p>Last year, Florida became the first state to restrict the use of cell phones in school. A law that took effect in July requires all Florida public schools to ban student cell phone use during class time and block social media on the school's <strong>wi-fi</strong>.</p>
<p>The states of Indiana and Ohio passed their own laws this year. Several others, including Oklahoma, Vermont, and Kansas, have also recently introduced what is being called “phone-free schools” legislation. New York Governor Kathy Hochul said she will push for legislation to ban cell phone use in the coming legislative session in 2025.</p>
<p><strong>Cell phone distraction</strong></p>
<p>In a recent public study, the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.pewresearch.org/short-reads/2024/06/12/72-percent-of-us-high-school-teachers-say-cellphone-distraction-is-a-major-problem-in-the-classroom/">Pew Research Center reported</a> that 72 percent of U.S. high school teachers say cell phone <strong>distraction</strong> is a major problem in the classroom.</p>
<p>Teachers report less of a problem with younger students. About 33 percent of middle school teachers and six percent of elementary school teachers see cell phone use as problematic.</p>
<p>The Associated Press (AP) reported that a California teacher complained of students watching Netflix during class. In Maryland, a teacher said students used <strong>gambling</strong> apps to place <strong>bets</strong> during the school day.</p>
<p>Many educators in the U.S. said students used social media, listened to music, and shopped online during the school day.</p>
<p>James Granger is a science teacher at a Los Angeles-area high school. He told the AP, “Students used to have an understanding that you aren't supposed to be on your phone in class. Those days are gone.” Granger added, “The only solution that works is to physically remove the cellphone from the student.”</p>
<p>Some students say such policies take away their independence and cut off their main method of communication with family and friends. Opposition also has come from parents who fear being cut off from their kids if there is a school emergency.</p>
<p>Jaden Willoughey is a student at Delta High School in rural Utah. He shares the concern about being out of contact with his parents if there is an emergency. But he also sees the upside, or good result, of turning in his phone at school.</p>
<p>At Delta High School, students are required to leave their phones at the door when entering every class. “It helps you focus on your work, and it's easier to pay attention in class,” Jaden said.</p>
<p>Kim Whitman is a leader of the Phone-Free Schools Movement, a group that advises schools. She told the AP she urges educators to make exceptions for students with special educational and medical needs.</p>
<p><strong>Back in Virginia</strong></p>
<p>Back in Virginia, school systems have been increasingly banning or severely restricting students' phone use.</p>
<p>For example, Loudoun County Public Schools, in northern Virginia, passed a new policy last month that generally bans elementary school students from using phones during the school day.</p>
<p>Middle school students are permitted to use their phones before or after school, but they are expected to store their phones in their <strong>lockers</strong>. In high school, students are expected to silence their phones and place them in storage during instructional time.</p>
<p>In Richmond, Virginia, the school system started a cell phone ban last year in some of its high schools and middle schools.</p>
<p>Jason Kamras is head of the Richmond school system. He said, “We saw more student <strong>engagement</strong> in class and fewer distractions throughout the day.” Additionally, he said, “Students reported spending more time talking with their <strong>peers</strong>.”</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Hai Do wrote this report for VOA Learning English based on reporting from the Associated Press and Pew Research.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>indicate </strong>–v. to show or suggest something is the case</p>
<p><strong>achieve</strong> <em>–v. </em>to reach a goal or do something that is notable</p>
<p><strong>cite</strong> <em>–v.</em> to quote the direct words of someone else or facts that come from a source</p>
<p><strong>wi-fi </strong><em>–n.</em> <em>(technology)</em> a short distance wireless connection</p>
<p><strong>distraction </strong>–n. the condition of having one's attention taken up by something that is not important at the time; a thing that is causing a loss of attention</p>
<p><strong>gambling </strong><em>–n.</em> the activity of playing games of chance for money</p>
<p><strong>bet </strong>–n. the act of putting money at risk in an effort to win more money</p>
<p><strong>locker </strong><em>–n.</em> a space, especially in schools, where people can put things and secure them with a lock</p>
<p><strong>engagement </strong><em>–n.</em> the condition of taking part in an activity, like a class, and being involved in it</p>
<p><strong>peer </strong><em>–n.</em> a person who is equal with others and like them at work, in school, or in several other situations</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Ukrainian Companies Develop Robotic Vehicles to Fight Russia (2024/7/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/ukrainian-companies-develop-robotic-vehicles-to-fight-russia.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Many new Ukrainian businesses are reportedly developing unmanned military vehicles for the country's war against Russia.</p>
<p>The operations often happen in empty <strong>warehouses</strong> or secret, underground factories, the Associated Press (AP) reports.</p>
<p>The weaponized vehicles reportedly aim to ease shortages of soldiers and equipment.</p><div class="contentImage"><img a="" alt="Andrii Denysenko, CEO of design and production bureau " an="" anton="" at="" by="" corn="" drone="" field="" friday="" ground="" in="" june="" northern="" odyssey="" photo="" prototype="" shtuka="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-bc6e-08dca6af8ada_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg" stands="" ukraine="" ukrprototyp=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Andrii Denysenko, CEO of design and production bureau "UkrPrototyp", stands by Odyssey, an 800-kilogram (1,750-pound) ground drone prototype, at a corn field in northern Ukraine, Friday, June 28, 2024. (AP Photo/Anton Shtuka)</span></div>
<p>Workers at laboratories in hundreds of workshops are using technology tools to build robot fighters to battle Russian forces, the AP said.</p>
<p>The AP reported that an estimated 250 new defense companies are currently involved in the production of war vehicles across Ukraine. The news agency noted that such operations can look similar to rural car repair shops.</p>
<p>Andrii Denysenko heads one of the new companies, or startups. He told the AP his employees can put together an unmanned ground vehicle, called the Odyssey, in just four days. The vehicle has a selling price of $35,000, which is about 10 percent less than an imported model.</p>
<p>Denysenko asked the AP not to publish details about his business to protect the operation and the people working there.</p>
<p>The work area is divided into small rooms for <strong>welding</strong> and body work. Workers produce the main structure, paint the vehicles green and then fit them with basic electronics, power systems and cameras and sensors.</p>
<p>Ukraine's military is considering several different models of new unmanned air, ground and sea vehicles produced by the startups. A fourth branch of Ukraine's military – the Unmanned Systems Forces - joined the army, navy and air force in May.</p>
<p>Engineers get production ideas from stories in defense magazines or online videos to produce less costly models. Weapons or smart elements can be added later.</p>
<p>“We are fighting a huge country, and they don't have any resource limits,” said Denysenko. “We understand that we cannot spend a lot of human lives. War is mathematics.”</p>
<p>Reporters from the AP watched the car-sized Odyssey vehicle spin and kick up dust as it rolled through a field of corn during a demonstration in the north of the country last month.</p>
<p>The 800-kilogram test model, or prototype, looks like a small tank. Developers of the vehicle say it can travel up to 30 kilometers on one battery charge. The prototype acts as a rescue-and-supply vehicle but could be changed to carry a <strong>remotely </strong>operated heavy machine gun or to clear landmines.</p>
<p>A Ukrainian government fundraising website for the Unmanned Systems Forces states that teams of robots “will become <strong>logistics</strong> devices, tow trucks, minelayers and deminers, as well as self-destructive robots.” “The first robots are already proving their effectiveness on the battlefield," the statement adds.</p>
<p>Mykhailo Fedorov is Ukraine's deputy prime minister for digital <strong>transformation</strong>. He is urging citizens to take free online courses and build military <strong>drones</strong> at home. Fedorov has called on Ukrainians to make a million drone flying machines per year.</p>
<p>“There will be more of them soon,” the Unmanned Systems Forces website said. "Many more.”</p>
<p>Denysenko's company is working on other projects as well. One is a motorized <strong>exoskeleton</strong> designed to increase a soldier's strength. Another carrier vehicle would be able to transport a soldier's equipment and even help him move uphill. “We will do everything to make unmanned technologies develop even faster. (Russia's) murderers use their soldiers as cannon <strong>fodder</strong>, while we lose our best people,” Fedorov wrote in a message published online.</p>
<p>Human Rights Watch and other international rights groups are calling for a ban on weapons that do not involve human decision making. This concern has been shared by others, including the U.N. General Assembly, American businessman Elon Musk and the founders of the Google-owned, London-based startup DeepMind.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>warehouse <em>–</em></strong><em>n.</em> a large building that provides centralized storage for a lot of goods and products that are then shipped to customers</p>
<p><strong>weld </strong><em> v.</em> to join pieces of metal together by heating them until they almost melt and then pressing them together</p>
<p><strong>remote </strong><em>– adj.</em> happening from far away</p>
<p><strong>logistics </strong><em>– n. </em>the practical arrangements for something</p>
<p><strong>transformation </strong><em>– n.</em> to completely change from one system to another, usually in an effort to improve it</p>
<p><strong>drone </strong><em>– n.</em> an unmanned, flying vehicle</p>
<p><strong>exoskeleton </strong><em>– n. </em>an artificial external supporting structure</p>
<p><strong>fodder </strong><em>– n.</em> people or things that are useful for the stated purpose</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Grow Your Own Tea Plants Year-round (2024/7/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/grow-your-own-tea-plants-year-round.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>People who grow their own food are familiar with planting tomatoes, peppers, squash, herbs, berries and other common fruits and vegetables.</p>
<p>However, they may not think of growing plants for drinks.</p>
<p><strong>Gardening </strong>expert Jessica Damiano recently wrote about plants you can grow to make tea. Damiano, who writes for the Associated Press, says that growing your own tea plants in the garden can provide enough leaves and flower <strong>buds</strong> to keep your tea pot filled year-round.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image provided by the Missouri Botanical Garden shows a hedge of Camellia sinensis plants. The plant's leaves are used to make white, green, black and oolong teas. (Missouri Botanical Garden via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-965b-08dc9c4106d0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image provided by the Missouri Botanical Garden shows a hedge of Camellia sinensis plants. The plant's leaves are used to make white, green, black and oolong teas. (Missouri Botanical Garden via AP)</span></div>
<p>And the plant to grow, she says, is camellia sinensis (var. sinensis), also known as the “tea plant.”</p>
<p>These <strong>evergreen</strong> plants are easy to grow in any amount of sunlight, from deep <strong>shade</strong> to full sun. However, ideal growing conditions are part sun to light shade. They require well-draining soil with a slightly <strong>acidic</strong> pH.</p>
<p>Young plants will take about two years to produce enough leaves for tea. In five years, one plant should provide enough for an average tea drinker. If you need more tea, Damiano says to plant more camellia sinensis.</p>
<p>Camellia sinensis is called the “tea plant” because white, green, black, and oolong teas all come from this plant. Their differences come from harvesting practices and after-harvest treatments.</p>
<p>For white tea, pick the flower buds before they fully open. Heat the buds in a pan over low heat, moving them often for about 10 minutes. Cool them and store in an airtight container.</p>
<p>For green, black and oolong tea, pick two or three of the youngest leaves from each stem, along with the leaf bud from each stem tip. Do this every 10 to 12 days as new growth develops.</p>
<p>Preparing green, oolong, or black tea all have different processes.</p>
<p><strong>Green tea</strong></p>
<p>For making green tea, briefly <strong>steam</strong> leaves over boiling water. Then put the leaves on a clean towel and let them sit for five minutes. Roll up the leaves in the towel gently to remove extra water. Remove the leaves from the towel, separate them, and place them on a baking sheet. Heat in an oven or toaster oven set to 148 degrees Celsius (300 degrees Fahrenheit) for 10 to 15 minutes or until the leaves are completely dry. <strong>Brew</strong> immediately or cool and keep them in an airtight container for future use.</p>
<p><strong>Oolong tea</strong></p>
<p>For making oolong tea, put the leaves in one layer on a baking tray. Put the tray in a sunny outdoor spot to let the leaves <strong>wilt.</strong> After 30 to 60 minutes, move the tray into the shade and move the leaves every hour for 8 to 10 hours. Next, place the leaves in a wide pan and cook them over low heat for 15 minutes, moving gently as needed to prevent burning. Let the leaves cool. And roll each leaf individually to keep its oils and flavors. They should be completely dry before storing in an airtight container.</p>
<p><strong>Black tea</strong></p>
<p>To make black tea, place leaves on a baking sheet in the sun for 10 to 12 hours to remove only 50 to 75 percent of the water. Then, cut the leaves into long pieces and roll into small balls. Place the balls in a warm room between 25 and 26 degrees Celsius (78 to 80 degrees F) that is not too dry of a room until they turn reddish-black. Then, dry them in an <strong>oven</strong> at 93 degrees Celsius (200 degrees F) for 5 minutes. Lower heat to 60 degrees C (140 degrees F) and continue drying for an additional hour. Cool and store in an airtight container.</p>
<p>Native<strong> </strong>to China, camellia sinensis var. sinensis is cold-hardy. That means it can survive in cold weather. However, it may need some protection to survive cold winters.</p>
<p>The same is true for another variety of this flower, camelia sinensis var. assamica. Native to India, this kind is more like a tree.</p>
<p>You will have to research which kinds of camellia sinensis can grow in your area.</p>
<p>On its website, the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://internationalcamellia.org/en-us/caring-for-camellias/winter-protection-of-camellias">International Camellia Society</a> gives you suggestions for how to protect these plants during a cold weather.</p>
<ul>
<li>Mulching: Apply a thick layer of mulch around the base to protect the roots.</li>
<li>Covering: Use a cloth to cover the plant during extreme cold.</li>
<li>Watering: Water the plant well before the first freeze.</li>
<li>Location: Plant your camellia in a sheltered spot, such as near a building, to protect it from cold winds.</li>
<li><strong>Pruning</strong>: Avoid pruning late in the season. New growth may not survive colder weather.</li>
</ul>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo. And I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Jessica Damiano reported this story for the Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>garden </strong><em>– v.</em><strong> </strong>to grow<strong> </strong>herbs, fruits, flowers, or vegetables</p>
<p><strong>bud </strong><em>– n. </em>a small growth at the tip or on the side of a plant stem that later develops into a flower, leaf, or new shoot</p>
<p><strong>evergreen </strong><em>– adj. </em>having foliage that remains green and functional through more than one growing season</p>
<p><strong>shade </strong><em>– n. </em>space sheltered from the heat and bright light of the sun</p>
<p><strong>acidic </strong><em>– adj. </em>Acidic soil tends to have mineral deficiencies that can affect plant growth. By definition, acidity is the characteristic of soil that has a pH level of less than 6.5 (a reading of 5.5 means the soil is very acidic).</p>
<p><strong>steam </strong><em>– v. </em>the invisible vapor into which water is changed when heated to the boiling point</p>
<p><strong>brew </strong><em>– v. </em>to prepare (as tea) by soaking in hot water</p>
<p><strong>wilt </strong><em>– v. </em>to lose or cause to lose freshness and become limp</p>
<p><strong>oven</strong> <em>– n. </em>a chamber used for baking, heating, or drying<em> </em></p>
<p><strong>prune </strong><em>– v.</em> to cut off or cut back parts of for better shape or more fruitful growth</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Democrats Back Harris as Biden Leaves Presidential Race (2024/7/23) | 拜登退选 民主党改推哈里斯</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/democrats-back-harris-as-biden-leaves-presidential-race.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>Democratic Party lawmakers, some governors, and financial donors are supporting U.S. Vice President Kamala Harris to be the party's presidential nominee.<br/>民主党议员、部分州长和财政捐助者开始支持美国副总统卡玛拉·哈里斯成为该党的总统候选人。</p><p>The move came shortly after President Joe Biden said on Sunday that he would not seek the presidency again. Biden made the surprise announcement on the social media website X. He also endorsed, or threw his support to, Harris.<br/>此举是在乔·拜登总统周日表示他不会寻求连任不久后做出的。拜登在社交媒体网站X上宣布了这一出人意料的消息。他还支持哈里斯。</p><p>Harris, who is 59 years old, quickly announced that she would seek the nomination. She said, “I will do everything in my power to unite the Democratic Party – and unite our nation – to defeat Donald Trump.”<br/>现年59岁的哈里斯很快宣布她将寻求提名。她说：“我将尽我所能团结民主党，团结我们的国家，打败唐纳德·川普。”</p><p>Last week, former President Donald Trump accepted the nomination of the Republican Party in the Midwestern city of Milwaukee, Wisconsin. He chose Ohio Senator J.D. Vance as his vice-presidential nominee.<br/>上周，前总统唐纳德·川普在威斯康星州中西部城市密尔沃基接受了共和党的提名。他选择俄亥俄州参议员J.D.万斯作为他的副总统候选人。</p><p>Biden's decision<br/>拜登的决定</p><p>Biden's decision to leave the 2024 race followed rising calls from Democrats urging him to “pass the torch” to a new generation.<br/>拜登决定退出2024年的竞选，此前民主党人呼吁他将“火炬”传递给新一代。</p><p>In his June 27 debate against Trump, the 81-year-old president often appeared to be unable to complete his thoughts. He also failed to press his case against the 78-year-old Trump or defend his work in The White House. Despite concerns from Democrats about his debate performance and decreasing electoral support, Biden said he would stay in the race.<br/>在6月27日与川普的辩论中，这位81岁的总统似乎经常无法自圆其说。他也没有对78岁的川普提起诉讼，也没有为自己在白宫的工作辩护。尽管民主党人对他的辩论表现和选举支持率下降表示担忧，但拜登表示他将继续参加竞选。</p><p>But on Sunday, he said in a statement, “I believe it is in the best interest of my party and the country for me to stand down and to focus solely on fulfilling my duties as president for the remainder of my term.” Biden's term ends in six months in January. Biden added that he plans to address the nation about his decision later this week.<br/>但周日，他在一份声明中表示，“我认为我退选，并在剩余任期内专注于履行总统职责，符合我的政党和国家的最佳利益。”拜登的任期将于明年1月结束，为期六个月。拜登补充说，他计划本周晚些时候就自己的决定向全国发表讲话。</p><p>In a statement, Harris spoke about Biden's withdrawal. She said, Biden “is doing what he has done throughout this life of service: putting the American people and our country above everything else.”<br/>哈里斯在一份声明中谈到了拜登的退出。她说，拜登“正在做他在整个从政生涯中所做的事情：把美国人民和我们的国家置于一切之上。”</p><p>The decision came just weeks before the start of the Democratic National Convention in Chicago on August 19. That is the event where the Democratic Party officially decides on its nominee. Before Biden's withdrawal, the party was considering a virtual vote for delegates before the convention.<br/>这一决定是在8月19日芝加哥民主党全国代表大会开始前几周做出的。这是民主党正式决定其候选人的大会。在拜登退出之前，该党正考虑在大会前对代表进行虚拟投票。</p><p>Harris' many firsts<br/>哈里斯的许多第一</p><p>Before becoming vice president, Harris served as Attorney General, a top law enforcement position, in the state of California. In 2017, she was elected to the U.S. Senate. Biden chose her in 2020 as a running mate after her own presidential campaign failed to gain enough support.<br/>在成为副总统之前，哈里斯曾担任加利福尼亚州检察总长。2017年，她当选为美国参议院议员。2020年她在总统竞选中未能获得足够，之后拜登选择她作为竞选伙伴。</p><p>If Harris is nominated by the Democratic Party to replace Biden, she would be the first Black woman and South Asian major party presidential nominee in the 248-year history of the United States.<br/>如果哈里斯被民主党提名接替拜登，她将成为美国248年历史上第一位黑人女性和南亚裔的主要政党总统候选人。</p><p>Harris's public approval rating has largely followed the president's approval numbers. Some opinion studies say Harris has a little more support than Biden when compared to Trump.<br/>哈里斯的公众支持率在很大程度上沿袭了拜登总统的支持率。一些民意研究表明，在与川普的较量中，哈里斯的支持率略高于拜登。</p><p>As vice president, one of her early assignments was to deal with the causes of migration in the country's southern border with Mexico. Harris also oversaw the administration's efforts on voting rights and election reforms. With a divided Congress, however, Harris was not able to achieve results.<br/>作为副总统，她早期的任务之一是处理该国与墨西哥南部边境的移民问题。哈里斯还监督了政府在投票权和选举改革方面的努力。然而，由于国会意见分歧，哈里斯未能取得成果。</p><p>Since the U.S. Supreme Court overturned federal protections for abortion rights in June 2022, Harris has been the leading voice to push for greater access.<br/>自2022年6月美国最高法院推翻联邦对堕胎权的保护以来，哈里斯一直是推动获得更大堕胎权的主要声音。</p><p>To mark the second anniversary of the court decision, Harris told supporters in Maryland, "This is a fight for freedom: the fundamental freedom of a woman to make decisions about her own body and not having her government tell her what to do."<br/>为了纪念法院判决两周年，哈里斯在马里兰州告诉支持者，“这是一场争取自由的斗争：女性对自己的身体做出决定的基本自由，而不是让政府告诉她该怎么做。”</p><p>I'm Jill Robbins.<br/>我是吉尔·罗宾斯。(21VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Evidence of ‘Rotten Egg’ Gas Found on Jupiter-like Exoplanet (2024/7/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/evidence-of-rotten-egg-gas-found-on-jupiter-like-exoplanet.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists say they have found evidence that the smelly molecule hydrogen sulfide exists in the atmosphere of a Jupiter-like planet. Hydrogen sulfide is the chemical compound that gives <strong>rotten</strong> eggs their bad smell.</p>
<p>The planet is called HD 189733b. It is an exoplanet, a term used to describe planets that exist outside of our own solar system. It was discovered in 2005.</p>
<p>Scientists had already identified similarities between HD 189733b and Jupiter, the oldest and largest planet in our solar system. But the exoplanet was previously not thought to hold hydrogen sulfide.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="An artist's concept of the planet HD 189733 b, located 64 light-years from Earth, orbiting close to its host star. (Roberto Molar Candanosa/Johns Hopkins University/Handout via REUTERS)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-da7f-08dca1bdb585_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">An artist's concept of the planet HD 189733 b, located 64 light-years from Earth, orbiting close to its host star. (Roberto Molar Candanosa/Johns Hopkins University/Handout via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>Astronomers who study this gas giant have said it is deep blue in color and that severe conditions exist in the atmosphere.</p>
<p>It has winds that can blow up to two kilometers per second. The exoplanet is believed to reach temperatures up to 930 degrees Celsius on the side facing the star that it orbits. Scientists also say it rains glass, which can be blown by fierce winds.</p>
<p>The weather on HD 189733b is so extreme, the American space agency NASA once <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/image-article/rains-of-terror-exoplanet-hd-189733b/">described</a> the planet as a “<strong>nightmare</strong> world.”</p>
<p>New observations by NASA's James Webb Space Telescope suggest that this is the first exoplanet where hydrogen sulfide has been identified. Scientists say the discovery has helped give them a better understanding of this stormy world.</p>
<p>The finding was recently explained in a study <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07760-y">appearing</a> in the publication <em>Nature</em>.</p>
<p>One of the leaders of the research was astrophysicist Guangwei Fu of Johns Hopkins University in Maryland. He told Reuters, “This is not a planet we humans want to visit, but a valuable target for furthering our understanding of planetary science."</p>
<p>Fu said HD 189733b is known as a “hot Jupiter” planet. However, it orbits 170 times closer to its star than Jupiter does to the sun. It completes one orbit every two days. Jupiter takes about 12 years to orbit the sun.</p>
<p>Fu noted that hot Jupiters are not found often. "About less than one in 100 star systems have them," he said.</p>
<p>Fu said he thinks the newly discovered “<strong>stinky</strong> smell” just adds another interesting element to what is already known about the planet. It is 64 light-years from Earth, in the <strong>constellation </strong>Vulpecula. A light-year is the distance light travels in a year, about 9.5 trillion kilometers.</p>
<p>It is closer to Earth than many exoplanets. This makes it “bright and easy for detailed studies,” Fu said. He noted, for example, that hydrogen sulfide would have been much harder to find on planets that are further away.</p>
<p>The Webb telescope – which became operational in 2022 – is able to observe a wider <strong>range</strong> of radiation wavelengths than earlier telescopes. This permits more detailed examinations of exoplanet atmospheres.</p>
<p>"Our research finds that HD 189733b is more similar to Jupiter than previously known," said Arizona State University astrophysicist Luis Welbanks. He was a member of the research team. "This planet is very much like Jupiter, but just hotter."</p>
<p>Jupiter, too, has small amounts of hydrogen sulfide in its atmosphere. But the exoplanet is about 10 percent larger than Jupiter in diameter and mass.</p>
<p>The Webb observations also confirmed earlier evidence showing the exoplanet has water and carbon dioxide in its atmosphere.</p>
<p>"With these three molecules, we are able to count the amount of oxygen, carbon and sulfur the planet has,” Welbanks said. That information, he added, gives scientists a chance to learn more about how the planet may have formed. It should also provide data on whether it is different from planets in our solar system.</p>
<p>Welbanks said the scientists are clearly not searching for life on such a hot, <strong>harsh</strong> planet. However, he noted that understanding its atmosphere permits them to “understand how physics and chemistry behave under different environments and to begin to put together the '<strong>recipe</strong>' for forming planets."</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Reuters reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>rotten</strong> <em>- adj.</em> suffering from decay</p>
<p><strong>nightmare </strong><em>– v.</em> a frightening or unpleasant experience</p>
<p><strong>stinky </strong><em>– adj. </em>having or producing an unpleasant smell</p>
<p><strong>constellation </strong><em>– adj. </em>a group of stars that forms a particular shape in the sky and has been given a name</p>
<p><strong>range </strong><em>–n.</em> a series of numbers or values that include the highest and lowest</p>
<p><strong>harsh </strong><em>– adj. </em>unpleasant, unkind or more severe than is necessary</p>
<p><strong>recipe </strong><em>– n. </em>a set of instructions explaining how to prepare and cook food</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Japanese Scientists Make Robot Face ‘Smile’ with Lab-Grown Skin (2024/7/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/japanese-scientists-make-robot-face-smile-with-lab-grown-skin.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">21 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Japanese scientists have found a way to attach living skin tissue to robotic faces and make them "smile." This breakthrough could be helpful not only in robotics, but also in <strong>cosmetics</strong> and medicine.</p>
<p>Researchers at the University of Tokyo started the process by growing human skin cells in the shape of a face. Then, they used attachments that are similar to the <strong>ligaments</strong> in a human to pull the tissue into a wide smile.</p>
<p><strong>First step to other breakthroughs</strong></p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="Robot scientists in Japan have created a robot face using tissue they grew in a lab. They see it as an important step toward developing more life-like robots." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-f9ad-08dca7414e13_w268_r1.jpg.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">Robot scientists in Japan have created a robot face using tissue they grew in a lab. They see it as an important step toward developing more life-like robots.</span></div>
<p>Lead researcher Shoji Takeuchi is a professor at the University of Tokyo. He said the result is an important step towards building more life-like robots. Using the attachments, he said, “it became possible to <strong>manipulate</strong> living skin for the first time.”</p>
<p>The study about the smiling robot appeared last month in <em>Cell Reports Physical Science</em>. It represents 10 years of research by Takeuchi and his lab on how to best combine biological and artificial machines.</p>
<p>Living tissue is better for this application than metals and plastics, Takeuchi said. He noted that brains and muscles are more <strong>efficient</strong> in use of energy and the skin can repair itself.</p>
<p>In the future, the researchers aim to add more elements to the lab-grown skin, including a <strong>circulatory</strong> system and nerves. That could lead to safer testing methods for cosmetics and drugs <strong>absorbed</strong>, or taken in, through the skin.</p>
<p>It could also produce more realistic and functional coverings for robots. The remaining issue is how people react to machines that appear almost lifelike, but do not look exactly like humans.</p>
<p>"There's still a bit of that <strong>creepiness</strong> to it," Takeuchi said about the robot.</p>
<p><strong>The uncanny valley</strong></p>
<p>He added, "I think that making robots out of the same materials as humans and having them show the same expressions might be one key to overcoming the <strong>uncanny</strong> valley."</p>
<p>The “uncanny valley” is an idea that relates to how humans react to robots or other machines that act like humans. “Uncanny” is an adjective that means “being beyond what is normal or expected.”</p>
<p>Japanese robotics scientist Masahiro Mori published a work, <em>Bukimi No Tani</em>, or “Uncanny Valley” in 1970. It proposed how people would react to lifelike robots, or androids.</p>
<p>Mori thought that at first, people would have <strong>positive</strong> feelings about robots that look a little bit like humans. But as robots got closer to being realistic human models, he believed those feelings would become more <strong>negative</strong>.</p>
<p>Those negative feelings are the so-called low point, or “valley,” in a chart that represents the relationship between the human-like appearance of robots and humans' feelings toward and acceptance of such robots.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Rocky Swift reported this story for Reuters. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English with additional information from the Brittancia Dictionary.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>cosmetic</strong> – <em>n</em>. a substance (such as a cream, lotion, or powder) that you put on your face or body to improve your appearance</p>
<p><strong>ligament</strong> – <em>n. </em>a tough piece of tissue in your body that holds bones together or keeps an organ in place</p>
<p><strong>eerie </strong>– adj. strange and mysterious</p>
<p><strong>manipulate</strong> – <em>v</em>. to move or control (something) with your hands or by using a machine</p>
<p><strong>circulatory</strong> – <em>adj</em>. of or relating to the circulation of blood through the body</p>
<p><strong>creepy</strong> – <em>adj.</em> producing a nervous shivery apprehension; annoyingly unpleasant</p>
<p><strong>affinity</strong> – n. an attraction to or liking for something</p>
<p><strong>uncanny valley</strong><em> – n.</em> the unsettling feeling that comes when robots start to resemble humans a little too closely.</p>
<p><strong>positive </strong>– <em>adj</em>. thinking about the good qualities of someone or something</p>
<p><strong>negative</strong>– <em>adj</em>. thinking about the bad qualities of someone or something</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Turkey’s Export of TV Shows Also Fuels Tourism (2024/7/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/turkey-s-export-of-tv-shows-also-fuels-tourism.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">21 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Turkey has become a leading exporter of television shows in recent years.</p>
<p>Millions of people are watching Turkish TV <strong>dramas</strong> known as Dizi. Many of the shows involve the nation's famous historical and cultural places.</p>
<p>Experts say the success of the television dramas has created a billion-dollar industry that continues to expand. Between 2020 and 2023, demand for Turkish TV series increased by 184 percent. That number comes from Los Angeles-based research company Parrot Analytics.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A production team is filming scenes of a Turkish drama with actor Paris Baktas and actress Yagmur Yuksel, Turkey, Tuesday, April 30, 2024. (AP Photo/Khalil Hamra)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-ab4e-08dca66d8ee2_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A production team is filming scenes of a Turkish drama with actor Paris Baktas and actress Yagmur Yuksel, Turkey, Tuesday, April 30, 2024. (AP Photo/Khalil Hamra)
</span></div>
<p>Izzet Pinto is chief of the Turkish media company Global Agency. “We reach over 400 million <strong>viewers</strong> every night around the world,” he said. Global Agency exports Turkish dramas to world markets. Pinto noted, “The soft power we create with Turkish dramas cannot be even compared to what could be done in politics.”</p>
<p>The Turkish drama <em>Deli Yurek</em> was the first to be exported. Turkey sent it to Kazakhstan in 2001. But it was the love story series called <em>Gumus </em>that brought fame to Turkish dizis. The story is about a traditional woman who must <strong>adapt</strong> to life in the city. Gumus grew hugely popular in the Middle East.</p>
<p>In 2006, viewers in Europe's southeastern Balkans area enjoyed <em>A Thousand and One Nights</em>, a series based on Middle Eastern folktales. The stories were set in modern-day Istanbul. Turkish TV also produced the show <em>Magnificent Century</em>, a popular historical drama based on the life of Ottoman Sultan Suleyman the Magnificent.</p>
<p>Turkey was once an importer of Latin American TV dramas known as telenovelas. Now, it is exporting TV shows to Latin American countries. In 2018, Venezuelan President Nicolás Maduro visited the set of the Turkish drama <em>Resurrection: Ertugrul</em>.</p>
<p>Haley Uganadi founded a website for fans of Turkish TV series called Dizilah. About 1.5 million people from the United States, Canada, Greece, India and Pakistan visit her website monthly.</p>
<p>Uganadi said the popularity of the dramas comes from their subjects. She said they are about family, friendship and love and usually involve rich people in Istanbul or historical stories.</p>
<p>Uganadi said the shows offer “something for everyone,” and added, “I see <strong>reflections</strong> of my mom, myself and my siblings” in them.</p>
<p>Pinto of Global Agency agrees that Turkish dramas are right for everybody. “There is no <strong>nudity</strong>, no cursing or bad words, not much hate,” he said, “So, it becomes watchable for the family.”</p>
<p>As Turkey's industry grows, it is expanding the themes of its series. For example, the series <em>Red Roses</em> explores issues affecting a family that is culturally Western and a <strong>fictional</strong> Islamic brotherhood.</p>
<p>During a recent period between filming, actor Ozcan Deniz told the Associated Press that <strong>diversification</strong> is important for industry growth.</p>
<p>He said, “Countries that were not able to transform (into) a different <strong>genre</strong> are now lagging behind in the export of series.” He added, “Turkey has now caught this momentum, but if it cannot diversify, if it cannot also tell different things, it will end somewhere.”</p>
<p><em>Resurrection: Ertugrul</em> is an example of the growing success of Turkish series. Mehmet Bozdag is a producer and writer. He said the first show of the series had over 157 million views on the Urdu language YouTube channel of Turkish state broadcaster TRT. Another series, <em>Foundation: Osman</em>, was broadcast in over 110 countries.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Robert Badendieck reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>drama </strong>–n. a story about a serious or realistic subject</p>
<p><strong>soft power</strong> <em>–n. </em>influence among nations that is not based on military strength but on cultural and non-tangible qualities</p>
<p><strong>viewer</strong> <em>–n.</em> a person who watches television</p>
<p><strong>reflection </strong><em>–n.</em> a similarity</p>
<p><strong>fictional </strong><em>–adj.</em> something from stories that is not real</p>
<p><strong>nudity </strong><em>–n.</em> the state of having no clothes on</p>
<p><strong>diversification </strong><em>–n.</em> the idea of being involved in several different areas to protect against losing too much if one area fails to produce</p>
<p><strong>flourish </strong><em>–v.</em> to grow and expand in health and wealth</p>
<p><strong>genre </strong><em>–n. (art)</em> a specific kind of art form with certain qualities</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Be Careful What You 'Bank On' (2024/7/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/be-careful-what-you-bank-on.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">20 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories</em> from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>On today's show, we take you to the bank.</p>
<p>Banks help us manage our money. When we make <strong>deposits</strong>, we put money in; when we make <strong>withdrawals</strong>, we take money out. Banks help us reach important life goals. We can borrow money from a bank to buy a house. A bank can loan us money to start a business.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Customers use ATMs at a Bank of America branch office in Boston, Oct. 16, 2009. (AP Photo/Lisa Poole, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-6a82-08dca75452eb_cx3_cy0_cw91_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Customers use ATMs at a Bank of America branch office in Boston, Oct. 16, 2009. (AP Photo/Lisa Poole, File)</span></div>
<p>So, we need to trust our banks. And that need for trust gives us some idiomatic expressions in American English that are connected to banks.</p>
<p>The first is simply <u>to bank on something.</u> If you bank on something, you trust it will happen. In fact, you count on it happening. Sometimes we use this expression to mean our strategy <strong>depends</strong> on something to happen.</p>
<p>Here are some examples:</p>
<p><em>When a city hosts the Olympics, they <u>bank on</u> drawing large crowds to see the games. </em></p>
<p><em>To win the election, the politician is <u>banking on</u> voters finding out about his opponent's <strong>scandals</strong>.</em></p>
<p>We often use this expression in a set phrase: to <u>bank on</u> the fact that something will happen.</p>
<p>For example, you can <u>bank on the fact that</u> a famous person caught doing something wrong will soon give a public apology. It is certain to happen.</p>
<p>You can <u>bank on the fact that </u>if I see chocolate cake, I will eat it. It is a given. It will happen.</p>
<p>If you are very sure something will happen, it's <u>like money in the bank.</u></p>
<p>When we have <u>money in the bank</u>, we count on it to be there when we need it. Banks offer guarantees that they will protect our money. So, if something is <u>like money in the bank</u>, it is a guarantee. It is a certainty.</p>
<p>When we say “<u>you can take that to the bank</u>,” we mean something is a sure thing. It is true or certain to happen.</p>
<p>We finish today's show with one more expression, which sounds like a funny situation.</p>
<p>If you <u>laugh all the way to the bank,</u> you make a lot of money with very little effort.</p>
<p>This expression also can mean that you are happy about making money from something that others think is unfair or even bad.</p>
<p>In other situations, it means that you make money from something that others think is a waste of time.</p>
<p>For example, when a woman started a <strong>organic</strong> homemade dog food business, her friends thought it was a <strong>silly</strong> idea. They even laughed at her idea. But it ended up being very successful and made her very rich. So, now she is the one laughing – <u>laughing all the way to the bank!</u></p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>.</p>
<p>If you want to learn English, the stories and programs at VOA Learning English can help you out. You can take that to the bank!</p>
<p>Until next time ... I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>deposit </strong><em>– n. </em>money deposited in a bank</p>
<p><strong>withdrawal </strong><em>– n. </em>an act or instance of withdrawing</p>
<p>especially : a removal of money from a bank account</p>
<p><strong>depend </strong><em>– v. </em>to place reliance or trust : to rely for support</p>
<p><strong>scandal </strong><em>– n. </em>a situation or event that is thought to be shocking and immoral and that everyone knows about : reports about actions or events that cause shock and disapproval:</p>
<p><strong>organic </strong><em>– adj. </em>relating to, producing, dealing in, or involving foods produced with the use of feed or fertilizer obtained from plants or animals and without the use of laboratory-made fertilizers, growth substances, antibiotics, or pesticides</p>
<p><strong>silly</strong> <em>– adj. </em>not showing common sense or good judgment</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>UN: World Population Expected to Reach 10.3 Billion in 2080s (2024/7/21) | 联合国预计全球人口本世纪80年代达峰</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/un-world-population-expected-to-reach-10-3-billion-in-2080s.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<p>The United Nations is predicting the world's population will reach 10.3 billion in the 2080s.<br/>
联合国预测，到本世纪80年代，世界人口将达到103亿。</p>
<p>The prediction appears in a new U.N. report. The report also suggests that the population will then slightly decrease to about 10.2 billion by the end of the century.<br/>
这一预测出现在一份新的联合国报告中。报告还表明，到本世纪末，人口将略微减少到约102亿。</p>
<p>John Wilmoth is head of the U.N. Population Division, which prepared the report. He told The Associated Press (AP) that there is a high probability that the world's population will reach its height, or peak, within the current century. He said the probability of that happening is about 80 percent. Wilmoth described that estimate as “a major change” compared to predictions from 10 years ago. At that time, the estimated probability was about 30 percent.<br/>
约翰·威尔莫斯是联合国人口司司长，该部门负责编写这份报告。他告诉美联社，世界人口很可能在本世纪内达到最高点。他说，这种情况发生的可能性约为80%。威尔莫斯将这一估计描述为与10年前预测相比的“重大变化”。当时估计发生这种情况的概率约为30%。</p>
<p>U.N. Assistant Secretary-General for Economic Development Navid Hanif recently spoke about the report at a briefing. He said the expectation that the world's population in 2100 will be lower than previously thought has “important policy implications for the sustainability of our planet.”<br/>
联合国负责经济发展的助理秘书长纳维德·哈尼夫最近在一次简报会上谈到了这份报告。他说，预计2100年世界人口将低于此前的预期，这“对我们地球的可持续性具有重要的政策影响”。</p>
<p>The world's population has continued to grow during the past 75 years, from an estimated 2.6 billion in 1950 to 8 billion in November 2022. Since then, it has increased about 2.5 percent to 8.2 billion.<br/>
在过去的75年里，世界人口持续增长，从1950年的估值26亿增长到2022年11月的80亿。自那以后，这一数字增长了约2.5%，达到82亿。</p>
<p>The report notes the population has already peaked in 63 countries and territories. These include China, Germany, Japan and Russia. Within this grouping, the total population is estimated to drop 14 percent over the next 30 years.<br/>
报告指出，有63个国家和地区的人口已经达到峰值。这些国家包括中国、德国、日本和俄罗斯。预计未来30年这一组国家的总人口将下降14%。</p>
<p>In another 48 countries and territories, the population is predicted to peak between 2025 and 2054. Those countries include Brazil, Iran, Turkey and Vietnam.<br/>
预计另外48个国家和地区的人口将在2025年至2054年间达到峰值。这些国家包括巴西、伊朗、土耳其和越南。</p>
<p>For the remaining 126 countries and territories, the population is expected to increase through 2054. The countries in this grouping include the United States, India, Indonesia, Nigeria and Pakistan. The report said these areas would see their populations peak in the second half of the century or later.<br/>
其余126个国家和地区的人口预计将一直增长到2054年。这一组国家包括美国、印度、印度尼西亚、尼日利亚和巴基斯坦。报告称，这些地区的人口将在本世纪下半叶或之后达到峰值。</p>
<p>For nine of these nations, the U.N. estimates the populations will double between 2024 and 2054.<br/>
联合国估计，其中9个国家的人口将在2024年至2054年间翻一番。</p>
<p>Wilmoth said these differences are notable. But he said, “it's important to understand that all populations are following a similar path.”<br/>
威尔莫斯说，这些差异是显著的。但他说，“重要的是要明白，所有国家的人口都走在类似的道路上。”</p>
<p>The U.N. report suggests the earlier population peak is predicted for several reasons.<br/>
联合国的报告表明，预测人口峰值提前有多个原因。</p>
<p>The report noted that worldwide, women are having an average of one less child than they did in 1990. In addition, the average number of live births per woman is below 2.1 in over half of all countries and territories. This is a level experts have identified as being necessary for a country's population to keep its size without migration.<br/>
报告指出，全世界妇女平均比1990年少生一个孩子。此外，在超过一半的国家和地区，每名妇女的平均活产数低于2.1。专家们认为，这个数字是一个国家在没有移民的情况下保持人口规模所必需的水平。</p>
<p>Wilmoth said the report shows that nearly 20 percent of the world has “ultra-low” fertility, with women having fewer than 1.5 live births.<br/>
威尔莫斯说，报告显示，世界上近20%的国家拥有“超低”生育率，女性活产不到1.5个。</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.<br/>
我是布莱恩·林恩。(21VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Church Bells in Spanish Town Ring Out a Return to Tradition (2024/7/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/church-bells-in-spanish-town-ring-out-a-return-to-tradition.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p class="MsoBodyText">The sound of <strong>church</strong> bells around the world is usually made by machine. But before newspapers, radio, telephones, television and the internet, bell ringing by hand communicated important information within small communities across Europe.</p>
<p>Now, a small school of bell ringers in northeastern Spain wants to recover the art of hand, or manual, bell ringing. The school's founder and leader, Xavier Pallàs, says there is a whole language of bell ringing to rescue and return to use.</p>
<p>The Vall d'en Bas School of Bell Ringers effort comes two years after the international community recognized the import of manual bell ringing in Spain. The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization, UNESCO, added the practice to its Humanity's Intangible Cultural Heritage list in 2022.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="View of the bell tower of the 12th-century Sant Rom&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;224; church, where students of the Vall d'en Bas School of Bell Ringers perform playing bells, in the small Spanish village of Joanetes, Spain, June 29, 2024. (AP Photo/Emilio Morenatti)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/79708420-3b0e-4a55-b62b-96a4f718cd7f_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">View of the bell tower of the 12th-century Sant Rom<i>&amp;#</i>224; church, where students of the Vall d'en Bas School of Bell Ringers perform playing bells, in the small Spanish village of Joanetes, Spain, June 29, 2024. (AP Photo/Emilio Morenatti)</span></div>
<p><strong>A method of messaging for centuries</strong></p>
<p>Pallàs' students have learned how to ring out calls for village celebrations, warnings of bad weather or fire, religious services, and deaths. Pallàs says bells could still "help mark the <strong>rituals</strong> that we need."</p>
<p>The change to mechanical ringing devices over the past century has flattened the bells' songs and muted their messaging powers, the teacher said. If the bells are played with expertise, he added, the sound can signal a time for celebrating or mourning. The sound can even signal when to run to the aid of a neighbor in need.</p>
<p>"For centuries, the tolling of church bells was our most important communication method," said Pallàs. He spoke inside the <strong>belfry </strong>that also serves as classroom, in the town of Joanetes.</p>
<p>"Machines cannot reproduce the richness of the sounds that we used to hear, so there has been a simplification and unification of bell ringing. The language has been lost little by little until now, when we are finally recognizing its worth."</p>
<p><strong>Reconnecting with the past</strong></p>
<p>Manual church bell ringing has continued in Eastern Orthodox countries. But most Christian churches in Western Europe today use electronic bell ringing systems.</p>
<p>The students at Vall d'en Bas include women and men from <strong>diverse</strong> professional backgrounds. One student was in his 20s. Several students were retirees.</p>
<p>All spent the past few months researching bell <strong>sequences</strong>, documenting their history and learning to play them.</p>
<p>Roser Sauri jumped at the chance to reconnect with her childhood. She worked to recover and play the sequence that had sounded in her grandfather's village to announce his baptism.</p>
<p>"The bells formed a part of my life," said Sauri, who now works in artificial intelligence.</p>
<p><strong>Honoring humans and God</strong></p>
<p>Juan Carles Osuna and two other students recently tolled for the death of a woman. That meant <strong>swinging</strong> the largest of the bells. It weighs 429 kilograms.</p>
<p>"It's an emotional experience,” Osuna said. “You feel your blood pumping. You feel the strength, and how you are communicating with everyone in earshot.”</p>
<p>He added, "For me it is an honor, it's a way to honor both humans and God."</p>
<p><strong>Dreaming of bell ringers across Spain</strong></p>
<p>Xavier Pallàs says he has a full class lined up for the fall and about 60 more people on an admission wait list. He believes that a recovery of bell ringing in a neighborhood or town's life could help strengthen local communities.</p>
<p>The school leader said, "This is a means of communication that reaches everyone inside a local community and can help it come together at <strong>concrete</strong> moments."</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><em>______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>church</strong> - <em>n. </em>a building for public holy services, especially of Christian belief</p>
<p><strong>ritual </strong>- <em>n. </em>ceremony, especially of religious tradition</p>
<p><strong>belfry </strong>- <em>n. </em>a bell tower</p>
<p><strong>diverse </strong>- <em>adj. </em>involving many different kinds of related or similar things</p>
<p><strong>sequence </strong>- <em>n. </em>the order in which things are or should be connected, related, or dated</p>
<p><strong>swing </strong>- <em>v. </em>to move quickly in a sweeping curve</p>
<p><strong>concrete </strong>- <em>adj. </em><strong> </strong>belonging to or based on actual experience; not abstract</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Who’s and Whose (2024/7/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/who-s-and-whose.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Mei Jen in China about the usage of two words that sound the same.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-8d3b-08dca12051c6_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>I have some question(s) about the words <em>whose </em>and <em>who's</em>. I sometimes have confusion when I hear. I am not always sure what word I am hearing. Can you please share with me your advice?</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>Thank you for writing to us Mei Jen. I'm happy to answer this question.</p>
<p>The easiest way to know which word you are hearing is to listen for the words that follow it.</p>
<p><strong>Who's</strong></p>
<p>We contract, or join together, the two words <em>who is</em> to make the contraction “who's.” Often, the next word you hear after “who's” is a verb, as in these examples:</p>
<p><em>Who's going to help us?</em></p>
<p><em>Who's making all that noise?</em></p>
<p><em>Who's using this computer?</em></p>
<p>Sometimes, you will hear a prepositional phrase or a noun phrase after the contraction “who's.”</p>
<p><em>Who's in the office today?</em></p>
<p><em>Who's the director of that film?</em></p>
<p>Last, we can contract the word “who” with the verb “has." So, the sentence “Who has already seen this film?” sounds like this:</p>
<p><em>Who's already seen this film?</em></p>
<p><strong>Whose</strong></p>
<p>Now, let's look at the possessive “whose," spelled w-h-o-s-e.</p>
<p>We use it to ask about who owns or has something. So, you should listen for a noun after the pronoun “whose," or you can listen for the adjectives “this,” “that,” “these,” or “those.”</p>
<p>For example, if we see a book on a desk and we do not know who owns it, we can ask either of the following questions:</p>
<p><em>Whose book is this?</em></p>
<p><em>Whose book is that?</em></p>
<p>You can hear the noun “book,” and you can also hear the adjectives “this” and “that” at the end of the question.</p>
<p>We use the word “this” if we are close to the book. If we are farther away from the book, we use the word “that.”</p>
<p>We use the adjectives “these” and “those” for plural things.</p>
<p><em>Whose shoes are these?</em></p>
<p><em>Whose bags are those?</em></p>
<p>We can also place the contraction “who's” and the possessive “whose” at the beginning of a noun clause. The noun clause begins after the main verb of the sentence, as in these examples:</p>
<p><em>I want to know who's going to drive the bus.</em></p>
<p><em>I want to know whose idea this was. </em></p>
<p>You can learn more about the possessive “whose,” including its use in relative clauses, in this Everyday Grammar on <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/everyday-grammar-the-mysterious-word-whose-/4479936.html">The Mysterious Word ‘Whose'</a>.</p>
<p>We hope today's lesson is helpful, Mei Jen.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, do you have a question about American English? Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.<em> </em></p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Climate Change Affects Traditional Spearfishing (2024/7/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/climate-change-affects-traditional-spearfishing.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Cold nights, on Chippewa Flowage, a lake in the state of Wisconsin, do not stop 15-year-old Gabe Bisonette. He has been learning spearfishing, a tradition of the Ojibwe Native American <strong>tribe</strong>, for a long time. Ojibwe and other <strong>indigenous</strong> people are fighting to keep this way of fishing alive.</p>
<p>But the number of walleye fish in the lake is decreasing due to warming waters, seasonal changes and lake development. Losing this fish would mean losing a food source for community members and a deep connection to tradition and nature.</p>
<p>Many in the community say that with science and good management, they will be able to continue this tradition in the future. But there is also concern about the changes that are already happening.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="John Baker holds a spear while getting ready to fish at the Chippewa Flowage on the Lac Courte Oreilles Reservation, Sunday, April 14, 2024, near Hayward, Wisconsin. (AP Photo/John Locher)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-0740-08dca4f32ae3_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">John Baker holds a spear while getting ready to fish at the Chippewa Flowage on the Lac Courte Oreilles Reservation, Sunday, April 14, 2024, near Hayward, Wisconsin. (AP Photo/John Locher)</span></div>
<p>“We've seen things here over the last couple of years that I've never seen before,” said Brian Bisonette, Gabe's uncle. He and Gabe are both members of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribe. The group is one of the bands of the Ojibwe people.</p>
<p>Bisonette is the <strong>conservation</strong> director of Lac Courte Oreilles Conservation Department. He said past tribal leaders understood the need for securing enough food to live in their homeland. So, they got the right to hunt, fish, and gather wild rice in certain areas as part of 19<sup>th</sup>-century treaties. These same treaties gave land to settlers.</p>
<p>But for a long time after that, the state of Wisconsin lessened treaty rights of tribes. In some cases, officials even arrested members for taking part in tribal activities.</p>
<p>A 1983 Supreme Court decision held up the rights of the Ojibwe people. As a result, angry locals showed up at lakes to trouble tribal members. They damaged vehicles, shouted racist comments and shot at spearfishers.</p>
<p>Today, officials guard every boat landing. But incidents still happen.</p>
<p>Tribes and local conservation teams are finding ways to protect walleye and the spearing tradition. Spearfishers are required to get permits that limit the number of fish they can take. And some lakes are filled with fish born in a <strong>hatchery</strong> and released into the lake. But still the goal in many cases is to increase natural <strong>reproduction</strong>.</p>
<p>“Whether it's tribal or non-tribal, this is a concern for all of us,” Bisonette said.</p>
<p><strong>Lake ecosystems in danger </strong></p>
<p>On another lake, Lac Courte Oreilles, Department of Natural Resources (DNR) biologist Max Wolter and supervisor Angelena Sikora look for walleye, too.</p>
<p>They capture, measure, and record the size and sex of the fish. The goal is to get a clear picture of the fish populations of <strong>inland</strong> lakes, including Chippewa Flowage and Lac Courte Oreilles.</p>
<p>The DNR gathers this information in partnership with tribal conservation partners and the Great Lakes Indian Fish and Wildlife Commission.</p>
<p>After examining the numbers, experts across all groups are noticing signs of change.</p>
<p>Wolter said, “It's not that the adult walleye are just dying out, it's that the amount of reproduction isn't happening at the same <strong>levels</strong> that it used to, especially in certain water bodies.”</p>
<p>Climate change is affecting the home of the fish. Walleyes do best in unclear waters. But because of long periods of severely dry weather, or drought, the flow of rivers into the lake has lessened. This leads to clearer water.</p>
<p>In 2022, Wisconsin's Department of Natural Resources updated its conservation plan for walleye, with a <strong>focus</strong> on climate change. And in January 2023, the Great Lakes Indian Fish and Wildlife Commission released the updated version of its climate change <strong>vulnerability</strong> report. The report addresses many concerns that tribal members have.</p>
<p><strong>Tribes are first to see change</strong></p>
<p>Tribal member Kelly Martin has been spearfishing with his family for many years. He has seen changes firsthand. One year he was surprised by how early the season started. There was no ice on the lake.</p>
<p>Martin also has seen waters changed by land development. After the pandemic, he observed a great increase in the building of lakefront homes. Martin himself works as a <strong>roofing</strong> contractor.</p>
<p>Many northern Wisconsin tribal members have watched as more people have moved into their small community. Some come to vacation or for a “climate-proof” home. The area has a large supply of fresh water and is safe from rising sea levels.</p>
<p>But those newcomers and summer visitors are not the ones who depend on nature for food. And they are not the ones fighting for traditions that go back generations.</p>
<p>As inland lakes warm with climate change, tribal members experience the effects first. With their generational knowledge of the lakes, Bisonette and others invested in spearfishing will continue fighting to do so.</p>
<p>For now, because of conservation efforts, Martin spears enough fish to help feed elders in the community. He and others work long hours preparing the fish and taking it people in the community. Martin says he loves these visits because he gets to listen to stories of the elders.</p>
<p>“Some of these people ... that's how they grew up. This is what their life is ... doing this. I just hope I get to be like that,” Martin said.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo. And I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Melina Walling And John Locher reported this story for the Associated Press from Wisconsin. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>tribe </strong><em>– n.</em><strong> </strong>a social group composed chiefly of numerous families, clans, or generations having a shared ancestry and language</p>
<p><strong>indigenous</strong> produced, growing, living, or occurring natively or naturally in a particular region or environment</p>
<p><strong>conservation </strong><em>– n. </em>a careful preservation and protection of something, <em>especially</em> <strong>: </strong>planned management of a natural resource to prevent exploitation, destruction, or neglect</p>
<p><strong>hatchery</strong> <em>– n. </em>a place for hatching eggs</p>
<p><strong>reproduction </strong><em>– n. </em>the process by which plants and animals give rise to offspring and which fundamentally consists of the segregation of a portion of the parental body by a sexual or an asexual process and its subsequent growth and differentiation into a new individual</p>
<p><strong>inland</strong> <em>–adj. </em>of or relating to the interior of a country</p>
<p><strong>level </strong><em>– n. </em>an amount of something especially in comparison with typical or expected amounts</p>
<p><strong>focus</strong> <em>– n. </em><strong> </strong>a center of activity, attraction, or attention</p>
<p><strong>vulnerability </strong><em>– n.</em> open to attack or damage</p>
<p><strong>roof </strong><em>– n.</em> the upper covering part of a building</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Ivory Coast Launches First Malaria Vaccine Program (2024/7/19) | 科特迪瓦开展儿童疟疾疫苗接种计划</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/ivory-coast-launches-first-malaria-vaccine-program.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>Health workers in Ivory Coast have launched the country's first child vaccination program against malaria.<br/>科特迪瓦的卫生工作者启动了该国首个儿童疟疾疫苗接种计划。</p><p>The effort aims to reduce cases of the mosquito-spread disease, which has become one of Africa's biggest killers.<br/>这项努力旨在减少疟疾这种蚊虫传播疾病的病例，疟疾已成为非洲最大的杀手之一。</p><p>Officials in the West African nation said the program is designed to cover about 250,000 children under the age of two. The three-shot vaccine was developed by Britain's Oxford University. The World Health Organization (WHO) approved the vaccine last October.<br/>这个西非国家的官员表示，该计划旨在覆盖约25万名两岁以下的儿童。这种三针疫苗是由英国牛津大学开发的。世界卫生组织去年10月批准了该疫苗。</p><p>Research has shown the vaccine to be more than 75 percent effective at preventing severe disease and death during the first year. A second shot, called a booster, aims to extend the protection for at least another year.<br/>研究表明，该疫苗在接种第一年预防重症和死亡的有效性超过75%。第二针被称为加强针，旨在将保护期延长至少一年。</p><p>India's Serum Institute has already made 25 million doses of the Oxford vaccine. It says it plans to make at least 100 million each year. The cost is $4 per dose.<br/>印度血清研究所已经生产了2500万剂牛津疫苗。该公司表示，计划每年至少生产1亿剂。每剂费用为4美元。</p><p>More than 95 percent of the world's estimated 249 million yearly malaria cases and 608,000 deaths happen in Africa. The disease most often affects children under the age of five, as well as pregnant women.<br/>据估计，全世界每年2.49亿例疟疾病例和60.8万例死亡病例中，95%以上发生在非洲。这种疾病最常见于五岁以下的儿童以及孕妇。</p><p>Pierre Demba is Ivory Coast's health minister. He told reporters the malaria vaccine launch demonstrates the government's desire to invest in the country's children. "They are the future of our country,” he said.<br/>皮埃尔·登巴是科特迪瓦的卫生部长。他告诉记者，疟疾疫苗的推出表明了政府投资于该国儿童的意愿。“他们是我们国家的未来，”他说。</p><p>Adrian Hill of Oxford University said in a statement that the effort “marks the start of a new era in malaria control.” He added that he hopes the shot will soon be available to all countries in Africa who want to use it.<br/>牛津大学的阿德里安·希尔在一份声明中表示，这一措施“标志着疟疾控制新时代的开始”。他补充说，希望这种疫苗很快能提供给所有想要使用它的非洲国家。</p><p>Ghana, Nigeria, Burkina Faso and the Central African Republic are among the nations that have already approved the vaccine. Other countries, including Cameroon, have begun widespread vaccination programs.<br/>加纳、尼日利亚、布基纳法索和中非共和国是已经批准该疫苗的国家之一。包括喀麦隆在内的其他国家已经开展广泛的疫苗接种计划。</p><p>Alice Kanga was one of many mothers who brought children to get vaccinated. She told reporters from The Associated Press, “It's really important for the children, for their health."<br/>艾丽丝·坎加是众多带孩子接种疫苗的母亲之一。她告诉美联社记者，“这对孩子们，对他们的健康来说真的很重要。”</p><p>In one poor neighborhood in the city of Abidjan, many women waited with their babies for shots, the French news agency AFP reported.<br/>据法国法新社报道，在阿比让市的一个贫困社区，许多妇女带着婴儿等着打针。</p><p>One mother brought her eight-month-old daughter, Awa. Sitting on her mother's knees and held tightly between her arms, the child cried while preparing to receive her first dose. "I'm happy,” Awa's mother said with a smile. “I have seen all the mothers who have come to be vaccinated against malaria."<br/>一位母亲带来了她八个月大的女儿阿瓦。孩子坐在母亲的膝盖上，紧紧地抱在怀里，在准备打第一剂疫苗时哭了。“我很高兴，”阿瓦的母亲笑着说。“我见过所有来接种疟疾疫苗的母亲。”</p><p>Officials from the WHO have warned that even with the new vaccination campaign, other measures should continue to be taken to stop disease spread. These include spraying with chemical insect killers and using bed nets for protection.<br/>世界卫生组织的官员警告说，即使有了新的疫苗接种运动，也应该继续采取其他措施来阻止疾病的传播。这些措施包括喷洒化学杀虫剂和使用蚊帐进行保护。</p><p>I'm Bryan Lynn.<br/>我是布莱恩·林恩。(21VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Language of the Olympic Games, Part 2 (2024/7/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/language-of-the-olympic-games-part-2.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In a recent <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/language-for-olympic-games-host-compete-expect/7682418.html" target="_blank">Everyday Grammar lesson</a>, we explored some language used to talk about the Olympic Games – the words host, compete, and expect. We invited listeners to answer our report with their own writing about the Olympics using those words.</p>
<p>Many VOA Learning English fans sent messages. Today, we will give <strong>feedback</strong> on two of the messages that we received.</p>
<p><strong>Fernando's message </strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-cc32-08dca5d046ba_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>Let's begin with a message written to us by Fernando from Columbia.</p>
<p>Here is part of what he wrote. Please note: “that time” <strong>refers</strong> to the Tokyo Olympics, scheduled for 2020 but held in 2021.</p>
<p><em>...By that time Paris, the France's capital was announced to be hosting the competitors to the 2024 (Olympic) games. </em></p>
<p><em>During the competition in Paris people around the world expect to watch a great competition where it will be broken many records; competitors will expect to be well hosted, and Paris expect to be the best host.</em></p>
<p>Fernando's message is clear and understandable, but we have a few suggestions that might help improve the writing.</p>
<p>In the first sentence, remove the article “the.” Instead of saying “Paris, the France's capital,” we say “Paris, France's capital.” We do not need the article because the possessive, “France's,” already gives us the exactness we need to know about what is being talked about. We might also say “Paris, the capital of France,” or simply “Paris, France.”</p>
<p>Overall, the first sentence has a <strong>passive </strong>structure. It might be better to change the sentence to the <strong>active</strong> voice. The active voice will make the sentence's meaning clearer. So, we might say this:</p>
<p><em>“By that time, the International Olympic Committee had announced that Paris, France, would host the 2024 Olympic Games.” </em></p>
<p>Our first suggestion for Fernando's second sentence involves articles. Instead of saying, “expect to watch a great competition,” we might remove the article “a” and say “expect to watch great competitions.” This makes more sense because the Olympics includes many different sports events.</p>
<p>We might also remove the pronoun “it” and slightly change the word order to something like this:</p>
<p><em>During the Olympic Games, people around the world expect to watch great competitions where many records will be broken.</em></p>
<p><strong>Eleni's message </strong></p>
<p>Now let's turn to part of a message from Eleni. Eleni is from Greece. She wrote to us about the creation of the Olympic Games.</p>
<p><em>The first Olympic Games were held in Greece every four years since 776 BC. </em></p>
<p><em>The host town was the ancient Olympia. The Olympic Games were dedicated to Zeus, the Supreme God of the Greek religion. </em></p>
<p><em>During the Olympic Games no wars were permitted. </em></p>
<p><em>On arrival, all athletes swore to compete with honor and respect. There were a few completions such as foot-race, wrestling, <strong>pentathlon</strong>, horse races, pankration- a mix of boxing and wrestling and the athletes competed naked probably for complete freedom of the movement. </em></p>
<p><em>Each city expected its own athletes to win in the Olympic Games. When that happened they were tearing down a part of the city walls to honor him. It meant that the city was protected by such great athletes... </em></p>
<p>Eleni's message was excellent. We have a few suggestions, beginning with the words “On arrival...”</p>
<p>We suggest creating an introductory clause and changing some of the wording to make the sentence clearer in meaning. We could rewrite it this way:</p>
<p><em>“When athletes arrived at Olympia, they swore to compete with honor and respect.”</em></p>
<p>We also suggest checking the spelling of a few words – “completion” should be replaced with competition, for example. And, we think adding punctuation, such as commas, might help make the message clearer.</p>
<p>Our final suggestion is for the second-to-last sentence. Eleni uses the pronoun “they.” But, who “they” are is not clear. Does “they” describe city officials, townspeople, fellow athletes?</p>
<p>We might also use a different verb form – “tore down” instead of “were tearing down,” as in this example:</p>
<p><em>When a city's athlete won a competition, the townspeople tore down part of the city walls to honor him. </em></p>
<p><strong>Closing thoughts </strong></p>
<p>All of the messages we received were excellent.</p>
<p>In terms of grammar, our main feedback is to pay careful attention to articles, to use active voice more often, and to clarify pronouns. That is, make sure that the pronoun very clearly refers to an exact noun.</p>
<p>We hope that all of you get to enjoy the Olympic Games. And we thank all our listeners who sent us messages about the international event.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>John Russell wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>feedback</strong> <em>-n.</em> helpful suggestions or advice for improvement</p>
<p><strong>refer</strong> <em>-- v.</em> to have a relation or connection</p>
<p><strong>passive</strong><em> -- adj. grammar</em> showing that the subject of a sentence is acted on or affected by the verb</p>
<p><strong>active</strong> <em>-- adj. grammar </em>showing that the subject of a sentence is the one doing the action expressed by the verb</p>
<p><strong>pentathlon</strong> <em>-- n.</em> an athletic contest involving participation by each contestant in five different events</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Rarest Whale in World Appears on New Zealand Beach (2024/7/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/rarest-whale-in-world-appears-on-new-zealand-beach.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>No one has ever seen a live spade-toothed whale. It is the world's rarest kind of whale. No one knows how many exist, what they eat, or even where they live in the southern Pacific Ocean.</p>
<p>However, scientists in New Zealand may finally get to learn more about them.</p>
<p>The country's conservation agency said Monday it believes a dead spade-toothed whale washed up on a South Island beach earlier this month. Scientists identified the whale by its color patterns and the shape of its skull, <strong>beak</strong> and teeth.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Department of Conservation rangers Jim Fyfe and Tūmai Cassidy walk alongside what is believed to be a rare spade-toothed whale, on July 5, 2024. (Department of Conservation via AP)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-4e8a-08dca5b1ac4b_cx6_cy15_cw91_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Department of Conservation rangers Jim Fyfe and Tūmai Cassidy walk alongside what is believed to be a rare spade-toothed whale, on July 5, 2024. (Department of Conservation via AP)
</span></div>
<p><strong>Very little is known </strong></p>
<p>Hannah Hendriks is a sea life expert for the Department of Conservation. She said, “This is going to lead to some <strong>amazing</strong> science and world-first information."</p>
<p>In the past, only a few other spade-toothed whales have appeared on New Zealand's beaches. Scientists did not have a chance to closely examine them. Now, they will be able to. They have moved the whale to a cold place for their investigation.</p>
<p><strong>Tribal groups value whales</strong></p>
<p>Researchers will work with local Māori <em>iwi</em>, or tribal groups, to plan how to examine the whale, the conservation agency said.</p>
<p>New Zealand's Indigenous people consider whales a <em>taonga</em> — a <strong>sacred</strong> treasure. In April, Pacific Indigenous leaders signed a treaty recognizing whales as "legal persons." However, that is not recognized in the laws of <strong>participating</strong> nations.</p>
<p><strong>Never seen alive</strong></p>
<p>Spade-tooth whales live deep in the ocean. They come to the surface so rarely that scientists only know their general location in the southern Pacific Ocean. It is home to some of the world's deepest ocean areas, Hendriks said.</p>
<p>"It's very hard to do research on marine mammals if you don't see them at sea," she said. "You don't know where to look."</p>
<p>Kirsten Young is a senior lecturer at Britain's University of Exeter. She studies spade-toothed whales. She wrote in an email that it took "many years and a <strong>mammoth</strong> amount of effort by researchers and local people" to identify the whales.</p>
<p>The new discovery "makes me wonder — how many are out in the deep ocean and how do they live?" Young said.</p>
<p>Researchers studying the mammal could not confirm if the species went <strong>extinct</strong>. Then in 2010, two whole spade-toothed whales, both dead, appeared on a New Zealand beach. Samples of their tissue later showed they were spade-toothed whales.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Charlotte Graham-McLay reported on this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>marine </strong>– <em>adj.</em> of or relating to the sea or the plants and animals that live in the sea</p>
<p><strong>amazing</strong> – <em>adj.</em> causing great surprise or wonder</p>
<p><strong>species</strong> – <em>n</em>. group of animals or plants that are similar and can produce young animals or plants : a group of related animals or plants that is smaller than a genus</p>
<p><strong>mammoth</strong> – <em>adj. </em>something that is very large</p>
<p><strong>extinct</strong> – <em>adj</em>. no longer existing</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Find Cave on Moon That Could House Future Explorers (2024/7/18) | 科学家发现月球洞穴可容纳未来宇航员</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/scientists-find-cave-on-moon-that-could-house-future-explorers.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content">
<p>Scientists have confirmed a cave on the moon, not far from where Neil Armstrong and Buzz Aldrin landed 55 years ago.<br/>
科学家们已经证实月球上有一个洞穴，距离尼尔·阿姆斯特朗和巴兹·奥尔德林55年前着陆的地方不远。</p>
<p>They suspect there are hundreds more that could house future astronauts.<br/>
他们怀疑还有数百个洞穴，可以用来容纳未来的宇航员。</p>
<p>An Italian-led team reported recently that there is evidence of a large cave that can be entered from the deepest known pit on the moon. It is located at the Sea of Tranquility, just 400 kilometers from Apollo 11's landing site.<br/>
一个由意大利领导的团队最近报告说，有证据表明，从月球上已知最深的深坑可以进入一个大洞穴。它位于宁静海，距离阿波罗11号着陆点仅400公里。</p>
<p>The pit, like the more than 200 others discovered there, was created by the collapse of a lava tube.<br/>
这个深坑和月球上发现的另外200多个坑一样，是由熔岩管坍塌造成的。</p>
<p>Researchers examined radar measurements by NASA's Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter, and compared the results with lava tubes on Earth. Their findings appeared in the scientific publication Nature Astronomy.<br/>
研究人员检查了美国宇航局月球勘测轨道器的雷达探测结果，并将其与地球上的熔岩管进行了比较。他们的发现发表在科学出版物《自然·天文学》上。</p>
<p>The radar data shows only the beginning part of the underground area, the scientists say. They estimate it is at least 40 meters wide and tens of meters long, probably more.<br/>
科学家们说，雷达数据只显示了这片地下区域的入口部分。他们估计它至少有40米宽，几十米长，也可能更长。</p>
<p>“Lunar caves have remained a mystery for over 50 years. So it was exciting to be able to finally prove the existence” of one, Leonardo Carrer and Lorenzo Bruzzone of Italy's University of Trento, wrote in an email.<br/>
意大利特伦托大学的莱昂纳多·卡雷尔和洛伦佐·布鲁佐内在一封电子邮件中写道：“月球洞穴50多年来一直是个谜。因此，能够最终证明其中一个洞穴的存在是令人兴奋的。”</p>
<p>Most of the pits seem to be in the moon's ancient lava plains, scientists say. There also could be some at the moon's south pole, the planned location of NASA's astronaut landings in the years to come. Permanently shadowed craters there are believed to hold frozen water that could provide drinking water and rocket fuel.<br/>
科学家说，大多数深坑似乎都位于月球古老的熔岩平原上。月球南极也可能有一些，这是美国宇航局规划的未来几年宇航员的着陆点。据信，那里的永久阴影陨石坑中有冷冻水，可以提供饮用水和火箭燃料。</p>
<p>During NASA's Apollo program, 12 astronauts landed on the moon, beginning with Armstrong and Aldrin on July 20, 1969.<br/>
在美国宇航局的阿波罗计划期间，有12名宇航员登上了月球，最开始是阿姆斯特朗和奥尔德林于1969年7月20日登月。</p>
<p>The findings suggest there could be hundreds of pits on the moon and thousands of lava tubes. Such places could serve as a natural shelter for astronauts, protecting them from cosmic rays and solar radiation as well as from very small meteorite strikes. The act of building living areas from nothing would be more difficult and take more time, even when including the possible need of strengthening the cave walls to prevent a collapse, the team said.<br/>
研究结果表明，月球上可能有数百个深坑和数千个熔岩管。这些地方可以作为宇航员的天然避难所，保护他们免受宇宙射线和太阳辐射的冲击，以及非常小的陨石的撞击。该团队表示，即使考虑到可能需要加强洞穴墙壁以防止坍塌，从零开始建造生活区的动作也会比这更加困难，也需要更多的时间。</p>
<p>Rocks and other material inside these caves — unchanged by the difficult surface conditions over the ages — also can help scientists better understand how the moon evolved, especially in terms of its volcanic activity.<br/>
这些洞穴内的岩石和其他物质——在艰苦的月表环境中多年来没有发生改变——也可以帮助科学家更好地了解月球是如何进化的，特别是在火山活动方面。</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.<br/>
我是约翰·拉塞尔。(21VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Tech Tip: Password Manager Can Simplify Logins, Improve Security (2024/7/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/tech-tip-password-manager-can-simplify-logins-improve-security.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>For most of us, using – and trying to remember – a collection of passwords is just a normal part of our digital lives. But it seems like the number of passwords we need for online activities just gets bigger and bigger.</p>
<p>Some passwords – especially for work-related systems – must be changed often. That makes passwords even harder to create and remember.</p>
<p>These difficulties can lead some people to reuse passwords to help simplify the process. But most security experts warn against this. Reusing passwords can make it easier for internet attackers, or hackers, to digitally seize personal accounts.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This Monday, June 19, 2017, photo shows fingers on a laptop keyboard in North Andover, Mass. (AP Photo/Elise Amendola)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-36da-08dca67bf6d5_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This Monday, June 19, 2017, photo shows fingers on a laptop keyboard in North Andover, Mass. (AP Photo/Elise Amendola)</span></div>
<p>One of the most suggested methods for effectively dealing with passwords is to employ a separate product called a password <strong>manager</strong>. These tools are not new. You have probably already heard of such tools and might have even tried one.</p>
<p>Here are some tips for deciding whether a password manager might be right for you.</p>
<p><strong>How does a password manager work?</strong></p>
<p>The general idea behind password managers is simple: Your passwords are stored securely in a digital <strong>vault</strong>. When you need to use a <strong>particular</strong> online service, the manager <strong>automatically</strong> enters login details and password fields for you.</p>
<p>The U.S. government's Cybersecurity &amp; Infrastructure Security Agency <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cisa.gov/secure-our-world/use-strong-passwords">notes</a>, “When we use a password manager, we only need to remember one strong password – the one for the password manager itself.”</p>
<p>Most password managers have a smartphone service, or app, that works with internet browsers and other apps. This means they can be set to open with a fingerprint or face identification. If on a computer, you can also sign into your password vault through a browser tool, called a plug-in, or by going to a website.</p>
<p>A good password manager should be able to create complex passwords using letters, numbers and special <strong>characters</strong> when setting up a new account. And, it should also recognize that you are signing into an online service for the first time and ask if you want to save the information you have entered.</p>
<p>Password managers can also protect against so-called <strong>phishing</strong> attempts. These usually appear as emails seeking to trick users into clicking onto a link to a false website designed to capture login details. A password manager can prevent such details from automatically being filling in if the web address is not the same as the one linked to the saved password.</p>
<p>Most password managers can store other information as well, such as bank and credit card PINs. Many also support passkeys, a new technology that companies like Google <a class="wsw__a" href="https://support.google.com/accounts/answer/13548313?hl=en#:~:text=Passkeys%20are%20a%20simple%20and,screen%20lock%2C%20like%20a%20PIN.">have launched</a> as a safer method than passwords.</p>
<p><strong>How do I choose the best one?</strong></p>
<p>There are many different password managers on the market. Some of the best-known systems include 1Password, Bitwarden, Dashlane, Bitdefender, Nordpass, Keeper and Keepass.</p>
<p>One of the best ways to choose the right manager is to look at online <strong>reviews</strong> based on professional testing and ratings. Britain's National Cyber Security Centre has also established a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.ncsc.gov.uk/collection/passwords/password-manager-buyers-guide">buyer's guide</a> to help users choose the right password manager.</p>
<p>Most services have free and paid versions. The free offerings come with restrictions, such as permitting only one device to be signed in at a time or limiting the number of passwords to store.</p>
<p>Top-rated managers work across different devices and services, with apps for Windows and Mac computers, as well as iOS and Android devices. And plug-ins can be downloaded for browsers like Chrome, Safari, Firefox, Edge, Brave and Opera.</p>
<p>Apple also has its own Keychain service for Macs and iOS devices.</p>
<p><strong>How secure are they?</strong></p>
<p>Good password managers use strong <strong>encryption</strong> methods that aim to prevent any other parties from seeing your data.</p>
<p>Pieter Arntz is a security researcher at California-based cybersecurity company Malwarebytes. He told The Associated Press that many password managers use the most secure kind of encryption available.</p>
<p>Arntz noted this kind of encryption can protect users even when their computers, devices or password managers are hacked. This is because encryption ensures the saved passwords are stored in an <strong>encoded</strong> state. This means the attacker would need to know the main password in order to read any of the saved passwords.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on a report from The Associated Press and government sources.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>manager</strong><em> – n. </em>something or someone that controls a system or operation</p>
<p><strong>vault</strong><em> – n.</em> a very secure location where valuable things are kept</p>
<p><strong>particular </strong><em>– adj. </em>used to describe one thing or person and not others</p>
<p><strong>automatic </strong><em>– adj. </em>working by itself with little human control</p>
<p><strong>phishing </strong><em>– n.</em> the practice of sending emails to people to trick them into giving personal information</p>
<p><strong>character </strong><em>– n. </em>a letter, sign or number that is used in writing or printing</p>
<p><strong>review </strong><em>– n.</em> a report in a newspaper, magazine or on the internet that gives an opinion about a new product or thing</p>
<p><strong>encryption </strong><em>– n. </em>the changing of information from one form to another, especially to hide its meaning</p>
<p><strong>encode </strong><em>– v. </em>to change something into a system for sending messages secretly, or to represent complex information in a simple or short way</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>S. Korean Beauty Industry Using AI to Develop New Products (2024/7/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/south-korean-beauty-industry-using-ai-to-develop-new-products.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>South Korean beauty products company AmorePacific has a new artificial intelligence (AI) laboratory that has become popular with <strong>customers</strong>.</p>
<p>At the lab, robots mix face products, and the latest technology recommends the best <strong>lipstick </strong>color for an individual.</p>
<p>Kwon You-jin is a 32-year-old customer at the company's skin <strong>cosmetics</strong> service.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Kwon Hyo-jin takes a photo for virtual makeup to analyze her skin color using AI technology, to get a color for lipstick at Amore Seongsu in Seoul, South Korea, June 7, 2024. (REUTERS/Kim Soo-hyeon)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-73ec-08dca2699eac_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Kwon Hyo-jin takes a photo for virtual makeup to analyze her skin color using AI technology, to get a color for lipstick at Amore Seongsu in Seoul, South Korea, June 7, 2024. (REUTERS/Kim Soo-hyeon)</span></div>
<p>"Everyone has their own <strong>specific</strong> skin tone, but usually they buy the most common color available <strong>over the counter</strong>," she said.</p>
<p>"Knowing more data about my own skin, and seeing the before-and-after firsthand, it's a very good experience," she said, after receiving an AI-created report on the condition of her skin.</p>
<p>A robot mixed a special makeup base, or foundation, that<strong> matched</strong> her skin color.</p>
<p>More cosmetics companies are using AI to increase sales. Internationally known<strong> brands</strong> such as L'Oréal and Sephora use the technology to make special products for customers.</p>
<p>Global beauty industry sales including cosmetics reached $625.6 billion in 2023, climbing each year since dropping in 2020 during the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
<p>That information comes from Statista Market Insights, a data and market research company.</p>
<p>AmorePacific said it uses AI to recommend the best choices for a customer from 205 different skin foundations or 366 different lip product colors.</p>
<p>Engineer Lee Young-jin, an adviser for AmorePacific's custom beauty business, said that developers used deep learning and machine learning methods to take the process that experts use to study data from many peoples' skins.</p>
<p>Experts said using AI instead of humans could speed up product development.</p>
<p>Yang Yong Suk, of South Korea's Electronics and Telecommunications Research Institute (ETRI), was co-developer of a deep learning model for a cosmetic product's <strong>texture</strong>.</p>
<p>"No matter how professional an expert is, individual <strong>deviations </strong>can be large, and <strong>evaluating</strong> cosmetics by consulting 30 to 40 experts all the time is difficult," Yang said.</p>
<p>"These days, product development time has shortened, and an ever-larger amount of new products are launched faster," Yang added.</p>
<p>The market for using AI in the beauty and cosmetics industries is predicted to more than double from $3.27 billion in 2023 to $8.1 billion in 2028.</p>
<p>The market research provider Business Research Company said in January that services such as personalized beauty recommendations, skin examinations, and virtual makeup artists will likely grow.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Hyun Young Yi and Daewoung Kim reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>customer</strong><em> –n.</em> a person or group that pays for a product or service</p>
<p><strong>lipstick </strong><em>– n.</em> a usually colored cosmetic in stick form for the lips</p>
<p><strong>cosmetics </strong><em>–n. (pl.)</em> products that are put on the body, especially the face, with the aim of increasing beauty or improving appearance</p>
<p><strong>specific</strong> <em>–adj.</em> relating to a particular instance, condition or thing</p>
<p><strong>over the counter</strong> <em>– adj.</em> sold without prescription</p>
<p><strong>match</strong><em> –v.</em> to put two things together that have similar qualities</p>
<p><strong>brand</strong><em> –n.</em> the name under which a product is sold which can only be used by the company owning the brand name</p>
<p><strong>texture </strong><em>– n.</em> the visual or tactile surface characteristics of something</p>
<p><strong>deviation</strong> <em>– n.</em> a departure or difference in something</p>
<p><strong>evaluate</strong><em> – v.</em> to determine the significance or condition of usually by careful study</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Where Is Bird Flu Spreading around the World? (2024/7/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/where-is-bird-flu-spreading-around-the-world.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Different versions of bird flu have been spreading around the world in recent years.</p>
<p>The virus, officially known as H5N1, is believed to have killed millions of wild and <strong>domestic</strong> birds worldwide. Some other animals have also been infected.</p>
<p>The virus infected a very small number of people as well. But, H5N1 largely has remained outside the human population. Most of the few human cases involved direct contact between people and infected birds.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Illustration shows test tubes labeled " bird="" dado="" file="" flu="" illustration="" january="" on="" photo="" ruvic="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/598094f6-f9d7-4f61-84fa-9988e9551f21_cx0_cy7_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Illustration shows test tubes labeled "Bird Flu" on January 14, 2023. (REUTERS/Dado Ruvic/Illustration/File Photo)</span></div>
<p>Reuters news agency recently explored areas of the world where versions of H5N1 have infected humans.</p>
<p><strong>United States</strong></p>
<p>In the United States, the first known cases of infected <strong>dairy </strong>cows happened in Texas in March. Currently, dairy cow groups in at least 12 states have been affected.</p>
<p>The U.S. Agriculture Department has said tests so far suggest the virus identified in cows is the same H5N1 found to have infected wild birds and farm birds, also called poultry. Four dairy workers who tested <strong>positive</strong> for the virus this year showed only minor signs of sickness, such as conjunctivitis, an eye condition.</p>
<p>Officials from the European Food Safety Agency (EFSA) said in a report the H5N1 virus spreading in the U.S. is related to a version only identified in North America so far.</p>
<p><strong>Mexico</strong></p>
<p>The World Health Organization (WHO) said on June 5 that a resident of Mexico died with the first known cases of H5N2 bird flu in humans. Mexico's government disputed that cause of death, saying instead the person died of another sickness. Officials said the person had no known contact with animals.</p>
<p><strong>Australia</strong></p>
<p>On June 7, the WHO said a child reported by Australia to have H5N1 had traveled to Kolkata, India. Genetic testing showed the virus was a version of H5N1. That version was known to have been spreading in Southeast Asia and has been identified in previous human infections and in poultry.</p>
<p>Separately, Australia is dealing with three outbreaks of different bird flu versions on poultry farms. These include H7N3, H7N8 and H7N9. Officials said those versions likely arrived on farms through wild birds.</p>
<p><strong>India</strong></p>
<p>In India, the WHO reported a case of human infection with bird flu on June 11. It was caused by the H9N2 version in a four-year-old child in the eastern Indian state of West Bengal. The agency said it was the second human infection of H9N2 bird flu from India following a case in 2019.</p>
<p>The H9N2 virus generally only causes mild sickness. But the WHO said further human cases could happen because this version is one of the most common at poultry farms in different areas.</p>
<p><strong>Vietnam</strong></p>
<p>In March, Vietnam reported a 21-year-old student had died from the H5N1 virus. He had no existing medical conditions. But officials said the student had had contact with wild birds from hunting a couple of weeks before signs of sickness appeared. No contact with dead or sick poultry was reported at the time.</p>
<p>The EFSA said Vietnam also reported an outbreak of H9N2 in a 37-year-old man.</p>
<p><strong>Cambodia</strong></p>
<p>Cambodia has reported five human cases of H5N1 as of June 20.</p>
<p><strong>Germany</strong></p>
<p>Germany reported a rare outbreak of H7N5 bird flu on a farm in a western part of the country near the border with the Netherlands. The case was identified July 4 by the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.woah.org/en/home/">World Organization for Animal Health</a>. The group said it was the first outbreak anywhere of H7N5 on the group's public records.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Reuters reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>domestic</strong><em> adj.</em> relating to the home and family relationships</p>
<p><strong>dairy </strong><em>– n.</em> containing or made from milk</p>
<p><strong>positive </strong><em>– adj. </em>in a medical test, positive means the person being tested has a disease or condition</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Is College Worth It? (2024/7/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/is-college-worth-it.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A new study says that Americans have increasing questions about the value and cost of a college education. Most of the people taking part in the study felt that higher education in the U.S. is headed in the “wrong direction.”</p>
<p>Gallup and the Lumina Foundation carried out the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/646880/confidence-higher-education-closely-divided.aspx">study</a>. It found that only 36 percent of adults said they had a “great deal” or “quite a lot” of <strong>confidence</strong> in higher education.</p>
<p>That confidence level has decreased steadily from 57 percent in 2015. That was the first year in which Gallup measured confidence in higher education.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - In this May 13, 2018, file photo, new graduates walk at the start of the Rutgers University graduation ceremony in New Jersey. Americans are saying the U.S. higher education system is headed in the “wrong direction.” (AP Photo/Seth Wenig, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-acbe-08dca0eb8a3e_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - In this May 13, 2018, file photo, new graduates walk at the start of the Rutgers University graduation ceremony in New Jersey. Americans are saying the U.S. higher education system is headed in the “wrong direction.” (AP Photo/Seth Wenig, File)</span></div>
<p>The <strong>decline</strong> is seen in all subgroups of people including sex, age, and political ties. Among Republican Party members in the study, the number of people with high confidence in higher education has dropped 36 percentage points over the last 10 years. That is far more than for Democratic Party members or independents.</p>
<p>Some of the opinions in the study might show concerns about the high cost of college and how race and other subjects are taught.</p>
<p>Fifty-nine-year-old Randy Hill is a registered Republican in Connecticut and a driver for a car service. He told the Associated Press, “It's so <strong>expensive</strong>, and I don't think colleges are teaching people what they need to get a job.” Hill said his nephew plans to do a welding <strong>apprenticeship</strong> after high school instead of going to college.</p>
<p>The June 2024 study found that 36 percent of adults feel strong confidence in higher education. That percentage is unchanged from the year before.</p>
<p>But the researchers said they were concerned that fewer Americans were saying that they had “some” confidence, and more were reporting “very little” or “none.” This year's findings show almost as many people have little or no confidence, 32 percent, as those with high confidence.</p>
<p>Experts say that fewer college graduates could worsen labor shortages in fields from health care to information technology. For those who do not go to college, it often means lower lifetime earnings.</p>
<p>Georgetown University's Center on Education and the Workforce said lifetime earnings for those without a <strong>bachelor's degree</strong> could be 75 percent less than for those with a degree. The center also said that during an economic downturn, those without college degrees are more likely to lose their jobs.</p>
<p>Courtney Brown is a vice president at Lumina, an education nonprofit group. It aims to increase the number of students who seek education beyond high school. She said, “What's shocking to me is that the people who have low or no confidence is actually increasing.”</p>
<p>This year's study added new, detailed questions in an effort to understand why confidence is shrinking.</p>
<p>Almost one-third of people in the study said college is “too expensive.” About 25 percent thought students are not getting the right education or taught what they need to succeed.</p>
<p>The study did not ask about the protests against the war in Gaza this year that divided many college communities. But people who took part said they had concerns about <strong>indoctrination</strong>, political <strong>bias</strong>, and that colleges are too liberal. Among those who said they lack confidence in college, 41 percent said political activity was a reason.</p>
<p><strong>Other findings</strong></p>
<p>Sixty-seven percent of adults in the study said colleges are headed in the “wrong direction.” That is more than two times higher than the 31 percent who think that colleges are going in the right direction.</p>
<p>Gallup noted that when people express confidence in higher education, they are thinking of four-year colleges. But the study found that more people have confidence in two-year community colleges.</p>
<p>Forty-nine percent of adults said they have “a great deal” or “quite a lot” of confidence in two-year programs, compared with 33 percent of Americans who feel that way about four-year colleges.</p>
<p>California college student Kristen Freeman said she understands why.</p>
<p>“It's about saving money. That's why I went to a two-year. It's <strong>more</strong> <strong>bang for your buck</strong>,” said Freeman who is a 22-year-old sociology major at Diablo Valley Community College. She plans to go to San Jose State University for the final two years of college.</p>
<p>Freeman said she understands the concerns about indoctrination and whether college prepares students for life and work. But she feels the only way to change structural problems is from the inside.</p>
<p>“I am learning about the world around me and developing useful skills in critical thinking,” Freeman said. “I think higher education can give students the <strong>spark</strong> to want to change the system.”</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p>And I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Jocelyn Gecker reported this story for The Associated Press. Hai Do adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>confidence </strong><em>–n.</em> a belief that something is good or worthwhile</p>
<p><strong>decline </strong><em>–n.</em> the process of becoming smaller, less effective or worse</p>
<p><strong>expensive </strong><em>–adj.</em> costly</p>
<p><strong>apprenticeship </strong><em>–n. </em>a position where a person is taught a trade and serves as an assistant to an established tradesman</p>
<p><strong>bachelor's degree</strong> <em>–n.</em> a degree given by a college or university for completing a course of study that usually takes four years</p>
<p><strong>indoctrination </strong><em>–n.</em> a process that conditions people to believe certain ideas</p>
<p><strong>bias </strong><em>–n.</em> the condition of being influence more by one set of ideas than another</p>
<p><strong>more bang for your buck </strong><em>–idiom</em> doing something that gives the greatest effect at the lowest cost</p>
<p><strong>spark </strong><em>–n.</em> a small amount of fire or electricity that can start a fire</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Can Resistance Training Keep Us Feeling Young? (2024/7/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/can-resistance-training-keep-us-feeling-young.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>Some experts suggest that lifting weights is the best way to keep our bodies strong and healthy as we age. Weight lifting is a type of resistance training.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Shigeo Takahashi, 83, uses a weight machine as he works out at the Fukagawa Sports Center in Tokyo, June 12, 2024. Experts say that as we age, weight-resistance training might deliver unexpected benefits. (AP Photo/Hiro Komae)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-b54b-08dc9f5f666a_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Shigeo Takahashi, 83, uses a weight machine as he works out at the Fukagawa Sports Center in Tokyo, June 12, 2024. Experts say that as we age, weight-resistance training might deliver unexpected benefits. (AP Photo/Hiro Komae)</span></div>
<p>Penn State University <a class="wsw__a" href="https://research.med.psu.edu/oncology-nutrition-exercise/patient-guides/strength-training/">College of Medicine</a> experts define resistance training as "a type of exercise that causes your muscles to work against an outside resistance."</p>
<p>Some experts claim resistance training can even slow aging.</p>
<p>Marcas Bamman has researched the effects of weight-resistance training on aging bodies for many years. He shared his advice recently with the Associated Press.</p>
<p>“Resistance training is in many ways the true <strong>fountain of youth</strong>,” Bamman said.</p>
<p>Our bodies do have biological limits. But Bamman said older people put too few demands on their bodies, not too many. He said that most age-related loss of strength, <strong>flexibility</strong>, and <strong>endurance </strong>comes from the lack of physical demands on our bodies, such as exercise.</p>
<p>Bamman said that strength training for several months can increase muscle mass and ability to the level of people 30 to 35 years younger. He added that a lot of people are interested in that message.</p>
<p><strong>Getting started</strong></p>
<p>Bamman's advice is mainly for people 60 years of age or older. However, he said no one should wait to start resistance training. He also suggests going to a <strong>gym</strong> to work out with weight machines. For beginners, he said machines are better.</p>
<p>However, experts at the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cdc.gov/physical-activity-basics/adding-older-adults/what-counts.html">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</a> say you do not need weight machines to do strength training. You can strengthen your muscles by using free weights — such as barbells or dumbbells — and <strong>resistance bands</strong>. You can also use your own body weight, for example, by doing <strong>push-ups </strong>or similar exercises.</p>
<p>Before starting any resistance training, experts suggest getting the advice of a medical doctor. For those using a gym with weight machines, Bamman also suggests getting a trainer, a person to teach you how to use the equipment. “It's actually quite safe,” he said. But he added that a good trainer “...can teach the movements properly.”</p>
<p><strong>How much is enough?</strong></p>
<p>You can go to a gym, do training at home or work out in a park. However, both Bamman and the CDC suggest doing resistance training twice a week. Bamman added that three times a week is even better. He also suggests non-weight-training days in between. For example, if you strength train on Monday, Wednesday, and Friday, then you should rest on Tuesday and Thursday.</p>
<p>He said, before resistance training, start with five to 10 minutes of light activity and stretching to warm up. Then, do between eight and 10 different resistance exercise movements.</p>
<p>Repeat each movement 10 times. Do these sets of 10 repetitions three times. Then move on to the next movement. When you reach the 10th repetition, you should feel you cannot do many more. If you could have done 10 more, you might want to increase the resistance.</p>
<p>Bamman also suggests that people should keep moving during their training. “Sometimes you see people who sit on the machine, do a set and then play with their phone for three to four minutes,” he observed.</p>
<p><strong>Women might gain more than men</strong></p>
<p>Bamman said strength training is important for both men and women. However, he said women might gain even more from resistance training than men.</p>
<p>Resistance training is a way to prevent osteoporosis<strong>,</strong> the loss of bone density. Bamman said that over time women face an increased risk of bone loss. They can develop problems in their hips and lower back.</p>
<p>Yasuko Kuroi is 72 and started resistance training about 20 years ago. She spoke to the AP at a public recreation center in Tokyo. She said, “I saw the men in the gym and I thought I could do that, too.”</p>
<p><strong>The body demands work</strong></p>
<p>Experts at Stanford University say <a class="wsw__a" href="https://longevity.stanford.edu/lifestyle/2023/04/11/stop-the-clock-the-shocking-truth-about-age-related-muscle-loss-and-steps-to-fight-back/">research</a> shows that between the ages of 20 and 80 we can lose between 35 percent and 40 percent of our muscle mass.</p>
<p>There is a popular English expression that can relate to the body's muscle mass: “Use it or lose it.”</p>
<p>Bamman says we are too easy on our bodies. He criticized health care professionals who are too easy on older people.</p>
<p>“Our human body is a demand-based system,” he explained. He added that if you continuously put low demands on your body, your body will adapt to that low demand.</p>
<p>“That's why we lose muscle mass, that's why we get weaker. We're not demanding much,” Bamman said.</p>
<p>However, if you put higher demands on your body with such activities as resistance training, your body has to <strong>adapt</strong> to these higher demands. The body adapts by making stronger bones and bigger muscles.</p>
<p>Bamman used the example of space flight, or extended bed rest. In these situations, people quickly lose strength.</p>
<p>“All of our systems as we age are capable of responding and adapting. They just need the <strong>stimulus</strong>.” He said he has seen positive effects for people in their 70s and 80s, and even for some in their 90s.</p>
<p>Bamman, 57, joked that he is now closer in age to the people who he studies. But he warned that there are no <strong>shortcuts</strong>. He criticized some programs for older adults that use only seated exercises. He said these do not put enough demands on the body.</p>
<p>And that's the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p>And I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Stephen Wade reported this story for The Associated Press from Tokyo. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>physiology</strong> <em>–n.</em> the science dealing with how living things physically operate</p>
<p><strong>fountain of youth </strong><em>–idiom</em> something that makes older people feel or believe they are young again</p>
<p><strong>flexibility </strong>–n. the ability to stretch and move the body, especially the arms, legs and back</p>
<p><strong>endurance </strong>–n. the ability to do an activity for a long time</p>
<p><strong>gym (gymnasium) </strong>–n. a building that has spaces and equipment for exercise</p>
<p><strong>resistance bands </strong>–n. flexible or rubber devices that people stretch using their arms or legs to strengthen their muscles</p>
<p><strong>push up </strong>–n. an exercise in which a person lies on the ground and pushes away from the ground with their arms</p>
<p><strong>adapt </strong>–v. to ability to change behavior to meet the needs of a new situation or condition</p>
<p><strong>stimulus </strong>–n. something that causes a response</p>
<p><strong>shortcut </strong>–n. a quicker, easier way of doing something that usually means not doing everything that is necessary to get a good result</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Fake Picassos Create Legal Trouble for Australian Museum (2024/7/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202407/fake-picassos-create-legal-trouble-for-australian-museum.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 July, 2024</span><br/>
<p>An art <strong>gallery</strong> in the Australian state of Tasmania presented three paintings as if they were works by the famed painter, Pablo Picasso. At first, the museum limited viewers to women. When that brought legal action against the museum, they moved the paintings to a women's <strong>bathroom</strong>.</p>
<p>Now it is clear people were reacting strongly to artworks that were not really by Picasso. Nor were other paintings said to be by other famed artists. The truth came out last week when the <strong>curator</strong> of the women-only show admitted she had painted them herself. The admission came after a reporter and the Picasso Administration in France questioned her about the paintings.</p>
<p><strong>An unusual museum</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this undated photo provided by the Museum of Old and New Art (MONA), Kirsha Kaechele poses with a painting in Hobart, Australia. " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-5317-08dca4e85294_cx0_cy27_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this undated photo provided by the Museum of Old and New Art (MONA), Kirsha Kaechele poses with a painting in Hobart, Australia. </span></div>
<p>The show's curator is Kirsha Kaechele. She admitted last week that she had painted the works. She wrote a blog post on the website of Tasmania's Museum of Old and New Art (MONA). The museum is known in Australia for its strange <strong>exhibitions</strong> and events.</p>
<p>The story began in 2020, when Kaechele created a women-only area, called the “Ladies <strong>Lounge</strong>,” for visitors to enjoy being only with women.</p>
<p>The so-called Ladies Lounge offered high tea, <strong>massages</strong> and champagne served by men. It was open to anyone who identified as a woman.</p>
<p>The lounge was supposed to display "the most important artworks in the world," Kaechele wrote, in order for men "to feel as excluded as possible."</p>
<p><strong>Legal action</strong></p>
<p>But in March, the Tasmanian Civil and Administrative <strong>Tribunal</strong> ordered MONA to stop denying men the right to enter the Ladies Lounge. The order came after a male visitor became angry that he could not enter the space in 2023.</p>
<p>Tribunal Deputy President Richard Grueber wrote in his decision that he found the exhibition to be discriminatory. He ruled that the man had suffered a <strong>disadvantage</strong>, in part because the artworks in the Ladies Lounge were so valuable.</p>
<p>Kaechele described the artworks to the tribunal as "a carefully curated selection of paintings by the world's leading artists, including two paintings that <strong>spectacularly</strong> demonstrate Picasso's genius."</p>
<p><strong>Adding a toilet</strong></p>
<p>Rather than admit men to the exhibit, Kaechele added a working <strong>toilet</strong> to the space, turning it into a women's bathroom<strong>.</strong> This gave the gallery a legal reason to deny entry to men.</p>
<p>International news organizations reported on the change to the exhibit earlier this year. They did not question that a gallery would hang Picasso paintings in a public bathroom.</p>
<p>However, the Guardian news agency reported last week that it asked Kaechele about the work. That led to her admission about making the paintings herself.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Charlotte Graham-McLay reported on this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>gallery</strong> – <em>n.</em> a room or building in which people look at paintings</p>
<p><strong>bathroom</strong> – <em>n</em>. a room in a public place with a toilet and sink</p>
<p><strong>curator </strong>– <em>n</em>. a person who is in charge of the things in a museum, zoo, or the like</p>
<p><strong>exhibition</strong> – <em>n.</em> <strong> </strong>an event at which objects (such as works of art) are put out in a public space for people to look at</p>
<p><strong>lounge</strong> – <em>n.</em> a comfortable room for relaxing in a public building</p>
<p><strong>massage</strong> – <em>n.</em> the action of rubbing or pressing someone's body in a way that helps muscles to relax or reduces pain in muscles and joints</p>
<p><strong>tribunal</strong> – <em>n.</em> a kind of court that has authority in a specific area</p>
<p><strong>disadvantage </strong>– <em>n. </em>loss, damage, or harm</p>
<p><strong>spectacular</strong> – <em>adj.</em> causing wonder and admiration; very impressive</p>
<p><strong>toilet</strong> — <em>n</em>. a large bowl attached to a pipe that is used for getting rid of bodily waste</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
