<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>VOA Special English</title>
        <link>https://www.21voa.com/special_english/</link>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <itunes:category>ESL</itunes:category>
        <itunes:author>VOA</itunes:author>
        <description>美国之音（以下称VOA）的英语节目，按播音速度可分为两种：Standard English （标准英语）和 Special English（特别英语）。

Special English 又叫“慢速英语”，是VOA 专为全世界非英语国家初学英语的听众安排的一种简易、规范的英语广播节目。该节目创始于50年代末期，是VOA 的专家们研究如何与世界各地的英语学习者进行交际的产物。它正式开播于1959年10月。当时只面向欧洲和中东，但由于这个节目适合许多国家英语学习者的需要，所以它的广播对象不久就扩大到世界其他地区，并很快在全世界范围内产生了广泛的影响。现在这个节目对欧洲、非洲和拉丁美洲每晚广播一次，对加勒比地区每晚广播一次（星期天除外），对东南亚广播次数最多，每天上午两次，晚上三次。

30多年来，VOA 为了办好Special English节目，进行了大量的调查研究工作，对播音速度、内容及用词范围都作了具体规定，基本上达到了既能为英语学习者提供信息，又不损害英语本身风格的目的，使之成为VOA 独具特色，拥有最大量听众的节目。

美国著名词汇学家S. B. Flexmer 指明了Special English的三条标准，也就是它所“特别”的地方：

1、它是一种由美国人最常用的1500个基本单词为主体构成的美国英语；

2、它用简短、明晰的句子写作和广播；

3、它以每分钟90个单词的速度，即2/3的Standard English（标准英语）速度进行广播。

Special English的节目可分为两大类：一类是新闻节目；一类是专题节目。

1．新闻节目

VOA Special English 的新闻广播向听众提供世界范围内的政治、经济、军事、外交、国际关系、宗教、天气以及各种重大事件和珍闻奇事等各个方面的信息，每天向东南亚地区广播五次，早上两次，晚上三次，每逢半点播出。

Special English新闻节目每次长约十分钟，大都播出十条左右新闻，近一千个单词，每条新闻多为一分钟，但偶尔也有长达两分钟的要闻。除头条新闻外，每条新闻都由一个电头引导，这样显得结构分明，条理清晰，适宜初学英语的人收听。在节目结束之前，播音员常常用三四句话重播其中三条新闻的提要以加深听众对要闻的印象。

Special English新闻中70%左右的内容与同时整点播出的Standard English新闻相同，但相同新闻的先后次序有所变动。每次节目的开头和结尾大同小异，格式比较固定。

2．专题节目（一）

Special English的专题节目（Feature Programs）,从时间上看，可分为两大类：一是每五分钟一次的专题，二是每十五分钟一次的专题。本节先介绍每项五分钟一次的专题材节目。

Special English五分钟一次的专题材节目安排在Special English新闻节目之后和（或）每十五分钟一次的专题材节目之前播出，每星期播七次。根据内容，可分为三个小类，即：Science Report（科学报道），逢星期一、三、五播出，每天播六遍；Agriculture Report（农业报道），逢星期二、四播出，每天播六遍；Words And Their Stories（词语掌故），逢星期六和星期天播出，每天播五遍。这三个专题材各具特色，具有相对的独立性，听众每听完一个节目，都会获得一个完整的印象。

Science Report（科学报道）这一专题材节目每周向听众介绍三篇有关现代科学技术最新发展情况的报道，涉及物理、化学、天文至高无上理、生物、环卫、心理、教育、医学和计算机等方面。适宜理工科大学生和科技工作者收集信息，积累资料，学习科技英语。

Agriculture Report（农业报道） Agriculture Report是为农业科技工作者和生产者安排的一个专题。它专门报道世界各国，特别是美国现代农业生产的最新成文汇报总务科 学家对农业生产某一方面的研究进展，以及他们对影响农业生产的某一自然现象进行分析和研究的近况。此外，它还经常向听众介绍发展中国家家业生产的一些有益经验等内容。

Words And Their Stories（词语掌故）这一专题节目，旨在向学习英语的听众介绍美国英语中生动有趣的词语和惯用法，并从科学研究和通俗词源学的角度来解释它们的含意、产生的背景及其在使用过程中的演变情况等。它通过讲故事的形式讲解每一个词语。这是VOA Special English中的优秀节目之一，是学习美国英语的极好材料。通过收听这一节目，听众不仅能学到娓娓动听的掌故和地道的美国英语，而且能增加美国的社会文化背景知识，历史传统与现状的了解。

VOA 为了更好地办好这个节目，便于听众收听学习，于1978年编辑出版了一本名为Words And Their Stories的书，共收集一百篇故事，作者是Herbert Sutcliffe, Harold Bermen 及VOA 该节目的部分编辑人员。在每次的实际广播中，播音员都以此书为蓝本，再根据需要对原稿进行适当增删。按每周两个故事计算，此书的一百个故事还不能满足一年的播音需要。于是编辑们就是重播部分词语掌故的同时，不断增加许多新的词语掌故，及时将词源学家的最新研究成果和不断增加的新词汇介绍给听众。收听实践证明，初学者在收听过程中必然会遇到许多人名、地名和一些较难的句子，有时甚至在听完之后还很难理解所播词语的确切含义及其汉语意思，为此，听众可参看1983年由中国对外翻译出版公司出版的该书英汉对照本中的有关部分。

3．专题节目（二）

VOA Special English的专题节目，除上节谈的五分钟一次的以外，还有本节要介绍的每十五分钟一次的节目。这类节目共有七个不同的小专题，以星期为单位循环，每天分四次复播出一个专题，但星期日和星期六的两个专题材每晚只播三遍，每次节目约十分钟，继每次五分钟的专题节目之后播出。

这类专题节目的基本结构是，在特定的伴声中先报告当次节目的名称，并扼要介绍其主要内容，然后播送节目正文。最后，在伴乐声中报告节目主持人和撰稿人的姓名，以邀请听众在下周的这个时间继续收听该节目而结束。

People in America（美国人物志） 这是有关美国历史名人的一个专题节目，每逢星期天晚上播出。它向听众介绍在美国历史上产生过重大影响、起过重要作用、作出了突出贡献的科学、文学、政治、或其他各方面的历史人物。节目一般都对他们的生平事迹进行简要的叙述，对其贡献作出评介，类似人物小传。有的重要人物事迹很多，必须用两次或几次的节目时间进行联播。对这样的节目要坚持收听，才会获得完整的印象。

TThis is America（今日美国） This Is America向听众介绍美国人民的生活、学习、工作和娱乐情况，是英语学习者解美国社会的一条渠道。该专题大都一个节目一个整体，每逢星期一晚播出。

Science in the News（科学新闻） 这一专题材主要对新近的科学技术新闻进行综述或摘要广播。向听众介绍世界各国在自然、医学、疾病、原子能、航天等方面的科研动态、成果、突破性进展及存在的困难。涉及当今世界人们普遍关心的重大问题，如核事故、航天飞机爆炸、自然灾害、环境污染和爱滋病等等。每逢星期二播出，每次播一到五条新闻摘要。

Explorations（自然探索） 每逢星期三晚上，听众可以收听到Explorations这一专题节目。该专题既涉及人类遨游太空、探索原子、研究自身、改造自然的现代技术，也报道发展中国家开发新资源，利用新工艺改善人民生活等方面的成就，其侧重点在各种科技实验和简易实用技术方面。该节目一般安排一段时间播一个系列，每次播出一个主题，以便能将某项新技术的研究和应用的全过程介绍给听众，电台还乐意为感兴趣的听众提供所需的文字材料。

The Making of a Nation（建国史话） 这一专题节目向听众介绍美利坚合众国从十三个殖民地区域到现代工业国的孕育、诞生以及形成超级大国的历史过程，并以历史为线索，特定的历史时期为单位，以重大的历史事件为主题材来叙述各个党派、各届总统和政府的历史作用与贡献。这是每个英语学习者都应了解的基本知识。The Making of a Nation每逢星期四播出。这是个系列节目，坚持收听，则有助于系统了解美国的历史概况。

American Mosaic（美国万花筒） American Mosaic是一个radio magazine（广播杂志）节目。该节目题材广泛、内容丰，展示着美国社会文化生活中比较轻松愉快的生活画面；听众收听该节目就如同在阅读一本图文并茂的杂志。它每次有三到五个小节目，涉及音乐、图书、技术和教育等方面的内容。我们既可以从中欣赏到著名歌唱的优秀歌曲，对美国音乐有所了解，又可以获取一些生动有趣的现代美国社会生活知识，随着播音员那亲切悦耳的声音步入美国风景如画的大好河山；同时还能听到世界各地的听众提出的有关英语语方文学等方面的问题和电台的解答。

American Stories（美国故事） 这一专题材节目安排在每星期六晚上播出。这样能使听众在学习和工作之余，得以轻松一下头脑。我们可以通过这一美国文学的“窗口”，接触各种流派、各类名家的文学作品。了解美国英语的时代特色，欣赏、学习美国人民运用语方的技巧，并从那些佳作名篇中获得艺术享受。该节目对短篇故事采取一次播一篇的方式，对中、长篇小说则先进行简写加工，再分几次播出全文。在播出故事正文之前，播音员常常先介绍故事的主要情节。对需要分几次节目时间播出的中长篇，在播第二或以后各部分之前，主持人还先重述已播部分的故事梗概，以唤起听众的回忆，使故事听起来更加连贯。</description>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          <item>
            <title>Black Women Mathematicians Receive Congressional Medals for Space Program Work (2024/9/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/black-women-mathematicians-receive-congressional-medals-for-space-program-work.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">19 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The United States Congress has honored four women known as the “hidden <strong>figures</strong>” of the space race with its highest civilian award.</p>
<p>The Congressional Gold Medal was presented Wednesday to the families of Katherine Johnson, Dorothy Vaughan, Mary Jackson and Christine Darden at the U.S. Capitol. Only Darden is still living. The 82-year-old watched the ceremony from her Connecticut home.</p>
<p>Lawmakers recognized the four Black mathematicians for their critical work early in the space program.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="House Speaker Mike Johnson, center, presents a Congressional Gold Medal posthumously to Joylette Hylick, left, and Katherine Moore, daughters of Katherine Johnson at the Capitol in Washington, Sept. 18, 2024." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/774810ae-f1c8-44dc-91ea-94b7d4c77221_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">House Speaker Mike Johnson, center, presents a Congressional Gold Medal posthumously to Joylette Hylick, left, and Katherine Moore, daughters of Katherine Johnson at the Capitol in Washington, Sept. 18, 2024.</span></div>
<p>They also presented a medal to all the women who worked as mathematicians, engineers and "human computers" in the American space program from the 1930s to 1970s.</p>
<p>Margot Lee Shetterly wrote the 2016 book <em>Hidden Figures</em> about the Black women mathematicians who supported the space program in the 1960s. It was made into a movie of the same name in 2017.</p>
<p>"By honoring them, we honor the very best of our country's spirit," Shetterly said at the ceremony.</p>
<p>The early space program employed hundreds of women to work as mathematicians at what is now NASA's Langley Research Center in Virginia. But, the Black mathematicians were not permitted to work with the white mathematicians because of racial separation policies at the time. The Black researchers' work went unrecognized for years.</p>
<p>The team used pencils, slide rulers and mechanical calculating machines to calculate the paths of rockets and orbiters in the atmosphere and in space. The path is called the trajectory.</p>
<p>“Our office computed all the trajectories,” Katherine Johnson told <em>The Virginian-Pilot</em> newspaper in 2012. “You tell me when and where you want it to come down, and I will tell you where and when and how to launch it,” she explained.</p>
<p>In 1961, Johnson did trajectory research<strong> </strong>for the Freedom 7 Mission, the first to carry an American into space. The next year, she checked the <strong>calculations</strong> made by a new NASA computer for astronaut John Glenn's planned orbits around the planet.</p>
<p>John Glenn did not trust the new computer. Days before the launch, he told NASA, “Get the girl to check the numbers.” John Glenn become the first American to orbit the Earth in 1962.</p>
<p>Johnson was awarded the Presidential Medal of Freedom – the nation's highest civilian honor<span style="font-size: 9pt;"> </span><span style="font-size: 9pt;">–</span> in 2015<span style="font-size: 9pt;">. Her work at NASA helped open doors for many other women to take part in the space program.</span></p>
<p>Dorothy Vaughan rose to become NASA's first Black female supervisor. Mary Jackson was NASA's first Black female engineer. And Christine Darden is best known for her <strong>sonic boom</strong> research.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Adithi Ramakrishnan </em><em>reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Caty Weaver adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>figure </strong>– <em>n. a </em>digit representing an amount (as of money earned or points scored) also, a<strong> </strong>bodily shape or form especially of a person</p>
<p><strong>calculate</strong> – <em>v.</em> to find (a number, answer, or the like) by using mathematical processes</p>
<p><strong>sonic boom</strong> - <em>n.</em> a loud explosive noise caused by the shock wave from an aircraft traveling faster than the speed of sound.</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Using Discourse Markers in American English (2024/9/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/everyday-grammar-using-discourse-markers.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>
Imagine you are watching an old American movie -- the crime film “Dirty Harry.”</p>
<p>You have heard that one part of the film is very famous in American culture.</p>
<p>You watch the <strong>scene</strong>, which sounds like this:</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Using Discourse Markers in American English " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/db01b03d-07d5-4c83-8ecf-e98da144d4f7_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Using Discourse Markers in American English </span></div>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p><em>You go to ask yourself one question: Do I feel lucky?</em></p>
<p><em>Well, do you, punk?</em></p>
<p>A sudden, strange thought comes to your mind. What is the purpose of the word <em>well?</em></p>
<p>You have heard different English speakers use the word in different ways, but you are not sure what it means.</p>
<p>In our Everyday Grammar report, we will explore the common <strong>adverb</strong> <em>well</em>. We will show you how Americans use it while they are speaking.</p>
<p>Do not fear. Unlike an unexpected meeting with Dirty Harry, this report will be painless!</p>
<p><strong>What are adverbs?</strong></p>
<p>Adverbs are one of the most difficult subjects in English grammar. They are difficult because they represent a large group of words that have different uses.</p>
<p>In general, the definition of an adverb is this: a word that describes a verb, an adjective, another adverb, or a sentence.</p>
<p>Adverbs are often used to show time, place or a way of doing things. They can also show a <strong>degree</strong> or measurement of something.</p>
<p>Consider the sentence, "I really like English grammar." The adverb <em>really </em>changes the meaning of the verb <em>like</em>. The adverb <em>really</em> increases the force of the statement.</p>
<p>There are also sentence adverbs. They limit or describe the meaning of an entire statement.</p>
<p>Sentence adverbs also provide more information about the sentence. These are sometimes called <strong>conjunctive adverbs</strong> or discourse markers. <strong>Regardless</strong> of the name you choose to call them, the purpose is the same: They connect sentences in the same way <strong>coordinating conjunctions</strong> do, but they provide a different kind of information.</p>
<p>Here is an example.</p>
<p>Let's consider the statement:</p>
<p><em>I love English; <u>however,</u> I do not love English grammar!</em></p>
<p>The word <em>however </em>is a conjunctive adverb that shows a <strong>contrast</strong> or comparison is coming.</p>
<p>You can read more about words like these in an earlier Everyday Grammar story called "Contrast and Concession."</p>
<p><strong>The case of "well"</strong></p>
<p>Today we are considering common conjunctive adverbs, or discourse markers, and how they are used in everyday-speech.</p>
<p>Let's go back to the word <em>well</em>. As you heard at the beginning of today's program, <em>well</em> can have a few different uses.</p>
<p><strong>1. Well indicates contrast or disagreement</strong></p>
<p>The first use is to show a contrast or even a disagreement. Consider this line from the ending of the American film “Some Like It Hot.”</p>
<p><em>"You don't understand, Osgood! I'm a man."</em></p>
<p><em>"<u>Well,</u> nobody's perfect..."</em></p>
<p>Here, the speaker uses <em>well </em>to show that a contrast is coming.</p>
<p>The first speaker, the actor Jack Lemmon, expects the second person to become angry when he states he is not a woman, but a man.</p>
<p>But Osgood reacts in an unexpected, or contrasting way. He does not act surprised at all!</p>
<p><strong>2. Wells shows uncertainty </strong></p>
<p>The second use of <em>well </em>is to show <strong>uncertainty</strong>, especially in answers.</p>
<p>Consider this exchange between two friends.</p>
<p><em>Do you mind if I borrow five dollars?</em></p>
<p><em><u>Well,</u></em><em> I'm not sure if I have any money with me...</em></p>
<p>In this example, the second speaker is a little slow in responding. The word <em>well </em>shows that she is not sure if she has the money. Or, maybe she knows she has five dollars, but she does not want to say so.</p>
<p>Whatever the case, the point is that <em>well </em>serves as a word that shows movement between the question and the answer. This <strong>transition</strong> shows that there is some uncertainty.</p>
<p><strong>3. To show a conversation is ending</strong></p>
<p>The third common use of <em>well </em>is to show a transition to the end of a conversation.</p>
<p>Consider this example. Imagine you are in a business meeting, and your boss makes the following statement:</p>
<p><em><u>Well,</u> this meeting has been very productive.</em></p>
<p>In this case, the word <em>well </em>is showing a transition to the end of the meeting. Your boss is showing that he wants the meeting to end soon.</p>
<p>In American culture, this is considered a careful, indirect way to end a conversation.</p>
<p>However, if a speaker directs your attention to the word "well," then the meaning changes. The statement can take on an angry, tense sound.</p>
<p>Consider the difference between these two statements:</p>
<p><em><u>Well,</u> this meeting has been very productive.</em></p>
<p><em><u>WELL,</u> this meeting has been very productive.</em></p>
<p>The first statement is a respectful way to end a meeting.</p>
<p>The second statement is a tense, perhaps angry way to bring a meeting to an end. If you heard the second statement in a business meeting, then you should know that something is wrong!</p>
<p><strong>Do you understand the uses of well?</strong></p>
<p>Think back to the movie scene you heard at the beginning of this report. Now that you have learned about the word <em>well, </em>consider what Dirty Harry might have meant.</p>
<p>Like any good crime film, we end with a few questions.</p>
<p>What do you think Dirty Harry meant when he said <em>well?</em> Does he use it in a way that has the same meaning as the uses of <em>well</em> we have discussed, or does he use it in a different way?</p>
<p>Leave your answers in the Comments Section on our website, <a class="wsw__a" href="http://www.21voa.com/" target="_blank">www.21voa.com</a>, or on 21VOA.COM.</p>
<p><em>Well,</em> I guess that is all for today's program. Until next time!</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p>And I'm Alice Bryant.</p>
<p><em>John Russell wrote this lesson for Learning English. George Grow was the editor.</em></p><div id="bottom">
<ins class="adsbygoogle" data-ad-client="ca-pub-3585518775245612" data-ad-format="auto" data-ad-slot="9284795419" data-full-width-responsive="true" style="display:block; text-align:center;"></ins>
<script>(adsbygoogle =window.adsbygoogle ||[]).push({});</script></div>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>scene </strong><em>– n.</em> a part of a play, movie, story, etc., in which a particular action or activity occurs</p>
<p><strong>adverb</strong> – n. a word that describes a verb, an adjective, another adverb, or a sentence and that is often used to show time, manner, place, or degree</p>
<p><strong>conjunctive adverb </strong><em>– n.</em><strong> </strong>a conjunction that connects two sentences with an adverbial emphasis</p>
<p><strong>coordinating conjunction</strong> <em>– n.</em> a conjunction (such as <em>and, or</em>, or <em>but</em>) that joins together words, phrases, or clauses of equal importance</p>
<p><strong>contrast </strong><em>– n.</em> to be different especially in a way that is very obvious</p>
<p><strong>uncertainty </strong><em>– n.</em> the quality or state of being uncertain</p>
<p><strong>degree </strong><em>– n.</em> a step in a process or order of classification</p>
<p><strong>regardless </strong>– <em>adv.</em> without being stopped by difficulty or trouble</p>
<p><strong>transition </strong><em>– n.</em> passage from one subject or place to another</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Police Try AI for Help with Crime Reports (2024/9/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/us-police-try-ai-for-help-with-crime-reports.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By VOA</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Some police departments in the United States are experimenting with artificial intelligence (AI) tools to help them produce incident reports. Police officers who have tried the AI chatbots praise the technology as a time-saver.</p>
<p>Yet some government lawyers, legal experts, and others have expressed concerns about the AI-produced reports.</p>
<p><strong>A “game changer” </strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Captain Jason Bussert demonstrates Draft One, an AI powered software that creates police reports from body cam audio, at Oklahoma City police headquarters on Friday, May 31, 2024 in Oklahoma City, Oklahoma. (AP Photo/Nick Oxford)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/903e495e-f879-485b-a0ae-b93d4ba04e06_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Captain Jason Bussert demonstrates Draft One, an AI powered software that creates police reports from body cam audio, at Oklahoma City police headquarters on Friday, May 31, 2024 in Oklahoma City, Oklahoma. (AP Photo/Nick Oxford)</span></div>
<p>One chatbot police are testing uses the same technology as ChatGPT. The company that sells it, Axon, is best known for developing the electroshock weapon called the Taser. It is also the leading supplier of body cameras in the U.S.</p>
<p>Matt Gilmore is a police officer in Oklahoma's capital, Oklahoma City. He describes the AI chatbot as a “game changer” for police work.</p>
<p>Recently, Gilmore and his police dog, Gunner, searched for a group of suspects for almost an hour. In the past, after completing a search, the officer would spend another 30 to 45 minutes writing up a report about the incident. But this time he used AI.</p>
<p>The tool considered all the sounds and radio talk recorded by the microphone attached to Gilmore's body camera. Then it produced a report.</p>
<p>The process took eight seconds.</p>
<p>“It was a better report than I could have ever written, and it was 100 percent accurate. It flowed better,” Gilmore said. The report even documented an event he did not remember: Another officer identifying the color of the car from which the suspects fled.</p>
<p>The new AI product is called Draft One. Axon's founder and CEO Rick Smith said it received the “most positive reaction” of any tool the company has offered.</p>
<p>“They become police officers because they want to do police work, and spending half their day doing data entry is just a <strong>tedious</strong> part of the job that they hate,” Smith said.</p>
<p>But he also noted legal and ethical concerns about the tool.</p>
<p>He said government lawyers prosecuting criminal cases want to be sure that police officers are responsible for writing their reports. Sometimes, officers are called to testify in court about cases they worked on.</p>
<p><strong>Prosecutors</strong> “never want to get an officer on the stand who says, well, ‘The AI wrote that, I didn't,'” Smith said.</p>
<p><strong>AI technology concerns</strong></p>
<p>AI technology is not new to police agencies. American police already use such tools to read license plates, identify suspects' faces, recognize the sounds of gunshots, and predict where crimes will happen.</p>
<p>In Oklahoma City, police showed the tool to local prosecutors before using it for criminal cases. The lawyers advised the police to be careful with the tool. For now, it is used only for minor incident reports that do not lead to arrests.</p>
<p>“So no arrests, no <strong>felonies</strong>, no violent crimes,” said Oklahoma City police Captain Jason Bussert, the head of information technology for the 1,170-officer department.</p>
<p>Police in the city of Lafayette, Indiana, have a different policy on the new tool. Police Chief Scott Galloway told the Associated Press that officers can use Draft One for every incident. He said the tool is very popular with the city force. It began using the tool earlier this year.</p>
<p>Police in Fort Collins, Colorado, are also permitted to use the AI tool on any kind of report. However, the head of the force's technology department said the tool does not work well in very noisy parts of the city.</p>
<p>Axon will not say how many police departments are using Draft One. Other companies including Policereports.ai and Truleo offer similar tools. Experts and police officials expect AI-generated reports to become more common in the coming months and years.</p>
<p>Some experts and observers are calling for public discussion about the use of AI tools to write police reports. Chatbots that use AI technology are not mistake-free. Sometimes these chatbots can produce false information.</p>
<p>That issue worries Andrew Ferguson, a law professor at American University.</p>
<p>“I am concerned that <strong>automation</strong> and the ease of the technology would cause police officers to be sort of less careful with their writing,” he said..</p>
<p>Ferguson said a police report is important in determining whether an officer's suspicion supports “someone's loss of liberty.” It is sometimes the only testimony a judge sees in a court case, particularly for minor crimes known as misdemeanors.</p>
<p>Human-created police reports also have problems, Ferguson noted. He said it is not yet known which kind of report writer, human or AI, is more dependable.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Sean Murphy and Matt O'Brien reported on this story for the Associated Press. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>prosecutor</strong> <em>– n. </em>an attorney who conducts proceedings in a court on behalf of the government</p>
<p><strong>tedious</strong> <em>– adj.</em> tiresome, boring</p>
<p><strong>felony </strong><em>– n.</em> a serious crime for which the punishment in federal law may be death or imprisonment for more than one year</p>
<p><strong>automation</strong> <em>– n.</em> automatically controlled operation of a process, or system by electronic devices that take the place of human labor</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How to Move an Elephant (2024/9/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/how-to-move-an-elephant.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>When it comes to the business of moving elephants, Dr. Amir Khalil and his team might be the best. The work experience of this Egyptian animal doctor includes possibly the most famous elephant relocation ever.</p>
<p>In 2020, Khalil's team saved Kaavan, an Asian elephant, from years of loneliness at a zoo in Pakistan. They flew him to Cambodia, where he could live a happier life at an elephant <strong>reserve</strong>.</p>
<p>At the time, Kaavan was called the “world's loneliest elephant.” The relocation project was a great success. But Kaavan was not the only elephant that needed help.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Charley, an ageing African elephant, is ready to move from the National Zoological Gardens in Pretoria, South Africa, to his new home. Special elephant movers made it happen, August 9, 2024.(AP Photo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a79ba61d-3f12-49a5-bda3-0685ed4833ac_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Charley, an ageing African elephant, is ready to move from the National Zoological Gardens in Pretoria, South Africa, to his new home. Special elephant movers made it happen, August 9, 2024.(AP Photo)</span></div>
<p>Next on the list was the last captive elephant in South Africa.</p>
<p>Charley, an aging African elephant, had outlived all the other elephants at a zoo in Pretoria. The zoo was Charley's home for more than 20 years. Wildlife experts say that elephants are <strong>sensitive</strong> animals. And Charley was showing signs of being deeply unhappy since his partner, Landa, died in 2020.</p>
<p>Zoo officials decided he should enjoy his final years in a better place for an old elephant. His new home would be a large private game reserve some 200 kilometers away. There, he would be able to make some new elephant friends.</p>
<p>As an animal rescue specialist at the Four Paws wildlife welfare organization, Khalil was a clear choice for this massive job.</p>
<p><strong>Charley's story</strong></p>
<p>Captured as a young calf in western Zimbabwe in the 1980s, Charley was taken from his <strong>herd</strong>. He spent 16 years in a South African circus. He then spent 23 years as the main <strong>attraction</strong> at Pretoria's National Zoological Garden. Zookeepers estimate Charley is 42 years old. He has spent 40 years in captivity.</p>
<p>“I don't know how many hundreds of thousands of people and children witnessed and enjoyed Charley,” said Khalil. “I think it's time for him to also enjoy life and to live as an elephant.”</p>
<p>Elephants are highly intelligent, highly social animals, Khalil said. While Charley was unhappy, he could also be <strong>naughty</strong> and playful. Khalil compared Charley's last few sad years at the zoo to someone watching the same movie every day, alone.</p>
<p>The technical parts of moving an elephant to a new home are complex. Khalil does not put the elephants to sleep. This is mainly because it is not good for such a big animal. But also, a sleeping elephant is hardly any easier to move.</p>
<p>And so, a process began of <strong>training</strong> an old elephant to step willingly into a large metal transport container. At some point, Khalil and his team would load Charley into this container.</p>
<p>Two other animal doctors, Dr. Marina Ivanova and Dr. Frank G<i></i>246;ritz, worked with Khalil as part of the Kaavan relocation team. They first met Charley two years ago. The meetings were meant to help the doctors decide how ready he was to move. They were also meant to help them earn Charley's trust.</p>
<p>The interactions were carefully controlled. They involved teaching Charley to <strong>respond</strong> to calls to walk up to a “training wall” that has spaces in it for the team to offer him a food reward. In Charley's case, pumpkins, papaya, and beetroot are his favorites.</p>
<p>The same process was finally used to attract Charley into the transport container. It was thought that it might take many months for Charley to learn to step happily into the container. But he was ready to go after less than two weeks of training.</p>
<p>“He was <strong>curious</strong>, and thinking, what is this new toy?” said Ivanova.</p>
<p>In late August, after an hours-long road trip on the back of a truck, Charley moved into his new home at the Shambala private game reserve.</p>
<p>This is a huge change for Charley. So, he will be held in an area separate from the main park for a few weeks to let him get used to his new home, the team said. The park contains wild elephant herds that Charley may join.</p>
<p>Khalil said it is still very rare for captive elephants to be reintroduced to a wild setting. He praised zoo and government officials for permitting this project to go ahead.</p>
<p>“It's a great message from South Africa that even an old elephant <strong>deserves</strong> a new chance,” he said.</p>
<p>At Shambala, Charley will be a wild elephant for the first time in 40 years with thousands of hectares of land to explore. He will have the freedom to take a mud bath. The animal doctors note that elephants are known to have a good memory. So, Charley may remember his life as a calf before he was captured.</p>
<p>Charley is already making contact with the other elephants in the park from his holding pen, Ivanova said. Elephants use deep <strong>rumbles</strong> to communicate. Those deep sounds can be heard five kilometers away.</p>
<p>“I hear him rumbling,” said Ivanova, happily. “We'll help him turn into a wild elephant again.”</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo. And I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Gerald Imray reported this story for The Associated Press from Cape Town, South Africa. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>reserve </strong><em>–n. </em>an area of land set apart</p>
<p><strong>sensitive </strong><em>–adj. </em>easily or strongly affected or hurt : readily affected or changed by the action of a certain thing</p>
<p><strong>herd </strong><em>–n. </em>a number of animals of one kind kept or living together</p>
<p><strong>attraction</strong> <em>–n</em>. something that pleases or draws people in</p>
<p><strong>naughty </strong><em>–adj. </em>behaving badly or improperly</p>
<p><strong>train</strong><em> -v. </em>to form by instruction, discipline, or drill<strong> </strong>:<strong> training </strong><em>–n.</em></p>
<p><strong>respond </strong><em>-v. </em>to react in response</p>
<p><strong>curious</strong> <em>–adj. </em>marked by desire to investigate and learn</p>
<p><strong>deserve </strong><em>-v. </em>to be worthy of</p>
<p><strong>rumble </strong><em>-v. </em>to make a low heavy rolling sound</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Can Noncitizens Vote in US Elections? (2024/9/19) | 非公民能在美国选举中投票吗？</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/can-noncitizens-vote-in-us-elections.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>United States law bans noncitizens from voting in federal elections, such as elections for president, the Senate, and the House of Representatives.<br/>美国法律禁止非公民在联邦选举中投票，如总统、参议院和众议院的选举。</p><p>Like many states, Pennsylvania also bans noncitizens from voting in elections for state offices.<br/>与许多州一样，宾夕法尼亚州还禁止非公民在州政府选举中投票。</p><p>A 1996 federal law permits fines and imprisonment for up to a year for noncitizens who vote in federal elections. Violators can also be deported. When people in the U.S. register to vote, they swear officially that they are U.S. citizens.<br/>1996年的一项联邦法律允许对在联邦选举中投票的非公民处以罚款和长达一年的监禁。违反者也可能被驱逐出境。当美国人登记投票时，他们要正式宣誓自己是美国公民。</p><p>In Pennsylvania, as in other states, people must meet requirements, including citizenship, to register to vote. The state constitution says a voter must "have been a citizen of the United States at least one month." They also have to prove that they live in the state and voting district.<br/>宾夕法尼亚州与其他州一样，人们必须满足包括公民身份在内的要求才能登记投票。州宪法规定，选民必须“已成为美国公民至少一个月”。他们还必须证明自己住在该州和选区内。</p><p>Ellen Lyon is a spokesperson for the Pennsylvania Department of State. Lyon said, if a noncitizen did try to vote in a Pennsylvania election, they would face punishment, including imprisonment and deportation.<br/>艾伦·莱昂是宾夕法尼亚州州务院的发言人。莱昂说，如果非公民确实试图在宾夕法尼亚州的选举中投票，他们将面临包括监禁和驱逐出境在内的惩罚。</p><p>The department is "not aware of any instances of noncitizens registering to vote or voting in any recent elections," Lyon said in an email to The Associated Press (AP).<br/>莱昂在给美联社的一封电子邮件中表示，该部门“没听说有任何非公民登记投票或在最近的任何选举中投票的情况”。</p><p>Ron Hayduk is a political science professor at San Francisco State University in California who studies voting laws for noncitizens. He said that studies show noncitizens are not illegally voting in big numbers.<br/>罗恩·海德克是加州旧金山州立大学研究非公民投票法的政治学教授。他说，研究表明，非公民并没有大量非法投票。</p><p>There have been some reports of noncitizens illegally casting ballots, Hayduk said, but such incidents are very rare.<br/>海德克说，美国有过一些关于非公民非法投票的报道，但此类事件非常罕见。</p><p>The Brennan Center for Justice is a research group at New York University. In 2017, the group studied 42 voting areas across the United States in the 2016 election. It reported that of 23.5 million votes cast, election officials found about 30 cases of possible noncitizen voting that they referred, or reported, to law enforcement.<br/>布伦南司法中心是纽约大学的一个研究小组。2017年，该小组研究了2016年大选中美国各地的42个投票区。据报道，在2350万张选票中，选举官员发现了大约30起可能是非公民投票的案件，他们将这些案件提交或报告给了执法部门。</p><p>The state of Georgia examined its voter lists in 2022 and found fewer than 2,000 times when noncitizens tried to register to vote over the last 25 years. None of those people were registered because they did not qualify. Millions of new Georgia voters registered during that time.<br/>佐治亚州在2022年审查了其选民名单，发现在过去25年里，非公民试图登记投票的次数不到2000次。这些人都没有登记成功，因为他们没有资格。在此期间有数百万格鲁吉亚新选民登记。</p><p>In 2017, Pennsylvania said that it had to fix a mistake that permitted noncitizen immigrants to register to vote when getting a driver's license. State election officials said noncitizen immigrants might have cast 544 ballots illegally — out of more than 93 million ballots in elections dating back 18 years, going back to 2000.<br/>宾夕法尼亚州在2017年表示，它必须纠正一个错误，即允许非公民移民在获得驾照时登记投票。州选举官员表示，自2000年以来，在为期18年的选举中投出的9300多万张选票中，非公民移民可能非法投出了544张选票。</p><p>Daniel Mallinson is an associate professor of public policy and administration at Penn State University in central Pennsylvania. He said claims that noncitizens are voting in large numbers have been "clearly debunked over and over and over again."<br/>丹尼尔·马林森是宾夕法尼亚州中部的宾夕法尼亚州立大学公共政策及管理专业的副教授。他说，非公民大量投票的说法“一次又一次地被明显揭穿”。</p><p>The AP says no state constitutions clearly permit noncitizens to vote. But some cities and towns in the states of California, Maryland and Vermont, as well as the District of Columbia, do permit voting by noncitizens in some local elections such as for school board and city council.<br/>美联社表示，没有州宪法明确允许非公民投票。但加利福尼亚州、马里兰州、佛蒙特州以及哥伦比亚特区的一些城镇确实允许非公民在一些诸如学校董事会和市议会选举的地方选举中投票。</p><p>I'm Jill Robbins.<br/>我是吉尔·罗宾斯。(21VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Companies Grow Cocoa Beans in Lab to Produce Chocolate (2024/9/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/companies-grow-cocoa-beans-in-lab-to-produce-chocolate.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Climate change pressures have led some companies to try growing cocoa in new environments to produce chocolate.</p>
<p>Some of the companies have set up growing operations in laboratories to produce cocoa from cell <strong>cultures</strong>. Others are experimenting with non-cocoa substances in an effort to create chocolate <strong>alternatives</strong>.</p>
<p>Higher temperatures worldwide have made it harder to grow cocoa beans in traditional rainforest environments. But worldwide demand remains high for chocolate. So, scientists and businesses are looking to create new products to meet that demand.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Chocolate callets are displayed at the California Cultured office in West Sacramento, Calif., Wednesday, Aug. 28, 2024. (AP Photo/Jeff Chiu)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/b024df80-4627-4071-b24c-73c8ec1d04e2_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Chocolate callets are displayed at the California Cultured office in West Sacramento, Calif., Wednesday, Aug. 28, 2024. (AP Photo/Jeff Chiu)</span></div>
<p>California Cultured is a plant cell culture company based in West Sacramento, California. It is growing cocoa from cell cultures inside a lab and plans to start selling its products next year. The process involves putting cocoa bean cells in a container with sugar water. This helps them quickly reproduce and <strong>mature</strong>.</p>
<p>Alan Perlstein, chief executive of California Cultured, spoke to the Associated Press. He said his company's process can produce a harvest in just one week. This compares to six to eight weeks for a traditional harvest. He said the method also uses a lot less water and labor than harvesting cocoa beans in a field.</p>
<p>Perlstein said he sees the demand for chocolate continuing to increase, while the supply decreases. Using alternative processing methods might be the only way to increase the supply of cocoa without causing environmental harm or greatly increasing costs, he said.</p>
<p>Cocoa trees grow about 20 degrees north and south of the equator in areas with warm weather and a lot of rain. But scientists fear further climate change will dry out the land in such areas.</p>
<p>The worldwide market for chocolate is huge. The chocolate market for <strong>candy</strong> worldwide reached $238.5 billion in 2023, research website <em>Statista</em> <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.statista.com/forecasts/983554/global-chocolate-confectionery-market-size">reports.</a> Sales in the United States alone reached more than $25 billion in 2023, the National Confectioners Association said. The trade organization represents the candy industry.</p>
<p>The price of cocoa increased earlier this year because of rising demand and West African crop losses from plant disease and weather changes. West Africa produces most of the world's cocoa.</p>
<p>Carla D. Martin is executive director of the U.S.-based Fine Cacao and Chocolate Institute. She told the AP that drops in the world cocoa supply have led some companies to look for ways to replace the <strong>ingredient</strong> that produces the taste of chocolate.</p>
<p>Planet A Foods is once such company in Planegg, Germany. It believes the taste of mass market chocolate is created not only by the bean itself, but also how it is <strong>fermented</strong> and cooked.</p>
<p>The company has tested out many ingredients, from olives to seaweed, to find a possible substitute. It is currently using a mix of oats and sunflower seeds as the best tasting chocolate alternative, said company spokesperson Jessica Karch. Planet A Foods calls the product “ChoViva,” which can be used in place of other ingredients in baked goods.</p>
<p>“The idea is not to replace the high quality, 80 percent dark chocolate, but really to have a lot of different products in the mass market,” Karch told the AP.</p>
<p>Similar efforts can be found in Israel. One company there, Celleste Bio, is taking cocoa bean cells and growing them indoors to produce cocoa powder and cocoa butter.</p>
<p>The company's co-founder, Hanne Volpin, said that within a few years the company aims to be able to produce cocoa no matter what the situation is with climate change and disease. Volpin added, “We only have a small field, but eventually, we will have a farm of bioreactors.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>culture</strong><em> – n. </em>the process of growing things, especially bacteria, for scientific purposes</p>
<p><strong>alternative</strong> <em>– n. </em>one of two or more things you can choose between</p>
<p><strong>mature </strong><em>– </em><em>v. </em>completely grow or develop</p>
<p><strong>ingredient </strong><em>– n.</em> one of the different foods used to make other foods</p>
<p><strong>ferment</strong> <em>– v. </em>when a substance is stored and the sugar in it changes into alcohol because of a chemical process</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Finnish Students Go Back to School with Books, Not Screens (2024/9/18) | 传统课本重新回归芬兰校园</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/finnish-students-go-back-to-school-with-books-not-screens.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>This autumn, students in the Finnish town of Riihimaki headed back to school with backpacks full of books. This marks a change from recent years.<br/>
今年秋天，芬兰里希马基镇的学生背着装满书籍的背包回到学校。这标志着近年来的一次变化。</p>
<p>For the past 10 years, the Finnish government pushed laptops and other electronic devices in the classroom.<br/>
在过去的10年里，芬兰政府在课堂上推广笔记本电脑和其他电子设备。</p>
<p>Finland's public education system is known for its good results and its readiness to try new teaching methods. Until recently, many schools gave laptops for free to all students from as early as age 11.<br/>
芬兰的公共教育体系以其良好的成绩和乐于尝试新教学方法而闻名。最近，许多学校向最小11岁的所有学生免费提供笔记本电脑。</p>
<p>But Finnish parents and teachers have become increasingly concerned over the effect of screens on children.<br/>
但芬兰的家长和老师越来越担心电子屏幕对孩子的影响。</p>
<p>Riihimaki is a town of about 30,000 people. It sits 70 kilometers north of the capital, Helsinki. In 2018, the town's middle schools stopped using most books. But this school year, schools in Riihimaki are going back to pen and paper.<br/>
里希马基是一个约有3万人的小镇。它位于首都赫尔辛基以北70公里处。2018年，该镇的中学停止使用大部分书籍。但本学年，里希马基镇的学校将回到纸和笔的时代。</p>
<p>"Young people are using phones and digital devices so much these days that we don't want school to be one of the places where children are only staring at screens," said Maija Kaunonen, an English teacher at Pohjolanrinne middle school.<br/>
Pohjolanrinne中学的英语老师麦杰亚·考诺宁说：“现在年轻人使用手机和数字设备的频率太高了，我们不希望学校成为孩子们只盯着屏幕的地方。”</p>
<p>The distractions that come with the use of digital devices make many children restless and unable to give their full attention to learning, Kaunonen said.<br/>
考诺宁说，使用数字设备带来的分心让许多孩子坐立不安，无法全神贯注于学习。</p>
<p>She added, "Most students just did the exercises as quick as they could” so they could then move on to using social media.<br/>
她补充道，“大多数学生只是尽可能快地做练习”，这样他们就可以继续使用社交媒体了。</p>
<p>"And it took them no time at all to change tabs in the browser. So when the teacher came round to them, they could say: 'Yes, I was doing this exercise'."<br/>
“他们在浏览器中切换窗口几乎不需要时间。所以当老师走过来时，他们可以说：‘是的，我正在做这个练习’。”</p>
<p>Across Finland, children's learning results have been slowly getting worse in recent years. In answer, the government plans new laws to ban the use of personal devices, such as phones, during school hours to cut back on screen time.<br/>
近年来，芬兰各地的儿童学习成绩逐渐恶化。作为回应，政府计划制定新的法律，禁止在上课时间使用手机等个人设备，以减少电子屏幕使用时间。</p>
<p>Improved concentration<br/>
提高注意力</p>
<p>One of Kaunonen's students is 14-year-old Elle Sokka. She said she did not always pay attention to the school subjects when learning digitally. Instead, she moved to another web page.<br/>
14岁的艾莉·苏卡是考诺宁的学生之一。她说，在数字化教学时，她并不总是将注意力放在学校科目上。相反，她转到了另一个网页。</p>
<p>Eighth-graders Miko Mantila and Inka Warro, both 14, said their concentration has improved since books returned to the classrooms.<br/>
14岁的八年级学生米克·曼蒂拉和因卡·瓦罗说，自从书本回到教室后，他们的注意力有所提高。</p>
<p>"Reading, for one, is much easier and I can read much faster from books," Mantila said.<br/>
曼蒂拉说：“首先阅读要容易得多，而且我从书本上读得更快。”</p>
<p>"And if you have to do homework late at night, it's easier to go to sleep when you haven't just been looking at a device," Warro added.<br/>
瓦罗补充道：“如果你必须在深夜做作业，那么当你不是一直盯着电子设备的时候就更容易入睡。”</p>
<p>Minna Peltopuro is a psychologist working with the town on the change. She said the total screen time should be cut because Finnish teenagers currently stare at a screen for up to six hours each day on average. She added that too much use of electronic devices comes with both physical and mental risks, such as eye problems and growing anxiety.<br/>
明娜·佩尔托普罗是一名与该镇合作进行改革的心理学家。她说，总屏幕使用时间应该减少，因为芬兰青少年目前平均每天盯着屏幕长达6个小时。她补充说，过度使用电子设备会带来身体和精神上的风险，比如视力问题和日益增长的焦虑。</p>
<p>Peltopuro added that the brain is at risk when trying to do more than one thing at a time. "Especially at a young age, one cannot manage it well," she said.<br/>
佩尔托普罗补充说，当试图同时做多件事时，大脑会面临风险。她说：“尤其是在年轻的时候，人们无法很好地应对它。”</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.<br/>
我是吉尔·罗宾斯。(21VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Report: Share of Foreign-Born in U.S. Grows to Highest Level in 100 Years (2024/9/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/us-report-share-of-foreign-born-in-u-s-grows-to-highest-level-in-100-years.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By VOA</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Last year, the percentage of U.S. <strong>residents</strong> who were foreign-born grew to its highest level in more than 100 years.</p>
<p>Recently, the U.S. Census Bureau released its yearly American Community Survey that provided detailed numbers.</p>
<p>The American Community Survey follows family life, income, education levels, disabilities, military service, and employment, among other subjects.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A man, part of a group of 50 new United States citizens, takes part in a naturalization ceremony before the San Diego Padres host the Minnesota Twins in a baseball game at Petco Park, Wednesday, Aug. 21, 2024, in San Diego. (AP Photo/Gregory Bull)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/6c5f7edb-77eb-4c20-a5a1-2c97d4cc0a1d_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A man, part of a group of 50 new United States citizens, takes part in a naturalization ceremony before the San Diego Padres host the Minnesota Twins in a baseball game at Petco Park, Wednesday, Aug. 21, 2024, in San Diego. (AP Photo/Gregory Bull)</span></div>
<p>The study, or survey, shows the share of people born outside the United States increased in 2023 to 14.3 percent from 13.9 percent in 2022.</p>
<p>International <strong>migrants</strong> have become a main cause of population growth in recent years.</p>
<p>Migrants are increasing their share of the population as Americans are having fewer children compared with years past. The percentage of the foreign-born population in the United States has not been this high since 1910 when it was 14.7 percent. At that time, waves of people came to the U.S. in search of a better life.</p>
<p>Luciana Bracho moved legally to Miami from Venezuela.</p>
<p>“We knew that here you can have savings, live well. Here you can have normal services such as water and electricity,” she said.</p>
<p>Bracho's move was part of a special official program known as a <strong>humanitarian parole program</strong>. She came with her boyfriend, parents and brother in April 2023. “I like Miami and the <strong>opportunities</strong> that I have had,” she said.</p>
<p>In 2023, international migrants accounted for more than two-thirds of the population growth in the United States. In the 2020s, they have made up almost three-fourths of U.S. growth.</p>
<p>The growth appears to be mainly people coming from Latin America. Their estimated share of the foreign-born population increased to 51.2 percent from 50.3 percent in 2022.</p>
<p>Latin Americans have increased among U.S. residents born in another country. The share of foreign-born residents from Europe and Asia has dropped a little.</p>
<p>Nicole Díaz was an opposition activist in Venezuela. She said she left after her life was threatened. Díaz lived in Peru and Ecuador before moving to the Miami area legally in February 2023 with her husband and nine-year-old daughter. Díaz described herself as “100 percent happy” living in South Florida, where the family pays $2,300 a month for a two-bedroom apartment.</p>
<p>“After being in different countries, working here is <strong>relaxed</strong>, despite the language,” Díaz said. “But housing is very expensive, and we have been evaluating moving to another state because here all the salary goes for the rent.”</p>
<p>Delaware was among the states with the largest increases in the foreign-born population from 2022 to 2023. The small state went to 11.2 percent from 9.9 percent. Georgia went to 11.6 percent from 10.7 percent. And New Mexico went from 10.2 percent from 9.3 percent.</p>
<p>The share of the foreign-born population dropped slightly in Washington, D.C., Idaho, Iowa, Maine, Minnesota, Montana, North Dakota and Oregon.</p>
<p>The Census Bureau numbers do not show whether people are in the United States legally or illegally. Illegal immigration has become a top political issue in 2024.</p>
<p>The study says the percentage of U.S. residents who say they are Hispanic, no matter what race, increased last year to 19.4 percent from 19.1 percent the year before.</p>
<p>At the same time, those who say they are “non-Hispanic white” dropped from 57.7 percent to 57.1 percent.</p>
<p>The share of U.S. residents who identify as Black dropped a little, from 12.2 percent to 12.1 percent.</p>
<p>And the share of U.S. residents who identify as Asian went from 5.9 percent to 6 percent.</p>
<p>The average age of U.S. residents continues to increase. The median age went from 39 in 2022 to 39.2 in 2023.</p>
<p>Americans born after World War II, from the 1940s to the mid-1960s, are known as the “baby boom” generation. They are now senior citizens.</p>
<p>The generation known as “millennials,” those born between the early 1980s and middle 1990s, are entering middle age. While the share of children under age 18 remained the same at 21.7 percent, the share of senior citizens aged 65 and over increased to 17.7 percent from 17.3 percent.</p>
<p>Other numbers show that working from home is decreasing after the COVID-19 pandemic. The share of employees working from home dropped last year to 13.8 percent from 15.2 percent in 2022.</p>
<p>The survey also showed that the median cost of renting, plus utilities and related costs, grew faster than median home values in 2023 for the first time in 10 years. The 3.8 percent rise in rental costs was the largest yearly increase since at least 2011. However, the share of renter income spent on rent and utility costs remained unchanged at 31 percent in 2023.</p>
<p>That finding suggests that incomes kept up with rent increases, the Census Bureau said.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p>And I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>Mike Schneider and Gisela Salomon reported on this story for the Associated Press. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>resident</strong> <em>–n.</em> a person who lives in a place</p>
<p><strong>migrant </strong><em>– n.</em> a person who moves from one country to another</p>
<p><strong>humanitarian parole program</strong> <em>– n.</em> an extraordinary measure only rarely used to bring an inadmissible foreign national into the United States for a temporary period of time</p>
<p><strong>opportunity </strong><em>–n.</em> a chance to do or get something that is good or helpful</p>
<p><strong>relax <em>–</em></strong><em> v.</em> to make less severe or strict, to relax</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>SpaceX Crew Returns to Earth after First Private Spacewalks (2024/9/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/spacex-crew-returns-to-earth-after-first-private-spacewalks.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The four-member crew of a private space flight has returned to Earth after a trip that included the first-ever spacewalks by non-professional astronauts.</p>
<p>American business leader Jared Isaacman organized and paid for the five-day <strong>mission</strong>, called Polaris Dawn. The American company SpaceX was a partner in the operation. It built both the Crew Dragon <strong>capsule</strong> and the Falcon 9 rocket that carried it to space.</p>
<p>The capsule dropped into the Gulf of Mexico near Florida early Sunday as planned.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image made from a SpaceX video shows the start of the first private spacewalk led by tech billionaire Jared Isaacman Thursday Sept. 12, 2024. (SpaceX via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/cde8a4a3-9aac-4069-b0a6-831406bbe973_cx5_cy10_cw74_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image made from a SpaceX video shows the start of the first private spacewalk led by tech billionaire Jared Isaacman Thursday Sept. 12, 2024. (SpaceX via AP)</span></div>
<p>The mission is historic for two reasons. First, Crew Dragon reached a top <strong>altitude</strong> of more than 1,400 kilometers. That was the highest level any crewed mission has reached since the American space agency NASA's Apollo program ended in the early 1970s.</p>
<p>Second, two crew members completed spacewalks during the mission. Isaacman was first to pop his head out of the Crew Dragon capsule on September 12. He spent about 10 minutes with the top half of his body outside the capsule as the spacecraft orbited hundreds of kilometers above Earth.</p>
<p>A video camera captured Isaacman saying at the time, "Back at home we all have a lot of work to do. But from here, Earth sure looks like a perfect world."</p>
<p>SpaceX engineer Sarah Gillis took a turn after Isaacman returned.</p>
<p>During each spacewalk, the astronauts kept their feet positioned inside the spacecraft. They moved their bodies in several exercises to test their spacesuits.</p>
<p>Until Polaris Dawn, only government astronauts and cosmonauts in government service had completed spacewalks.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p>The other Polaris Dawn crewmembers were SpaceX engineer Anna Menon, and Scott Poteet, a retired American Air Force officer. They did not leave the spacecraft. However, they wore the same kind of spacesuits as Isaacman and Gillis. They needed the protection as the capsule environment was depressurized for the space walks.</p>
<p>Isaacman had said a main goal of the mission would be to test the new spacesuit design in preparation for long-term stays in space. SpaceX has said the suits are equipped with the latest data-gathering instruments, as well as cameras and improved <strong>mobility</strong> systems.</p>
<p>Before the mission launched, SpaceX said the crew planned to carry out a series of experiments aboard the Crew Dragon capsule. Among these were a test of laser-based satellite communication between the spacecraft and Starlink, SpaceX's internet satellite system. The laser method – which has also been tested by NASA – is designed to greatly increase space communication speeds.</p>
<p>Many of the experiments dealt with observations of how human health is affected during long space missions. Among these will be tests with special contact lenses containing microelectronics that can continuously identify changes in eye pressure and shape.</p>
<p>Isaacman is the head of payment processing company Shift4Payments. He has an estimated personal worth of $2 billion. Isaacman has not said publicly how much he paid SpaceX for its service.</p>
<p>Polaris Dawn is the first of three planned missions under the Polaris program. The second will also use a Dragon capsule, while the third and final is expected to use SpaceX's Starship rocket. SpaceX chief Elon Musk has said his company plans to use Starship to carry future space travelers to the moon and Mars.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters, Agence France-Presse and SpaceX. </em></p>
<p><strong>____________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_21MSnzgP"><strong>mission </strong></a><em>– n.</em> an important project or trip, especially involving space travel</p>
<p><strong>capsule </strong><em>– n. </em>the part of a spacecraft that people live in</p>
<p><strong>altitude </strong><em>– n. </em>the height of something above sea level</p>
<p><strong>mobility</strong> <em>– n. </em>the ability to walk and move freely</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Poisonous Plants Look Like Safe Ones (2024/9/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/poisonous-plants-look-like-safe-ones.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle Report</em>.</p>
<p>Actor Alicia Silverstone worried fans on social media recently. While on a trip to England, she posted a TikTok video of herself tasting a poisonous berry she found along a sidewalk.</p>
<p>Silverstone, who appeared in the 1995 movie <em>Clueless</em>, said she thought the fruit was a tomato. But when she bit into it and found that it had an unusual taste, she realized that it was not the common food.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - An employee touches the flower of a Datura Stramonium plant, part of the nightshade family, at The Royal Botanic Gardens in London, Monday, Sept. 22, 2014. The nightshade family is known to have toxins in fruit or in stems and leaves.(AP Photo/Kirsty Wigglesworth, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4bc3b83a-7259-440e-870a-fa7c6e0171be_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - An employee touches the flower of a Datura Stramonium plant, part of the nightshade family, at The Royal Botanic Gardens in London, Monday, Sept. 22, 2014. The nightshade family is known to have toxins in fruit or in stems and leaves.(AP Photo/Kirsty Wigglesworth, File)</span></div>
<p>Plant expert, Jessica Damiano, recently wrote about poisonous plants that look like common foods for the Associated Press.</p>
<p>She said the fruit that looked like a tomato appears to have been a Jerusalem cherry.</p>
<p>Often sold as a houseplant, all parts of the Jerusalem cherry are poisonous. The American Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals says the plant is not only harmful to humans but also to dogs, cats and horses.<strong> </strong>Eating large amounts can be deadly. Silverstone was lucky because she did not swallow the berries.</p>
<p>She is also lucky because the berries were reddish orange. This means they were <strong>ripe</strong>. While all parts of the Jerusalem cherry are poisonous, the plant's unripe berries can be especially dangerous. They can cause problems with the central nervous and gastrointestinal systems. <strong>Symptoms</strong> from eating the fruit include mental <strong>confusion</strong>, stomach pain, high body temperature, <strong>vomiting</strong>, <strong>paralysis</strong> and more.</p>
<p>The Jerusalem cherry is a member of the nightshade family. It is in the same family of plants that includes tomatoes, eggplants, peppers, potatoes and tomatillos. Although the fruits of those crops are safe to eat, their leaves are <strong>toxic</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Other toxic lookalikes</strong></p>
<p>The Jerusalem cherry is not the only toxic plant that looks like a safe one.</p>
<p>The poisonous Carolina horsenettle fruit also looks like a tomato. However, its common name is a <strong>dead giveaway</strong> that it is dangerous. It is called devil's tomato. It is also known as devil's potato to add to the confusion.</p>
<p>Other members of the nightshade family are poisonous in different ways. For example, a plant named deadly nightshade, or belladonna, is so toxic that it was used as a murder weapon in Europe during the Middle Ages, a time more than 500 years ago. Its berries, however, could be mistaken for blueberries.</p>
<p>Pokeweed and Virginia creeper fruits also look like blueberries, and both can be deadly if eaten.</p>
<p>Lilies are toxic, but they look like <strong>edible</strong> wild onion or garlic grasses, especially when they first come out of the ground.</p>
<p>Edible wild onion and garlic grasses have other toxic lookalikes, too -- including a plant sometimes called death camas. These plants grow in lawns and wild areas in the spring, and they are a common cause of livestock poisoning. They are dangerous for humans, too.</p>
<p>Toxic carrot and parsley lookalikes can also make you sick. Wild parsnip has flowers like a carrot and leaves like parsley. Simply touching it can cause a skin problem called photodermatitis. It causes sun sensitivity that can last for a year. Poison hemlock looks similar but is much larger. Eating that plant can lead to breathing problems.</p>
<p>Creeping buttercup looks like flat-leaf parsley. It is an <strong>invasive</strong> plant that can cause severe stomach pain, vomiting, diarrhea, and heart problems.</p>
<p>And the deadly Canadian moonseed can be <strong>confused </strong>with wild grape. However, its taste is so <strong>bitter</strong> that you would likely spit it out before swallowing it. This is a good thing because eating it can lead to death.</p>
<p>If you think you have swallowed a toxic plant by mistake, contact a poison control center in your area or your doctor. There is additional information on the website <a class="wsw__a" href="http://www.poison.org">poison.org</a>.</p>
<p>Damiano advises to use common sense with plants you find in the wild. If you are not completely sure that something is food, do not eat it.</p>
<p>And that's the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report. I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Jessica Damiano reported this story for The Associated Press from New York City. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><em>___________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>ripe</strong> <em>–adj. </em>fully developed; ready for harvest</p>
<p><strong>symptom<em> </em></strong><em>–n. </em>the sign that disease is present or that something is wrong with a person's health</p>
<p><strong>confusion </strong><em>–n. </em>being unable to think clearly : <strong>confuse </strong><em>-v.</em></p>
<p><strong>vomiting </strong><em>–n. </em>the condition of expelling what is in your stomach through your mouth<strong> : vomit </strong><em>-v.</em></p>
<p><strong>paralysis </strong><em>–n. </em>the loss of the ability to move one's muscles</p>
<p><strong>toxic </strong><em>–adj.</em> poisonous</p>
<p><strong>dead giveaway </strong>–idiom a fact or detail that makes the true nature of something impossible to ignore</p>
<p><strong>edible </strong><em>–adj. </em>fit and safe to be eaten</p>
<p><strong>invasive </strong><em>–adj. </em>tending to spread especially in a quick or aggressive manner: such as</p>
<p><strong>bitter </strong><em>–adj.</em> one of the major tastes that people have which is very unpleasant to most people</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Japan Celebrates Historic Emmy Award Wins for 'Shogun' (2024/9/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/japan-celebrates-historic-emmy-award-wins-for-shogun.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By VOA<br/>
<span class="datetime">16 September, 2024</span><br/>
</span>
<p>Japan is celebrating the record-breaking Emmy Award wins of the American television series <em>Shogun</em>. Many Japanese, however, say they have not watched the series.</p>
<p><em>Shogun </em>is<em> </em>a historical <strong>fiction</strong> that explores the country's warring <strong>dynasties</strong> in the <strong>feudal</strong> period. It crushed all-time records at the television awards ceremony on Sunday in Los Angeles, California. The series won 18 Emmys in all. And it became the first non-English-language winner of the highly sought award for best <strong>drama</strong> series.</p>
<p>Lead actor Hiroyuki Sanada, who played Lord Toranaga, became the first Japanese man to win an Emmy for acting. Anna Sawai became the first woman of Asian ancestry to win an Emmy for acting. She played Lady Mariko.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="Some of the cast and crew of 'Shogun,' winner of the Emmy for Outstanding Drama Series pose in the press room during the 76th Emmy Awards in Los Angeles, California, on September 15, 2024. (Photo by Robyn Beck/AFP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/74636940-18ed-49a9-884d-7b10be9781b1_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">Some of the cast and crew of 'Shogun,' winner of the Emmy for Outstanding Drama Series pose in the press room during the 76th Emmy Awards in Los Angeles, California, on September 15, 2024. (Photo by Robyn Beck/AFP)</span></div>
<p>"As a Japanese, I'm happy Sanada won," Kiyoko Kanda, a 70-year-old retiree, told the news group Agence France-Presse in Tokyo. "He worked so hard since he moved to Los Angeles," she said. But she admitted that she has only watched the show's <strong>trailer</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>'Groundbreaking' realism key to ‘Shogun' success</strong></p>
<p><em>Shogun</em> is available only on Disney's streaming platform, which is relatively new in Japan.</p>
<p>"I want to watch it. I'm curious to know how Japan is <strong>portrayed</strong>," Kanda said.</p>
<p>Otsuka, who chose not to give her first name, said she, too, has not watched the show. "But I saw the news and I'm happy he won."</p>
<p>The 63-year-old Sanada began acting at the age of five in Tokyo. He moved to Los Angeles after appearing in <em>Last Samurai</em> in 2003.</p>
<p>Yusuke Takizawa, age 41, also saw only the trailer for <em>Shogun</em>. But he said he could tell the show was a high-quality production.</p>
<p>"I was impressed by the high-spirited acting, the attention to detail and the film technology," Takizawa told AFP outside Osaka Castle, a major historical site where some of the story is set.</p>
<p>"I think many young people will want to try their hand in Hollywood after watching Sanada," he said.</p>
<p><strong>From page to film, again...</strong></p>
<p>Shogun was adapted from a popular 1975 book of the same name by writer James Clavell. The series, filmed in Canada, tells the story of Lord Toranaga, who fights for his life against his enemies alongside Mariko and British sailor John Blackthorne.</p>
<p>A first television production of Shogun came out in 1980 and centered on Blackthorne.</p>
<p>The new <em>Shogun</em> is not. It also breaks away from years of prejudiced representations of Japan in Western entertainment media. Notably, the 2024 production is mostly in Japanese, not English.</p>
<p>Sanada, who also co-produced the series, is credited with bringing a new level of cultural and historical understanding to <em>Shogun</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p>_____________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>fiction</strong><em>– n.</em> something invented by the imagination</p>
<p><strong>dynasty</strong> <em>– n. </em>a powerful group or family that maintains its position for a considerable time</p>
<p><strong>feudal </strong><em>– adj.</em> of, or relating to, the system of political organization prevailing in Europe from the 9th to about the 15th centuries having as its basis the relation of lord to vassal</p>
<p><strong>drama </strong><em>– n.</em> a movie or television production with characteristics (such as conflict) of a serious play</p>
<p><strong>trailer </strong><em>– n.</em> a chosen group of scenes that are shown to advertise a movie</p>
<p><strong>portray </strong><em>– v. </em>to play the role of</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>The Debate: Will AI Take Away Many Human Jobs? (2024/9/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/the-debate-will-ai-take-away-many-human-jobs.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>ChatGPT and other <strong>generative AI</strong> tools have raised concerns that<strong> chatbots</strong> will replace many kinds of workers. Writers, <strong>editors</strong>, and <strong>customer </strong>service representatives are among the jobs that could be affected.</p>
<p>But some people are suggesting that AI might not reduce jobs as many people fear. Instead, the technology might turn out to be more like the technological developments of the past, such as the steam engine, electricity or the internet.</p>
<p>Supporters reason that AI might destroy some jobs while creating others. They also say that the technology will probably make workers more productive, <strong>benefiting</strong> themselves, their employers and the economy.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Customer Experience Representatives Stanley Solis, center, and other representatives take calls at an Alorica center, Monday, Aug. 19, 2024, in San Antonio. (AP Photo/Eric Gay)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/18d6a3ea-2fc1-49ed-b3be-f62d22e81241_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Customer Experience Representatives Stanley Solis, center, and other representatives take calls at an Alorica center, Monday, Aug. 19, 2024, in San Antonio. (AP Photo/Eric Gay)</span></div>
<p><strong>Looking for lessons from history </strong></p>
<p>Nick Bunker is an economist at the Indeed Hiring Lab, part of a job search website. He said he thinks AI “will affect many, many jobs — maybe every job indirectly” to some degree.</p>
<p>Bunker added that he does not believe the technology is going to lead to a lot of unemployment. “We have seen other big technological events in our history, and those didn't lead to a large rise in unemployment. Technology destroys but also creates. There will be new jobs that come about,” he said.</p>
<p>Artificial intelligence gives machines the ability to perform tasks once thought to require human intelligence. The basic technology has existed in early versions for many years.</p>
<p>Some reports say it began with a problem-solving computer program called Logic Theorist. The program was developed in the 1950s at what is now Carnegie Mellon University in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. More recent examples include voice assistants like Apple's Siri, Amazon's Alexa, or IBM's chess-playing computer, Deep Blue, which defeated then-world champion Garry Kasparov in 1997.</p>
<p><strong>Predictions and current evidence </strong></p>
<p>Sam Altman is the chief of OpenAI, the creator of ChatGPT. Altman said in a discussion at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) in May that he believes, “AI is going to eliminate a lot of current jobs, and this is going to change the way that a lot of current jobs function.''</p>
<p>Some people say that AI chatbots are not replacing human workers in a widespread way. Challenger, Gray &amp; Christmas, a company that tracks job cuts, said it has yet to see much evidence of job losses caused by AI.</p>
<p>However, the fear that AI is a threat to some kinds of jobs has a basis in reality.</p>
<p>Suumit Shah is an Indian business owner who announced last year that he had replaced 90 percent of his customer support workers with a chatbot named Lina. Shah's company, Dukaan, helps customers set up e-commerce sites to sell goods online. Shah said the average amount of time it took to answer a customer's question shrank from 1 minute, 44 seconds to “instant.” The chatbot also cut the time needed to resolve problems from more than two hours to just over three minutes.</p>
<p>A 2023 study by researchers at Princeton University, the University of Pennsylvania and New York University identified jobs most exposed to AI models. The jobs included telemarketers and teachers of English and foreign languages. But being affected by AI does not necessarily mean losing your job to it. AI can free people to do more creative jobs.</p>
<p>The Swedish company IKEA introduced a customer-service chatbot in 2021 to deal with simple questions. Instead of cutting jobs, IKEA kept 8,500 customer-service workers to advise buyers on interior design and to deal with complex customer calls.</p>
<p>Chatbots can also make workers more efficient. Erik Brynjolfsson of Stanford University, Danielle Li and Lindsey Raymond of MIT studied 5,200 customer-support agents at a large company. The agents used a generative AI-based assistant. The AI tool provided valuable suggestions. It also supplied links to useful company documents.</p>
<p>The researchers found that those who used the chatbot were 14 percent more productive than workers who did not use the chatbot. The workers who used AI took more calls and completed them faster. The biggest productivity gains — 34 percent — came from the least-experienced, least-skilled workers.</p>
<p>Alorica is a company in Irvine, California, that runs customer-service centers around the world. The company has introduced an artificial intelligence translation tool that lets its representatives communicate with customers who speak any of 200 different languages and 75 dialects.</p>
<p>The Real-time Voice Language Translation tool also lets customers and Alorica agents speak and hear each other in their own languages.</p>
<p>“It allows (Alorica reps) to handle every call they get,” said Rene Paiz, a vice president of customer service. Paiz added, “I don't have to hire externally' just to find someone who speaks a specific language.</p>
<p>Alorica said it is not cutting jobs. It continues to seek new employees who are comfortable with new technology.</p>
<p>“We are still actively hiring,'' Paiz says. “We have a lot that needs to be done out there.''</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p>And I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>Paul Wiseman reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>generative AI</strong> <em>– n. </em>artificial intelligence that is capable of generating new material (such as images or writing)</p>
<p><strong>chatbot </strong><em>– n.</em> a program that is designed to carry out a discussion with human beings</p>
<p><strong>editor</strong><em> –n.</em> a person who prepares writing, so it is ready for publication</p>
<p><strong>customer</strong> <em>–n.</em> a person or group that pays for goods or services</p>
<p><strong>benefit </strong><em>– v.</em> to produce good or helpful results or effects</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>NASA Rocket Confirms Existence of Earth’s Hidden Electric Field (2024/9/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/nasa-rocket-confirms-existence-of-earth-s-hidden-electric-field.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">15 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The American space agency NASA says it has confirmed the long-suspected existence of an electric field that surrounds Earth.</p>
<p>A rocket named Endurance gathered the information that led to the confirmation. Endurance launched from Norway on May 11, 2022. The launch site was the closest possible to the North Pole.</p>
<p>Endurance reached a top altitude of 768 kilometers. The rocket captured data on the electric field during its 19-minute flight before splashing down in the sea, off the coast of Greenland.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image shows the Endurance rocket lifting off from the Ny-&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/i&gt;197;lesund launch center in Svalbard, Norway, on May 11, 2022. (Image Credit: NASA/Brian Bonsteel)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e91e0609-0df5-4026-9c15-4f49dab23ce3_cx2_cy13_cw95_w268_r1.png"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">This image shows the Endurance rocket lifting off from the Ny-<i>&amp;#</i>197;lesund launch center in Svalbard, Norway, on May 11, 2022. (Image Credit: NASA/Brian Bonsteel)</span></div>
<p>NASA says that since the 1960s, spacecraft flying over Earth's <strong>poles</strong> have recorded collections of particles flowing from the planet's atmosphere into space. But the cause of these outflows long remained a mystery. Scientists lacked the technology and tools to confirm an electric field and further explore it.</p>
<p>But the development in recent years of new observation methods and instruments led NASA to plan the Endurance mission. So the agency built the rocket and a new data instrument and planned the launch.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p>NASA scientist Glyn Collinson, an expert in space instrument design, led the Endurance mission.</p>
<p>Collinson <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UCM1MaYC5lM&amp;t=29s">explains</a> in a video that scientists believe the electric field they searched for was one of three energy fields affecting Earth. The others are gravitational and magnetic. Scientists are calling the third energy field the “ambipolar electric field.”</p>
<p>A NASA statement <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/science-research/heliophysics/nasa-discovers-long-sought-global-electric-field-on-earth/#h-launching-a-rocket-from-the-arctic">says</a> scientists believe the ambipolar field is an influential driver of the “polar wind.” They described the wind as “a steady outflow of charged particles into space that occurs above Earth's poles.” Scientists believe the ambipolar electric field <strong>counteracts</strong> some of the effects of gravity.</p>
<p>This electric field lifts the charged particles in Earth's upper atmosphere “to greater heights than they would otherwise reach,” NASA said. Scientists had theorized this electric field began at around 250 kilometers high. This is where atoms in our atmosphere break apart into negatively charged electrons and positively charged ions. This activity helps form a part of Earth's atmosphere known as the ionosphere.</p>
<p>NASA noted the Endurance mission permitted researchers to successfully identify and measure “a planet-wide electric field thought to be as <strong>fundamental</strong> to Earth as its gravity and magnetic fields.” A <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07480-3.epdf?sharing_token=I_iijIlqb3HMon5ISI-xBdRgN0jAjWel9jnR3ZoTv0Nyrlc02oJzExWUuDgAFVXFWQm-5tl5ZQFVbDbaRGPu8BS5_R9K9Au1gs-SKWxRrjMbJ2eV5VK-jFk3v5NbIHray3_BN5_uObULF-IXEID0EETe47O4K1uAgQiM7aC8d4E%3D">study</a> describing the team's results recently appeared in the publication <em>Nature</em>.</p>
<p>NASA said studying the ambipolar electric field is important because it “may have shaped our planet's <strong>evolution</strong> in ways yet to be explored.” In addition, the agency said further study of this field can help scientists better understand other planets and possibly find ones with conditions that may support life.</p>
<p>Leader Collinson said that, during the mission, the instrument on the rocket was able to measure an electrical voltage of 0.55 volts. He said this level is very low, about the same voltage used to power a watch <strong>battery</strong>. But, he noted that 0.55 volts was “just the right amount” to explain the outflows of particles driving the polar wind.</p>
<p>Collinson said he finds the results “incredibly important” because the newly confirmed electric field can counter the effects of gravity and “basically lifts the skies up.” He described the field as a kind of “<strong>conveyor belt</strong> that's lifting this atmosphere up into space.”</p>
<p>Alex Glocer is a project scientist for the Endurance mission and was a co-writer of the study. He said he agrees with those findings. “That's more than enough to counter gravity – in fact, it's enough to launch them upwards into space at supersonic speeds,” Glocer said. Supersonic describes speeds that are greater than the speed of sound.</p>
<p>The team said the study results suggest the ambipolar electric field also greatly increases the density of the ionosphere at higher atmospheric positions.</p>
<p>Collinson said, “Any planet with an atmosphere should have an ambipolar field. Now that we've finally measured it, we can begin learning how it's shaped our planet as well as others over time.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from NASA. </em></p>
<p><strong>______________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>pole </strong><em>– n.</em> either part of an axis of a sphere and especially of Earth's axis</p>
<p><strong>counteract </strong><em>– v. </em>the reduce a bad effect of something else</p>
<p><strong>fundamental</strong> <em>– adj. </em>relating to the most important or main part of something</p>
<p><strong>evolution </strong><em>– n.</em> a gradual process of change and development</p>
<p><strong>battery </strong><em>– n.</em> an object that provides electricity for things such as radios, toys, cars, etc.</p>
<p><strong>conveyor belt </strong><em>– n.</em> a continuous moving piece of rubber or metal that is used to transport objects from one place to another</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Brazilian Dog Excels at Footvolley (2024/9/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/brazilian-dog-excels-at-footvolley.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The Brazilian sport of footvolley is a popular activity on sunny days along Rio de Janeiro's coast. But, recently, people stopped to watch one especially exceptional player: a three-year-old named Floki. But the young player is not a child. Floki is a dog.</p>
<p>He is also very good at footvolley.</p>
<p>The rules of footvolley are almost the same as <strong>beach</strong> volleyball. However, the game requires a lower <strong>net</strong> and a soccer ball replaces the volleyball. Similar to soccer, the rules bar players from using their hands on the ball.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="The border collie named Floki plays footvolley, a combination of soccer and volleyball, on Leblon beach in Rio de Janeiro, Sunday, Sept. 8, 2024. (AP Photo/Bruna Prado)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/88b6f09c-68d1-4e0b-a6e8-1ab7456b930e_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">The border collie named Floki plays footvolley, a combination of soccer and volleyball, on Leblon beach in Rio de Janeiro, Sunday, Sept. 8, 2024. (AP Photo/Bruna Prado)</span></div>
<p>Not a problem for the four-legged Floki. He jumps up and hits the ball with his mouth.</p>
<p>Floki has become popular on social media in Brazil, with hundreds of thousands of followers on services such as Instagram and TikTok.</p>
<p>Floki's owner, Gustavo Rodrigues, is a footvolley trainer, or coach.</p>
<p>Floki entered Rodrigues' life as a <strong>puppy</strong> and demonstrated his sporty qualities early on. At just 2 months old, he started playing with small balloons. He would jump in the air to reach them.</p>
<p>Rodrigues started Floki out on an exercise called “altinha.” It involves a group standing in a circle and passing a soccer ball through the air for as long as possible.</p>
<p>In 2023, Floki started playing the complex, competitive game of footvolley.</p>
<p>Footvolley players need skills such as <strong>agility </strong>and timing. Just two people must cover an entire half court. This requires quick and surefooted moves on soft sand under the hot sun.</p>
<p>Floki was a natural. A star was born.</p>
<p>Rodrigues, age 26, said about Floki, “He does things that even some professionals don't — like positioning on the court."</p>
<p>Rodrigues added that, during play, Floki always “turns toward the ball to always hit it straight on.”</p>
<p>It is clear this high-energy dog lives for this game. Even when resting on the beach, Floki was paying careful attention to a nearby footvolley competition.</p>
<p>When playing, he makes dog sounds to communicate with Rodrigues. Floki barks to let his human teammate know he is open for a pass. The dog appears to understand the basic rules of the game.</p>
<p>Sometimes, he surprises the other team with an unexpected drive of the ball over the net. He scores a point and then he jumps into Rodrigues' arms to celebrate.</p>
<p>One of the watchers on a recent Sunday was Luiza Chioli, who had traveled to Rio from Sao Paulo. She already knew the famous Floki from TikTok. She said she was surprised that the real dog was as good at footvolley as the videos had suggested.</p>
<p>“Seeing social media, we had thought it was just cuts, that they used the best takes,” said Chioli, 21. “But we saw he played, performed the whole time, did really well. It's really cool.”</p>
<p>Proposals for partnerships and business deals with Rodrigues and Floki followed the dog's growing stardom. The two live in the capital Brasilia. However, they often travel to Rio and other Brazilian states for games, marketing appearances and social media work.</p>
<p>I'm Ashely Thompson.</p>
<p><em>David Biller reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>__________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>beach</strong> <em>-- n.</em> a seashore area</p>
<p><strong>net </strong><em>-- n.</em><strong> </strong>an open-meshed fabric woven together at regular intervals</p>
<p><strong>puppy</strong> <em>-- n.</em> a young dog</p>
<p><strong>agility </strong><em>– n.</em> the ability to move with quick easy grace</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>In Greece, Village Appears when Lake Dries Up (2024/9/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/in-greece-village-appears-when-lake-dries-up.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">14 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A sunken Greek village has begun to reappear after water levels dropped in the lake that covered it. Extreme hot, dry weather is blamed for the disappearing Lake Mornos.</p>
<p>The village of Kallio was flooded in 1980 to create the lake. The plan aimed to help supply the ever-increasing water demands of the national capital about 200 kilometers away. Now, long stretches of dried soil mixed with old bricks surround the ruins of the Kallio.</p>
<p>"Day by day, the water goes down," said Dimitris Giannopoulos, mayor of central Greece's Dorida area. Reuters news agency reports Lake Mornos supplies water to nearly half of Greece's population.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="The images shows the reappearing remains of buildings of the village of Kallio, which was intentionally flooded in 1980 to create a reservoir to supply water needs of Greek's capital Athens on September 3, 2024.(REUTERS/Stelios Misinas)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/6d294fa1-1e3b-417d-b340-016ae150b792_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">The images shows the reappearing remains of buildings of the village of Kallio, which was intentionally flooded in 1980 to create a reservoir to supply water needs of Greek's capital Athens on September 3, 2024.(REUTERS/Stelios Misinas)</span></div>
<p>Last winter brought little snow to Greece. This summer brought heatwaves but little rain to the country. Last winter was Greece's warmest on record.</p>
<p>Greece's dry climate makes it especially <strong>susceptible</strong> to the effects of a warming planet. The conditions worsened summer wildfires including some that reached outer areas of Athens last month. Scientists say extreme weather is now driving the dropping lake level.</p>
<p>"It is an <strong>alarm bell</strong>," said Efthymis Lekkas, a professor of disaster management at the University of Athens. "We don't know what will happen in the coming period. If we have a rainless winter, things will get difficult."</p>
<p>Giannopoulos noted that the Mount Giona mountain that rises up from the lake used to be snow-covered. But it saw none last winter. Around the lake, some trees have taken on a yellowish color. "They lack water. This has never happened before," Giannopoulos said.</p>
<p>Wells in the area are now drying up, he added. And surrounding villages – which do not take water from the lake – suffered water cuts this summer. A local firefighter chief said the risk of wildfires increases as the forests become drier.</p>
<p>Satellite images suggest the lake's surface area shrank from around 16.8 square kilometers in August 2022 to just 12 this year.</p>
<p>In addition, water supplies at three other water bodies dropped to 700 million cubic meters in August. This water supplies Attica, an area of around 4 million people that includes Athens. That was down from 1.2 billion cubic meters in 2022, the country's environment ministry said.</p>
<p>The Greek government says the state-run Athens water company had begun supplying those areas with additional sources of water. Former residents of Kallio were surprised to see the village again. But some said they were saddened by its current state.</p>
<p>"I used to see it full and say it was a beach. Now all you see is dryness," said 90-year-old Konstantinos Gerodimos.</p>
<p>His 77-year-old wife Maria added: "If it continues like this, the entire village will appear, all the way to the bottom, where the church and our home was."</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Reuters reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>susceptible</strong> <em>– adj. </em>easily influenced or harmed by something</p>
<p><strong>alarm</strong> <em>– n. </em>a loud noise or a public announcement that warns of danger</p>
<p><strong>bell </strong><em>– </em><em>n. </em>a hollow, metal object, shaped like a cup, with a piece of metal inside that makes a ringing sound</p>
<p><strong>entire</strong> <em>– </em><em>n. </em>whole</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What Is Your 'North Star'? (2024/9/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/what-is-your-north-star.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">14 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>In life, there are times when we lose our way, both <strong>literally</strong> and <strong>figuratively</strong>.</p>
<p>We might get lost walking in the woods or sailing at sea. Those are examples of being literally lost. We could also lose our way while on our career path. That is an example of being figuratively lost.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A meteor streaks in the night sky during the annual Perseid meteor shower on the island of Lastovo, Croatia, Aug. 12, 2023. " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-5a50-08db9c1fa6ad_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A meteor streaks in the night sky during the annual Perseid meteor shower on the island of Lastovo, Croatia, Aug. 12, 2023. </span></div>
<p>If you are physically lost and do not have a <strong>compass,</strong> you could use the stars in the night sky to know which way to go, especially the North Star.</p>
<p>Experts at NASA, America's space agency, say this about the North Star: “If you're in the Northern Hemisphere, it can help you <strong>orient </strong>yourself and find your way, as it's located in the direction of true north (or geographic north, as opposed to <strong>magnetic</strong> north).</p>
<p>They add that the North Star is not the brightest star in the sky. But it is usually easy to see, even from cities.</p>
<p>The North Star can also help if you get lost figuratively.</p>
<p>As the world changes around you and grows more complex, you can look to your North Star to help guide you. Your North Star can keep you <strong>focused</strong> and <strong>on track</strong>. It reminds you of what is important.</p>
<p>Some people may say their North Star is their <u>guiding light</u>. It is something very important to them, and it keeps them on the right path.</p>
<p>Your North Star can also be your personal <strong>mission statement. </strong>It can include your <strong>principles</strong> and guiding beliefs. Your North Star can give your life meaning and direction.</p>
<p>For some people, their North Star may be a religion. For others, it might be a purpose, like teaching people to read. Or a North Star can be a mix of important things.</p>
<p>A similar term for North Star is your <u>moral compass</u>. Like the North Star, a moral compass points you in the right direction.</p>
<p>There is another term that is linked to the North Star. A lodestar is also a star which is used to find one's way. And it can also mean a person who serves as an <strong>inspiration</strong>, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_UQvhQCJt">model</a> or guide.</p>
<p>The Merriam Webster online dictionary explains that both meanings of “lodestar” date back to the 1300s. The English poet Geoffrey Chaucer used both meanings of the word in his poems. However, by the 1600s, the literal meaning fell out of common use. Today, we still use “lodestar” in a figurative way meaning something or someone who guides us.</p>
<p>During a difficult or important time, many things can act as your North Star or lodestar.</p>
<p>For example, when a woman went through a difficult <strong>divorce</strong>, her close friend was her lodestar and helped her through it.</p>
<p>Another example might be when a music teacher and musician moved to a new city. He did not know anyone. He felt lost and alone. So, music was his North Star. It kept him busy, provided him with employment, and later led to great friendships with other musicians.</p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>. Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>_______________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>literally </strong><em>–adv.</em> the actual definition of a word or how it is normally used</p>
<p><strong>figuratively </strong><em>–adv.</em> an imaginative use of words that is not direct or literal</p>
<p><strong>compass </strong><em>–n.</em> a device that, in its simplest form, points to one of the magnetic poles of Earth</p>
<p><strong>orient </strong><em>–v. </em>to put something in the right position related to other things</p>
<p><strong>magnetic </strong>–adj. having the qualities of magnetism</p>
<p><strong>focus </strong>–v. to place your energy and attention in one place</p>
<p><strong>on track </strong><em>–phrase</em> going as expected and in the right direction</p>
<p><strong>mission statement </strong><em>–n.</em> a statement of purpose in which a person or company says what the mean to do and what causes them to do it</p>
<p><strong>principle </strong><em>–n.</em> a moral rule or belief that helps you know what is right and what is wrong</p>
<p><strong>inspiration </strong><em>–n.</em> something that provides energy and ideas to carry out an action</p>
<p><strong>divorce </strong><em>–n. </em>the action or an instance of legally ending a marriage</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>James Earl Jones’ Darth Vader Voice Can Speak Anew with AI (2024/9/14)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/james-earl-jones-darth-vader-voice-can-speak-anew-with-ai.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">13 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>During his more than 60-year acting career, James Earl Jones' voice became a star of its own. Jones died this week at the age of 93.</p>
<p>One of Jones' career decisions continues to be an issue of debate: his permission to let artificial intelligence (AI) reproduce his performances as Darth Vader for new projects.</p>
<p>Skywalker Sound and Ukrainian software company Respeecher used AI to recreate Jones' Darth Vader for the 2022 show <em>Obi-Wan Kenobi</em>. The show appears on the streaming service Disney+.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - James Earl Jones arrives at the Tony Awards on June 12, 2016, in New York. (Photo by Charles Sykes/Invision/AP, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f95e2016-256a-445b-b22b-71f5b0b20bd7_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - James Earl Jones arrives at the Tony Awards on June 12, 2016, in New York. (Photo by Charles Sykes/Invision/AP, File)</span></div>
<p>The voice of actor Mark Hamill was also “de-aged” using Respeecher. Hamill played Luke Skywalker in the first <em>Star Wars</em> movie. His AI-manufactured voice was used in the series' television show <em>The Mandalorian</em>. Disney+ launched the show in 2019.</p>
<p>Voice actors say they fear AI could reduce the number of jobs because the technology can reproduce one performance into many. The concern led American unionized video game performers to go on strike in July.</p>
<p>For some observers, Jones' decision to permit AI to reproduce his voice raises questions about voice acting as an art. But the decision also could help develop AI agreements that fairly pay actors for AI-based performances.</p>
<p>Zeke Alton is a voice actor and member of SAG-AFTRA's interactive media agreement negotiating committee. He said it is “amazing” that Jones was involved in the process of reproducing his voice.</p>
<p>“If the game companies, the movie companies, gave the <strong>consent</strong>, <strong>compensation transparency</strong> to every actor that they gave James Earl Jones, we wouldn't be on strike,” Alton said. “It proves that they can do it. They just don't want to for people that they feel don't have the <strong>leverage</strong> to <strong>bargain</strong> for themselves.”</p>
<p>Hollywood's video game performers called for a strike after more than 18 months of negotiations over a new interactive media agreement with industry leaders. The negotiators could not reach an agreement on artificial intelligence protections.</p>
<p>Members of the union have said they are not opposed to AI. They say they are worried, however, that technology could replace them.</p>
<p>Concerns over such use of AI were among the reasons that film and television workers went on strike last year. The work stoppages went on for four months.</p>
<p>Neither Skywalker Sound nor Respeecher answered a request for comment from Associated Press reporters. But a sound editor with Skywalker Sound spoke to <em>Vanity Fair </em>magazine about the issue. The worker reported that Jones approved the use of old recordings to keep Darth Vader alive. The worker added that Jones guided the new performances.</p>
<p>Jones' contract could set an example of <strong>properly</strong> bargaining with an actor over their likeness, said Sarah Elmaleh. She is chair of SAG-AFTRA's interactive negotiating committee. Elmaleh, a voice actor, said there is a chance for these tools to be used in “meaningful, smart artistic decisions.”</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Caty Weaver adapted this story for VOA Learning English from reports by the Associated Press and Reuters. </em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>consent </strong>- <em>n. </em>approval of what is done or suggested</p>
<p><strong>compensation </strong>- <em>n. </em>payment in the form of salary or wages</p>
<p><strong>transparency </strong>- <em>n. </em><strong> </strong>the quality or state of being transparent</p>
<p><strong>leverage </strong>- <em>n. </em>power, effectiveness</p>
<p><strong>bargain </strong>- <em>v. </em>to negotiate over the terms of a purchase, agreement, or contract</p>
<p><strong>properly </strong>- ad<em>v. </em>in an acceptable or suitable way</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Perhaps and Maybe (2024/9/14)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/perhaps-and-maybe.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">13 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Renata in Brazil about the usage of the words “perhaps” and “maybe.”</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/3c866149-fa04-4f35-8778-206251032463_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>I'm trying to learn English, but from now I [have] a question about what's the difference between "perhaps" and "maybe".</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>Thank you for writing to us, Renata. I'm happy to answer this question.</p>
<p>The two words mean the same thing. We use them to express the idea that we are guessing or unsure about something. However, there are some differences in how we use the two words.</p>
<p>Language researchers use the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://nam10.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.english-corpora.org%2Fcoca%2F&amp;data=05%7C02%7CAndrewSmith%4021voa.com%7C749494b552994caa362908dcbcaf0592%7Cba99e87c673541c2b1c1354eee3a8659%7C0%7C0%7C638592707116585301%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=16C39dnI2Wx52MxTMBgizzwHDhiORhP4RHKn8Zsskn8%3D&amp;reserved=0" title="https://nam10.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.english-corpora.org%2Fcoca%2F&amp;data=05%7C02%7CAndrewSmith%4021voa.com%7C749494b552994caa362908dcbcaf0592%7Cba99e87c673541c2b1c1354eee3a8659%7C0%7C0%7C638592707116585301%7CUnknown%7CTWF">Corpus of Contemporary American English</a> to study the usage of words. They have found that speakers of American English use “maybe” more than twice as often as the word “perhaps.” The Corpus contains over one billion words collected from American print, video, and audio media.</p>
<p>Here is an example of the use of “maybe:”</p>
<p><em>A: Are you going to the beach this weekend?</em></p>
<p><em>B: Maybe—but I need to check the weather first. </em></p>
<p>In this situation, if a speaker used the word “perhaps” instead of “maybe,” it might sound too formal, or serious, in American English.</p>
<p>However, in written English, we often use the word “perhaps” instead of “maybe.” You can find many examples of both of these words in stories on our website at <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/">www.21voa.com</a>.</p>
<p>In writing, we can use <strong>commas</strong> to place the word “perhaps” between <strong>phrases</strong> or <strong>clauses</strong> in a sentence. Consider this example:</p>
<p><em>It is easy, perhaps, to train a young dog to obey its owner. But training an older dog might not be so easy. </em></p>
<p>Note that if we put the word “maybe” in place of “perhaps” in this writing example, it might not seem like good writing to a native speaker.</p>
<p>Sometimes a writer will choose to use the word “maybe” instead of “perhaps” to communicate a particular feeling. Consider the following example:</p>
<p><em>Government officials say the new trade deal will help the economies of both countries. Maybe. Such predictions have often been wrong in the past. </em></p>
<p>Here, by using the word “maybe,” the writer communicates more strongly a feeling that the government officials might be wrong.</p>
<p>Finally, be careful not to confuse the <strong>adverb</strong> “maybe” with the verb phrase “may be.” You can learn more about this by reading the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/maybe-and-may-be-are-driving-me-crazy-/4807820.html"><em>Ask a Teacher</em> program called “Maybe and May Be Are ‘Driving Me Crazy.'"</a></p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, do you have a question about American English? Perhaps you would like to know how American English has changed over the years. Or maybe you just need to know how to use particular words. Whatever your question may be, send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>comma</strong><strong> </strong>–n. a punctuation mark that often separates clauses, phrases, or words in a series</p>
<p><strong>phrase</strong> <em>–n. </em>a group of words that express an idea but do not form a complete sentence</p>
<p><strong>clause</strong> <em>–n.</em> a group of words expressing an idea that can, on their own, form a sentence</p>
<p><strong>adverb</strong><strong> </strong>–n. a word that modifies a word expressing action, time, place, manner or degree</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Why Is Helium Causing Problems with Spacecraft? (2024/9/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/why-is-helium-causing-problems-with-spacecraft.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Helium leaks have been a major problem for spacecraft and rockets.</p>
<p>Recent reports about Boeing's Starliner and SpaceX's Polaris Dawn mission have involved problems controlling helium. Recently, the Starliner had a helium leak in a <strong>propulsion</strong> system. Polaris Dawn also had helium issues on its ground equipment.</p>
<p>Helium leaks have affected past <strong>missions </strong>including the Indian Space Research Organization's Chandrayaan 2 and the European Space Agency's Ariane 5.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - In this image provided by the European Space Agency, Europe's new rocket Ariane 6 launches from Kourou, French Guiana, Tuesday, July 9, 2024. (Stephane Corvaja/European Space Agency via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/fe8f7d36-a8ef-4238-bfbd-77db50ecfd76_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - In this image provided by the European Space Agency, Europe's new rocket Ariane 6 launches from Kourou, French Guiana, Tuesday, July 9, 2024. (Stephane Corvaja/European Space Agency via AP)</span></div>
<p>Recently, Reuters news agency explored why spacecraft and rockets use helium, and why it can cause problems:</p>
<p><strong>Why is helium used on spacecraft? </strong></p>
<p>Helium is inert, meaning it does not chemically react with other substances. It also does not burn. Helium's atomic number is 2, making it the second lightest element after hydrogen.</p>
<p>Rockets need to reach exact speeds and <strong>altitudes</strong> to maintain their orbits. Heavier rockets need more energy to fly and use more fuel. They also require more powerful engines, which are costlier to develop, test, and maintain.</p>
<p>Helium has an extremely low boiling point of -268.9 degrees Celsius. This means that it remains a gas even in extremely cold environments like space. That is an important quality because many rocket fuels are stored at low temperatures.</p>
<p>Helium is not<strong> toxic</strong>. But it cannot be breathed on its own because it displaces oxygen. Humans need oxygen to live.</p>
<p><strong>How is helium used in rockets? </strong></p>
<p>Because of its special qualities, helium is used to pressurize fuel tanks. It helps ensure fuel flows to the rocket's engines without stopping. Helium is also used for cooling systems.</p>
<p>As fuel and oxidizer are burned in the rocket's engines, helium fills the resulting empty space in the tanks, maintaining the correct pressure inside.</p>
<p>Because it is non-reactive, it can safely mix with other contents in the tanks.</p>
<p><strong>Is helium more likely to leak? </strong></p>
<p>Helium's small atomic size and low molecular weight mean its atoms can escape through small spaces or seals in storage tanks and fuel systems.</p>
<p>However, because there is very little helium in the Earth's atmosphere, leaks can be easily <strong>detected</strong>. This makes the gas important for identifying possible problems in a rocket or spacecraft's fuel systems.</p>
<p>In May, hours before Boeing's Starliner spacecraft made its first attempt to launch an astronaut crew, sensors inside the spacecraft detected a small helium leak. The American space agency NASA spent several days studying the leak before deciding it was low risk.</p>
<p>Additional leaks were detected in space after Starliner launched in June. Such discoveries played a part in NASA's decision to bring Starliner back to Earth without its crew.</p>
<p>As a result, two NASA astronauts who flew to the International Space Station aboard a Starliner capsule will need to return to Earth on a SpaceX vehicle early next year.</p>
<p>The <strong>frequency </strong>of helium leaks across space-related systems, some engineers say, has shown an industry-wide need for <strong>innovation</strong>. Innovation is needed in the design of valves and the mechanisms that tighten them. A valve is a mechanical device that controls the flow of a gas or fluid.</p>
<p><strong>Can another gas be used? </strong></p>
<p>Some rocket scientists have experimented with gases such as argon and nitrogen, which are also inert and can sometimes be less costly. Helium, however, is much more common in the space industry.</p>
<p>In Europe's new Ariane 6 rocket, designers replaced the helium that was used in the rocket's <strong>predecessor</strong> Ariane 5. The Ariane 6 has a new pressurization system. The new system changes a small amount of liquid oxygen and hydrogen <strong>propellants </strong>to gas, which then pressurizes those fluids for the rocket engine.</p>
<p>That system failed in space, however, during the final part of Ariane 6's otherwise successful launch in July. The failure of the new system added to the international rocket industry's list of pressurization difficulties.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Nivedita Bhattacharjee reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>__________</em>____________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>propulsion </strong><em>– n. </em>the act of driving forward or onward</p>
<p><strong>mission</strong><em> –n.</em> a flight by an aircraft or spacecraft which has a specific goal</p>
<p><strong>altitude </strong><em>– n.</em> the vertical elevation of an object above a surface (such as sea level or land)</p>
<p><strong>toxic </strong><em>– adj.</em> containing or being poisonous material</p>
<p><strong>detect</strong> <em>–v. </em>to discover or find</p>
<p><strong>frequency </strong><em>-- n.</em> the proportion or percentage of items in a particular category in a set of data</p>
<p><strong>innovation </strong>–<em> n.</em> the introduction of something new</p>
<p><strong>predecessor </strong><em>– n.</em> one that precedes or comes before</p>
<p><strong>propellant </strong><em>– n.</em> something that drives forward or onward</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US School Shooting Raises Questions about Classroom Phone Bans (2024/9/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/us-school-shooting-raises-questions-about-classroom-phone-bans.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A mass shooting at an American high school has raised questions about policies restricting cellphone use in classrooms.</p>
<p>The shooting took place September 4 at Apalachee High School in the southern state of Georgia. The suspect was identified as Colt Gray, a 14-year-old student at the school. The shooting left two students and two teachers dead. Nine others were injured.</p>
<p>During the shooting, some students at Apalachee High School used cellphones to call their parents to let them know what was happening. Others made calls to loved ones to leave messages they thought might end up being final goodbyes.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A family embraces during a vigil for the victims of the Apalachee High School shooting at Jug Tavern Park in Winder, Georgia, on September 4, 2024, after a shooting took place. (Photo by CHRISTIAN MONTERROSA / AFP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f8d70bc5-c5c3-4c7b-8f34-37124174fbb6_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A family embraces during a vigil for the victims of the Apalachee High School shooting at Jug Tavern Park in Winder, Georgia, on September 4, 2024, after a shooting took place. (Photo by CHRISTIAN MONTERROSA / AFP)</span></div>
<p>Some opponents of cellphone bans in schools have said such situations demonstrate a reason cellphones should not be completely banned from classrooms. They believe phone bans can cut off a possible lifeline for parents to make sure their children are safe during school shootings or other emergencies.</p>
<p>But supporters of such restrictions – including many teachers – say the rules are needed. They say cellphones can cause many <strong>distractions</strong> for students.</p>
<p>Keri Rodrigues is president of the National Parents Union, an education activist group. She said she understands that parents “are deeply concerned about whether or not they're going to get timely information” about their kids in emergency situations.</p>
<p>Rodrigues told The Associated Press (AP), “The fact of the matter is parents and families cannot <strong>rely</strong> on schools to effectively communicate with us in times of emergency, and this has happened time and again.”</p>
<p>Nationwide, 77 percent of U.S. schools say they currently ban cellphones for non-school-related work. That number comes from the National Center for Education Statistics. But experts say the number is misleading and does not necessarily mean students are following the bans or that all schools are effectively enforcing them.</p>
<p>In the southern state of Arkansas, Republican Governor Sarah Huckabee Sanders offered school districts a state-supported financial assistance program. It helps administrators buy containers to hold students' phones during the school day.</p>
<p>In California, Democratic Governor Gavin Newsom has urged school districts to restrict cellphone use. He is considering signing legislation that would require schools to enact restrictions.</p>
<p>Newsom recently told reporters, “I'd hate to see another school shooting be the reason that we bring TVs into the classroom and then disrupt our children's education.” He explained that permitting schoolchildren to have cellphones in school is almost like letting them watch television in class. Doing so, Newsom said, can “greatly <strong>disrupt</strong>” the learning process.</p>
<p>But opponents of phone bans say the device can be helpful for students facing dangerous situations at school. For example, some students caught in the Apalachee shooting were able to use their phones to contact loved ones during moments they feared could be their last.</p>
<p>One student, high school junior Julie Sandoval, told the AP she texted her mother from inside the school, “I love you. I love you so much...” In another message, she wrote, “I'm sorry I'm not the best daughter. I love you.”</p>
<p>Sandoval said she heard another student during the shooting speaking with her mother on the phone. She was heard saying, “They're shooting up the school! They're shooting up the school!”</p>
<p>But some supporters of phone restrictions warn that permitting students to use phones during shootings or other emergencies could put them in even more danger.</p>
<p>Kim Whitman is co-founder of the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://phonefreeschoolsmovement.org/">Phone-Free Schools Movement</a>. The group supports school policies to keep cellphones out of students' hands during class. “What's even more important to me is their safety,” Whitman said. She noted, for example, that a child on the phone with a loved one during a school emergency might miss important guidance from teachers or school officials. “That's a worse <strong>scenario</strong> in my mind,” Whitman added.</p>
<p>Students in other school shootings have used cellphones to inform school officials or parents about the incidents. During the 2022 school shooting in Uvalde, Texas – which killed 21 people – a fourth-grader called 911 to get help. And during a 2018 shooting at Florida's Marjory Stoneman Douglas High School, students used their phones to communicate with loved ones and shoot video of the shooting.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>distraction</strong> <em>– n. </em>something that makes you stop giving your attention to something else</p>
<p><strong>rely</strong> <em>– v. </em>to depend on</p>
<p><strong>disrupt </strong><em>– v.</em> to interrupt the normal course of something</p>
<p><strong>scenario </strong><em>– n.</em> a description of a situation, or of a situation that may develop in the future</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>You Really Should Learn Modals! (2024/9/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/you-really-should-learn-modals-everyday-gramamr.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Adam Brock</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>
For VOA Learning English, this is Everyday Grammar.</p>
<p>This week we are going to show you how to give advice using <strong>modal verbs</strong>. Modal verbs (called <em>modals</em> for short) are <strong>auxiliary verbs</strong> that express a speaker's <strong>attitude</strong> and the strength of that attitude.</p>
<p>For example, "He should visit Prague."</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-acda-08dbbaced82d_w100_r1.png"/></div>
<p>In this sentence, <em>should</em> is the modal verb, and<em> visit</em> is the main verb.</p>
<p>The simple form of a verb goes after a modal. Do not add the third person "s" to a verb after a modal. It would sound strange to say, "He should visits Prague" or, "He should to visit Prague." The correct way is, "He should visit Prague."</p>
<p>There are about 17 modals in English — grammar experts do not agree on an exact number. Today we will focus on three common modals used for giving advice: <em>should, ought to, </em>and<em> had better.</em></p>
<p><strong>Using <em>should</em></strong></p>
<p>Let's start with <em>should</em>. <em>Should</em> has multiple meanings. It can be used to express <strong>certainty</strong>, such as, "He should be here by 5 o'clock." <em>Should</em> can be a substitute for the <strong>conditional</strong> word <em>if</em>. You might hear someone say, "Should you need help, just ask me."</p>
<p>But more often, we use<em> should</em> to give suggestions and friendly advice, such as, "You should apply for that job," or "You should try that new restaurant."</p>
<p>The past form of the modal <em>should</em> is <em>should have</em> + the past participle. For example, "I should have brought my wallet." Notice that the main verb <em>brought</em> is in the <strong>past participle</strong> form.</p>
<p>Use <em>should have</em> to express regret, or a negative feeling about the past. Imagine you trusted someone and that person later cheated on you. You could say, "I should have known better than to trust him." The Beatles used the expression in a popular song.</p>
<p><em>I should have known better with a girl like you<br/>
That I would love everything that you do<br/>
And I do<br/>
Hey hey hey</em></p>
<p><strong>Using <em>ought to</em></strong></p>
<p>The next modal we will talk about is <em>ought to</em>. <em>Ought to</em> is another modal for giving advice. Sometimes <em>ought to</em> sounds more like "otta" as in this romantic song by Al Green.</p>
<p><em>Sit back down and talk to me<br/>
About how you want to be<br/>
You ought to be with me<br/>
Yeah you ought to be with me</em></p>
<p><em>Ought to</em> is similar in meaning to <em>should</em>, but it is not used as often. In modern American English, <em>ought to</em> is seldom used with the past tense or in the question form.</p>
<p><strong>Using <em>had better</em></strong></p>
<p>Let's move on to <em>had better</em>. <em>Had better </em>is stronger than <em>should </em>and <em>ought to</em>. <em>Had better</em> carries an indirect threat.</p>
<p>For example, if you said, "You had better finish the report," you are not making a polite suggestion. You are making an indirect threat.</p>
<p>In other words, if you don't finish the report, you are in trouble. Authority figures sometimes use <em>had better</em> when speaking to people below them. Parents also use this form often.</p>
<p>Listen to cartoon character Malory Archer. Malory is the head of a spy agency. People think she is <strong>arrogant </strong>and heartless. Listen to her tone when she uses <em>had better</em>.</p>
<p><em>Oh for — I'll send up some help.<br/>
And Missy, you had better watch it!</em></p>
<p>As you can hear, Malory is not making a polite suggestion. She is threatening someone in a lower position.</p>
<p><em>Had better</em> is not always impolite, it could express a sense of urgency as in, "Your plane is leaving! You <em>had better</em> run!" In other words, "If you don't run, you will miss your flight." <em>Had better</em> has no past tense or question form.</p>
<p><strong>Modals in rapid speech</strong></p>
<p><em>Should, ought to, </em>and<em> had better</em> can be difficult for English learners to hear. Native speakers often shorten these words in casual conversation. In rapid speech, modals seem to disappear because they are shortened and often fall on <strong>unstressed syllables</strong>.</p>
<p>We will read some examples for you. The first sentence will be in slow, careful speech. Then we will read it again in rapid, informal speech.</p>
<p><em>I should have been listening to what she had to say.<br/>
I shoulda been listenin' ta what she had t' say.</em></p>
<p><em>You ought to be ashamed of yourself.<br/>
You otta be ashamed of yourself.</em></p>
<p><em>You had better decide what you want to do.<br/>
You'd better decide whatcha wanna do.</em></p>
<p>That's all the advice we have for you today. There is much more to learn about modals. We will cover them in more detail in future episodes. Until then, you should practice modals with British punk band, The Clash.</p>
<p><em>Darling you've got to let me know<br/>
Should I stay or should I go?<br/>
If you say that you are mine<br/>
I'll be here till the end of time<br/>
So you've got to let me know<br/>
Should I stay or should I go?</em></p>
<p>I'm Pete Musto.</p>
<p>And I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Adam Brock wrote this lesson for Learning English. Jill Robbins was the editor.</em></p><div id="bottom">
<ins class="adsbygoogle" data-ad-client="ca-pub-3585518775245612" data-ad-format="auto" data-ad-slot="9284795419" data-full-width-responsive="true" style="display:block; text-align:center;"></ins>
<script>(adsbygoogle =window.adsbygoogle ||[]).push({});</script></div>
<p><em>Now it's your turn. Think of a friend whom you would like to give advice. Write to us in the Comments section. Write two sentences - using should, ought to, or had better - giving advice. We'll give you feedback.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>modal verb </strong>- a verb (such as <em>can, could, shall, should, ought to, will</em>, or <em>would</em>) that is usually used with another verb to express ideas such as possibility, necessity, and permission</p>
<p><strong>auxiliary verb</strong> - a verb (such as <em>have</em>, <em>be</em>, <em>may</em>, <em>do</em>, <em>shall</em>, <em>will</em>, <em>can</em>, or <em>must</em>) that is used with another verb to show the verb's tense, to form a question, etc.</p>
<p><strong>attitude</strong> – <em>n.</em> the way you think and feel about someone or something</p>
<p><strong>certainty</strong> – <em>n. </em>the state of being or feeling about how likely it is that something will happen</p>
<p><strong>conditional</strong> – <em>adj.</em> showing or used to show that something is true or happens only if something else is true or happens</p>
<p><strong>past participle</strong> - the form of the verb that is used with "have" in perfect tenses and with "be" in passive constructions</p>
<p><strong>arrogant</strong> – <em>adj.</em> having or showing the insulting attitude of people who believe that they are better, smarter, or more important than other people</p>
<p><strong>unstressed</strong> – <em>adj.</em> not having an accent</p>
<p><strong>syllable</strong> – <em>n.</em> any one of the parts into which a word is naturally divided when it is pronounced</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>World Produces 52 Million Metric Tons of Plastic Pollution Yearly (2024/9/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/world-produces-52-million-metric-tons-of-plastic-pollution-yearly.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">11 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The world creates about 52 million metric tons of plastic pollution every year, a new study says.</p>
<p>More than two-thirds of that plastic comes from the Global South – a term that loosely describes developing countries.</p>
<p>The amount of pollution is enough to fill New York City's Central Park with plastic waste as high as the Empire State Building, researchers at the University of Leeds in Britain say.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A man walks on a railway track littered with plastic and other waste materials on Earth Day in Mumbai, India, April 22, 2024. (AP Photo/Rafiq Maqbool, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e41552a7-912f-4c53-952c-8761a3211cfc_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">FILE - A man walks on a railway track littered with plastic and other waste materials on Earth Day in Mumbai, India, April 22, 2024. (AP Photo/Rafiq Maqbool, File)</span></div>
<p>They examined waste produced on the local level at more than 50,000 cities and towns across the world for a study released recently in the publication Nature.</p>
<p>The study examined plastic that goes into the open environment. It did not examine plastic that goes into <strong>landfills</strong> or is properly burned. For 15 percent of the world's population, government fails to collect and <strong>dispose of </strong>waste, the study said.</p>
<p>This lack of collection and disposal is a big reason Southeast Asia and Sub-Saharan Africa produce the most plastic waste.</p>
<p>Lagos, Nigeria, released the most plastic pollution of any city, said Costas Velis, the study's lead writer. The other biggest plastic-polluting cities are New Delhi in India, Luanda in Angola, Karachi in Pakistan, and Cairo, in Egypt.</p>
<p>India leads the world in producing plastic pollution, with more than 9.3 million metric tons a year. That number is far more than double the next big-polluting nations, Nigeria and Indonesia. China, often criticized for pollution, is in fourth place but is making big improvements in reducing waste, Velis said. Other top plastic polluters are Pakistan, Bangladesh, Russia and Brazil. The top eight nations are responsible for more than half of the world's plastic pollution, the study's data suggests.</p>
<p>The United States takes 90th place in plastic pollution with more than 47,600 metric tons. And Britain takes 135th place with nearly 4,600 metric tons, the study says.</p>
<p>In 2022, most of the world's nations agreed to make the first legally <strong>binding</strong> treaty on plastic pollution, including in the oceans. Final treaty negotiations take place in South Korea in November.</p>
<p>The study used artificial intelligence to research plastics that were improperly burned — about 57 percent of the pollution — or just <strong>dumped</strong>. In both cases, very small microplastics, or nanoplastics, are what change the issue from a marine life problem to a human health threat, Velis said.</p>
<p>Several studies this year have looked at how common microplastics are in our drinking water and in people's tissue, such as hearts, brains and testicles. Doctors and scientists are still not quite sure how microplastics threaten human health.</p>
<p>Velis called the spread of microplastics “everybody's problem” and one that will be an issue for future generations.</p>
<p>“We shouldn't put the blame, any blame, on the Global South,” Velis said. “And we shouldn't praise ourselves about what we do in the Global North in any way.”</p>
<p>The problem is a lack of resources and ability of government to provide the necessary services to citizens, Velis said.</p>
<p>Outside experts worried that the study's attention on pollution, rather than overall plastic production, means the plastic industry is not held responsible.</p>
<p>The <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.unep.org/interactives/beat-plastic-pollution/#:~:text=If%20historic%20growth%20trends%20continue,after%20a%20single%20short%20use." target="_blank">United Nations Environment Program estimates</a> that plastic production is likely to rise from about 400 million metric tons a year to more than 1.1 billion metric tons. And many scientists believe plastic production releases large amounts of greenhouse gas that contribute to climate change.</p>
<p>Neil Tangri is senior director of science and policy at GAIA, a group of international organizations working on waste and environmental programs.</p>
<p>Tangri said of the study's researchers, “These guys have defined plastic pollution in a much narrower way, as really just macroplastics that are <strong>emitted</strong> into the environment after the consumer, and it risks us losing our focus on the <strong>upstream</strong> and saying, hey now all we need to do is manage the waste better.”</p>
<p>Tangri added, “It's necessary but it's not the whole story.”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Seth Borenstein reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>landfill </strong><em>– n.</em> a system of trash and garbage disposal in which the waste is buried between layers of earth</p>
<p><strong>dispose of </strong><em>– v.</em> to get rid of</p>
<p><strong>bind </strong><em>-- v. </em>to put under an obligation</p>
<p><strong>dump</strong> <em>– v. </em>to get rid of something in a careless way</p>
<p><strong>emit</strong><em> -- v. </em>to give off or to throw out; to release</p>
<p><strong>focus </strong><em>– n. </em>a center of activity or attention</p>
<p><strong>upstream </strong>–<em> n.</em> in or to a position within the production stream closer to manufacturing processes</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Apple Launches New iPhone ‘Built for AI’ (2024/9/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/apple-launches-new-iphone-built-for-ai.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Apple has launched its latest device, the iPhone 16. The company said it designed the new phone with the latest artificial intelligence (AI) technology.</p>
<p>Apple announced four new iPhone 16 models during a launch event September 9 from its headquarters in Cupertino, California. It said the new models are equipped with special <strong>chips</strong> to support the increased power needed for AI operations.</p>
<p>Apple says the AI built into the devices is part of its newly developed Apple Intelligence technology. Apple leader Tim Cook spoke at the launch event. He said the new iPhone 16 models had been “designed for Apple Intelligence from the ground up.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="The new iPhone 16 is displayed during an announcement of new products at Apple headquarters Monday, Sept. 9, 2024, in Cupertino, Calif. (AP Photo/Juliana Yamada)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/8a8f513c-5f28-492a-9409-d321f4dd6c5e_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">The new iPhone 16 is displayed during an announcement of new products at Apple headquarters Monday, Sept. 9, 2024, in Cupertino, Calif. (AP Photo/Juliana Yamada)</span></div>
<p>Apple Intelligence is available to users of the new iPhone 16 models, as well as the 15 Pro and 15 Pro Max. Users must also be running iOS 18.1, which is expected to launch in October. Apple Intelligence can also be used with iPads and Macs.</p>
<p>The company <a class="wsw__a" href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/121115#:~:text=Apple%20Intelligence%20is%20the%20personal,you%2C%20while%20protecting%20your%20privacy.">describes the technology</a> as a “personal intelligence system” designed to help users “communicate, work, and express” themselves.</p>
<p>The new AI tools, or features, are designed to improve on past ones, including the company's 13-year-old Siri digital assistant. Company officials say they aim to get Siri to better understand requests and actions of the user.</p>
<p>One new feature of iPhone 16 models lets users search for pictures in their images collection by describing what an image looks like. AI tools can also help users create personal emojis and can organize and provide brief descriptions of emails. Other AI features include improved camera and video production <strong>functions</strong>.</p>
<p>The new iPhone models are also equipped with a new <strong>button</strong> that reacts to clicks and hand movements to make it easier and faster to set up shots, capture images and start video recording.</p>
<p>The company says the iPhone 16 models will be available for pre-order on September 13. But since the new AI tools require the iOS 18 update, users will have to wait until they receive that to use the features. Apple has said the iOS 18 release will roll out from October through December. American English will be the first available language, followed by more to be added next year.</p>
<p>The price for an iPhone 16 will start at just under $800. The top model will cost almost $1200.</p>
<p>Apple's push to include AI tools in its new devices is partly seen as a reaction to moves by competitors like Samsung and Google. Both of those companies have already offered users powerful new AI tools in their latest smartphone models.</p>
<p>In addition to the new AI features offered, Apple has also teamed up with ChatGPT developer OpenAI to give users the chance to use that company's technology for more complex operations. In June, Apple <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/apple-partners-with-openai-to-bring-ai-tools-to-ios-devices/7659640.html">announced</a> it was working with OpenAI to create a series of AI tools for iPhones and other personal devices.</p>
<p>Apple officials have noted that all users have the ability to turn off any AI tools they do not want. The company has long claimed it highly values personal privacy and says it has built tools into its operating systems to protect user data. Apple said it took the same steps to provide privacy protections for its new AI tools.</p>
<p>Besides announcing the new AI-equipped devices, Apple also introduced new models of its Apple Watch and AirPods headphones.</p>
<p>The Apple Watch Series 10 has a larger and brighter <strong>display</strong> that aims to improve views from any position. The changes to Apple Watch also include additional health features, such as a sleep <strong>monitor</strong> tool that aims to identify the disorder sleep apnea.</p>
<p>Apple says the new AirPods 4 come with an improved chip for better audio quality, as well as more active noise cancellation. The devices are also equipped with a tool to help users find lost AirPods. It plays a sound when Apple's Find Me app is used to find lost devices.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from Apple, The Associated Press and Reuters. </em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>chip</strong> <em>– n.</em> a small part of a computer that stores and helps process information</p>
<p><strong>function</strong> <em>– v. </em>to work or operate in a particular way</p>
<p><strong>button </strong><em>– v.</em> a switch that is pressed to control an operation or piece of equipment</p>
<p><strong>display </strong><em>– n.</em> an electronic device that shows information from a computer</p>
<p><strong>monitor </strong><em>– v.</em> to watch something carefully and record the results</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Turkey’s Homeless Dogs Find Families in Other Countries (2024/9/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/turkey-s-homeless-dogs-find-families-in-other-countries.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Ashley Thompson</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A law that recently passed in Turkey requires the country's four million <strong>stray</strong> dogs to be impounded, or put in animal shelters. The legislation aims to place all strays into city shelters by 2028.</p>
<p>Supporters of the law, which passed in July, say it aims to prevent dog attacks, road accidents, and the spread of rabies.</p>
<p>But critics say the law may lead to many dogs being euthanized, or killed. Animal lovers, activists and organizations are working to find homes for Turkey's street dogs, including homes overseas.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Deezi, a dog from a shelter in Istanbul, Turkey, walks with its new owners Caroline and Meike in Haarlem, Netherlands September 3, 2024. (REUTERS/Piroschka van de Wouw)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/b62760c9-361f-4955-917e-0621a6963b78_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Deezi, a dog from a shelter in Istanbul, Turkey, walks with its new owners Caroline and Meike in Haarlem, Netherlands September 3, 2024. (REUTERS/Piroschka van de Wouw)</span></div>
<p>Animal rights activist Nilgul Sayar runs a shelter for dogs near Istanbul. She has sent hundreds of dogs overseas for adoption. She said demand for international dog <strong>adoptions</strong> has jumped since the law passed.</p>
<p>"We have around 20 to 25 dogs ready to fly," Sayar said. "People continue to reach out to us (for adoption). I hope we will send more dogs soon. They will all have good homes."</p>
<p>It can take up to four months to get a dog ready to travel to the European Union with the necessary paperwork and vaccinations. And it can cost over $1,100.</p>
<p>Sayar said it often takes years to find homes for the large, old and disabled dogs that make up the majority of the animals in her shelter.</p>
<p>Dali and Deezi used to be stray dogs living on the streets of Istanbul. They were caught and put in Sayar's shelter. But today, Dali and Deezi live in the Netherlands, where they enjoy a comfortable life.</p>
<p>"We wanted to support these dogs and find loving families abroad," said Ali Okay, who volunteered to fly with them from Turkey to Belgium. The animals were later taken to the Netherlands by the non-governmental organization Animal Care Projects.</p>
<p>Dog shelters across Turkey can currently hold around 100,000 animals. Cities are to build more shelters to meet the requirements of the new law.</p>
<p>Thousands of Turks have protested against the law in recent weeks. Stray dogs and cats can be seen in streets across Turkey. They are loved and cared for by many people. Large stray dogs sometimes sleep in shop doorways, with people <strong>gently</strong> stepping around them.</p>
<p>In <strong>response</strong> to the new law, some companies are adopting strays for their offices. One hotel on the coast built a dog shelter to introduce them to foreign visitors. Some animal doctors are offering free vaccinations when people choose to adopt animals from the streets.</p>
<p>Turkey used to trap and <strong>neuter</strong> dogs and then return them to the streets. Critics of the new law say dog numbers would have been under control if that policy had been carried out.</p>
<p>Dali is now in a foster home in the Netherlands awaiting adoption. Deezi is settling into her new home and is calm and happy, said new owner Caroline Dieleman.</p>
<p>Dieleman was mourning the death of one of her dogs in June. When she heard about Turkey's new law, she decided to rescue Deezi.</p>
<p>"The new law makes me feel sick physically but also powerless," said Dieleman. "This was a little thing I could do...it is one dog only, from how many dogs. But one is better than none."</p>
<p>I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>The Reuters news agency reported this story. Ashley Thompson adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>stray </strong><em>–adj.</em> not belonging to anyone or having a home</p>
<p><strong>adoption </strong><em>–n.</em> a process in which a family takes someone else, usually a child, but the term is used for animals too, to legally become part of their family</p>
<p><strong>gently </strong><em>–adv.</em> done in a careful, soft or light way</p>
<p><strong>response </strong><em>–n.</em> the result of or answer to an action, rule or question</p>
<p><strong>neuter </strong><em>–v.</em> to remove the reproductive glands of an animal so it cannot reproduce</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Colleges Report Effects of Ban on Race-based Admissions (2024/9/11)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/colleges-report-effects-of-ban-on-race-based-admissions.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">10 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Some top universities in the United States are reporting drops in the number of Black students in their incoming classes. At other colleges, including Princeton University and Yale University, the share of Black students changed little.</p>
<p>This fall's class is the first admitted since a Supreme Court ruling barred <strong>affirmative action </strong>in higher education.</p>
<p>Several schools have seen changes in numbers of Asian, Hispanic and Native American students, but trends are still unclear. Experts and colleges say it will take years to measure the full effect of the ruling.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Graduates of the University of North Carolina take pictures at the Old Well on campus in Chapel Hill, N.C., June 30, 2020. (AP Photo/Gerry Broome, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/2593e06d-9c7e-4450-b1fd-407bf8e71506_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Graduates of the University of North Carolina take pictures at the Old Well on campus in Chapel Hill, N.C., June 30, 2020. (AP Photo/Gerry Broome, File)</span></div>
<p>The end of affirmative action is not the only possible reason for the changing numbers. Some colleges are changing requirements, making test results more important. Earlier this year, there was a problem with the federal government's college financial aid process.</p>
<p>On September 5, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill (UNC) reported drops in <strong>enrollment</strong> among Black, Hispanic and Native American students in its incoming class. It was one of the colleges at the center of the Supreme Court case.</p>
<p>The population of Black students dropped nearly 3 percentage points this fall, to 7.8 percent. Hispanic student enrollment fell from 10.8 percent to 10.1 percent, while the incoming Native American population fell half a percentage point to 1.1 percent, according to the university. The incoming Asian student population rose 1 percentage point to 25.8 percent. The share of white students, at 63.8 percent, hardly changed.</p>
<p>Rachelle Feldman is UNC's vice provost for enrollment. She said the delay in the student aid process was another possible influence on the enrollment numbers.</p>
<p>"We are <strong>committed</strong> to following the new law,” Feldman said. She also said the school administration is committed to making sure all North Carolina's students know that they are welcome at UNC and can succeed there.</p>
<p>Other universities reported sharp drops in Black student enrollment. The Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) said the percentage of incoming Black students fell from 15 percent to 5 percent. Another Massachusetts school, Amherst College, reported the percentage fell from 11 percent to 3 percent.</p>
<p>At Tufts University in Massachusetts, the drop in the share of Black students was smaller, from 7.3 percent to 4.7 percent. At Yale, the University of Virginia and Princeton, the change year-over-year was less than a percentage point.</p>
<p>Changes in enrollment for other demographic groups were more mixed. At MIT, for example, the percentage of Asian students increased from 40 percent to 47 percent. However, its Hispanic and Latino percentage dropped from 16 percent to 11 percent. And MIT's percentage of white students stayed about the same.</p>
<p>But at Yale, the percentage of Asian students fell from 30 percent to 24 percent. White students at Yale went from 42 percent of the class to 46 percent. Hispanic and Latino students saw an increased representation of 1 percentage point.</p>
<p>Colleges have started looking for other ways to preserve the <strong>diversity</strong> they say is critical to university life.</p>
<p>JT Duck is head of admissions at Tufts University in Massachusetts. He said the school would work with community organizations to reach underrepresented, low-income students and students whose parents did not graduate from college. He suggested that people not worry too much about year-to-year changes in enrollment.</p>
<p>At UNC, vice provost Feldman said the university wants to make sure "anyone from any background knows they can earn their way here."</p>
<p>Katharine Meyer works at the Brookings Institution. She said it is hard to tell which policy change is having a greater effect. But so far, she said, the drops in underrepresented minority students are smaller than in previous cases. California passed a ban on affirmative action in 1995 and Michigan did so in 2014. But since those bans, Meyer said, colleges have developed more effective, non-race-based ways of <strong>recruiting</strong> and enrolling a diverse class.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Annie Ma and Makiya Seminera </em><em>reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>affirmative action</strong> – <em>n</em>. the practice of improving the educational and job opportunities of members of groups that have not been treated fairly in the past because of their race, sex, or the like</p>
<p><strong>enroll</strong> –<em> v</em>. to take (someone) as a member or participant</p>
<p><strong>committed</strong> – <em>adj</em>. willing to give your time, energy, and the like to something</p>
<p><strong>diversity </strong>– n. the state of having people who are different races or who have different cultures in a group or organization</p>
<p><strong>recruit</strong> – <em>v</em>. to find suitable people and get them to join a company, an organization, the armed forces, et</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>UN: Schools in Gaza Are Closed as Fighting Continues (2024/9/11)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/un-schools-in-gaza-are-closed-as-fighting-continues.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">10 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The new school year in the Palestinian territories officially began on Monday. But all schools in Gaza are closed after 11 months of war. There is no sign of a ceasefire.</p>
<p>Israel gave new orders to people in the northern Gaza Strip to leave their homes. The order came after rockets were fired into Israel from Gaza.</p>
<p>Umm Zaki has a son, Moataz, who is 15 years old. He was supposed to begin 10th grade. Instead, he woke up in the family's tent in Deir al-Balah in central Gaza. Water is more than one kilometer away from the tent.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Palestinian students attend a class in a tent in Khan Younis, in the southern Gaza Strip, September 4, 2024. (REUTERS/Hatem Khaled)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/80e7ef5c-ad80-4d20-b123-db1abb2ab96e_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Palestinian students attend a class in a tent in Khan Younis, in the southern Gaza Strip, September 4, 2024. (REUTERS/Hatem Khaled)</span></div>
<p>The mother of five told Reuters by text message, "Usually, such a day would be a day of celebration, seeing the children in the new <strong>uniform</strong>, going to school, and dreaming of becoming doctors and engineers. Today all we hope is that the war ends before we lose any of them."</p>
<p>The Palestinian Education Ministry said all Gaza schools were closed and 90 percent of them had been destroyed or damaged in the war. The war started after Hamas gunmen attacked Israeli towns on October 7 killing about 1,200 people.</p>
<p>The U.N. Palestinian aid agency UNRWA operates about half of Gaza's schools. Many of them are now emergency shelters housing thousands of displaced families.</p>
<p>UNRWA Director of Communications Juliette Touma told Reuters, "The longer the children stay out of school the more difficult it is for them to catch up on their lost learning.” She added that they are then more likely to become “a lost generation.” They are at risk for the dangers of “child marriage, child labor, and <strong>recruitment</strong> into armed groups."</p>
<p>The education ministry said there are already 625,000 Gazans registered for school who would be missing classes. Another 58,000 six year olds should have registered to start first grade this year.</p>
<p>Last month, the UNRWA started a back-to-learning program in 45 of its shelters. Teachers set up games, <strong>drama</strong>, arts, music and sports activities to help with children's mental health.</p>
<p><strong>Order to evacuate</strong></p>
<p>Nearly all of Gaza's 2.3 million people have been forced from their homes at least once. Some have had to flee 10 times.</p>
<p>In the latest <strong>evacuation</strong> order, Israel told residents of an area in the northern Gaza Strip that they must leave their homes. Rockets had been fired from there into southern Israel the day before.</p>
<p>The United Nations urged Palestinians in the northern Gaza Strip to attend medical centers to get children under the age of 10 years old vaccinated against polio. There have been breaks in the fighting to permit a vaccination campaign. The U.N. hopes to vaccinate 640,000 children in Gaza. The territory's first polio case in around 25 years was recently reported.</p>
<p>U.N. officials said the campaign in the southern and central Gaza Strip had so far reached more than half of the children there needing the vaccine. Four weeks later, the children must get a second vaccination to complete the treatment.</p>
<p>Touma, the U.N. official, said 450,000 of the children targeted by the campaign had been vaccinated.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Nidal al-Mughrabi reported this story for Reuters. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>uniform </strong><em>–n.</em> clothing that is just like clothing worn by others at a school or in some kinds of jobs</p>
<p><strong>recruit</strong> – <em>v</em>. to persuade (someone) to join you in some activity or to help you</p>
<p><strong>drama </strong>– <em>n</em>. the art or activity of performing a role in a play</p>
<p><strong>evacuate</strong> – <em>n</em>. to leave (a dangerous place)</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Remembering American Actor James Earl Jones (2024/9/11) | 美国演员詹姆斯·厄尔·琼斯周一去世</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/remembering-american-actor-james-earl-jones.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>American actor James Earl Jones died Monday. He was 93 years old.<br/>
美国演员詹姆斯·厄尔·琼斯周一去世。享年93岁。</p>
<p>His agent, Barry McPherson, said Jones died at his home in the Hudson Valley area of New York. The cause of death was not reported.<br/>
他的经纪人巴里·麦克弗森表示，琼斯在纽约哈德逊谷地区的家中去世。死因尚未公布。</p>
<p>Jones was probably most famous around the world for his performance as Darth Vader in the Star Wars movie series.<br/>
琼斯可能因在《星球大战》系列电影中饰演达斯·维德而闻名于世。</p>
<p>In interviews, Jones said he loved playing the part of Darth Vader, and of being part of the Star Wars story. "When I walk out tonight there will be kids with posters to sign,” he once said.<br/>
在采访中，琼斯说他喜欢扮演达斯·维德这个角色，也喜欢成为《星球大战》故事的一部分。他曾说过：“当我今晚走出家门时，会有孩子们拿着海报签名。”</p>
<p>“I love it. I love that I was a part of that cult."<br/>
“我喜欢这个。我喜欢自己成为那种狂热的一部分。”</p>
<p>His deep and powerful voice took on a career of its own.<br/>
他深沉而有力的嗓音走上了自己的职业生涯。</p>
<p>Jones voiced the part of Mufasa in The Lion King. He won a Grammy award in 1977 for the spoken word album, Great American Documents.<br/>
琼斯为《狮子王》中的木法沙配音。1977年，他凭借诵读专辑《伟大的美国文献》获得格莱美奖。</p>
<p>But the voice did not come naturally to Jones. As a child, he suffered from a severe speech problem.<br/>
但琼斯的声音并不是与生俱来。小时候，他患有严重的言语障碍。</p>
<p>James Earl Jones was born in the state of Mississippi in 1931. He had a severe stutter. As a result, he mostly stopped speaking.<br/>
詹姆斯·厄尔·琼斯于1931年出生于密西西比州。他严重口吃。因此，他基本上不太说话。</p>
<p>He moved to Michigan when he was six. His grandparents became his legal guardians and raised him there.<br/>
他六岁时搬到了密歇根州。他的祖父母成为了他的法定监护人，并在那里抚养他长大。</p>
<p>In high school, Jones recovered his voice through his own poetry and the guidance of a teacher. Jones began to read his poems aloud to the class. His speaking improved.<br/>
在高中时，琼斯通过自己的诗歌和老师的指导找回了他的嗓音。琼斯开始向全班大声朗读他的诗。他的口语有所提高。</p>
<p>He went on to study acting at the University of Michigan. He also played on the university's basketball team.<br/>
他继续在密歇根大学学习表演。他还参加了该大学的篮球队。</p>
<p>Jones then served in the United States Army from 1953 to 1955.<br/>
琼斯于1953年至1955年在美国陆军服役。</p>
<p>In 1965, James Earl Jones became one of the first Black actors in America to play a continuing part on a daytime television drama.<br/>
1965年，詹姆斯·厄尔·琼斯成为美国首批在日间电视剧中扮演连续角色的黑人演员之一。</p>
<p>In his more than 70 years in show business, Jones played lead parts in many plays by William Shakespeare, including Hamlet, Macbeth, King Lear and Othello.<br/>
在他70多年的演艺生涯中，琼斯在威廉·莎士比亚的许多戏剧中扮演主角，包括《哈姆雷特》、《麦克白》、《李尔王》和《奥赛罗》。</p>
<p>He received Tony awards for several performances in Broadway plays, including The Great White Hope in 1969 and Fences in 1987.<br/>
他因在百老汇戏剧中的几场演出获得了托尼奖，包括1969年的《拳王奋斗史》和1987年的《栅栏》。</p>
<p>He received Emmy awards for his work in television, as well.<br/>
他也因在电视上的工作而获得艾美奖。</p>
<p>And in 2011, the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences awarded Jones an Oscar to recognize his work in film.<br/>
2011年，美国电影艺术与科学学院授予琼斯奥斯卡奖，以表彰他在电影方面的工作。</p>
<p>His famous voice was also used in many television commercials.<br/>
他著名的嗓音也出现在许多电视广告中。</p>
<p>For years, the news network CNN has used Jones' voice recording, "This is CNN," for its station identification.<br/>
多年来，新闻网络CNN一直使用琼斯的录音“This is CNN”作为其电台标识。</p>
<p>James Earl Jones was married twice, both times to actors. He second wife, Cecilia Hart Flynn, died in 2016. Jones is survived by his son from his second marriage, Flynn Earl Jones, and his brother, Matthew.<br/>
詹姆斯·厄尔·琼斯结过两次婚，两次都娶的是演员。他的第二任妻子Cecilia Hart Flynn于2016年去世。琼斯身后留下了他第二次婚姻中的儿子弗林·厄尔-琼斯和他的兄弟马修。</p>
<p>Jones continued to work well past the usual retirement age. His most recent work included performing again as Darth Vader in the Star Wars television miniseries Obi Wan Kenobi.<br/>
琼斯继续工作到通常的退休年龄。他最近的作品包括在《星球大战》电视迷你剧《欧比-万·克诺比》中再次饰演达斯·维德。</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.<br/>
我是凯蒂·韦弗。(21VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Climate Group: Summer 2024 Was Hottest on Record (2024/9/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/climate-group-summer-2024-was-hottest-on-record.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A European climate service says summer 2024 was the hottest on record. The declaration makes it even more likely that this year will also turn out to be the warmest ever measured.</p>
<p>The summer heat data came from the European Union's Copernicus Climate Change Service. <a class="wsw__a" href="https://climate.copernicus.eu/about-us">Copernicus</a> aims to provide detailed data on “past, present and future climate in Europe and the rest of the world.”</p>
<p>The service said that during the months of June, July and August, temperatures worldwide averaged 16.8 degrees Celsius. That was 0.03 degrees warmer than in 2023.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Children cool off as they play on a fountain at Stavros Niarchos Foundation Cultural Center, in Athens, Greece, July 18, 2024. (AP Photo/Petros Giannakouris)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-8369-08dcacd63f83_cx0_cy8_cw94_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Children cool off as they play on a fountain at Stavros Niarchos Foundation Cultural Center, in Athens, Greece, July 18, 2024. (AP Photo/Petros Giannakouris)</span></div>
<p>Copernicus records only date back to 1940. But American, British and Japanese records go back to the mid-19th century. Those records suggest the last 10 years have been the hottest since official climate data measurements started.</p>
<p>Copernicus Director Carlo Buontempo told The Associated Press the Augusts in both 2024 and 2023 tied for the hottest Augusts at 16.82 degrees Celsius. The service reported July was the first time in more than a year that the world did not set a record. But because June 2024 was so much hotter than June 2023, this summer as a whole was the hottest, it said.</p>
<p>Buontempo noted that the high temperatures also likely pushed air <strong>humidity</strong> levels to record highs during the past summer.</p>
<p>The Copernicus chief said all the latest data suggests 2024 will likely break the record for the warmest year ever recorded. “In order for 2024 not to become the warmest on record, we need to see very significant <strong>landscape</strong> cooling for the remaining few months,” Buontempo added. But he noted, that “doesn't look likely.”</p>
<p>Climate scientists say the record temperatures have real <strong>consequences</strong> for many people around the planet.</p>
<p>Jonathan Overpeck is a climate scientist at the University of Michigan. He told the AP the continued warming will lead to “more misery around the world” in places seeing the most extreme temperatures.</p>
<p>Overpeck suggested Phoenix, Arizona as an example. The southwestern American city has already experienced more than 100 days of temperatures over 37.8 degrees Celsius this year.</p>
<p>“With longer and more severe heat waves come more severe <strong>droughts</strong> in some places, and more intense rains and flooding in others,” he said. “Climate change is becoming too <strong>obvious</strong>, and too costly, to ignore,” Overpeck added.</p>
<p>Jennifer Francis is a climate scientist at the Woodwell Climate Research Center in Cape Cod, Massachusetts. She said more communities worldwide are now having to deal with “violent and dangerous” conditions that include extreme heat, floods, wildfires and high winds.</p>
<p>In an email to the AP, Francis compared people living in areas with extreme climate to those living in conflict areas. She said that in both cases, people get so used to the situation they can become “<strong>deaf</strong>” to the severe conditions surrounding them every day.</p>
<p>Copernicus chief Buontempo noted an El Ni<i></i>241;o weather system fueled part of last year's record heat. El Ni<i></i>241;o is a warming of surface temperatures in the eastern and central Pacific Ocean. The event usually causes hot, dry weather in Asia and Australia. It can also drive weather changes in other parts of the world.</p>
<p>But the El Ni<i></i>241;o effect has ended, Buontempo said. Now, human-caused climate change from fossil fuel use is again the main driver of increased temperatures, he said.</p>
<p>“It's really not surprising that we see this, this heat wave, that we see these temperature extremes,” Buontempo said. “We are <strong>bound</strong> to see more.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>humidity</strong> <em>– n. </em>a measurement of how much water there is in the air</p>
<p><strong>landscape</strong> <em>– n. </em>the appearance of an area of land</p>
<p><strong>consequence </strong><em>– n.</em> the result of an action or situation, especially one with a bad result</p>
<p><strong>drought </strong><em>– n.</em> a long period when there is little or no rain and people do not have enough water</p>
<p><strong>obvious </strong><em>– adj. </em>easy to understand or see</p>
<p><strong>deaf </strong><em>– adj. </em>to ignore something because it is too often seen or heard</p>
<p><strong>bound </strong><em>– adj. </em>very likely</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How Bad Are Ultraprocessed Foods? (2024/9/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/how-bad-are-ultraprocessed-foods.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Most Americans eat ultraprocessed foods every day. These are foods that you cannot make at home because they contain flavors and chemicals that change the taste or feel of the food.</p>
<p>Such food may also go through preparation methods that are not possible in a home kitchen. They are usually high in salt, sugar and fat. Americans may eat them in the form of sugary cereals at breakfast, frozen pizzas at dinner, and in-between bites like potato chips, sodas and ice cream.</p>
<p>Ultraprocessed foods make up about 60 percent of the American diet. For children and teenagers, it is even higher – about two-thirds of what they eat.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A customer makes a purchase at a convenience store in Boston in this July 12, 2005 file photo. (AP Photo/Lisa Poole, file)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-795e-08dcc9034574_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A customer makes a purchase at a convenience store in Boston in this July 12, 2005 file photo. (AP Photo/Lisa Poole, file)</span></div>
<p>Scientists have connected eating ultraprocessed foods to poor health results. Being overweight is one such result and that may lead to diabetes and heart disease. Other possible health risks include depression and <strong>dementia</strong>. One recent study suggested that eating these foods may raise the risk of early death.</p>
<p>Nutrition science is complex, though, and most research so far has found connections -- not proof -- regarding the health effects of these foods.</p>
<p>Food manufacturers argue that processing increases food safety and food supplies. They say it also offers a low-cost, easy way to provide a <strong>diverse</strong> and nutritious diet.</p>
<p>The Associated Press asked several nutrition experts to explain these foods so that people can make informed choices.</p>
<p><strong>What are ultraprocessed foods?</strong></p>
<p>Most foods are processed, whether it is by freezing, grinding, <strong>fermentation</strong>, <strong>pasteurization</strong> or other means. In 2009, Brazilian <strong>epidemiologist</strong> Carlos Monteiro and his team first proposed a way to classify foods by how much they are processed, not by their nutrient content. This is called the Nova classification system. It is used by international bodies like the World Health Organization.</p>
<p>Kevin Hall is a researcher who studies <strong>metabolism</strong> and diet at the National Institutes of Health. He said that foods at the top of the Nova four-level <strong>scale</strong> are foods prepared with industrial processes and ingredients such as additives, colors and <strong>preservatives</strong> that you could not use in a home kitchen.</p>
<p>"These are most, but not all, of the packaged foods you see," Hall said.</p>
<p><strong>Are ultraprocessed foods harmful?</strong></p>
<p>Not all processing is unhealthy, Hall noted. Whole-grain bread, yogurt, tofu and infant <strong>formula</strong> are all highly processed, for example. But they are also nutritious.</p>
<p>Still, many studies suggest that diets high in ultraprocessed foods are tied to poor health results. The exact cause is still unclear.</p>
<p>Hall and his partners carried out a small study with 20 people who came to live at a health center for a month. Some of the people ate ultraprocessed foods, while others ate unprocessed foods. The two groups got the same amount of calories, sugar, fat, fiber and nutrients for two weeks. They could eat as much as they liked.</p>
<p>When people ate the diet of ultraprocessed foods, they took in about 500 calories per day more than when they ate unprocessed foods, researchers found. They gained an average of about 1 kilogram during the study period. People who ate only unprocessed foods for the same amount of time lost about 1 kilogram.</p>
<p>A new study is currently taking place and its results should appear next year.</p>
<p><strong>Should ultraprocessed foods be regulated?</strong></p>
<p>Dr. Neena Prasad is director of the Bloomberg Philanthropies' Food Policy Program. She said such foods are often made to be both low-cost and very tasty.</p>
<p>"You just can't stop eating them," Prasad said. She said she believes leaders have enough facts to change policies. This could mean raising taxes on sugary drinks, limiting salt in these foods and controlling how advertisers sell the foods to children.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, Food and Drug Administration Commissioner Robert Califf told a group of food policy experts that ultraprocessed foods are a complex subject. However, Califf said, "We've got to have the scientific basis and then we've got to follow through."</p>
<p><strong>How should consumers manage ultraprocessed foods at home?</strong></p>
<p>Aviva Musicus is science director for the Center for Science in the Public Interest. She said buyers should check information printed on food containers and make choices based on the current U.S. Dietary Guidelines.</p>
<p>"We have really good evidence that added sugar is not great for us. We have evidence that high-<strong>sodium</strong> foods are not great for us," she said.</p>
<p>Musicus added, "We have great evidence that fruits and vegetables which are <strong>minimally</strong> processed are really good for us."</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jonel Aleccia reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>dementia</strong> – <em>n</em>. a mental illness that causes someone to be unable to think clearly or to understand what is real and what is not real</p>
<p><strong>diverse </strong>– <em>adj</em>. made up of people or things that are different from each other</p>
<p><strong>convenient</strong> – <em>adj</em>. allowing you to do something easily or without trouble</p>
<p><strong>fermentation</strong> – <em>n</em>. to go through a chemical change that results in the production of alcohol</p>
<p><strong>pasteurization</strong> – <em>n</em>. a process in which a liquid (such as milk or cream) is heated to a temperature that kills harmful germs and then cooled quickly</p>
<p><strong>epidemiology</strong> – <em>n. </em>the study of how disease spreads and can be controlled</p>
<p><strong>metabolism</strong> – <em>n.</em> the chemical processes by which a plant or an animal uses food, water, and the like5 to grow and heal and to make energy</p>
<p><strong>scale</strong> –<em> n</em>. a range of levels of something from lowest to highest</p>
<p><strong>sodium</strong> – <em>n</em>. a soft silver-white element that is found in salt, baking soda, and other compounds</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Deadly Typhoon Yagi Hits Factories in Northern Vietnam (2024/9/10) | 台风“摩羯”给越南北部工厂造成沉重打击</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/deadly-typhoon-yagi-hits-factories-in-northern-vietnam.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>A powerful ocean storm caused deadly floods and landslides in the northern part of Vietnam over the weekend. Typhoon Yagi is the strongest such storm to hit the country in years.<br/>周末，一场强大的海洋风暴在越南北部造成了致命的洪水和山体滑坡。台风“摩羯”是多年来袭击该国的最强风暴。</p><p>In Phu Tho province, a bridge over the Red River collapsed Monday. Reports said 10 cars and trucks and two motorbikes fell into the river. Rescuers saved three people from the river. Thirteen others are missing.<br/>在富寿省 ，一座横跨红河的桥梁周一坍塌。报道称，10辆汽车、卡车和两辆摩托车掉进了河里。救援人员从河里救出了三个人。另有13人失踪。</p><p>In Cao Ban province, a landslide pushed a bus carrying 20 people into a flooded stream.<br/>在高平省，一场山体滑坡将一辆载有20人的公共汽车推入洪水中。</p><p>In the northern town of Sa Pa, a popular area for foreign visitors, a landslide killed six people on Sunday.<br/>在北部城镇萨帕这个外国游客的热门地区，周日发生了一场山体滑坡，造成六人死亡。</p><p>The storm is responsible for at least 59 deaths in Vietnam, officials said.<br/>官方表示，这场风暴在越南造成至少59人死亡。</p><p>Yagi effects Vietnam's industry<br/>台风“摩羯”对越南工业的影响</p><p>Northern Vietnam is a center for manufacturing. Many foreign companies have operations there, and it is a base for export activity.<br/>越南北部是制造业中心。许多外国公司在那里开展业务，它也是出口基地。</p><p>State newspaper Lao Dong reported many businesses were closed Monday because of heavy damage. The storm destroyed several factories. Others had water leaks that damaged goods and costly equipment.<br/>越南官媒《劳动报》报道称，周一许多企业因严重受损而关闭。这场风暴摧毁了几家工厂。其他工厂则发生漏水，毁坏了货物和昂贵的设备。</p><p>Damage to electrical equipment in Haiphong and Quang Ninh provinces caused power outages Monday. The two provinces are industrial centers for export goods. Factories for electric vehicle maker VinFast, Pegatrong, a supplier for Apple, and electronics supplier USI were among those without power.<br/>海防省和广宁省的电力设备损坏导致周一停电。这两个省是出口商品的工业中心。电动汽车制造商VinFast、苹果供应商和硕以及电子产品供应商USI的工厂都处于停电状态。</p><p>Prime Minister Pham Minh Chinh visited the port city of Haiphong on Sunday and approved aid worth $4.6 million.<br/>越南总理范明政周日访问了港口城市海防，并批准了价值460万美元的援助。</p><p>Korean manufacturer LG Electronics reported no injuries among its employees. But it said the storm flooded a building that stored its finished products, including refrigerators and washing machines. Hong Sun, the chair of the South Korean business association in Vietnam, said there was a lot of damage.<br/>韩国制造商LG电子报告称，其员工没有受伤。但该公司表示，风暴淹没了一座储存其成品的建筑，包括冰箱和洗衣机。韩国驻越南商会主席洪荪表示，损失惨重。</p><p>State-operated power company EVN said more than 5.7 million customers had lost power and many power lines had been broken.<br/>国有电力公司越南电力集团表示，超过570万客户断电，许多电力线被破坏。</p><p>Bruno Jaspaert is head of DEEP C, a Belgian industrial developer and operator. Jaspaert oversees factories in Haiphong and Quang Ninh provinces. He said, “Everyone is scrambling to make sites safe, and stocks dry.”<br/>布鲁诺·贾斯帕尔特是比利时工业开发商和运营商DEEP C的负责人。贾斯帕尔特负责监管海防省和广宁省的工厂。他说：“每个人都在争先恐后地确保厂址安全，库存干燥。”</p><p>The typhoon made landfall on Saturday in northeast Vietnam. At its strongest, the storm had winds measured at 149 kilometers an hour.<br/>这场台风于周六在越南东北部登陆。风暴最强时，风速达每小时149公里。</p><p>By Sunday, the storm had weakened to a tropical depression, a storm below the level of a typhoon. However, Vietnam's weather agency continues to warn of landslides.<br/>截至周日，风暴已减弱为热带低气压，其强度低于台风。然而，越南气象局继续警告山体滑坡风险。</p><p>VN Express reported that the water levels of several rivers in northern Vietnam remain dangerously high.<br/>《越南快报》报道称，越南北部几条河流的水位仍然高得危险。</p><p>The deadly storm also affected other parts of Southeast Asia. Reports say 20 people in the Philippines and four in southern China also died in the storm. On China's Hainan Island, officials reported that more than 50,000 homes were damaged or destroyed.<br/>这场致命的风暴也影响了东南亚的其他地区。报道称，菲律宾有20人，中国南部也有4人在风暴中丧生。在中国海南岛，官员们报告说，有5万多所房屋受损或被毁。</p><p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.<br/>我是小马里奥·里特。(21VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Could Electricity for Bitcoin Mining Become Energy for AI? (2024/9/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/could-electricity-for-bitcoin-mining-become-energy-for-ai.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>U.S. technology companies are increasingly purchasing or<strong> leasing</strong> energy <strong>assets</strong> held by <strong>bitcoin</strong> miners.</p>
<p>These moves come as technology companies hurry to secure a supply of electricity for their growing artificial intelligence (AI) and cloud computing data centers.</p>
<p>Those data centers are driving the fastest increase in U.S. electricity demand since 2000. The demand is growing faster than the <strong>electricity grid</strong>. That means big technology companies, like Amazon and Microsoft, are aiming to secure large amounts of electricity.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A group of buildings housing cryptocurrency miners sits in the foreground of a power generating station at the Scrubgrass Plant in Kennerdell, Pennsylvania, U.S., March 8, 2022. Picture taken March 8, 2022. (REUTERS/Alan Freed)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/144aa8b5-ad35-4706-b267-e0cca74f3300_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A group of buildings housing cryptocurrency miners sits in the foreground of a power generating station at the Scrubgrass Plant in Kennerdell, Pennsylvania, U.S., March 8, 2022. Picture taken March 8, 2022. (REUTERS/Alan Freed)</span></div>
<p>Growing power demand is affecting the cryptocurrency mining industry – an industry that uses a lot of energy.</p>
<p>Some miners are making a profit by leasing or selling their power-connected <strong>infrastructure </strong>and centers. But other miners cannot get enough electricity to stay in business.</p>
<p>Greg Beard is chief of Stronghold Digital Mining, a publicly traded bitcoin mining company based in Pennsylvania.</p>
<p>"The AI battle for <strong>dominance </strong>is a battle being had by the biggest and best <strong>capitalized </strong>companies in the world and they care like their lives depend on it that they win," he said. "Do they care about what they pay for power? Probably not."</p>
<p>Electric Power Research Institute is a non-profit energy research company based in Palo Alto, California. It said in May that data centers could use up to nine percent of total electricity produced in the U.S. by 2030. That is more than double their current use. This change comes as technology companies are paying a lot to grow their computing centers.</p>
<p>The International Energy Agency (IEA) says that data centers currently account for about 1 to 1.3 percent of world electricity use. Crypto mining uses 0.4 percent. The IEA says that difference is expected to grow.</p>
<p>Experts expect 20 percent of bitcoin mining power<strong> capacity</strong> to move to AI by the end of 2027. Over the past year, bitcoin miners have increasingly competed with AI data center owners for the same power production centers and business deals. That is what heads of more than six publicly traded U.S. crypto mining companies told Reuters.</p>
<p>One example took place in Pennsylvania. Marathon Digital Holdings is the world's biggest publicly traded bitcoin miner. Two <strong>sources</strong> who know about the situation said the company was among those considering a nuclear-powered data center owned by Talen Energy in Pennsylvania. But technology company Amazon bought the center in a deal announced in March.</p>
<p>Many large miners that own land and are connected to power centers are changing the way they do business. They are marketing their property and energy services to AI and cloud computing companies and doing less crypto mining.</p>
<p>"We've gotten a lot of interest from everyone from an Amazon or Google," said Kerri Langlais. He is an official for bitcoin miner TeraWulf. The company has a center in New York that can produce 770 megawatts of electricity.</p>
<p>Core Scientific is a crypto miner that a court recently permitted to restructure after its earlier financial failure. In June, Core Scientific became the first bitcoin miner to announce a major agreement. The deal was to lease its power-connected production centers to the company CoreWeave, which is supported by Nvidia. The deals are estimated to be worth more than $6.7 billion over 12 years.</p>
<p>Several miners have since said they would lease or act as <strong>subcontractors</strong> to develop AI data centers.</p>
<p>Morgan Stanley said providing electricity for AI and cloud computing could be profitable for big crypto miners. The investment bank said it could make their centers as much as five times more valuable.</p>
<p>Morgan Stanley also said technology companies could save billions of dollars by buying or leasing space from a miner with at least 100 megawatts of electricity production. It said such deals could cut the wait times for a data center to launch by about 3.5 years.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Laila Kearney and Mrinalika Roy reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>lease</strong> <em>– v.</em> to use (something) for a period of time in return for payment</p>
<p><strong>asset </strong><em>–n.</em> something that is of value that can usually be exchanged for money</p>
<p><strong>bitcoin</strong> <em>–n.</em> a digital currency created for use in online transactions</p>
<p><strong>electricity grid</strong> <em>–n. </em>the system of electricity generation, transmission and distribution that covers a large area of a country</p>
<p><strong>infrastructure</strong> <em>– n.</em> the resources (such as buildings or equipment) required for an activity</p>
<p><strong>dominance</strong> <em>–n.</em> the ability to control</p>
<p><strong>capitalized</strong> <em>— adj.</em> to have a lot of money or to possess the ability to borrow or get money from investors easily</p>
<p><strong>capacity </strong><em>– n. </em>power to produce, perform, or deploy</p>
<p><strong>source</strong><em> –n.</em> the provider of information about a subject</p>
<p><strong>subcontractor</strong> <em>– n.</em> an individual or business contracting to perform part or all of another's contract</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>SpaceX Mission to Include First Spacewalk for Private Citizens (2024/9/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/spacex-mission-to-include-first-spacewalk-for-private-citizens.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A private space <strong>mission</strong> will seek to launch non-astronauts to a high orbit and include the first private spacewalks in history.</p>
<p>The American space company SpaceX's flight is cleared to launch from Florida's Kennedy Space Center beginning September 7. The American space agency NASA operates the center. The exact launch date will depend on weather conditions.</p>
<p>American businessman Jared Isaacman organized and paid for the mission, called <a class="wsw__a" href="https://polarisprogram.com/dawn/" target="_blank">Polaris Dawn</a>. He and three people will crew the mission. Isaacman is the head of payment processing company Shift4Payments. He has an estimated personal worth of $2 billion. But he has not said publicly how much he paid SpaceX for the Polaris Dawn mission.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Anna Menon, Scott Poteet, Jared Isaacman and Sarah Gillis, crew members of Polaris Dawn, a private human spaceflight mission, attend a press conference at the Kennedy Space Center in Cape Canaveral, Florida, U.S. August 19, 2024. (REUTERS/Joe Skipper)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/8114e020-690b-45ec-b003-d3fedfcf902e_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Anna Menon, Scott Poteet, Jared Isaacman and Sarah Gillis, crew members of Polaris Dawn, a private human spaceflight mission, attend a press conference at the Kennedy Space Center in Cape Canaveral, Florida, U.S. August 19, 2024. (REUTERS/Joe Skipper)</span></div>
<p>The crewmembers will travel in SpaceX's Crew Dragon spacecraft on a SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket. The company expects the spacecraft to reach an altitude of about 1,400 kilometers. That would be the highest any crewed mission has reached since NASA's Apollo program ended in the early 1970s.</p>
<p>Isaacman is the mission commander for Polaris Dawn. Also taking part in the flight will be Scott Poteet, a retired U.S. Air Force Colonel and two SpaceX employees, Sarah Gillis and Anna Menon. Gillis is a mission specialist at SpaceX, while Menon is a lead space operations engineer. The crew is expected to spend five days in orbit.</p>
<p>Polaris Dawn will reach its highest altitude on its first day. The Crew Dragon will briefly enter the Van Allen radiation belt, an area filled with high-energy charged particles that can present health risks to humans over extended periods.</p>
<p>This will provide a chance to test the effectiveness of SpaceX's newly designed spacesuits. SpaceX says the clothing is equipped with data instruments, cameras and improved <strong>mobility</strong> systems. SpaceX says tests of the spacesuit will help the company design and develop future space missions to the moon and Mars.</p>
<p>A statement by SpaceX <a class="wsw__a" href="https://polarisprogram.com/dawn/">said</a> one main goal of Polaris Dawn will be to carry out research “with the aim of better understanding the effects of spaceflight and space radiation on human health.”</p>
<p>Speaking about the mission's risks, Isaacman told reporters, "Whatever risk is <strong>associated</strong> <strong>with</strong> it, it is worth it." He added, "We have no idea what it could do to really change the <strong>trajectory</strong> of humankind ... there has to be some first steps in this direction."</p>
<p>The crew will orbit nearly three times higher than the International Space Station (ISS). But this is far short of the record-breaking distance of over 399,117 kilometers set by NASA's Apollo 13 crew in 1970.</p>
<p>Isaacman is expected to guide the other crew members on the mission's planned spacewalk on day three of the mission. Each member is expected to spend about 20 minutes in space.</p>
<p>So far, only government astronauts from the U.S., former Soviet Union and Russia, the European Space Agency, Canada and China have carried out spacewalks. More than 270 spacewalks, using American and Russian spacesuits, have been carried out from the ISS since its launch in 2000, Reuters news agency reports.</p>
<p>The next day will be spent testing laser-based satellite communication between the spacecraft and Starlink, SpaceX's internet satellite system. The laser method – which has also been tested by NASA – is designed to greatly increase space communication speeds.</p>
<p>The crew also plans to carry out 40 experiments aimed at improving our understanding of human health during long space missions. Among these will be tests with special contact lenses containing microelectronics that can continuously identify changes in eye pressure and shape.</p>
<p>At the end of the mission, Crew Dragon will aim for a parachute landing off the coast of Florida. A SpaceX recovery ship will be waiting for the crew's arrival.</p>
<p>Polaris Dawn is the first of three planned missions under the Polaris program. The second Polaris mission will also use a Dragon capsule, while the third and final is expected to use SpaxeX's Starship rocket. SpaceX chief Elon Musk has said his company plans to use Starship to carry future space travelers to the moon and Mars.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from Reuters, Agence France-Presse, SpaceX and Polaris.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>mission</strong><em> – n. </em>an important project or trip, especially involving space travel</p>
<p><strong>mobility</strong> <em>– n. </em>the ability to walk and move freely</p>
<p><strong>associate </strong><em>– </em><em>v. </em>to connect someone or something in your mind with someone or something else</p>
<p><strong>trajectory </strong><em>– n.</em> the curved path an object follows after it has been thrown or shot into the air</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Gazan Teen Musician Sings for Children at War (2024/9/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/gazan-teen-musician-sings-for-children-at-war.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In the war-damaged streets of northern Gaza's Jabalia refugee camp, 15-year-old Youssef Saad rides his bicycle with his musical instrument <strong>strapped</strong> on his back. The instrument he carries is called an oud. The sound of the oud is common in much Middle Eastern music.</p>
<p>Saad is bringing his instrument to a day center for children in the camp. There, he plays the oud and sings for children who have suffered through 11 months of war.</p>
<p>Saad says he tries to offer the children a little happiness or a way to temporarily forget about their difficult situation.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this frame captured from video, Palestinian teenager Youssef Saad sits on the rubble of his house as he plays oud to bring joy to children, amid Israel-Hamas conflict, in Jabalia refugee camp in the northern Gaza Strip September 2, 2024. (REUTERS/Mahmoud Issa)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/392454cc-1821-461a-832a-c00a0a264626_cx0_cy5_cw89_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this frame captured from video, Palestinian teenager Youssef Saad sits on the rubble of his house as he plays oud to bring joy to children, amid Israel-Hamas conflict, in Jabalia refugee camp in the northern Gaza Strip September 2, 2024. (REUTERS/Mahmoud Issa)</span></div>
<p>"The homes in my city were once full of dreams," Saad said. As he spoke, he looked at the destroyed buildings in the refugee camp. Before the war, the refugee camp had a large population. “Now, they're gone,” he said.</p>
<p>Saad was studying music at the Edward Said National Conservatory of Music in nearby Gaza City before the war started. Like many other buildings, the conservatory was destroyed during the fighting. Saad and his four <strong>siblings</strong> are now living with relatives after his own home was destroyed.</p>
<p>Saad's father, a government worker with the Palestinian Authority, always supported Saad's dream of becoming a musician. Saad now centers his efforts on playing his oud and singing at the Jabalia center for children.</p>
<p>The war started after the Palestinian Islamist group Hamas attacked Israel on October 7 last year. Hamas terrorists killed some 1,200 people and took 250 hostages from southern Israel, according to Israeli estimates.</p>
<p>Since then, Israel has sought to destroy Hamas in Gaza. According to the Hamas-run health ministry, almost 41,000 Palestinians have been killed in the conflict. Airstrikes and fighting have destroyed thousands of buildings in Gaza.</p>
<p>"Every house holds a tragedy," Saad said. "Some have lost their mother, others their father, their neighbor, or their friend."</p>
<p>Even with the danger, Saad has a strong desire to continue his work with the children.</p>
<p>"We try to help improve their mental health, even if it means putting myself at risk," he said. "This is my duty to the children."</p>
<p>Saad added that he lives by an expression that carries him through the darkest days: "If you live, live free, or die standing like trees."</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith adapted this story for VOA Learning English based on reporting from Reuters news agency. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>strap </strong><em>-v</em>. to secure or carry an object using flexible material such as leather or nylon.</p>
<p><strong>sibling(s) </strong><em>- n</em>. one of two or more persons having the same parents; brothers and sisters</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>‘Dead Giveaway’ Is Not as Dark as It Sounds (2024/9/8)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/dead-giveaway----not-as-dark-as-it-sounds.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">07 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories</em> from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>On this program we explore words and expressions in the English language. We give examples, notes on usage and sometimes use them in short conversations.</p>
<p>Today we talk about an expression that sounds very serious and dangerous: a <u>dead giveaway</u>. A “giveaway” is just as it sounds: You give something to someone else.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - An archeologist holds an ancient mummified bird, found inside the burial site, Tomb of Tutu, at al-Dayabat, Sohag, Egypt, April 5, 2019. (Reuters/Mohamed Abd El Ghany)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/034E3BBC-76CB-4FEE-8297-E958461D2688_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - An archeologist holds an ancient mummified bird, found inside the burial site, Tomb of Tutu, at al-Dayabat, Sohag, Egypt, April 5, 2019. (Reuters/Mohamed Abd El Ghany)</span></div>
<p>But a <u>dead giveaway</u> has nothing to do with tragedy or death.</p>
<p>In this expression, the word “dead” has another meaning you might not have known about.</p>
<p>In some common usages, the adjective “dead” can mean exact, correct or complete. For example, if someone is <u>dead right</u>, they are completely correct and there is no doubt about it. And, if someone is <u>dead wrong</u>, they are totally wrong.</p>
<p>In some trades, the word “dead” is a really good thing. For example, when something is <u>dead center</u>, it is exactly at the center. In building, <u>dead level</u> means perfectly <strong>horizontal</strong>—just what you want. However, you never say “dead plumb.” Plumb already means perfectly <strong>vertical</strong>.</p>
<p>So, a <u>dead giveaway</u> is a detail or action that gives away the truth completely and totally. It is like a <strong>clue</strong> that answers a question. A <u>dead giveaway</u> shows a truth, fact, or <strong>intention</strong> in an <strong>obvious </strong>way.</p>
<p>In other words, a <u>dead giveaway</u> leaves little room for misunderstanding.</p>
<p>Now, let's hear the expression in some examples.</p>
<p><em>A completely dark house and a huge pile of mail outside the door were two <u>dead giveaways</u> that no one had been home in quite some time.</em></p>
<p><em>She said that she was staying home for the night. But with all the <strong>makeup</strong> on her face, her hair <strong>styled</strong>, and her party clothes on, her appearance was a <u>dead giveaway</u>. She was clearly going out. </em></p>
<p><em>The expression on his face was a <u>dead giveaway</u> that he was guilty. He couldn't even look me in the eyes! </em></p>
<p>English has another expression that is similar. A <u>telltale sign</u> is an important detail or fact the clarifies the truth. It gives more supporting evidence.</p>
<p>We often pair telltale with the words “sign” or “<strong>symptom</strong>.”</p>
<p>Let's hear some examples:</p>
<p><em>Well, my friend has missed work all week and hasn't responded to my calls. Those may be <u>telltale symptoms</u> of a bigger problem. </em></p>
<p><em>When the parents returned from their trip, they saw <u>telltale signs</u> everywhere in the house that their children had thrown a party. </em></p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this <em>Words and Their Stories.</em></p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>horizontal </strong><em>–n.</em> a line that is goes from side to side perfectly as though it is following the horizon</p>
<p><strong>vertical </strong><em>–adj.</em> going up and down at a right angle from the horizontal</p>
<p><strong>intention </strong><em>–n.</em> what someone means to do</p>
<p><strong>obvious </strong><em>–adj.</em> without doubt or confusion; clear and straightforward</p>
<p><strong>symptom </strong><em>–n.</em> the sign that something is present, especially a disease</p>
<p><strong>makeup </strong><em>–n.</em> products that are put on the face to improve a person's appearance</p>
<p><strong>styled </strong><em>–adj.</em> being formed and shaped to look appealing to others</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>South Korea’s Kimchi Threatened by Warming Weather (2024/9/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/south-korea-s-kimchi-threatened-by-warming-weather.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>One of the most popular foods in South Korea is kimchi. It is a kind of <strong>fermented</strong> cabbage or other vegetables. Now farmers, manufacturers and scientists say climate change is affecting the quality and quantity of the napa cabbage used to make the dish.</p>
<p>Cabbage grows best in cooler climates. Growers usually plant it in mountainous areas where temperatures during the summer growing season used to stay mostly below 25 degrees Celsius.</p>
<p>Studies show that warmer weather tied to climate change is now threatening these crops. There may even come a time when it will be too hot for South Korea to be able to grow napa cabbage.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Kimchi in a jar at the Kimchi Culture Institute in Namyangju, South Korea, August 21, 2024. (REUTERS/Kim Soo-hyeon)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/ee2ae5e9-a271-4fc2-95bf-dfb34d4073ef_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Kimchi in a jar at the Kimchi Culture Institute in Namyangju, South Korea, August 21, 2024. (REUTERS/Kim Soo-hyeon)</span></div>
<p>Lee Young-gyu studies diseases that attack plants. He said the best temperatures for cabbage are between 18 and 21 degrees Celsius.</p>
<p>In the fields and in <strong>kitchens</strong> - both in factories and homes - farmers and kimchi makers are already feeling the change.</p>
<p><strong>Spicy</strong>, fermented kimchi is made from other vegetables such as radish, cucumber, and green onion, but the most popular form is still mostly cabbage.</p>
<p>The Agriculture Ministry calls Lee Ha-yeon a Kimchi Master because of her knowledge of kimchi. She said that in higher temperatures, the heart of the cabbage goes bad, and the root softens.</p>
<p>"If this continues, then in the summertime we might have to give up cabbage kimchi," said Lee.</p>
<p><strong>Shrinking crop area</strong></p>
<p>The government <strong>statistics</strong> agency reports the area of highland cabbage farmed last year was about 4,000 hectares. That is less than half of what it was 20 years ago.</p>
<p>The Rural Development Administration, a state farming organization, predicts that the farmed area for napa cabbage will shrink in the next 25 years to just 44 hectares. They expect there will be no cabbage grown in the highlands by 2090.</p>
<p>Researchers point to three reasons for such a small area of crops. They include higher temperatures, unpredictable heavy rains and unwanted insects and diseases that become more difficult to control in the warmer and longer summers.</p>
<p>South Korea's kimchi industry is already fighting lower-priced imports from China, which are mostly served in restaurants. Those imports rose by almost seven percent for the year through the end of July. That is the highest level ever.</p>
<p><strong>New cabbage varieties</strong></p>
<p>The government is trying to prevent high prices and shortages by storing large amounts of cabbage. Scientists are also racing to develop crop <strong>varieties</strong> that can grow in warmer climates, handle changes in rainfall and resist <strong>fungal</strong> infections.</p>
<p>Seventy-one-year-old Kim Si-gap is a farmer who has worked in the cabbage fields of the eastern region of Gangneung all his life. Kim fears these varieties will be more costly to grow. And they might not taste the same.</p>
<p>"When we see the reports that there will come a time in Korea when we can no longer grow cabbage, it was shocking on the one hand and also sad at the same time," Kim said.</p>
<p>"Kimchi is something we cannot not have on the table. What are we going to do if this happens?"</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Sebin Choi, Hyun Young Yi, Daewoung Kim and Jihyun Jeon reported this story for Reuters. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>ferment</strong> – v. to go through a chemical change that results in the production of alcohol</p>
<p><strong>kitchen </strong><em>–n.</em> a room where cooking is done</p>
<p><strong>spicy</strong> - <em>of food: </em>flavored with or containing strong spices and especially ones that cause a burning feeling in your mouth</p>
<p><strong>statistic</strong> – <em>n</em>. number that represents a piece of information (such as information about how often something is done, how common something is, or the like)</p>
<p><strong>variety</strong> <em>– n.</em> a particular kind of person or thing</p>
<p><strong>fungal </strong><em>–adj.</em> related to fungus, a form of life that is neither plant nor animal such as mushrooms</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How to Summarize (2024/9/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/how-to-summarize.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Yutaro in Japan about how to summarize what you hear or read.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/ffd46340-4068-4ddf-9eee-82598b433e09_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>I enjoy listening to VOA Learning English every night. I have a question about "summarizing." How do I summarize a speech, paper, or other <strong>text</strong> I've listened to? I have to improve my summary skills to pass the upcoming entrance exam.</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>Thank you for writing to us, Yutaro. I'm happy to answer this question.</p>
<p>“Summarize” is the verb form of the word “summary.” A summary briefly explains the main ideas of a piece of writing or a speech but does not include all the details. It is often only one or two <strong>paragraphs</strong> long.</p>
<p>Being able to summarize is a useful skill to have, not only for passing exams but also for working in professions. To summarize well, you need to separate the main ideas from less important details.</p>
<p>You can use the following method to do this:</p>
<p>First, read or listen to the material one time without writing any notes. This will help your mind <strong>focus </strong>on understanding the ideas. Next, read or listen again. But this time, write notes and be sure to identify the main ideas along with some details. You can mark main ideas by putting a star next to them, underlining them, or using a colored pen to mark them.</p>
<p>Next, take a separate piece of paper and try to write only the main ideas. Then, decide which details are necessary to include so that the main ideas are clear. Remember, in a summary, you cannot include every detail. This is sometimes difficult to do at first and requires careful thought.</p>
<p>If you can, let a few hours pass between the time when you first take notes and the time when you write the main ideas. This is a good way to see if you can remember and organize the main points in your mind.</p>
<p>You can also try the following method to prepare a summary:</p>
<p>Try to explain the material as if you were talking about it with your friends or family. In those situations, you would naturally just focus on the main ideas and possibly add a few important details. <strong>Practice</strong> explaining the ideas by speaking out loud. When you speak, you will probably discover the things you can explain clearly and those things you need to <strong>check</strong> again.</p>
<p>Finally, you can write the summary, keeping in mind the way you presented the main ideas when you spoke about them.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, do you have a question about American English? Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>text</strong><strong> </strong>–n. written words; a piece of writing</p>
<p><strong>paragraph </strong><em>–n. </em>usually a group of sentences that explain one idea</p>
<p><strong>focus</strong> <em>–v.</em> to direct your attention on something</p>
<p><strong>practice</strong> –v. to do a task several times in an effort to learn it and to do it better</p>
<p><strong>check</strong><strong> </strong>–v. to look or read over something you have already done to make sure it is correct</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Question if Melting Ice in Antarctica Will Continue to Increase (2024/9/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/scientists-question-if-melting-ice-in-antarctica-will-continue-to-increase.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Increasing amounts of ice have been melting on the continent of Antarctica over the past ten years. Now, scientists are wondering if the increase in melting is temporary or if it will continue—and perhaps melt even faster—for years into the future.</p>
<p>Nearly 1,500 experts who study Antarctica gathered in southern Chile last week to share results of their research. They discussed the extreme weather events that struck parts of the continent this year: heavy rainfall, unusually warm temperatures, and strong dry winds.</p>
<p>The researchers say these events added to recent increases in melting. However, detailed weather data for Antarctica dates back only about 40 years. That is one reason climate scientists are unsure if the current melting is temporary or the beginning of a longer <strong>trend</strong>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This 2020 photo provided by the British Antarctic Survey shows the Thwaites glacier in Antarctica. (David Vaughan/British Antarctic Survey via AP, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/fe01afdc-9d71-4e31-90f2-0732713c9818_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This 2020 photo provided by the British Antarctic Survey shows the Thwaites glacier in Antarctica. (David Vaughan/British Antarctic Survey via AP, File)</span></div>
<p>NASA estimates show a possible 58-meter rise in the average worldwide sea level if all Antarctic ice melted. Studies have shown that about a third of the world's population lives below 100 vertical meters of sea level.</p>
<p>Liz Keller is a paleoclimate specialist from the Victoria University of Wellington in New Zealand. She says scientists have never before seen Antarctic ice melting so quickly. She also spoke about the increasing amounts of carbon dioxide gas, CO2, in the earth's atmosphere.</p>
<p>“You might see the same rise in CO2 over thousands of years, and now it's happened in 100 years," Keller said. Carbon dioxide traps heat in the atmosphere.</p>
<p>Mike Weber is a paleooceanographer from the University of Bonn in Germany. He studies the movements of Antarctic ice over thousands of years. He said records dating back 21,000 years show at least eight times when the ice melted quickly. He added that the data show the periods of ice loss sometimes lasted for hundreds of years. This led to much higher sea levels around the world.</p>
<p>Weber said scientists want to know if the melting seen during the last ten years has started a melting trend that will last for centuries.</p>
<p>"Maybe we're entering such a <strong>phase</strong> right now," he said. "If we are, at least for now, there will be no stopping it."</p>
<p>Some of the scientists in Chile agreed that the most harmful rise in sea level can still be avoided if fossil fuel <strong>emissions</strong> decrease. Weber noted that when glaciers melt, the earth's land can rise because there is less weight pushing it down. Recent research suggests that if the melting does not happen too quickly, the rising land could nearly equal the rise in sea level. But if the melting happens too quickly, the rise in land could not meet the increase in sea level.</p>
<p>"If we keep emissions low, we can stop this eventually," said Weber. "If we keep them high, we have a runaway situation and we cannot do anything."</p>
<p>Mathieu Casado is a paleoclimate and polar meteorologist at France's Climate and Environment Sciences Laboratory. He has examined ice from all over Antarctica to estimate temperatures dating back 800,000 years.</p>
<p>Casado said that the last time the Earth was this warm was 125,000 years ago and that sea levels then were 6 to 9 meters higher. He and other scientists said the speed and amount at which carbon is entering the atmosphere has never been so high.</p>
<p>Gino Casassa is a glaciologist and head of the Chilean Antarctic Institute. He said that current estimates show sea levels rising by 4 meters by 2100 and more if emissions continue to grow.</p>
<p>"What happens in Antarctica doesn't stay in Antarctica," said Casassa, adding that global atmospheric, ocean and weather systems are linked to the continent.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Alexander Villegas reported this story for Reuters news agency. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>trend </strong><em>-n. </em>a tendency or development continuing over a period of time</p>
<p><strong>phase </strong><em>-n. </em>a particular stage or period of time in a process</p>
<p><strong>emissions </strong><em>-n. </em>gases released into the atmosphere</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Japan Considers Four-day Work Weeks (2024/9/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/japan-considers-four-day-work-weeks.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Japan is a nation so hardworking that the Japanese language has a term for working oneself to death. Now, the government is trying to deal with a labor shortage.</p>
<p>One solution is to get more people and companies to accept four-day workweeks. The Japanese government first supported a shorter working week in 2021. Few companies have signed on, however. The Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare said only about eight percent of companies permit three days off a week, while seven percent give their workers the required one day off.</p>
<p>Hoping to get small and medium-sized businesses to change, the government started a "work style reform" campaign. It pushes shorter hours and other <strong>flexible </strong>plans for work along with paid time off and limits on overtime. The labor ministry recently started offering free services and resources to help companies make the change.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Commuters walk in a passageway during a rush hour at Shinagawa Station, Feb. 14, 2024, in Tokyo. " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/83f41a40-d8a8-4b01-9e53-5818368a08f8_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Commuters walk in a passageway during a rush hour at Shinagawa Station, Feb. 14, 2024, in Tokyo. </span></div>
<p><strong>'Innovating how we work'</strong></p>
<p>A ministry website explains the "hatarakikata kaikaku" campaign, which means "<strong>innovating</strong> how we work." It says that when workers can choose how they work, they will have a better outlook on the future and the economy will grow.</p>
<p>The department handling the new support services for businesses says only about three companies have asked for their advice.</p>
<p>Such changes will not come easily in the Japanese culture, where being a “workaholic,” or frequently working overtime, has long been highly valued. That is credited for the country's national recovery and fast economic growth after World War II.</p>
<p>There is great pressure to be the same as the others in one's work group. People usually take vacations at the same time of year as their co-workers. Although the law and labor agreements limit overtime, some work longer hours without pay.</p>
<p><strong>Death from overwork</strong></p>
<p>A recent government report dealt with "karoshi." That is the Japanese term meaning "death from overwork.” The report said Japan has at least 54 such deaths a year, including from heart attacks.</p>
<p>Tim Craig wrote a book called <em>Cool Japan: Case Studies from Japan's Cultural and Creative Industries</em>.</p>
<p>"Work is a big deal here. It's not just a way to make money, although it is that, too," said Craig.</p>
<p>Some officials think it is time to change that way of thinking to save the workforce. Japan's birth rate continues to fall, and the work culture is said to be one reason for that. Government reports expect that, at the current rate, the working age population will drop by 40 percent to 45 million by 2065.</p>
<p>Supporters of the three-days-off model say it helps people remain in the workforce longer. It would give them more time to raise children and care for older relatives. For retirees living on retirement pensions, it would provide additional income.</p>
<p><strong>More time for family</strong></p>
<p>Akiko Yokohama works at Spelldata, a technology company that lets employees work a four-day work week. She takes Wednesdays off along with Saturdays and Sundays. The extra day off allows her to get her hair done, go to other <strong>appointments</strong> or go shopping.</p>
<p>Her husband works in real estate. He also gets Wednesdays off but works weekends, which is common in his industry. Yokohama said that it lets <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_VCzGJW20">her</a> and her husband go on midweek family outings with their elementary-school age child.</p>
<p>But there are signs of change. A few companies, including Uniqlo, Ricoh and Hitachi have begun offering a four-day workweek.</p>
<p>A recent Gallup public opinion study measured employee <strong>engagement</strong>. Gallup said Japan has among the least engaged workers of all nationalities it has studied. Only six percent of the Japanese who answered described themselves as engaged at work compared to the worldwide average of 23 percent.</p>
<p>That means relatively few Japanese workers felt happy and highly involved in their workplace. Most were putting in their hours without investing <strong>passion</strong> or energy.</p>
<p>Kanako Ogino is president of Tokyo-based NS Group. She thinks offering flexible hours is needed for filling jobs in the service industry, where women are most of the work force. The company offers 30 different <strong>scheduling</strong> patterns, including a four-day workweek, but also taking long periods off in between work.</p>
<p>To ensure none of the NS Group's workers feel out of place for choosing a different schedule, Ogino asks each of her 4,000 employees twice a year how they want to work. Voicing your own needs is disapproved in Japan, where you are expected to sacrifice for the common good.</p>
<p>"The view in Japan was: You are cool the more hours you work, putting in free overtime," Ogino said with a laugh. "But there is no dream in such a life."</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins. And I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Yuri Kageyama reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>flexible</strong> – <em>adj</em>. easily changed</p>
<p><strong>overtime </strong>– <em>n</em>. time spent working at your job that is in addition to your normal working hours</p>
<p><strong>innovate</strong> – <em>v</em>. to do something in a new way</p>
<p><strong>appointment </strong>–n. an activity that you need to go to at a certain time such as a visit to a doctor or dentist</p>
<p><strong>engagement</strong> – <em>n</em>. the act or state of being involved with something</p>
<p><strong>passion</strong> – <em>n</em>. a strong feeling of enthusiasm or excitement for something or about doing something</p>
<p><strong>schedule</strong> – <em>v</em>. to plan (something) at a certain time</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Bob Dylan Teaches You about Questions, Count Nouns (2024/9/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/bob-dylan-teaches-you-about-questions-count-nouns.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Nobel prize winner Bob Dylan is considered to be one of the best American <strong>songwriters</strong>.</p>
<p><em>The answer, my friend, is blowin' in the wind </em></p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/751c1814-7982-4e08-8553-d7162a1152b4_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p><em>The answer is blowin' in the wind</em></p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p>In today's <em>Everyday Grammar</em>, we will explore how <em>Blowin' in the Wind</em>, a famous Bob Dylan song, can teach you about English grammar. You will learn about question words, nouns and more.</p>
<p>Let's begin by listening to part of the song:</p>
<p><strong>Blowin' in the Wind</strong></p>
<p><em>Yes, and how many years must a mountain exist </em></p>
<p><em>Before it is washed to the sea? </em></p>
<p><em>And how many years can some people exist </em></p>
<p><em>Before they're allowed to be free?</em></p>
<p>Dylan's song has a group of questions, one after the other, followed by an answer:</p>
<p><em>The answer, my friend, is blowin' in the wind </em></p>
<p><em>The answer is blowin' in the wind</em></p>
<p><strong>Questions</strong></p>
<p>Let's explore the grammar of the words in greater detail. In English, we use question words – what, where, how - to ask for information.</p>
<p>The word “how” generally asks about manner – the way in which something is done. For example, imagine you saw a <strong>circus</strong> performer swallow fire.</p>
<p>You might ask them:</p>
<p><em>How did you do that?</em></p>
<p>But when used with words such as “much” and “many,” how asks about <strong>quantities</strong>.</p>
<p>For example, you might hear an American ask the following about a price:</p>
<p><em>How much money does it cost?</em></p>
<p>Or</p>
<p><em>How much [money] does it cost?</em></p>
<p>Here is another example of a quantity question:</p>
<p><em>How many people came to the Bob Dylan concert?</em></p>
<p>But, how do we know when to use “much” and when to use “many?</p>
<p><strong>Noncount vs. count nouns</strong></p>
<p>The answer is about nouns.</p>
<p>We describe nouns as either common or proper. Common nouns include words such as music, song or guitar. The words themselves do not point to an exact, specific thing. Proper nouns include words with an exact, single meaning - Bob Dylan, the United States of America, <em>Blowin' in the Wind</em> and so on.</p>
<p>There are two kinds of common nouns – count and noncount nouns. Count nouns include words like guitar or song. You can count guitars and songs. Consider the following statements:</p>
<p><em>I own five guitars. </em></p>
<p><em>I wrote 3 songs.</em></p>
<p>The question form “how many...” is used with plural count nouns. For example:</p>
<p><em>How many guitars do you own? </em></p>
<p><em>I own five guitars.</em></p>
<p>Noncount nouns include words like money or music.</p>
<p><em>I need to make money. </em></p>
<p><em>I love music.</em></p>
<p>In general, the question form “how much...” is used with noncount nouns.</p>
<p><em>How much money did you spend on that new guitar? </em></p>
<p><em>I spent all of the money that I earned last week!</em></p>
<p>How does this discussion connect with the Bob Dylan song?</p>
<p><strong>A series of questions using countable nouns</strong></p>
<p>If you listen carefully to the Bob Dylan song, you will notice that the structure “how many...” plays an important part.</p>
<p><em>Yes, and how many times can a man turn his head</em></p>
<p><em>And<strong> pretend</strong> that he just doesn't see? </em></p>
<p>And consider these lines:</p>
<p><em>Yes, and how many ears must one man have </em></p>
<p><em>Before he can hear people cry? </em></p>
<p><em>Yes, and how many deaths will it take till he knows </em></p>
<p><em>That too many people have died?</em></p>
<p>Questions about count nouns make the base of Dylan's song. He does not sing about noncount nouns. He does not ask “how much...”?</p>
<p>And the answer to his questions is always the same:</p>
<p><em>The answer, my friend, is blowin' in the wind </em></p>
<p><em>The answer is blowin' in the wind</em></p>
<p><strong>Closing thoughts</strong></p>
<p>The next time you listen to any song in English, try to look for some kind of <strong>pattern</strong>.</p>
<p>One way to think about Dylan's song is that it is about questions, answers and count nouns. But other songs have different structures, ideas and grammar points. By carefully studying songs, you can learn a lot about English grammar.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>John Russell wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. Caty Weaver was the editor.</em></p><div id="bottom">
<ins class="adsbygoogle" data-ad-client="ca-pub-3585518775245612" data-ad-format="auto" data-ad-slot="9284795419" data-full-width-responsive="true" style="display:block; text-align:center;"></ins>
<script>(adsbygoogle =window.adsbygoogle ||[]).push({});</script></div>
<p><em>______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>songwriter</strong> <em>– n.</em> a person who writes the words or music to songs</p>
<p><strong>quantity </strong><em>– n.</em> an amount or number of something</p>
<p><strong>pretend</strong><em> – v.</em> to act as if something is true when it is not true</p>
<p><strong>ear </strong><em>– n.</em> the part of the body that you hear with</p>
<p><strong>pattern</strong><em> – n.</em> the regular and repeated way in which something happens or is done</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Tech Tip: How to Make Your Smartphone Last Longer (2024/9/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/tech-tip-how-to-make-your-smartphone-last-longer.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">04 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Many people are now holding on to their smartphones longer than in the past. This is true for several reasons. The cost of phones has been rising for years. And device <strong>updates</strong> are no longer as meaningful as before.</p>
<p>This has made it even more important for smartphone users to take good care of their devices. But how long can a smartphone user expect their device to last? Many experts say if they are cared for effectively, phones can last up to five years, possibly even longer.</p>
<p>Chris Hauk is a technology expert with the website <a class="wsw__a" href="https://pixelprivacy.com/">Pixel Privacy</a>. He told The Associated Press (AP), “As long as you take care of your phone and keep it updated, you're going to get at least four or five good years of use out of it."</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file photo, the iPhone 15 Pro is shown after its introduction on the Apple campus, Sept. 12, 2023, in Cupertino, Calif. (AP Photo/Jeff Chiu, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-b1df-08dcc937ae4b_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">In this file photo, the iPhone 15 Pro is shown after its introduction on the Apple campus, Sept. 12, 2023, in Cupertino, Calif. (AP Photo/Jeff Chiu, File)</span></div>
<p>The AP offers these additional tips for smartphone users looking to keep their devices for as long as possible.</p>
<p><strong>Battery care</strong></p>
<p>One of the most important elements affecting smartphone life is the <strong>battery</strong>.</p>
<p>iPhone maker Apple <a class="wsw__a" href="https://support.apple.com/en-gb/105105">says</a> a rechargeable battery's age has little to do with when it was manufactured. Instead, it depends on a complex mix of things, including temperature and charging history. “As lithium-ion batteries chemically age, the amount of charge they can hold <strong>diminishes</strong>, resulting in reduced battery life and reduced <strong>peak </strong>performance,” Apple says.</p>
<p>Samsung, which uses the Android operating system in its smartphones, says its lithium-ion batteries perform best when kept above a 50 percent charge. The company advises against running the battery completely down.</p>
<p>In an <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.samsung.com/nz/support/mobile-devices/tips-for-battery-charging-and-how-to-make-your-battery-last-longer/?srsltid=AfmBOoqq5ryP3FW-5ayEv5LdwNOY3djQadld6M7Z_oX6FA4azys6RGJK">online guide</a>, Samsung also said that repeatedly letting the battery go to zero percent may shorten its life and decrease overall performance. “If this happens, you'll need to charge the battery more frequently and it may last only a few hours before needing a charge.”</p>
<p><strong>Avoid extreme temperatures</strong></p>
<p>Apple says its batteries already warm up as they charge, so phones should not be charged in very hot temperatures. Charging an iPhone in heat above 35 degrees Celsius, for example, “can permanently reduce battery lifespan.”</p>
<p>Samsung also says extreme heat or cold can damage batteries. It warns users not to leave their phones inside vehicles or other contained spaces in very hot or cold weather.</p>
<p>Google created the Android operating system and makes Pixel smartphones. It warns that hot batteries lose power faster, even when not being used.</p>
<p><strong>Change your power settings </strong></p>
<p>Look at changing your smartphone settings so <strong>apps</strong> and other device operations use less power. Doing this can extend your battery's daily life and give more time between charges.</p>
<p>Examples include turning down the phone's screen brightness, changing to a dark theme and making the screen power off sooner. You can also look at battery usage in the device's settings to identify power-hungry apps that can be turned off or removed.</p>
<p>Also, if an iPhone's power level drops below 10 percent, users can turn on the low power setting to stretch battery life before the next charge. Android phones have a similar “power saving mode.” But while this setting can be left on all the time, experts say doing so can affect the phone's overall performance.</p>
<p>Samsung says another power-saving move is to turn off Bluetooth or Wi-Fi when they are not being used. Apple, however, advises iPhone users to leave these on because they use very little power when not connected.</p>
<p><strong>Use protection</strong></p>
<p>Many smartphone users already know the benefits of using screen protectors and device cases. Experts advise not using plastic versions, which can damage the phone's face. Device website iFixit suggests choosing ones made with either Thermoplastic polyurethane (TPU) material – which combines both plastic and rubber – or <strong>tempered </strong>glass. Both offer more solid protection.</p>
<p><strong>Keep your device clean</strong></p>
<p>Smartphones can collect dirt and other materials that can block port openings and hurt performance. Experts say a toothpick or toothbrush can be used to get rid of much of these substances. But they advise users to make sure the process is removing the material, not pushing it deeper inside.</p>
<p><strong>Update your device</strong></p>
<p>Software is another important part in extending a phone's lifespan. Experts suggest downloading the latest operating system updates often. This will limit problems related to the device's privacy, security and battery operations.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>update</strong> <em>– n. </em>when new information or features are added to an existing thing</p>
<p><strong>battery</strong> <em>– n. </em>a device that chemically stores electricity so it can be used as direct current in electrical circuits such as computers and motors</p>
<p><strong>diminish </strong><em>– </em><em>v. </em>to become less or to make something become less</p>
<p><strong>peak </strong><em>– adj.</em> the highest level or value of something</p>
<p><strong>app</strong> <em>– n. </em>a computer program that is designed to do one task or set of tasks and is usually aimed at use on mobile devices</p>
<p><strong>tempered </strong><em>– </em><em>adj. </em>treated with material to increase the strength and effectiveness of something</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Employers Use Wearable Devices to Measure Workers’ Temperature (2024/9/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/employers-use-wearable-devices-to-measure-workers-temperature.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">04 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>On a hot summer day, workers recently worked to remove asbestos and <strong>hazardous</strong> waste at Oak Ridge National Laboratory in Tennessee. It is a former nuclear center that the government wants to tear down.</p>
<p>The men wore full-body protective clothing and used respirators to clean the air they breathe. But the clothing does not protect them from high temperatures inside the building and inside their heavy clothing. On their arms, they wear devices that record their heart rates, movements and levels of exertion. The aim is to look for heat stress.</p>
<p>Stephanie Miller oversees safety and health for the company responsible for the cleanup. She watches a computer to observe each worker's data looking for danger of overheating.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="A SlateSafety armband is worn by Wyatt Fischer, a furnace mason employee at Cardinal Glass, Thursday, Aug. 22, 2024, in Menomonie, Wis. (AP Photo/Abbie Parr)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-88ab-08dcc6a89151_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">A SlateSafety armband is worn by Wyatt Fischer, a furnace mason employee at Cardinal Glass, Thursday, Aug. 22, 2024, in Menomonie, Wis. (AP Photo/Abbie Parr)</span></div>
<p>Miller said, “Heat is one of the greatest risks that we have in this work, even though we deal with high radiation, hazardous chemicals and heavy metals.”</p>
<p><strong>Heat in the workplace</strong></p>
<p>The issue of heat in the workplace has been getting more attention since a 2021 report from the research organization Atlantic Council. The group said the United States loses an average of $100 billion each year from “heat-<strong>induced</strong>” reductions in productivity.</p>
<p>The Environmental Protection Agency said from 1992 to 2022, 986 people died from heat-related causes in U.S. workplaces.</p>
<p>Employers have measured heat-related stress by checking employees' temperatures with thermometers. More recently, firefighters and military members have swallowed thermometer <strong>capsules</strong>.</p>
<p>As the world experiences record-high temperatures, employers are exploring wearable technologies, like <strong>sensors</strong> and <strong>armbands</strong>, to help keep workers safe. They collect body temperature and warn workers to take breaks when they get too hot.</p>
<p>Perrigo, a drug company, gave SlateSafety <strong>armbands</strong> to more than 100 employees at its baby food factory. The devices estimate the wearer's body temperature. A reading of 101.3 results in an alert, or a warning.</p>
<p>Another device from the Massachusetts company Epicore Biosystems uses sweat to find out if a worker is overheating.</p>
<p>Experts say the effectiveness of some devices remains unproven although research has shown that some successfully predict body temperature. A 2022 study said age, sex, and the amount of water in the air make it difficult to measure body temperature.</p>
<p><strong>Privacy concerns</strong></p>
<p>However, some groups worry that employers will use the technology to punish people for taking needed breaks.</p>
<p>Travis Parsons is with the Laborers' Health and Safety Fund of North America, a labor rights group. Parsons said, “Any time you put a device on a worker, they're very concerned about <strong>tracking</strong>, privacy, and how are you going to use this against me.”</p>
<p>United Cleanup Oak Ridge is the partnership that is responsible for cleaning up the nuclear reactor in Tennessee. The company says it uses medical examinations to make work decisions. Miller, the health supervisor said the company sent a few employees to see their personal doctors who found out they had heart problems.</p>
<p>At Perrigo, safety official Rob Somers said supervisors look at information on people with several alerts and speak to them to see if there is “a reason why they're not able to work in the environment.”</p>
<p>Adam Schwartz is with the Electronic Frontiers Foundation, a civil liberties group based in San Francisco. He said the idea that companies could keep years of medical information on employees raises privacy concerns. He said the information could be used to withhold health plans or dismiss workers.</p>
<p>Schwartz said, “The device could hurt...because you could raise your hand and say, ‘I need a break,' and the boss could say, ‘No, your heart rate is not <strong>elevated</strong>, go back to work.'”</p>
<p>To reduce such risks, employers should permit workers to accept or reject using the devices. They could process only necessary information and <strong>delete</strong> the information in 24 hours, Schwartz said.</p>
<p>Ikusei Misaka, a professor at Tokyo's Musashino University, raised another concern. Misaka noted that information gathered from wearing such devices could result in workers getting unwanted marketing for goods or services.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Cathy Bussewitz reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>hazardous</strong> <em>–adj. </em>dangerous</p>
<p><strong>-induced </strong><em>–adj.</em> -produced</p>
<p><strong>capsule </strong>–n. a rounded piece of medicine or medical device meant to be swallowed</p>
<p><strong>sensor </strong>–n. an electrical device that measures something in the physical world and turns it into an electrical signal</p>
<p><strong>armband </strong><em>–n.</em> something that is worn on the arm that can have a device attached to it</p>
<p><strong>tracking</strong> <em>–n. </em>following something or someone to find out more about it</p>
<p><strong>elevate </strong><em>–v.</em> to lift something up or bring it to a higher level</p>
<p><strong>delete </strong><em>–v.</em> to completely remove something so that it is no longer there</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Women in Chad Seek Right to Own, Control Land (2024/9/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/women-in-chad-seek-right-to-own-control-land.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>When Milla Nemoudji <strong>divorced </strong>her husband following years of physical abuse, she found herself without a way to earn a living. The 28-year-old lived in a village in southern Chad. Though she grew up in a farming family, she struggled to earn money in a community where men usually control <strong>access</strong> to land.</p>
<p>Divorce is rare in Chad, and she received little support. She sold fruits and other goods. And in the rainy season, she worked in fields as a laborer.</p>
<p>Last year, however, she joined a women's collective that arrived in her village, Binmar. The village is just outside of Chad's second-largest city, Moundou.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Twenty-eight-year-old Milla Nemoudji, a woman who was divorced by her husband following years of physical abuse, is photographed in a village of Binmar, Chad, Friday, July 19, 2024. (AP Photo/Robert Bociaga)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-2abd-08dcc8ffb2d0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Twenty-eight-year-old Milla Nemoudji, a woman who was divorced by her husband following years of physical abuse, is photographed in a village of Binmar, Chad, Friday, July 19, 2024. (AP Photo/Robert Bociaga)
</span></div>
<p>The collective gave Nemoudji access to land. It also gave her the ability to make decisions on its use. She farmed cotton, peanuts and sesame and earned enough money to pay for basic needs.</p>
<p>The struggle for land rights comes from Chad's dual legal system. Recent government laws give any citizen the right to own land. But in rural areas, people follow customary law instead of the modern government's law. And village chiefs control who can use land.</p>
<p>The village chiefs require yearly payments. Women in these villages often cannot own or <strong>inherit</strong> land. That leaves them dependent on male family members. It also limits their chance to have more influence in their society. And it gives them fewer choices when they are the victims of <strong>domestic violence</strong>.</p>
<p>Nemoudji told reporters with the Associated Press, "There's no one to come to your aid, although everyone knows that you are suffering.”</p>
<p>She added, "If women weren't losing access to farmlands, they would dare to leave their husbands earlier."</p>
<p><strong>Collective land use</strong></p>
<p>Adèle Noudjilembaye founded N-Bio Solutions, the collective Nemoudji joined, in 2018. It is a rare program in Chad that negotiates on behalf of women with traditional chiefs. The chiefs connect the collective to local people with available land they are willing to <strong>lease</strong>.</p>
<p>Noudjilembaye runs five collectives so far, and each has around 25 members.</p>
<p>These efforts are slowly gaining popularity. But Noudjilembaye said that some women who face domestic violence do not leave their situation “because of financial dependency, fear of societal judgement or lack of support.”</p>
<p>In Chad, life is difficult for women who attempt to <strong>assert</strong> their rights.</p>
<p>"The system failed me when I sought help after my husband burned down my house," Nemoudji said. When she reported the incident to the village chief, "nothing was done to solve my dispute."</p>
<p>Despite the lack of support from village leaders and local officials, Nemoudji and other women in Binmar have found strength in the collective.</p>
<p>Marie Depaque is another village woman who struggled financially after her second husband refused to support her children from her first marriage. She said, "Our fight for land rights is not just about economic survival but also about justice, equality and the hope for a better future."</p>
<p>Nemoudji dreams of better educational <strong>opportunities</strong> for the children in her community so they can break the cycle of poverty and violence. She works in the community for changes in the land ownership system.</p>
<p>"Knowing my rights means I can seek help from <strong>authorities</strong> and demand justice," she said.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Robert Bociaga reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>divorce</strong> – v. to legally end your marriage with (your husband or wife)</p>
<p><strong>access</strong> – <em>n</em>. a way of being able to use or get something</p>
<p><strong>inherit</strong> – <em>v</em>. to receive (money, property, etc.) from someone when that person dies</p>
<p><strong>domestic violence</strong> – <em>n.</em> violent or aggressive behavior within the home, typically involving the violent abuse of a spouse or partner.</p>
<p><strong>lease</strong> – <em>v. </em>to create a legal agreement that lets someone use a car, house, or land for a period of time in return for payment</p>
<p><strong>assert</strong> – <em>v</em>. to state (something) in a strong and definite way</p>
<p><strong>opportunity</strong> – <em>n</em>. an amount of time or a situation in which something can be done</p>
<p><strong>authorities</strong> – <em>n</em>. <em>(pl.)</em> people who have power to make decisions and enforce rules and laws</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Why Is Polio Still a Problem? (2024/9/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/why-is-polio-still-a-problem.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Polio was driven out of much of the world more than 30 years ago after a series of successful vaccination campaigns. But the viral disease is still spreading in a small number of nations.</p>
<p>The recent discovery of the first polio case in Gaza in 25 years led world health officials to set new goals to get rid of the disease in all areas.</p>
<p><strong>What is polio?</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A Palestinian child is vaccinated against polio, amid the Israel-Hamas conflict, in Deir Al-Balah in the central Gaza Strip, September 1, 2024. (REUTERS/Hussam Al-Masri)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/cf690179-c80a-4f07-ab79-af98aac4e9e4_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A Palestinian child is vaccinated against polio, amid the Israel-Hamas conflict, in Deir Al-Balah in the central Gaza Strip, September 1, 2024. (REUTERS/Hussam Al-Masri)</span></div>
<p>Polio is an infection caused by a virus that mostly affects children under the age of five. Most infected people do not have any <strong>symptoms</strong>. But some can experience a high body temperature, headaches, <strong>vomiting</strong> and <strong>stiffness</strong> of the backbone, or spine.</p>
<p>The World Health Organization (WHO) says polio can affect the nervous system and cause <strong>paralysis</strong> within hours. The U.N. agency estimates 1 in 200 polio cases results in permanent paralysis, usually of the legs. Among children who are paralyzed, up to 10 percent die when their breathing muscles stop working.</p>
<p>The virus spreads from person to person, entering the body though the mouth. It is most often spread through contact with the waste from an infected person. Sometimes, it is also passed through water or food.</p>
<p><strong>How bad was polio in the past?</strong></p>
<p>Polio has existed for hundreds of years. The Associated Press says that Ancient Egyptian writings show children using sticks to walk and having wasted legs or arms, suggesting the effects of polio.</p>
<p>Before the first vaccine was developed in the 1950s, polio was among the world's most feared diseases. A 1916 outbreak in New York killed more than 2,000 people. The worst recorded U.S. outbreak in 1952 killed more than 3,000 people. Many who survived polio suffered lifelong effects, including paralysis and deformed limbs. Others whose breathing muscles were paralyzed required specialized lung treatments.</p>
<p><strong>When did the campaign to destroy polio begin?</strong></p>
<p>The WHO passed a resolution in 1988 calling for polio to be eradicated, or destroyed, worldwide. The effort followed a successful campaign against smallpox eight years earlier.</p>
<p>The WHO's first plan was to <strong>eradicate</strong> polio by 2000. The U.N. agency cooperated with the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, UNICEF and Rotary International. The campaign centered on increasing the production of a vaccine and launching vaccination efforts. As a result, polio cases dropped by more than 99 percent.</p>
<p>Afghanistan and Pakistan are the only countries where the spread of polio has never been stopped. There have also been outbreaks in several other countries, mostly in Africa. The WHO and its partners now aim to eradicate polio by 2026.</p>
<p><strong>Why have efforts to fight polio taken so long?</strong></p>
<p>Health experts say stopping polio outbreaks requires vaccinating at least 95 percent of the world's population. Vaccinating people is more difficult in nations that have conflicts or weak health systems.</p>
<p>The vaccine given by mouth does not cost a lot to manufacture and is better at preventing infection. But it contains weakened, live polio virus. In rare cases, the vaccine can spread or cause polio in unvaccinated people. In even rarer cases, live virus from the vaccine can <strong>mutate</strong> into a new form that could start new outbreaks.</p>
<p>Health officials have become more successful at reducing the number of cases caused by the natural polio virus. The majority of infections in the world today are related to the vaccine.</p>
<p>Scott Barrett is a professor at Columbia University in New York City who has studied polio eradication. He told the AP, “The problem with trying to eradicate polio is that the need for <strong>perfection</strong> is so great and there are so many weak links.” He added that while the technical ability to destroy polio exists, “We live in a <strong>vastly</strong> imperfect world.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>symptom </strong><em>– n. </em>a physical feeling or problem that suggests a person has a particular sickness</p>
<p><strong>vomit </strong><em>–v.</em> to expel what is in the stomach through the mouth</p>
<p><strong>stiffness </strong><em>–n. </em>a difficulty in either slowness or pain in moving a part of the body</p>
<p><strong>paralysis</strong> <em>– n. </em>being unable to move all of part of the body because of sickness or injury</p>
<p><strong>eradicate </strong><em>–v.</em> to completely remove or destroy</p>
<p><strong>mutate </strong><em>– </em><em>v. </em>to cause a gene to change and create an unusual characteristic in a plant or animal</p>
<p><strong>perfection </strong><em>–n.</em> a state in which no error or fault exists</p>
<p><strong>vastly </strong><em>– adv.</em> to a very large extent</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Schools Use Money, Fun, Support to Get Students to Class (2024/9/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/us-schools-use-money-fun-support-to-get-students-to-class.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Flerentin Jean-Baptiste missed school so often that he had to repeat his first year at Medford High School near Boston.</p>
<p>Jean-Baptiste said, at school, "You do the same thing every day." He was <strong>absent</strong> 30 days in his first year.</p>
<p>Then the <strong>principal</strong> of the school did something different: She let students play organized sports during lunch — if they attended all their classes. In other words, she offered high school students a play period that is usually part of the school day for young children.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Flerentin “Flex” Jean-Baptiste, 16, of Medford, Mass., poses for a photo at Medford High School, Friday, Aug. 2, 2024, in Medford. (AP Photo/Josh Reynolds)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-a769-08dcc0c19c33_cx1_cy0_cw84_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Flerentin “Flex” Jean-Baptiste, 16, of Medford, Mass., poses for a photo at Medford High School, Friday, Aug. 2, 2024, in Medford. (AP Photo/Josh Reynolds)</span></div>
<p>"It gave me something to look forward to," said 16-year-old Jean-Baptiste. The following year, he cut his absences in half. Schoolwide, the share of regularly absent students dropped from 35 percent in March 2023 to 23 percent in March 2024. That was one of the biggest reductions among Massachusetts high schools.</p>
<p>The Associated Press and Stanford University economist Thomas Dee have studied attendance numbers from 42 states and Washington, D.C. They found that years after the school closings from the COVID-19 pandemic, schools in nearly every state are still struggling with attendance.</p>
<p>About one in four students in the 2022-23 school year were <strong>chronically</strong> absent. That means they missed at least 10 percent of the school year. That number represents about 12 million children in states reporting numbers of absent students.</p>
<p>Before the pandemic, only 15 percent of students missed school that often.</p>
<p>After spending as much as a year at home during the pandemic, many children see school as more than they can handle, uninteresting or socially <strong>stressful</strong>. Some children and parents are deciding it is no problem to stay home. That makes completing class work even harder.</p>
<p>In all but one state, Arkansas, absence rates remain higher than they were before the pandemic. Still, the problem appears to have passed its highest point; almost every state saw absenteeism go down at least a little during the two full school years ending in 2023.</p>
<p>Schools are trying to identify students with attendance problems so they can help. They are also trying to communicate better with parents. Some parents might not know their child is missing a lot of school or its effects on their performance.</p>
<p>Experts say schools must get creative to meet their students' needs.</p>
<p><strong>Pay money or care about students</strong></p>
<p>In Oakland, California, chronic absenteeism in public schools sharply rose from 29 percent before the pandemic to 53 percent during the 2022-23 school year. Officials asked students what would make them want to come to class. They answered, money and a <strong>mentor</strong>.</p>
<p>In spring 2023, the Oakland school district received a <strong>grant</strong> to pay 45 students $50 weekly to attend school every day. Sixty percent of those in the program improved their attendance. Zaia Vera is the district's head of social-emotional learning. Vera said paying students cannot continue for a long time, but many absent students lacked dependable housing or were helping to support their families. "The money is the <strong>hook</strong> that got them in the door."</p>
<p>A caring teacher made a difference for 18-year-old Golden Tachiquin. She completed her studies at Oakland's Skyline High School this spring. Coming back to school after the pandemic, she felt lost and <strong>anxious</strong>. She later realized these feelings made her feel physically sick. She was absent at least 25 days that year.</p>
<p>One Afro-Latina teacher seemed to understand her culturally and made Tachiquin feel she belonged in class. Tachiquin already received good grades.</p>
<p>In Massachusetts, Medford High School requires administrators to welcome and talk with students each morning, especially those who miss a lot of class.</p>
<p>But playtime at lunch has had the greatest effect on improved attendance, Principal Marta Cabral said. High school students need freedom and a chance to move their bodies, she said. "They're here for seven hours a day. They should have a little fun."</p>
<p><strong>Long-term problems</strong></p>
<p>Many of the reasons given for students missing school early in the pandemic are still in place. They include financial difficulty, transportation problems, mild illness and mental health struggles.</p>
<p>For example, a study from the University of Southern California said parents reported that almost one fourth of chronically absent students had emotional or behavioral problems, compared with just seven percent of those with good attendance.</p>
<p>At Fresno's Fort Miller Middle School, half of the students were chronically absent. Two reasons kept coming up: dirty clothing and no transportation. The school bought a washer and dryer for families to use. It also provided a vehicle to pick up students who missed the bus. Fresno's chronic absenteeism improved to 35 percent during the school year ending in 2023.</p>
<p>Fourteen-year-old Melinda Gonzalez missed the school bus about once a week. So, she called for rides from the school vehicle.</p>
<p>"I don't have a car; my parents couldn't drive me to school," Gonzalez said. "Getting that ride made a big difference."</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p>And I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jocelyn Gecker, Bianca Vázquez Toness and Sharon Lurye reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>absent</strong><em> – adj.</em> not present at a usual or expected place</p>
<p><strong>chronically</strong> – adv. in a way that is continuing or occurring again and again for a long time</p>
<p><strong>stressful</strong><em> – adj.</em> making you feel worried or anxious</p>
<p><strong>mentor</strong> – <em>n</em>. someone who teaches or gives help and advice to a less experienced and often younger person</p>
<p><strong>grant </strong><em>–n.</em> an amount of money from a government or organization meant for a specific purpose and which does not have to be repaid</p>
<p><strong>hook</strong> – <em>n. </em>something (such as part of a song) that attracts people's attention</p>
<p><strong>anxious</strong> – <em>adj</em>. afraid or nervous especially about what may happen</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Ukraine's Children Celebrate First Day of School, But Missiles Still Fly (2024/9/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/ukraine-s-children-celebrate-first-day-of-school-but-missiles-still-fly.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Schoolchildren in the southern Ukrainian city Zaporizhzhia celebrated the traditional first day of school on Sunday. The ceremonies began just hours after warnings of Russian air raids sounded through the city.</p>
<p>Zaporizhzhia is just 40 kilometers from the war's front. That danger is never far from the minds of teachers and families at one of the city's schools.</p>
<p>Russian artillery and missiles strike there so often that local officials were forced to ban large gatherings. Only students starting their first and last years could take part in the ceremony.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="First-graders attend the traditional ceremony for the first day of school in Zaporizhzhia, Ukraine, Sunday Sept. 1, 2024. (AP Photo/Evgeniy Maloletka)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/17dfd924-8623-4c5c-86f9-bda21cb4ef31_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">First-graders attend the traditional ceremony for the first day of school in Zaporizhzhia, Ukraine, Sunday Sept. 1, 2024. (AP Photo/Evgeniy Maloletka)
</span></div>
<p>The Associated Press is not identifying the school for security reasons.</p>
<p><strong>Limited space in shelter</strong></p>
<p>The children wore traditional Ukrainian clothing and carried flowers. Each first year student held the hand of a final year student in a small parade.</p>
<p>The school once had 800 students but about 300 fled the city seeking safer places. The remaining children <strong>alternate</strong> one week of study at school with one week of online study. That is because the school's bomb shelter can hold only around 250 people.</p>
<p>That shelter is about 75 meters away from the main school building, across an open playground. School director Kostiantyn Lypskyi said the youngest students work in a classroom just above the underground shelter. The rest of the school operates in the main building.</p>
<p><strong>Lessons held underground</strong></p>
<p>“We prepared everything for the new school year. We equipped the <strong>bunker</strong> in case of air <strong>alarms</strong>, so children will have a safe space because our school will continue lessons during the air raid alarms in the bunker,” he said.</p>
<p>Sunday's ceremony went on without problems.</p>
<p>Olha Komarova-Lesko is the mother of an 11th <strong>grader</strong> and a 6th grader. She said she was hopeful for the coming school year. She sees it as the best solution for the present conditions.</p>
<p>“We are happy that the children had the chance to go to the celebration today just as in the prewar times,” she said, “This is really exciting and joyful.”</p>
<p>Russia launched large numbers of missiles and drones on the capital Kyiv Monday, wounding three people and damaging schools. On Tuesday, Russian missiles killed at least 41 people and wounded over 180 in Poltova, a city in the central eastern part of Ukraine.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Lori Hinnant </em><em>reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>despite</strong> –<em> prep.</em> in defiance or contempt of;<strong> </strong>without being prevented by</p>
<p><strong>bunker</strong> – <em>n</em>. a strong building that is mostly below ground and that is used to keep people safe from attacks</p>
<p><strong>alarm</strong> – <em>n</em>. a device that makes a loud sound as a warning or signal</p>
<p><strong>grader</strong> – <em>n</em>. US: a student in a particular grade in school</p>
<p><strong>alternate</strong> – <em>v.</em> to place or do (different things) so that one follows the other in a repeated series</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>AI App Helps People with ADHD (2024/9/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/ai-app-helps-people-with-adhd.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>Becky Litvintchouk did not think she would be able to finish the many tasks needed to start her own business. She has Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder, or ADHD. It affects every part of her life and hurts her ability to <strong>focus</strong> on one thing at a time.</p>
<p>So, two years ago, she turned to artificial intelligence, or AI. She uses an app called Claude. It helps her decide which contracts are the best for her cleaning-wipes business, GetDirty. Using the app means she does not need to read each contract, word for word. She also created business plans by telling the <strong>generative</strong> AI bot what her goals were. It then created steps for her to reach them.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Entrepreneur Becky Litvintchouk works on her computer at a co-working space on Monday, Aug. 12, 2024, in New York. (AP Photo/Andres Kudacki)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-5ed1-08dcc6ac6364_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Entrepreneur Becky Litvintchouk works on her computer at a co-working space on Monday, Aug. 12, 2024, in New York. (AP Photo/Andres Kudacki)</span></div>
<p>“It's been just massively <strong>instrumental</strong>. I probably would not be where I am today,” Litvintchouk said of using AI.</p>
<p>People with ADHD experience difficulties with focusing, organizing and controlling<strong> </strong>urges. Experts say generative AI tools can help them finish tasks more quickly.</p>
<p>However, they also warn that such tools should not replace traditional treatments for ADHD. Some experts also have concerns about possibly using AI too much. They also worry about privacy risks.</p>
<p><strong>Will apps replace ADHD treatment?</strong></p>
<p>John Mitchell is an associate professor at Duke University School of Medicine in North Carolina. He said that AI apps should be used as “one tool in a toolbox.” AI should not take the place of traditional treatments, such as developing organizational skills or taking medications.</p>
<p>He compared using AI to help ADHD with swimming and staying alive in the water. “If you're kind of <strong>treading water</strong> in your job and AI's a <strong>life</strong> <strong>preserver</strong>, well, that's great you're staying above water.” But, he added, “you still don't know how to swim.”</p>
<p><strong>What else can the apps do?</strong></p>
<p>Litvintchouk, a married mother of four living in New York City, dropped out of high school and left the workforce. Research shows that these things are more likely to happen to people with ADHD.</p>
<p>Aside from helping with her business, she uses ChatGPT to help with food shopping. Food shopping and meal planning are tasks that can be difficult for people with ADHD because these tasks require organizational skills.</p>
<p>After sharing her method with another mom with ADHD, she decided more people needed to know about it. She started making videos on TikTok about the AI tools she uses to help with her ADHD struggles.</p>
<p>Generative AI tools can help people with ADHD break down big tasks into smaller, more doable steps. Chatbots can offer advice for specific things and make people feel like they are talking with a real person. Some AI apps can also help with reminders and productivity.</p>
<p>Software engineer Bram de Buyser said he created Goblin.tools with his <strong>neurodivergent</strong> friends in mind. The tool's most popular feature is the “magic to-do.” A user can enter a task and the bot will create a to-do list. It can even break down large items on the list into smaller tasks.</p>
<p>“I'm not trying to build a cure,” de Buyser said, “but something that helps them out (for) two minutes out of the day that they would otherwise struggle with.”</p>
<p><strong>What kinds of problems could apps create?</strong></p>
<p>Russell Fulmer is a professor at Husson University in the northeastern state of Maine. He described the research around AI and ADHD as “<strong>inconclusive</strong>.” In other words, the results of its usefulness are still not known.</p>
<p>Experts say they see how AI can have a positive effect on the lives of people with anxiety and ADHD. But, Fulmer said, such tools may not work well for everyone, including people of color with ADHD. He pointed to chatbot responses that have been racist and unfair toward certain groups of people at times.</p>
<p>Valese Jones is a publicist and founder of Sincerely Nicole Media. She was <strong>diagnosed</strong> with ADHD as a child. She uses AI bots to help with reading and responding to emails as well as proofreading public relations plans. But chatbot responses do not always go along with who she really is.</p>
<p>“There are <strong>cadences</strong> in my writing where you can kind of pick up on the fact that I'm southern, and that's on purpose,” said Jones, who is Black. She purposefully writes in a way that shows her culture. However, the responses she gets back from bots often do not show that.</p>
<p>Software engineer de Buyser said that using AI chatbots as a personal assistant has a big upside: They are never tired and never sleep.</p>
<p>The downside? They also create privacy issues. When you give an AI chatbot your personal information, emails, calendar and personal writings, you are giving it to a big company, he warned.</p>
<p>And that's the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p>And I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Kenya Hunter reported this story for The Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted the story for Learning English.</em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>focus</strong> <em>-n.</em> a center of activity, attraction, or attention</p>
<p><strong>generative </strong><em>-adj. </em>having the power or function of generating, originating, producing, or reproducing</p>
<p><strong>instrumental </strong><em>-adj. </em>serving as a crucial means, agent, or tool</p>
<p><strong>tread water </strong><em>-v. </em>while in deep water a person float in an upright position by moving their legs slightly</p>
<p><strong>life</strong> <strong>preserver </strong><em>-n. </em>a device (such as a life jacket or life buoy) designed to save a person from drowning by providing buoyancy in water</p>
<p><strong>neurodivergent </strong><em>-adj. </em>having or relating to a disorder or condition (such as autism spectrum disorder, attention deficit disorder, dyslexia, or obsessive-compulsive disorder) that impacts the way the brain processes information : exhibiting or characteristic of variations in typical neurological development</p>
<p><strong>inconclusive </strong><em>-adj. </em>leading to no conclusion or definite result</p>
<p><strong>diagnose </strong><em>-n.</em> to recognize (something, such as a disease) by signs and symptoms</p>
<p><strong>cadence </strong><em>-n. </em>a rhythmic sequence or flow of sounds in language</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What Is the Oropouche Virus Found in US Travelers to Cuba? (2024/9/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/what-is-the-oropouche-virus-found-in-us-travelers-to-cuba.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>American health officials have identified a virus spread by insects in more than 20 people who visited Cuba. The virus is officially called Oropouche. It is also known as sloth fever.</p>
<p>The U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) said August 27 it had received reports of 21 cases in the United States. All of the cases – 20 in Florida and one in New York – involved people who had traveled to Cuba.</p>
<p>European health officials said they had identified 19 cases of the virus, nearly all of them in travelers.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image provided by the USDA Agricultural Research Service shows a closeup of a mosquito on human skin. (USDA Agricultural Research Service via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-30ce-08dcc8675abf_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image provided by the USDA Agricultural Research Service shows a closeup of a mosquito on human skin. (USDA Agricultural Research Service via AP)</span></div>
<p>The CDC <a class="wsw__a" href="https://wwwnc.cdc.gov/travel/notices/level1/oropouche-fever-brazil">explains</a> that Oropouche is usually spread through the bites of small flies called midges, as well as mosquitoes. Signs, or symptoms, of the sickness usually start three to 10 days after an insect bite. They can include headache, high temperature, joint <strong>stiffness</strong>, stomach problems and sensitivity to light.</p>
<p>The CDC says most virus cases last from three to six days and people generally recover without any long-term effects. There is currently no <strong>specific</strong> treatment or vaccine for the sickness.</p>
<p><strong>Where did Oropouche come from?</strong></p>
<p>The Oropouche virus is native to forested <strong>tropical</strong> areas. It was first identified in 1955 in the Caribbean island nation of Trinidad and Tobago. The virus was named after a nearby village and water system.</p>
<p>The sickness is sometimes called sloth fever because scientists investigating the virus found it in a three-toed sloth. Researchers believed the sloths were important in spreading the virus between insects and animals.</p>
<p><strong>How does it spread?</strong></p>
<p>The virus is spread to humans by small biting flies called midges, and by some kinds of mosquitoes. Humans have become infected while visiting forested areas and are believed to be responsible for helping the virus make its way to towns and cities. So far, person-to-person transmission, or spread, has not been documented.</p>
<p><strong>How many cases have there been?</strong></p>
<p>The virus has recently caused large outbreaks in Amazon areas where it was known to exist. It has also been found in new areas of South America and the Caribbean. About 8,000 local infections have been reported in Bolivia, Brazil, Colombia, Cuba, and Peru.</p>
<p>Most patients returning from Cuba reported their symptoms between May and July. Three of the patients were hospitalized, with no deaths reported, the CDC <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/volumes/73/wr/mm7335e1.htm?s_cid=mm7335e1_w">said</a> in its <em>Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report</em>.</p>
<p><strong>What are the symptoms and treatments?</strong></p>
<p>Symptoms can seem similar to other tropical diseases like dengue, Zika or malaria. The most common ones include <strong>fever</strong>, headaches and muscle pains. Some infected people also suffer from <strong>diarrhea</strong>, unsettled stomach, <strong>vomiting</strong> or skin reactions.</p>
<p>Some patients can suffer symptoms repeatedly. And one in 20 people may experience more severe symptoms like bleeding, meningitis and encephalitis. The virus rarely causes death, although there were recent reports of deaths in two healthy young people in Brazil.</p>
<p>There are no vaccines to prevent infections and no medicines are currently available to treat the symptoms.</p>
<p><strong>Are there other concerns?</strong></p>
<p>In Brazil, officials are investigating reports that infections might be passed on from pregnant women to their unborn babies. This kind of spread was documented during Zika outbreaks nearly 10 years ago.</p>
<p>The CDC has issued guidance that pregnant women should avoid non-necessary travel to Cuba. The agency also suggested that all travelers take steps to prevent insect bites, such as using insect <strong>repellents</strong> and wearing long-sleeved shirts and long pants.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press and Reuters reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>stiff </strong><em>– adj. </em>hard and difficult to move</p>
<p><strong>specific </strong><em>– adj. </em>exact or containing details</p>
<p><strong>tropical</strong> <em>– adj. </em>from or in the hottest parts of the world</p>
<p><strong>fever </strong><em>– </em><em>n. </em>a high body temperature caused by sickness</p>
<p><strong>diarrhea </strong><em>– n.</em> a sickness in which a person's solid waste is more liquid than usual and comes out of the body more often</p>
<p><strong>vomit</strong> <em>– v. </em>to have the food, liquid, etc., that is in your stomach come out through your mouth because you are sick</p>
<p><strong>repellent </strong><em>– </em><em>n. </em>a substance used to keep insects away</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Man Jailed for Poaching, Now Protects Zimbabwe’s Natural Resources (2024/9/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202409/a-man-jailed-for-poaching-now-protects-zimbabwe-s-natural-resources.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">02 September, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A Zimbabwean who formerly hunted animals illegally is now in a program that turns such poachers into protectors of wildlife.</p>
<p>Forty-seven-year-old Tembanechako Mastick grew up hunting, a tradition in his community. He also planted crops and raised farm animals, or livestock. But dry weather conditions made farming less profitable. So, he turned to illegal hunting, also called poaching.</p>
<p>Then, last year, he got caught. Mastik had poached some small <strong>game</strong> from Savé Valley Conservancy. It is one of the largest private game reserves in Africa. Mastick was jailed for nearly three months.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Tembanechako Mastick, a former poacher who now teaches conservation, poses inside his cattle pen in Chiredzi, Zimbabwe near the Save Valley Conservancy, Wednesday, July 10, 2024. (AP Photo/Tsvangirayi Mukwazhi)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-c7d1-08dcc3b61757_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Tembanechako Mastick, a former poacher who now teaches conservation, poses inside his cattle pen in Chiredzi, Zimbabwe near the Save Valley Conservancy, Wednesday, July 10, 2024. (AP Photo/Tsvangirayi Mukwazhi)</span></div>
<p>Now, he is in a program that aims to turn poachers into <strong>conservationists</strong>.</p>
<p>Recently, Mastick was with a group of men. They found the <strong>den</strong> of some hyenas that had recently attacked livestock. The bones of the goats showed what happened. Some of the men suggested using fire to burn any hyenas remaining in the den. But Mastick warned against killing the animals, whether for <strong>revenge</strong> or for meat.</p>
<p>He said, “I began to realize that animals are for the benefit of the entire community, so poaching is a selfish act.”</p>
<p>Spreading that message is not easy. Across southern Africa, conflict between humans and wild animals is increasing. Dry weather, illegal hunting, tree-clearing, and the changing of forest to farmland have pushed wildlife closer to people.</p>
<p>Elephants raid vegetable gardens. Lions, hyenas, wild dogs and jackals target cattle and goats of farmers. D<i><i>onkey</i></i>s that work on farms are not safe either.</p>
<p>Zimbabwe's parks agency said it has received three to four thousand calls about wildlife problems in the past three years. Tinashe Farawo of the Zimbabwe National Parks and Wildlife Management Authority said the conflicts are likely to increase during the dry months ahead.</p>
<p>Mastick remembers when there were good harvests of corn, millet and cotton. The wild animals stayed in the forest back then.</p>
<p>He said the problems began after the country's land reform program went into effect in 2000. People started farming on land held by the Savé Valley Conservancy. The Conservancy said it lost 30 percent of the wildlife habitat on its 303,000 hectares of land.</p>
<p>At the same time, drought hit Mastick's village. “...Lions began targeting our livestock. Elephants also became a problem, hyenas too,” he said. There was not enough land to feed livestock, and people from neighboring villages crossed into the reserve to get wood.</p>
<p>Dingani Masuku of the conservancy said, “All resources are <strong>scarce</strong>. So we have to compete (with animals) for those resources...The resources are getting <strong>leaner</strong> and leaner.”</p>
<p>Mastick often has to calm angry villagers who have lost livestock. He knows about the problem. He starts each day by counting his own cattle, goats and d<i><i>onkey</i></i>s. Once he had 45 goats. Now, he has only 10. Wild animals have eaten the rest. Mastick himself has bites from animals including from a leopard attack.</p>
<p>“Without crop harvests we have to turn to livestock to raise money for school fees, food and other necessities so people are justified to be angry,” he said. But he added, “I help them understand that killing the animals is not the solution.”</p>
<p>Part of his message is that jail is difficult. His family suffered while he was in prison because he had been the family's only<strong> </strong>earner.</p>
<p>Several of his 20 children stopped going to school.</p>
<p>But in jail, he learned new skills including <strong>carpentry</strong>. Now, he makes chairs and tables in his workshop that have been popular with visitors and locals. Men visit his workshop, and Mastick tells them about conservation. He also speaks at village gatherings, funerals and community meetings.</p>
<p>There is no information about poaching in the area. But Mastick believes the number of poachers has dropped since he started his efforts.</p>
<p>Masuku of the Conservancy said people believe Mastick and gain hope from his work as a carpenter.</p>
<p>He said, “People know that he has been through it, he has been there and that poaching does not pay and that is why he is reforming.”</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Farai Mutsaka reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>game </strong><em>–n.</em> animals that can be hunted</p>
<p><strong>conservationist</strong><em> –n. </em>a person who protects and manages natural resources, so they last for the future</p>
<p><strong>den</strong> <em>–n.</em> a cave or hole where animals shelter</p>
<p><strong>revenge </strong><em>–n.</em> when a person sets out to punish someone who hurt them in some way</p>
<p><strong>scarce </strong><em>–adj.</em> difficult to find</p>
<p><strong>lean </strong><em>–adj.</em> thin or having little or nothing</p>
<p><strong>breadwinner </strong><em>–n.</em> the person whose income supports a family</p>
<p><strong>carpentry </strong><em>–n.</em> the job of making things out of wood</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
