<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>VOA Special English</title>
        <link>https://www.21voa.com/special_english/</link>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <itunes:category>ESL</itunes:category>
        <itunes:author>VOA</itunes:author>
        <description>美国之音（以下称VOA）的英语节目，按播音速度可分为两种：Standard English （标准英语）和 Special English（特别英语）。

Special English 又叫“慢速英语”，是VOA 专为全世界非英语国家初学英语的听众安排的一种简易、规范的英语广播节目。该节目创始于50年代末期，是VOA 的专家们研究如何与世界各地的英语学习者进行交际的产物。它正式开播于1959年10月。当时只面向欧洲和中东，但由于这个节目适合许多国家英语学习者的需要，所以它的广播对象不久就扩大到世界其他地区，并很快在全世界范围内产生了广泛的影响。现在这个节目对欧洲、非洲和拉丁美洲每晚广播一次，对加勒比地区每晚广播一次（星期天除外），对东南亚广播次数最多，每天上午两次，晚上三次。

30多年来，VOA 为了办好Special English节目，进行了大量的调查研究工作，对播音速度、内容及用词范围都作了具体规定，基本上达到了既能为英语学习者提供信息，又不损害英语本身风格的目的，使之成为VOA 独具特色，拥有最大量听众的节目。

美国著名词汇学家S. B. Flexmer 指明了Special English的三条标准，也就是它所“特别”的地方：

1、它是一种由美国人最常用的1500个基本单词为主体构成的美国英语；

2、它用简短、明晰的句子写作和广播；

3、它以每分钟90个单词的速度，即2/3的Standard English（标准英语）速度进行广播。

Special English的节目可分为两大类：一类是新闻节目；一类是专题节目。

1．新闻节目

VOA Special English 的新闻广播向听众提供世界范围内的政治、经济、军事、外交、国际关系、宗教、天气以及各种重大事件和珍闻奇事等各个方面的信息，每天向东南亚地区广播五次，早上两次，晚上三次，每逢半点播出。

Special English新闻节目每次长约十分钟，大都播出十条左右新闻，近一千个单词，每条新闻多为一分钟，但偶尔也有长达两分钟的要闻。除头条新闻外，每条新闻都由一个电头引导，这样显得结构分明，条理清晰，适宜初学英语的人收听。在节目结束之前，播音员常常用三四句话重播其中三条新闻的提要以加深听众对要闻的印象。

Special English新闻中70%左右的内容与同时整点播出的Standard English新闻相同，但相同新闻的先后次序有所变动。每次节目的开头和结尾大同小异，格式比较固定。

2．专题节目（一）

Special English的专题节目（Feature Programs）,从时间上看，可分为两大类：一是每五分钟一次的专题，二是每十五分钟一次的专题。本节先介绍每项五分钟一次的专题材节目。

Special English五分钟一次的专题材节目安排在Special English新闻节目之后和（或）每十五分钟一次的专题材节目之前播出，每星期播七次。根据内容，可分为三个小类，即：Science Report（科学报道），逢星期一、三、五播出，每天播六遍；Agriculture Report（农业报道），逢星期二、四播出，每天播六遍；Words And Their Stories（词语掌故），逢星期六和星期天播出，每天播五遍。这三个专题材各具特色，具有相对的独立性，听众每听完一个节目，都会获得一个完整的印象。

Science Report（科学报道）这一专题材节目每周向听众介绍三篇有关现代科学技术最新发展情况的报道，涉及物理、化学、天文至高无上理、生物、环卫、心理、教育、医学和计算机等方面。适宜理工科大学生和科技工作者收集信息，积累资料，学习科技英语。

Agriculture Report（农业报道） Agriculture Report是为农业科技工作者和生产者安排的一个专题。它专门报道世界各国，特别是美国现代农业生产的最新成文汇报总务科 学家对农业生产某一方面的研究进展，以及他们对影响农业生产的某一自然现象进行分析和研究的近况。此外，它还经常向听众介绍发展中国家家业生产的一些有益经验等内容。

Words And Their Stories（词语掌故）这一专题节目，旨在向学习英语的听众介绍美国英语中生动有趣的词语和惯用法，并从科学研究和通俗词源学的角度来解释它们的含意、产生的背景及其在使用过程中的演变情况等。它通过讲故事的形式讲解每一个词语。这是VOA Special English中的优秀节目之一，是学习美国英语的极好材料。通过收听这一节目，听众不仅能学到娓娓动听的掌故和地道的美国英语，而且能增加美国的社会文化背景知识，历史传统与现状的了解。

VOA 为了更好地办好这个节目，便于听众收听学习，于1978年编辑出版了一本名为Words And Their Stories的书，共收集一百篇故事，作者是Herbert Sutcliffe, Harold Bermen 及VOA 该节目的部分编辑人员。在每次的实际广播中，播音员都以此书为蓝本，再根据需要对原稿进行适当增删。按每周两个故事计算，此书的一百个故事还不能满足一年的播音需要。于是编辑们就是重播部分词语掌故的同时，不断增加许多新的词语掌故，及时将词源学家的最新研究成果和不断增加的新词汇介绍给听众。收听实践证明，初学者在收听过程中必然会遇到许多人名、地名和一些较难的句子，有时甚至在听完之后还很难理解所播词语的确切含义及其汉语意思，为此，听众可参看1983年由中国对外翻译出版公司出版的该书英汉对照本中的有关部分。

3．专题节目（二）

VOA Special English的专题节目，除上节谈的五分钟一次的以外，还有本节要介绍的每十五分钟一次的节目。这类节目共有七个不同的小专题，以星期为单位循环，每天分四次复播出一个专题，但星期日和星期六的两个专题材每晚只播三遍，每次节目约十分钟，继每次五分钟的专题节目之后播出。

这类专题节目的基本结构是，在特定的伴声中先报告当次节目的名称，并扼要介绍其主要内容，然后播送节目正文。最后，在伴乐声中报告节目主持人和撰稿人的姓名，以邀请听众在下周的这个时间继续收听该节目而结束。

People in America（美国人物志） 这是有关美国历史名人的一个专题节目，每逢星期天晚上播出。它向听众介绍在美国历史上产生过重大影响、起过重要作用、作出了突出贡献的科学、文学、政治、或其他各方面的历史人物。节目一般都对他们的生平事迹进行简要的叙述，对其贡献作出评介，类似人物小传。有的重要人物事迹很多，必须用两次或几次的节目时间进行联播。对这样的节目要坚持收听，才会获得完整的印象。

TThis is America（今日美国） This Is America向听众介绍美国人民的生活、学习、工作和娱乐情况，是英语学习者解美国社会的一条渠道。该专题大都一个节目一个整体，每逢星期一晚播出。

Science in the News（科学新闻） 这一专题材主要对新近的科学技术新闻进行综述或摘要广播。向听众介绍世界各国在自然、医学、疾病、原子能、航天等方面的科研动态、成果、突破性进展及存在的困难。涉及当今世界人们普遍关心的重大问题，如核事故、航天飞机爆炸、自然灾害、环境污染和爱滋病等等。每逢星期二播出，每次播一到五条新闻摘要。

Explorations（自然探索） 每逢星期三晚上，听众可以收听到Explorations这一专题节目。该专题既涉及人类遨游太空、探索原子、研究自身、改造自然的现代技术，也报道发展中国家开发新资源，利用新工艺改善人民生活等方面的成就，其侧重点在各种科技实验和简易实用技术方面。该节目一般安排一段时间播一个系列，每次播出一个主题，以便能将某项新技术的研究和应用的全过程介绍给听众，电台还乐意为感兴趣的听众提供所需的文字材料。

The Making of a Nation（建国史话） 这一专题节目向听众介绍美利坚合众国从十三个殖民地区域到现代工业国的孕育、诞生以及形成超级大国的历史过程，并以历史为线索，特定的历史时期为单位，以重大的历史事件为主题材来叙述各个党派、各届总统和政府的历史作用与贡献。这是每个英语学习者都应了解的基本知识。The Making of a Nation每逢星期四播出。这是个系列节目，坚持收听，则有助于系统了解美国的历史概况。

American Mosaic（美国万花筒） American Mosaic是一个radio magazine（广播杂志）节目。该节目题材广泛、内容丰，展示着美国社会文化生活中比较轻松愉快的生活画面；听众收听该节目就如同在阅读一本图文并茂的杂志。它每次有三到五个小节目，涉及音乐、图书、技术和教育等方面的内容。我们既可以从中欣赏到著名歌唱的优秀歌曲，对美国音乐有所了解，又可以获取一些生动有趣的现代美国社会生活知识，随着播音员那亲切悦耳的声音步入美国风景如画的大好河山；同时还能听到世界各地的听众提出的有关英语语方文学等方面的问题和电台的解答。

American Stories（美国故事） 这一专题材节目安排在每星期六晚上播出。这样能使听众在学习和工作之余，得以轻松一下头脑。我们可以通过这一美国文学的“窗口”，接触各种流派、各类名家的文学作品。了解美国英语的时代特色，欣赏、学习美国人民运用语方的技巧，并从那些佳作名篇中获得艺术享受。该节目对短篇故事采取一次播一篇的方式，对中、长篇小说则先进行简写加工，再分几次播出全文。在播出故事正文之前，播音员常常先介绍故事的主要情节。对需要分几次节目时间播出的中长篇，在播第二或以后各部分之前，主持人还先重述已播部分的故事梗概，以唤起听众的回忆，使故事听起来更加连贯。</description>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          <item>
            <title>Colombian Scientists Develop Substance to Protect Bees from Chemicals (2024/10/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/colombian-scientists-develop-substance-to-protect-bees-from-chemicals.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists in Colombia say they have developed a new food substance that protects bees from dangerous chemicals used in farming. They claim it will protect the insects' brains from <strong>neurological</strong> damage caused by chemicals called <strong>pesticides</strong>.</p>
<p>As <strong>pollinators</strong>, bees are extremely important in the <strong>preservation</strong> of natural <strong>ecosystems</strong> and food production.</p>
<p>The plant-based food substance enables bees to deal with neurotoxins commonly used in agriculture. It protects their <strong>motor </strong>system and memory harmed by the chemicals.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Bees from the apiary of the Universidad del Rosario are raised for the research of the formula to protect the brain of bees and other pollinators affected by exposure to insecticides, Bogota, Colombia, October 17, 2024. (REUTERS/Luisa Gonzalez)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e06ec738-6b40-49b1-a386-c1356183412a_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Bees from the apiary of the Universidad del Rosario are raised for the research of the formula to protect the brain of bees and other pollinators affected by exposure to insecticides, Bogota, Colombia, October 17, 2024. (REUTERS/Luisa Gonzalez)</span></div>
<p>Researchers at Colombia's Rosario University in Bogota developed the substance. They partnered with scientists from the Colombian Universidad Javeriana and the University of Arizona in the United States.</p>
<p>"This is a nutritional solution to the problem bees face when <strong>exposed </strong>to pesticides," said Andre Riveros, a professor at Rosario University. Riveros explained that the food substance causes the bees to develop protection against pesticides.</p>
<p>The substance is created with flavonoids, which are known for their health benefits. Flavonoids come from plants and are a kind of secondary metabolite. Secondary metabolites are substances made by plants that make them competitive in their environment.</p>
<p>During the first round of testing, scientists put the bees to sleep and placed them into small laboratory tubes. Then, they fed the bees the substance one by one.</p>
<p>Testing has now moved to real-world situations in a bee colony at the university, said Juan Jose Ovalle. He is a natural science student at Rosario University.</p>
<p>"We already know that there are molecules that improve the bees' health. We already know that there are molecules that prevent neuronal damage caused by pesticides," Ovalle said.</p>
<p>He added it was important to continue the work to increase the effectiveness of these methods to support bees.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Camilo Cohecha reported this story for Reuters from Bogota, Columbia. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>neurological </strong><em>– adj.</em> of, relating to, or affecting the nervous system</p>
<p><strong>pesticide </strong><em>– n.</em> a substance used to destroy pests</p>
<p><strong>pollinator </strong><em>– n. </em>something (as an insect) that pollinates flowers</p>
<p><strong>preservation </strong><em>– n. </em>the activity or process of keeping something valued alive, intact, or free from damage or decay</p>
<p><strong>ecosystem </strong><em>– n. </em>a system made up of an ecological community of living things interacting with their environment especially under natural conditions</p>
<p><strong>motor </strong><em>– n.</em> of, relating to, or being a motor neuron or a nerve containing motor neurons :<strong> </strong>of, relating to, concerned with, or involving muscular movement</p>
<p><strong>exposed </strong><em>– v. </em>not shielded or protected</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How Hard Should You Train? (2024/10/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/how-hard-should-you-train.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>“No pain, no gain” is an old saying in English. It means that one has to suffer or work hard in order to succeed or make progress.</p>
<p>The expression is now often used to push people to train harder or exercise more to get good effects.</p>
<p>But just how much pain do you have to have from weight training? The answer depends on what you are trying to gain, fitness experts say.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Toshiyuki Honma, 70, uses a lat pulldown machine as he works out at the Fukagawa Sports Center in Tokyo, Wednesday, June 12, 2024. If you are getting up there in years, weight-resistance training might deliver unexpected benefits. (AP Photo/Hiro Komae)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/39f3b60c-bbd4-4e46-84f8-2d0ea8c53920_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Toshiyuki Honma, 70, uses a lat pulldown machine as he works out at the Fukagawa Sports Center in Tokyo, Wednesday, June 12, 2024. If you are getting up there in years, weight-resistance training might deliver unexpected benefits. (AP Photo/Hiro Komae)</span></div>
<p>For years, some trainers have told people that to get the best results, they need to train “until failure.”</p>
<p>Training “until failure” means that you do an exercise until you cannot do one more <strong>repetition</strong>. Some recent studies, however, suggest training “until failure” with weights may only help some people.</p>
<p>“If somebody wants to increase muscle mass as much as they possibly can, then training to failure is something to consider,” said Michael Zourdos of Florida Atlantic University.</p>
<p>Zourdos co-wrote a review of 55 research papers on the subject in the scientific publication <em>Sports Medicine</em>.</p>
<p>Zourdos and <strong>colleagues</strong> found that lifting weights “until failure” may build bigger muscles. But training in such a way is not needed to increase strength. He said people who work out hard, but do not push themselves to <strong>exhaustion</strong>, will still likely make their health and fitness better. “There is a difference between training for health and training for <strong>elite</strong> performance <strong>benefits</strong>,” he said.</p>
<p>For the average person simply looking to increase their fitness levels, Zourdos said it is much easier to get results. He explained people who work out regularly would benefit from an intense session that comes within five to 10 repetitions of failure.</p>
<p>He also said “failure training” often comes at a cost. People who train until failure might be so tired and in so much pain that they skip their next workout or two.</p>
<p>In rare cases, extremely difficult training can even be harmful. One example is the condition called rhabdomyolysis, where damaged muscles begin to break down, possibly causing kidney damage.</p>
<p>James Fisher is a sport science expert and advisor in Southampton, England. He said many people are not interested in the idea of working until complete exhaustion.</p>
<p>“What we're really talking about is how hard you should work when you go to the <strong>gym</strong>,” he said.</p>
<p>Fisher added that the idea should be understood to mean that people can spend less time in the gym — if they work hard.</p>
<p>“If you're short on time, then you can push yourself harder, and then you don't need to work out as long,” he said.</p>
<p>Fisher explained that to increase strength, it is necessary to push your muscles to a certain level.</p>
<p>“If you lift a weight you can easily lift ten times or more, you never really work hard enough,” he said. “Now, if we increase the weight so that on the ninth and 10th rep, it feels ... hard, that will benefit your muscle...”</p>
<p>Still, Fisher said that the best workout is “one that people will actually do,” regardless of how hard they push themselves. He said that strength training is probably the best single thing people can do for their health, quality of life and <strong>longevity</strong>.</p>
<p>Whatever your fitness goal, Fisher said the idea of failure training can be included into your workout. People should then rest the muscle group they have trained for about two days, he said.</p>
<p>For people who have more experience, experts suggest saving the failure training for some of the workouts, or on the last set of exercises in your session.</p>
<p>“It's not meant to be for every person, every time they work out,” Fisher said. “This is a tough way to exercise.”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Maria Cheng reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>repetition</strong> <em>– n.</em> a motion or exercise (such as a push-up, squat, or pullup) that is repeated and usually counted</p>
<p><strong>colleague</strong> <em>– n.</em> a fellow worker or professional</p>
<p><strong>exhaustion </strong><em>– n.</em> the act or process of using up all of your energy; the act or process of using all of a muscle's ability</p>
<p><strong>elite </strong><em>-- adj. </em>superior in quality, skill, etc.</p>
<p><strong>benefit </strong><em>– n.</em> a good or helpful result or effect</p>
<p><strong>gym </strong><em>-- n. </em>a space containing equipment for weight training, cardiovascular training, etc.</p>
<p><strong>longevity </strong><em>-- n. </em><strong> </strong>length of life</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Teen Smoking in US Drops to Lowest Level in 25 Years (2024/10/29) | 美国青少年吸烟率降至25年来最低水平</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/teen-smoking-in-us-drops-to-lowest-level-in-25-years.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><p>A new government study suggests U.S. teen smoking rates reached an all-time low this year.<br/>一项新的政府研究表明，美国青少年吸烟率今年达到了历史最低水平。</p><p>The study was a survey of American youth carried out by the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC).<br/>这项研究是美国疾控预防中心对美国青少年进行的一项调查。</p><p>The survey involved middle school students – which includes grades six through eight – and high school students in grades nine through 12. Nearly 30,000 students from 283 U.S. schools took part in the effort, which was carried out from January to May.<br/>该调查涉及六至八年级的初中生以及九至十二年级的高中生。来自美国283所学校的近3万名学生参加了这项今年一月到五月进行的调查。</p><p>An estimated 33 percent of youth took part in the voluntary survey.<br/>据估计，33%的青少年参加了这项自愿调查。</p><p>The study showed a 20 percent drop in the number of middle and high school students who said they recently used at least one tobacco product. These include cigarettes, electronic cigarettes, nicotine patches and hookahs.<br/>研究显示，最近至少使用过一种烟草制品的中学生人数下降了20%。这些制品包括香烟、电子烟、尼古丁贴片和水烟。</p><p>That number decreased from 2.8 million last year to 2.25 million this year. The result suggested the change was the lowest usage rate of those products since the CDC survey began in 1999.<br/>这一数字从去年的280万下降到今年的225万。该结果表明，这是自1999年美国疾控预防中心开始调查以来，这类产品的最低使用率。</p><p>The Associated Press (AP) reports the drop is largely explained by another recent government survey showing e-cigarette use among U.S. youth in 2024 fell to its lowest level in 10 years.<br/>美联社报道称，这一下降主要是由于最近的另一项政府调查显示，2024年美国青少年的电子烟使用率降至10年来的最低水平。</p><p>The youth e-cigarette rate fell to under six percent this year, a drop of 7.7 percent over last year. That was the lowest rate at any time during the past 10 years. Government records show e-cigarettes are the most commonly used tobacco products among teens. The second most common is the nicotine patch.<br/>今年，青少年电子烟的使用率从去年的7.7%，降至6%以下。这是过去10年的最低使用率。政府记录显示，电子烟是青少年中最常用的烟草产品。第二常用的是尼古丁贴片。</p><p>In 1999, nearly 30 percent of American high school students smoked. In 2024, it was just 1.7 percent. Currently, the share of middle school students who smoke is also at its lowest rate. Recent use of hookahs also dropped, from 1.1 to 0.7 percent.<br/>1999年，近30%的美国高中生吸烟。2024年，这一比例仅为1.7%。目前，初中生吸烟的比例也处于最低水平。最近水烟的使用率也从1.1%下降到0.7%。</p><p>CDC officials said the decreases are linked to several measures. These include product cost increases, public health education campaigns, age restrictions and more aggressive enforcement actions against makers and sellers to children.<br/>美国疾控预防中心官员表示，这一下降与多项措施有关。这些措施包括产品成本上涨、公共卫生教育活动、年龄限制，以及对向儿童的制造商和销售商采取更严厉的执法行动。</p><p>Among high school students, use of any tobacco product dropped from 13 to 10 percent in 2024 while e-cigarette use fell from 10 to eight percent. The survey showed there was no change reported for middle school students who generally vape or smoke less than older children.<br/>在高中生中，2024年烟草产品的使用率从13%下降到10%，而电子烟的使用率则从10%下降到8%。调查显示，对于比高中生使用电子烟或吸烟更少的初中生来说，烟草使用率没有变化。</p><p>The study found that tobacco use among girls and Hispanic students fell. But it rose among American Indian and Alaska Native students. The survey also showed the current use of nicotine patches increased among white youth.<br/>研究发现，女孩和西班牙裔学生的烟草使用率下降。但它在美洲印第安人和阿拉斯加原住民学生中有所上升。调查还显示，目前白人青年使用尼古丁贴片的情况有所增加。</p><p>I'm Bryan Lynn.<br/>我是布莱恩·林恩。(21VOA.COM原创翻译，请勿转载，违者必究！)</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists: Brown Dwarf Identified 30 Years Ago Is Two Objects (2024/10/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/scientists-brown-dwarf-identified-30-years-ago-is-two-objects.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">27 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Astronomers have made a surprising discovery about the first brown dwarf ever identified. New observations suggest the object is actually two brown dwarfs orbiting each other.</p>
<p>The American space agency NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/missions/webb/nasas-webb-identifies-tiniest-free-floating-brown-dwarf/">describes</a> a brown dwarf as an object that “<strong>straddles</strong> the dividing line between stars and planets.”</p>
<p>Brown dwarfs form like stars. This means they can grow dense and hot enough to collapse under their own gravity. But they never grow dense or hot enough to begin the process of <strong>nuclear fusion</strong> needed to turn into a star, NASA said. Because of this, brown dwarfs are sometimes called failed stars.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This illustration provided by Caltech depicts the orbits of brown dwarf twins, Gliese 229Ba and Gliese 229Bb, The pair of stars orbits a cool M-dwarf star every 250 years. (K. Miller, R. Hurt/Caltech/IPAC)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f5a86277-c1a7-496f-876e-f4f926a73449_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This illustration provided by Caltech depicts the orbits of brown dwarf twins, Gliese 229Ba and Gliese 229Bb, The pair of stars orbits a cool M-dwarf star every 250 years. (K. Miller, R. Hurt/Caltech/IPAC)</span></div>
<p>Many brown dwarfs are similar to gas giant planets and weigh just a few times more than the mass of Jupiter. Others can be much larger.</p>
<p>The first brown dwarf was discovered in 1995 by researchers from the California Institute of Technology (Caltech). The discovery was made with the help of the institute's Palomar Observatory near San Diego, California.</p>
<p>But after many years of studying the object, known as Gliese 229B, scientists wondered why its brightness was less than expected for an object of its size.</p>
<p>New research now shows that the brown dwarf is actually two objects. The observations came from the Very Large Telescope, which sits in a desert area of northern Chile. Those observations showed that one of the brown dwarfs is about 38 times the mass of Jupiter, while the other is 34 times Jupiter's mass.</p>
<p>In a statement, the researchers said data collected by the telescope suggests the two objects orbit each other every 12 days. That is less than half the time it takes for the moon to orbit the Earth. “The observed brightness levels of the pair match what is expected for two small <strong>dim</strong> brown dwarfs in this mass <strong>range</strong>,” the statement added.</p>
<p>The two brown dwarfs are gravitationally linked to each other in what is known as a binary system. Such a situation is commonly observed among stars but is rare for brown dwarfs.</p>
<p>After the new discovery, the two objects were given new names – Gliese 229Ba and Gliese 229Bb. The brown dwarfs are believed to orbit a star called a red dwarf. The two sit about 19 light-years away from our solar system. A light-year is the distance light travels in one year – about 9.5 trillion kilometers.</p>
<p>The research was co-led by Jerry Xuan, a graduate student at Caltech. He said in a statement that Gliese 229B was always considered “the <strong>poster child</strong>” for a brown dwarf.</p>
<p>"And now we know we were wrong all along about the nature of the object,” he added. “It's not one but two. We just weren't able to <strong>probe </strong>separations this close until now."</p>
<p>Astronomers had identified brown dwarf pairs before, but never any that orbited each other so closely. The research results recently appeared <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-08064-x">in a study</a> in the publication <em>Nature</em>.</p>
<p>The team that discovered Gliese 229B in 1995 included Rebecca Oppenheimer. At the time, she was a Caltech graduate student. She is now an astrophysicist at the American Museum of Natural History in New York City. She was also a member of the latest research team.</p>
<p>Oppenheimer said, “It shows you how <strong>weird</strong> the universe is, and how different solar systems are from our own.” She added that she sees the new finding as “the most exciting and <strong>fascinating</strong> discovery” in this area of astrophysics in many years.</p>
<p>Caltech's Jerry Xuan said the discovery suggests there might be other brown dwarfs closely orbiting each other. He added that he hopes the latest finding can lead to a greater understanding of brown dwarf development.</p>
<p>"We still don't really know how different brown dwarfs form, and what the <strong>transition</strong> between a giant planet and a brown dwarf is,” Xuan said.</p>
<p>He added, “This goes to show how complex and <strong>messy</strong> the star formation process is. We should always be open to surprises."</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from the Associated Press, Reuters and Caltech. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>straddle </strong><em>– v. </em>to be on both sides of something</p>
<p><strong>nuclear fusion </strong><em>– n.</em> the process of joining two nuclei to produce energy</p>
<p><strong>dim </strong><em>– adj. </em>not very bright</p>
<p><strong>range </strong><em>–n.</em> a series of values</p>
<p><strong>poster child </strong><em>– n.</em> someone or something that is used to represent a particular quality</p>
<p><strong>probe </strong><em>– v.</em> to examine something carefully, especially with the goal of finding something hidden</p>
<p><strong>weird </strong><em>–n.</em> strange or not normal</p>
<p><strong>fascinating </strong><em>–adj.</em> very interesting</p>
<p><strong>transition </strong><em>– n. </em>a change from one kind of something to another</p>
<p><strong>messy </strong><em>– adj.</em> not done wel</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Agency Issues Final Rules for Flying Air Taxis (2024/10/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/us-agency-issues-final-rules-for-flying-air-taxis.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The U.S. government has issued final rules for operating air taxis. It has also set training and approval requirements for pilots.</p>
<p>The U.S. Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) announced the new rules. They were announced October 22.</p>
<p>The FAA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.faa.gov/air-taxis">explains</a> that air taxis belong to a kind of aircraft known as Advanced Air Mobility (AAM) flyers. These aircraft are generally highly <strong>automated</strong> and electrically powered. They also have <strong>vertical</strong> take-off and landing abilities, the agency said.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This file images shows an electric vertical takeoff and landing (eVTOL) aircraft, flying above the Joby eVTOL aircraft, during a demonstration of eVTOLs Nov. 13, 2023, in New York. (AP Photo/Bebeto Matthews, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/429dbd2a-32f7-4136-9075-7c488652775f_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This file images shows an electric vertical takeoff and landing (eVTOL) aircraft, flying above the Joby eVTOL aircraft, during a demonstration of eVTOLs Nov. 13, 2023, in New York. (AP Photo/Bebeto Matthews, File)</span></div>
<p>Air taxis are part of the AAM group, or category. But they are also considered “power-lift” vehicles. The aircraft have elements of both airplanes and helicopters, the FAA said. Other power-lift vehicles are designed to transport goods rather than people.</p>
<p>These aircraft take off and land vertically but can fly like fixed-wing planes. Many companies have designed and built such models and are working to get them to market. But the efforts have been delayed because of a lack of final requirements, or regulations, governing their use.</p>
<p>FAA Administrator Mike Whitaker said powered-lift aircraft represent “the first new category of aircraft in nearly 80 years.” He added that the new rules are meant to <strong>open the door</strong> to supporting widespread AAM operations in the U.S. in the future.</p>
<p>Whitaker said the new rules aim to make sure “this new generation of aircraft <strong>maintain</strong> the high level of safety that defines modern aviation.” The goal is to establish requirements to ensure that AAMs “are able to safely operate in our National Airspace System alongside existing aircraft.”</p>
<p>The FAA has said air taxi operations will begin slowly. In the beginning, air taxis will use existing travel paths and landing structures currently used by helicopters. The new rules will permit pilots to train with a single set of flight controls. Past FAA rules required two flight controls – one for the student and one for the flight <strong>instructor</strong>.</p>
<p>Air taxi supporters call the aircraft a cleaner choice compared to passenger airplanes, which burn jet fuel. Supporters have called for widespread expansion of the flyers beginning as early as 2025. But experts say current technology limitations make it likely air taxis will only be able to operate at first in large cities.</p>
<p>One company developing AAMs is California-based Joby Aviation. It praised the new FAA rules. Company chief JoeBen Bevirt said the rules “will ensure the U.S. continues to play a global leadership role in the development and <strong>adoption</strong> of clean flight.”</p>
<p>Some airline companies have said they see air taxis as a way to transport passengers to airports. In 2022, Delta Air Lines said it would invest $60 million in Joby. And this month, Toyota announced a $500 million investment in the company. United Airlines is backing another California-based company, Archer Aviation. The Associated Press reports that United has ordered 200 aircraft, which Archer said could be worth up to $1 billion.</p>
<p>Former acting FAA Administrator Billy Nolen is currently Archer's chief safety officer. He told the Reuters news agency that the new FAA rules represent a big step forward for the future deployment of flying air taxis.</p>
<p>"Now we've got a roadmap," Nolen said.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press, Reuters and the Federal Aviation Administration reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>automated </strong><em>– adj. </em>when something is controlled by machines rather than people</p>
<p><strong>vertical </strong><em>– adj.</em> pointing straight up from a surface</p>
<p><strong>open the door </strong><em>– idiom. </em>to make something easier or more likely to happen</p>
<p><strong>maintain </strong><em>– v. </em>to make something continue in the same way</p>
<p><strong>instructor </strong><em>– n. </em>a person who trains others how to do something</p>
<p><strong>adopt </strong><em>– v.</em> to accept or start something new</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Exploring the 'Butterfly Effect' (2024/10/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/exploring-the-butterfly-effect.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Butterflies are <strong>delicate</strong> insects. Their wings are thin and can be easily damaged. So, how can a butterfly cause major things to happen?</p>
<p>That is the idea behind the expression <u>butterfly effect.</u></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This August 19, 2015, photo shows a monarch butterfly landing on a flower in Vista, California. (AP File Photo/Gregory Bull)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/16F8E90F-DF91-462D-9A6F-826A25794F3C_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This August 19, 2015, photo shows a monarch butterfly landing on a flower in Vista, California. (AP File Photo/Gregory Bull)</span></div>
<p>The theory goes like this: When a butterfly <strong>flaps</strong> its wings on one side of the planet it can make a small change that, over time, could lead to a big event, like a storm, all the way on the other side of the planet.</p>
<p>The <u>butterfly effect</u> is when very small changes lead to large and unpredictable changes in the future.</p>
<p><em>For example, let's say a group of television writers demand higher pay. Their employers refuse. So, the writers go on strike. Then television actors join the strike. Their action forces the television industry to stop production. Then, other businesses that support that industry are affected and so are the towns and communities where those businesses are centered. These changes all resulted from that first demand for higher pay.</em></p>
<p>A similar expression involves the game of dominoes -- the <u>domino effect</u>.</p>
<p>Dominoes are small rectangular game pieces. One way to play with dominoes is to set them up in a line or pattern. Then you push the domino at the start of the line into the one next to it and so on and so on ... until all the dominos fall down. You started the <u>domino effect</u> with your single push of a single domino.</p>
<p>The <u>butterfly effect</u> and <u>domino effect</u> are <u>chain reactions</u>. One thing leads to another. We often say that something sets off a <u>chain reaction</u>.</p>
<p>Here is an example:</p>
<p><em>The angry argument between the two friends set off a <u>chain reaction</u> of events that no one could have predicted. One thing led to another and now they are enemies. </em></p>
<p>You can also call this a <u>chain of events</u>. Like <u>butterfly effect</u> and <u>domino effect</u>, one event causes, or <strong>triggers,</strong> the next one to happen.</p>
<p>Now, let's hear two friends use some of these expressions:</p>
<p><em>A: Hey, I'm having the official opening for my bookstore this weekend. You should stop by.</em></p>
<p><em>B: I will! And congratulations. You've been working on that for a while. </em></p>
<p><em>A: Nearly a year. There are so many steps in starting a business. </em></p>
<p><em>B: How did you begin?</em></p>
<p><em>A: It was a <u>domino effect</u>. As soon as I finished the first thing, the next thing to do became clear, and the next and the next. </em></p>
<p><em>B: Sounds like starting that <u>chain of events</u> was important.</em></p>
<p><em>A: Absolutely.</em></p>
<p><em>B: As a writer, did you always want to own a bookstore? </em></p>
<p><em>A: It's funny you ask. When I was little, my friend's parents owned a bookstore. I'd hang out there for hours!</em></p>
<p><em>B: It's like the <u>butterfly effect</u>. Something that happened a long time ago, affected your future today. </em></p>
<p><em>A: Hmm, that sounds like a good story to write. </em></p>
<p>And that's <em>Words and Their Stories</em>.</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>delicate</strong> <em>– adj. </em>easily torn or damaged</p>
<p><strong>flap </strong><em>– v. </em>to move or cause to move with a beating motion</p>
<p><strong>domino </strong><em>– n. </em>a flat rectangular block (as of wood or plastic) whose face is divided into two equal parts that are blank or bear usually from one to six dots arranged as on dice faces</p>
<p><strong>trigger </strong><em>– n. </em>something that causes something else to happen</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Halloween in America: Costumes, Candy, Costs for Night of Fright (2024/10/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/halloween-in-america-costumes-candy-costs-for-night-of-fright.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>October 31 is Halloween. But many Americans have been preparing for the holiday for weeks. And businesses are hoping for good profits from Halloween purchases.</p>
<p>The National Retail Federation (N.R.F.) is the largest U.S. trade group representing sellers of material goods. It expects total Halloween spending in 2024 to reach about $11.6 billion. That sounds like a healthy amount, but it would be a drop from the year before. The N.R.F. says total Halloween spending in 2023 was a record-setting $12.2 billion.</p>
<p>So, you might wonder: What are Americans buying for Halloween and how do they celebrate the holiday?</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A towering Halloween human skeleton appears with a giant canine skeleton in front of a house in Westchester County, N.Y., on Sept. 23, 2024. (AP Photo/Julia Rubin)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/6208ce32-8b3d-4c13-86d8-5aebc362d253_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A towering Halloween human skeleton appears with a giant canine skeleton in front of a house in Westchester County, N.Y., on Sept. 23, 2024. (AP Photo/Julia Rubin)</span></div>
<p>Halloween traditions in America are linked to Celtic beliefs in ancient Britain. The Celts believed that spirits of the dead would return to their homes on October 31, the day of the autumn feast. Celts would build huge fires to frighten away any evil spirits that might return.</p>
<p>People from Scotland and Ireland brought these ideas with them when they came to America. Some believed that spirits played tricks on people on the last night of October.</p>
<p>In modern America, the holiday mostly belongs to children. After dark, children wear special clothing, called costumes. They often appear as frightening creatures like vampires, ghosts and witches. The children walk around their neighborhoods, <strong>knocking</strong> on doors of homes. When someone answers a door, the children yell “trick or treat.” If the people in the homes do not give them a sweet treat, the children may play a trick on them.</p>
<p>Some of the purchases people make for Halloween include candy and costumes. This year, the N.R.F. expects the superhero character Spider-Man to be the most popular children's costume.</p>
<p>Children are not the only Americans in costumes on Halloween, however. Adults also dress up in costumes and attend Halloween parties, parades and other events. These celebrations often include costume competitions, with prizes for the most frightening, inventive or humorous costumes.</p>
<p>Overall, the N.R.F. reports, total spending on costumes for Halloween 2024 is expected to reach a total of $3.8 billion. It says buyers will spend $3.5 billion on Halloween candy.</p>
<p>Americans also enjoy<strong> decorating</strong> their homes for Halloween.</p>
<p>People hang <strong>fake</strong> skeletons, witches, spiders and other scary things around their doors and from trees and bushes. They also cut scary faces into pumpkins and light them to create a strange <strong>glow</strong>.</p>
<p>Some people do a little decorating, others do a lot, and still others do none at all. But, the N.R.F. says researchers estimate Americans will spend about $3.8 billion dollars to dress up their houses for Halloween this year.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Caty Weaver wrote this story for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>knock </strong>- <em>v. </em>to strike something hard</p>
<p><strong>character </strong>- <em>n. </em><strong> </strong>someone who appears in a book, movie, etc.:<strong> </strong>a representation of an individual personality in a fictional or dramatic work</p>
<p><strong>decorate </strong>- <em>v. </em>to make more attractive by adding something that is beautiful or becoming</p>
<p><strong>fake<em> </em></strong><em>- adj. </em>not true, real, or genuine</p>
<p><strong>glow</strong><em><strong> </strong>- n.</em><strong> </strong>to shine with or as if with an intense heat</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Thinking in English (2024/10/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/thinking-in-english.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Hoang in Vietnam about how to think in English.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/3ae349fb-f634-471c-a1a6-86f1808061e0_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>People say that to speak English <strong>fluently</strong>, you need to think in English. So how can I think in English faster? When I talk with foreigners...with the first <strong>conversation</strong>, I talk very slowly and the remaining time I use for thinking. And with the second conversation (because I've been talking before), I feel natural and I speak more fluently.</p>
<p>So how can I be fluent like the second conversation when I'm having the first conversation?</p>
<p>Thank you,</p>
<p>Hoang</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Hoang.</p>
<p>It can be difficult to fully explain how to think in a foreign language. That is because the explanation asks us to consider the relationship between thoughts and the language we use to express them.</p>
<p>However, we can still notice what happens when we think in a foreign language. And we can compare it to times when we have to <strong>pause</strong> and <strong>translate</strong> from our native language.</p>
<p>Consider what happens when you exchange simple greetings, questions, and answers in a foreign language. If someone asks you in English, “How are you today?” you can probably answer without pausing or translating from your native language. For example, you can quickly reply, “I'm fine, thank you. And how are you?”</p>
<p>This example shows us the basic things we need for thinking in a foreign language. In this situation, you know all the words you need to say. You don't need to stop and think about the grammar. And you have heard and said these phrases so many times that your response is <strong>automatic</strong>.</p>
<p>The reason the second conversation you talk about feels more natural is because you have already heard and used some of the <strong>vocabulary</strong> and grammar you need. So, for any subject you want to discuss, you will be able to think in English after you have learned and practiced what you need to say many times.</p>
<p><strong>Steps for thinking in English</strong></p>
<p>Here are some suggestions for learning to think in English:</p>
<p>Choose a subject you are interested in discussing. Then, imagine you are speaking with another person. How easily and quickly can your mind find the vocabulary and grammar you need? Note when you need to pause to find vocabulary or think about grammar. Next, learn the vocabulary and grammar and then practice using them several times. Repeat the words until they become automatic.</p>
<p>If you can plan ahead and practice in your mind what you will likely talk about, then your first conversation might feel easier and similar to a second conversation.</p>
<p>You can find more advice for thinking in English in our <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/train-your-mind-to-think-in-english/5023664.html"><em>Education Tips</em> article, “Train Your Brain to Think in English.”</a></p>
<p>Keep in mind that, to think in English, you need to read, listen to, and speak as much English as possible. This will help your mind use English more easily.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? We'd like to hear from you. Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please include where you are from in your email, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.<em> </em></p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>fluently </strong><em>–adv.</em> speaking easily and well</p>
<p><strong>conversation </strong><em>–n.</em> a discussion between people</p>
<p><strong>translate </strong><em>–v.</em> to take the words of one language and turn them into another language</p>
<p><strong>pause </strong><em>–v.</em> to stop and take a moment while doing an activity</p>
<p><strong>automatic </strong><em>–adj.</em> something done without extra thought</p>
<p><strong>vocabulary </strong><em>–n.</em> the words a person knows and is able to use correctly</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Polio Rises in Pakistan Ahead of a New Vaccination Campaign (2024/10/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/polio-rises-in-pakistan-ahead-of-a-new-vaccination-campaign.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">24 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In Pakistan, polio cases are rising ahead of a new vaccination campaign. Violence targeting health workers has also hurt years of efforts toward making the country polio-free.</p>
<p>The <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/poliomyelitis">World Health Organization says</a> polio is a highly infectious disease caused by a virus. The disease largely affects children under age five. The virus is <strong>transmitted</strong> from person to person and spread mainly through contact. It invades the nervous system and causes a person to be unable to move arms, legs or muscles, a condition called paralysis. Among those paralyzed, up to 10 percent die when their breathing muscles become <strong>immobilized</strong>.</p>
<p>Since January, health officials have confirmed 39 new polio cases in Pakistan, compared to only six last year, said Anwarul Haq. He is with the National Emergency Operation Center for Polio Eradication. Eradication means getting rid of something completely.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A police officer stands guard as a health worker, right, gives a polio vaccine to a child in a neighborhood of Peshawar, Pakistan, September 9, 2024. (AP Photo/Muhammad Sajjad)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e7e90a02-bc2f-4d4e-bfab-333d8926bac6_cx0_cy7_cw89_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A police officer stands guard as a health worker, right, gives a polio vaccine to a child in a neighborhood of Peshawar, Pakistan, September 9, 2024. (AP Photo/Muhammad Sajjad)</span></div>
<p>The new nationwide campaign starts on October 28. The campaign aims to vaccinate<strong> </strong>at least 32 million children.</p>
<p>“The whole purpose of these campaigns is to achieve the target of making Pakistan a polio-free state,” Haq said.</p>
<p>Pakistan regularly launches campaigns against polio despite attacks on the workers and police assigned to protect them.</p>
<p>Militants falsely claim that the vaccination campaigns are a Western attempt to<strong> </strong>sterilize<strong> </strong>children. To sterilize means to make someone unable to produce children.</p>
<p>Most of the new polio cases were reported in the southwestern Balochistan and southern Sindh <strong>provinces</strong>. The next two areas with the most cases are Khyber Pakhtunkhwa and eastern Punjab.</p>
<p>The <strong>locations</strong> worry officials since previous cases were from the northwest areas bordering Afghanistan. In September, this is where the Taliban government suddenly stopped a house-to-house vaccination campaign.</p>
<p>Afghanistan and Pakistan are the two countries in which the spread of the possibly deadly, paralyzing disease has never been eradicated. Officials in Pakistan have said that the Taliban's decision will have major effects beyond the Afghan border. People from both sides frequently travel to each other's country.</p>
<p>The WHO has confirmed 18 polio cases in Afghanistan this year. All but two of these cases were in the south of the country. That number is up from six cases in 2023.</p>
<p>In June, Afghanistan started a house-to-house vaccination campaign for the first time in five years. The campaign has helped to reach the majority of children targeted, officials at the WHO said.</p>
<p>Health officials in Pakistan say they want both sides to hold anti-polio campaigns at the same time.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo adapted this story for VOA Learning English based on an Associated Press news report.</em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>transmit </strong><em>– v.</em> to transfer from one person or place to another</p>
<p><strong>immobile </strong><em>– adj. </em>incapable of being moved</p>
<p><strong>province </strong><em>– n. </em>an administrative district or division of a country</p>
<p><strong>location </strong><em>– n. </em>a place fit for or having some particular use</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Finally, a World Series for Baseball (2024/10/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/finally-a-world-series-for-baseball.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By VOA</span><br/><span class="datetime">24 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Baseball has long called its championship the World Series although it only involves teams playing in the United States and Canada.</p>
<p>It started in 1903 when the Pittsburgh Pirates of the National League beat the Boston Americans of the American League for the championship. But the first official World Series, as it is known today, was in 1905 between the New York Giants and the Philadelphia Athletics.</p>
<p>Since then, the New York Yankees have won 27 World Series titles, more than any other team. This year, the Yankees will face the Los Angeles Dodgers for what sports fans believe will be a World Series seen around the world.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Los Angeles Dodgers' Shohei Ohtani celebrates after their win against the New York Mets in Game 6 of a baseball NL Championship Series, Sunday, Oct. 20, 2024, in Los Angeles. The Dodgers will face the New York Yankees in the World Series. (AP Photo/Ashley Landis)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/df51d02f-5f37-47d3-86d0-7c5ed086be4c_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Los Angeles Dodgers' Shohei Ohtani celebrates after their win against the New York Mets in Game 6 of a baseball NL Championship Series, Sunday, Oct. 20, 2024, in Los Angeles. The Dodgers will face the New York Yankees in the World Series. (AP Photo/Ashley Landis)
</span></div>
<p>The competition is a best-of-seven-game championship. That means four wins in the series are needed to become the champion.</p>
<p>This year's series might have everything that sports fans could want. It is a competition between teams from the two largest cities in the U.S. It is a competition between the two best teams in baseball. And the contest involves two of the biggest baseball stars, Shohei Ohtani of Japan and Aaron Judge of the U.S.</p>
<p>Both players have already won the Most Valuable Player Award or MVP, given to the best player in the National League and the American League. Ohtani has won it twice and Judge once. The two are likely to be named MVP in each league again this year.</p>
<p>Ohtani joined the Dodgers earlier this year with a record 10-year <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/japan-s-ohtani-gets-700-million-biggest-team-sports-deal/7393301.html">contract valued at $700 million</a>. After receiving the largest contract ever in team sports history, Ohtani hit 54 <strong>home runs</strong>, <strong>stole</strong> 59 <strong>bases</strong>, and led the National League in almost all offensive numbers.</p>
<p>Talking to reporters on Tuesday, October 22, Judge called Ohtani “the best player in the game.” He added that Ohtani “hits for average, he hits for power, the speed.”</p>
<p>But Judge himself holds the American League record with 62 home runs in 2022. This year, he leads all of baseball, hitting 58 home runs. And he also leads all of baseball, both American and National Leagues, in offensive numbers, including 144 <strong>RBIs</strong>, 133 <strong>walks</strong>, on-base percentage, and <strong>slugging percentage</strong>.</p>
<p>As expected, Ohtani led the Dodgers to the best record in the National League, and Judge captained the Yankees to the best record in the American League. The two best players, though, have a lot of help.</p>
<p>The Dodgers have two former MVPs, Mookie Betts and Freddie Freeman, in the <strong>lineup</strong>. The Yankees have just one former MVP in Giancarlo Stanton. But they also have Juan Soto of the Dominican Republic, who is often called a “generational <strong>talent</strong>” in the game.</p>
<p>The first game of the 2024 World Series will start on Friday, October 25. The games are sold out meaning all tickets have been sold. But, for those who still want to watch the game in person, it is possible to pay more than $1,000 for a seat or up to $10,000 for the best seats in the reselling market StubHub.</p>
<p>Others can watch the television broadcast that is expected to set a record for people watching in Ohtani's home country of Japan.</p>
<p>After the Dodgers beat the New York Mets to get to the World Series, Ohtani told reporters, “The goal was to get this far.”</p>
<p>As for Judge, “getting a chance to play on the biggest stage and in the biggest moment, I think that's going to be pretty cool to watch,” he said.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Hai Do wrote this report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>home run </strong>–n. to score in baseball by hitting a fair ball out of play</p>
<p><strong>(stolen) bases</strong> <em>–n. (pl.) </em>the number of times that a batter who has reached a base has moved to another base, closer to home, when someone else is batting</p>
<p><strong>RBI (runs batted in)</strong><em> –n.</em> the number of times a player has scored or caused a teammate to score</p>
<p><strong>walk</strong> –n. to reach base without being credited with a hit</p>
<p><strong>slugging percentage </strong>–n. a measure of the quality of hits a batter has</p>
<p><strong>lineup </strong><em>–n.</em> the official list of players who start a baseball game</p>
<p><strong>talent </strong><em>–n.</em> a skilled player</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Grammar and Halloween (2024/10/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/grammar-and-halloween.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">24 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>An interesting holiday in the United States is coming up soon. Halloween happens on the last day of October. If you have lived in the U.S., you have probably noticed many changes in the month or so before Halloween. Let's hear about some of them and explore the vocabulary and expressions you might hear this time of year.</p>
<p><strong>‘Trick-or-treat'</strong></p>
<p>First, you should know about trick-or-treating. Children <strong>dress</strong> <strong>up</strong> in special clothes, or costumes, to look like frightening creatures. They might dress up as little <strong>vampires</strong>, <strong>ghosts</strong> and <strong>witches </strong>or superheroes. Then their parents walk with them to the homes of neighbors, where the children knock at the door and call out, “Trick or treat!”</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-4cc8-08dbd581255f_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>Some people believe the custom goes back to an old Celtic celebration in which people went from door to door asking for firewood. The Celts believed that the spirits of the dead would return to their homes on October 31, the day of the autumn feast. The Celts would build large fires to frighten away evil spirits on that night.</p>
<p>In modern-day Halloween, the children ask for candy. That's the “treat” part. The “trick” part is what happens if you do not give them something.</p>
<p>Before Halloween, communities might create a “<strong>haunted</strong> house” in an old house or an open field. Visitors can walk through the place and be frightened and surprised by unusual noises and people dressed up like ghosts or spirits.</p>
<p>Fear plays a big part in Halloween celebrations. The words we use to talk about fear include “scary,” an adjective to show something causes fear and “afraid” an adjective that describes the person who feels fear. We might say, “I'm scared of ghosts,” to say we are afraid of ghosts.</p>
<p>Another word we use to describe things that cause fear is “<strong>spooky</strong>.” Little people trying to look like ghosts might say, “Boo!” to frighten others. Let's put some of these expressions together to see how they work.</p>
<p><em>Greg has a really scary costume this year. He said “Boo!” to me and I jumped!</em></p>
<p><em>Caty's house looks really spooky with all those skeletons and spider webs that she put out in her yard.</em></p>
<p><em>I'm not afraid of ghosts but seeing people dressed up as witches scares me!</em></p>
<p>You will see that stores begin offering many kinds of candies in small packages. We call these “individually wrapped” treats. They are meant for handing out to children as part of trick-or-treating. Some candy makers call these small packages “fun-sized” treats.</p>
<p><strong>Halloween decorations</strong></p>
<p>People put some strange things on and around their homes for Halloween. People hang toy spiders, skeletons and other scary <strong>decorations</strong> on trees and bushes. You will see pumpkins everywhere. People often empty the pumpkins and make scary faces on them. Then they place a candle inside so the pumpkin face shines in the night. We call these “jack-o-lanterns.”</p>
<p>The custom of carving scary faces into vegetables is believed to come to us from the Irish. They had an old story about a wandering soul named Stingy Jack. They carved faces in turnips to frighten him away. When they came to America, they found the pumpkin was widely available. So, they carved faces into pumpkins, and made what we call the jack-o-lantern today. Now, children carry plastic buckets made to look like a carved pumpkin. They fill them with candy as they trick-or-treat around their neighborhood.</p>
<p>We close with a usual conversation around Halloween in the U.S. See how many traditions and customs you can spot.</p>
<p><em>A: Are you going to any Halloween parties this year?</em></p>
<p><em>B: No, I have to take my kids trick-or-treating. Then I'm too tired to dress up and go out to a party. Are you going?</em></p>
<p><em>A: Yes, I'm going to be a vampire this year. My block has a great party with a haunted house every year.</em></p>
<p><em>B: Oh, I wish I could go. Hey, will you help me carve these pumpkins? I want to put them out front.<br/>
B: Sure, I love carving jack-o-lanterns. Can I have some of that candy while I'm working?</em></p>
<p><em>A: Of course. Help yourself to those fun-sized Hershey bars. I only have a hundred of them.</em></p>
<p>Does your culture have any celebrations where you dress up or give out treats? Write to us in the comments to tell us about them!</p>
<p>And that's Everyday Grammar for Halloween. Boo!</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jill Robbins wrote this lesson for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"> </h2>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>dress up </strong><em>– v.</em> to wear a special kind of clothing for a festival or event</p>
<p><strong>vampire – </strong><em>n. </em>a dead person who leaves the grave at night to bite and suck the blood of living people</p>
<p><strong>ghost – </strong><em>n. </em>the soul of a dead person thought of as living in an unseen world or as appearing to living people</p>
<p><strong>witch – </strong><em>n. </em>a woman who is thought to have magic powers</p>
<p><strong>candy – </strong><em>n. </em>a sweet food made with sugar or chocolate</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Caribbean Island of Anguilla Gets Big Lift from AI (2024/10/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/caribbean-island-of-anguilla-gets-big-lift-from-ai.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">23 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p class="Body">The Caribbean island of Anguilla is getting a economic lift from companies registering internet addresses through the British territory.</p>
<p class="Body">The companies are seeking to show they are involved in the artificial intelligence (AI) industry. One way to do this is to secure an internet address that ends in .ai. Anguilla owns the right to issue the .ai <strong>domain</strong> ending to organizations. It gained that right in the 1990s, based on the territory's name.</p>
<p class="Body">Other nations and territories have similar control over domain registrations with letters with links to their name. For Anguilla, the popular rise of AI has permitted the territory to make a lot of money from new registrations ending in .ai.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This file photos shows a ChapGPT logo on a smartphone in West Chester, Pa., Wednesday, Dec. 6, 2023. (AP Photo/Matt Rourke, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/2f8a8a9e-980e-40ce-bb27-192e06483703_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This file photos shows a ChapGPT logo on a smartphone in West Chester, Pa., Wednesday, Dec. 6, 2023. (AP Photo/Matt Rourke, File)</span></div>
<p class="Body">Some examples from the technology world include Google, which uses google.ai for its AI offerings. The chief of social media service X, Elon Musk, chose to register x.ai as the homepage for X‘s Grok AI tool. And AI search engine Perplexity uses perplexity.ai.</p>
<p class="Body">In Anguilla, earnings from web domain registration increased by four times last year to $32 million as the rise in AI systems increased sharply. The earnings now account for about 20 percent of the total amount the government brings in. Before the increased interest in AI, the amount remained at about five percent.</p>
<p class="Body">Anguilla's government – which uses the gov.ai domain – collects money each time an .ai web address is re-registered. It also gets paid when new addresses are registered and <strong>expired</strong> ones are sold off to new buyers. Some registrations have brought in tens of thousands of dollars.</p>
<p class="Body">Anguilla is 91 square kilometers and has a population of about 16,000. Its ocean areas and natural offerings bring in foreign visitors. But the island has faced economic difficulties since the COVID-19 pandemic, and it can be hit by powerful storms.</p>
<p class="Body">Anguilla does not have its own AI industry. But the territory's premier, Ellis Webster, hopes that will one day change. He told the Associated Press it was just luck that Anguilla was <strong>assigned</strong> the .ai domain. It could also have gone to nearby Antigua, which has the same letters in its name.</p>
<p class="Body">Webster said the money from domain registrations eases pressure on government finances and helps support several important projects. But, he said the territory must be careful not to completely depend on it.</p>
<p class="Body">“You can't predict how long this is going to last,” Webster told the AP. “So I don't want to have our economy and our country and all our programs just based on this.“</p>
<p class="Body">To help keep up with the explosive growth in .ai registrations, Anguilla signed a deal with a U.S.-based company, Identity Digital, to <strong>manage</strong> the process. The company has said it plans to add all .ai domain services to its systems by the start of next year.</p>
<p class="Body">There are currently more than 533,000 .ai web domains, an increase of more than 10 times since 2018. Webster predicts domain-related earnings will keep rising, possibly even doubling this year from last year's $32 million.</p>
<p class="Body">He noted the money can finance the expansion of the territory's airport, provide free medical care for older citizens and complete a technology job training center for high school students.</p>
<p class="Body">The income also provides “budget support” for other projects the government plans to launch, Webster said. One of those is a national development program that includes money for hurricane recovery efforts.</p>
<p class="Body">I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p class="Body"><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p class="Body"><strong>______________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p class="Body"><strong>domain </strong><em>– n</em><em>.</em><em> </em>a subdivision of the internet that links websites with digital addresses</p>
<p class="Body"><strong>expire </strong><em>–</em><em> </em><em>v. </em>to become no longer effective</p>
<p class="Body"><strong>manage</strong><strong> </strong><em>–</em><em> </em><em>v. </em>to do something or deal with something successfully</p>
<p class="Body"><strong>assign </strong>–v. to officially give something through a process to someone else such as a domaine name</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>New Zealand Puts Limits on Goodbyes (2024/10/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/new-zealand-puts-limits-on-goodbyes.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">23 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>While emotional goodbyes are common at airports, one airport in New Zealand is not having any of it.</p>
<p>Travelers at New Zealand's Dunedin Airport have a new three-minute limit to say goodbye at the airport's <strong>drop off</strong> area.</p>
<p>The goal is to prevent traffic jams at the travel center.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A sign informing time limits for visitors to the passenger drop-off area outside Dunedin Airport in Momona, New Zealand, Oct. 8, 2024. (Sarah Soper/Dunedin Airport via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/6655fa9c-5bc8-4981-9e1d-d1ce683d961e_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A sign informing time limits for visitors to the passenger drop-off area outside Dunedin Airport in Momona, New Zealand, Oct. 8, 2024. (Sarah Soper/Dunedin Airport via AP)</span></div>
<p>A sign warns: “<strong>Max</strong> hug time three minutes.” Anything longer and people should go to the parking lot instead.</p>
<p>The limit was put in place in September to “keep things moving smoothly,” airport chief Dan De Bono told the Associated Press. It was the airport's way of reminding people that the area was for “quick <strong>farewells</strong>” only.</p>
<p>The sign, however, has caused a big reaction on social media, De Bono said.</p>
<p>“We were accused of <strong>breaching</strong> basic human rights and how dare we limit how long someone can have a hug for,” he said. But others welcomed the change.</p>
<p>The signs were meant as a different answer to the problem. In Britain, airports warn of seizing vehicles with wheel clamps or fines for drivers parked in drop-off areas. Some British airports have fees for all drop-offs no matter how long.</p>
<p>De Bono said three minutes was enough time to “pull up, say farewell to your loved ones and move on.” “The time limit is really a nicer way of saying, you know, get on with it,” he added.</p>
<p>De Bono added that a 20-second hug is long enough to release the <strong>hormone</strong> oxytocin, which is linked to feelings of well-being among other things. Anything longer is just “really awkward,” said the chief, noting that there are no “hug” police.</p>
<p>However, visitors might be asked to move long hugs to the parking lot where they can stop at no cost for up to 15 minutes.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Charlotte Graham-McLay reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>drop off </strong><em>–v. (phrasal)</em> to bring someone to a place where they are going and leave them there to continue their travels</p>
<p><strong>max</strong> <strong>(maximum) </strong><em>–adj. </em>the most possible</p>
<p><strong>farewell</strong> <em>–n.</em> wishing a person a good, safe trip</p>
<p><strong>breach </strong><em>–v.</em> to go beyond or outside of a limit or boundary</p>
<p><strong>hormone </strong><em>–n.</em> a substance made by the body that influences its processes</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US: North Korea Has Sent Troops to Russia (2024/10/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/us-north-korea-has-sent-troops-to-russia.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/><span class="datetime">23 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The United States said on Wednesday that it had seen evidence of North Korean troops in Russia. And South Korean intelligence officials told lawmakers that about 3,000 soldiers had been sent to support Russia's war against Ukraine.</p>
<p>Speaking in Rome, Italy, U.S. Defense Secretary Lloyd Austin said, "There is evidence that there are DPRK troops in Russia.” DPRK is short for the Democratic People's Republic of Korea, North Korea's official name.</p>
<p>Austin said it would be "very, very serious" if the North Koreans were preparing to fight alongside Russia in Ukraine, as Ukraine's government has claimed. However, the defense chief added that it remained to be seen what the North Korean soldiers are doing in Russia.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A man walks past a newspaper displayed on a street for the public in Seoul on October 21, 2024, with coverage on North Korea's decision to deploy thousands of soldiers to Ukraine. (Photo by Anthony WALLACE / AFP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/b0605646-44fe-42cc-8cfc-81770b7bd268_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A man walks past a newspaper displayed on a street for the public in Seoul on October 21, 2024, with coverage on North Korea's decision to deploy thousands of soldiers to Ukraine. (Photo by Anthony WALLACE / AFP)</span></div>
<p><strong>3000 troops sent to Russia</strong></p>
<p>South Korean intelligence first reported that the Russian navy had taken 1,500 North Korean special warfare troops to Russia last week. And Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelenskyy said his government had intelligence information saying that 10,000 North Korean soldiers are preparing to join the invading Russian forces.</p>
<p>South Korean lawmakers then said that intelligence chief Cho Tae-yong told them another 1,500 had entered Russia, with thousands more expected to follow.</p>
<p>Park Sun-won, a member of a parliamentary intelligence committee, said after the briefing that troops seem to have gone to several training centers in Russia. They are “adapting to the local environment,” Park added.</p>
<p>South Korean intelligence officials also said that North Korea had sent more than 13,000 containers of artillery, missiles and other weapons to Russia since August 2023.</p>
<p>The Ukraine conflict broke out when Russia invaded the country in February 2022. The war has largely been fought along the front lines in eastern Ukraine, with huge numbers of <strong>casualties </strong>on both sides.</p>
<p>Austin said the North Korean deployment could be additional evidence that the Russian military was having problems with <strong>manpower</strong>.</p>
<p>In the past, Russia has dismissed South Korea's claims about the North's troop deployment, calling it "fake news." And a North Korean representative to the United Nations in New York called the claims "groundless rumors" at a meeting on Monday.</p>
<p>Both countries have also denied weapons transfers. But the two countries have agreed to increase military ties. And they signed a <strong>mutual</strong> defense treaty at a meeting in June.</p>
<p>Lee Seong-kweun, another South Korean lawmaker, said intelligence officials confirmed that Russia had <strong>recruited</strong> a "large number" of <strong>interpreters</strong> for the North Korean soldiers. The Russians are also training the North Korean soldiers in the use of modern military weapons, such as drones.</p>
<p>North Korea has 1.2 million troops - one of the largest standing armies in the world. But it has not fought in large conflicts since the 1950-1953 Korean War.</p>
<p>Many experts question how much North Korean troops would help Russia, noting a shortage of battle experience. They say North Korea wants to get Russian economic support and wants its help to modernize the North's weapons systems.</p>
<p>On Tuesday, South Korea's presidential office urged an immediate withdrawal of the North's troops from Russia. South Korean officials warned that it may consider supplying lethal weapons to Ukraine if military ties between Russia and North Korea went too far.</p>
<p>I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>Hai Do adapted this story for Learning English based on reporting from Reuters and The Associated Press.</em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>casualty</strong> - n. a person who is hurt or killed during war or accident</p>
<p><strong>manpower</strong> - n. the number of people available</p>
<p><strong>mutual</strong> - adj. shared between two or more people or groups</p>
<p><strong>recruit</strong> - v. to find suitable people to join organization or armed forces...</p>
<p><strong>interpreter</strong> - n. a person who translates words that someone is speaking from another language</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Big Tech Companies Aim to Develop Small Nuclear Reactors (2024/10/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/big-tech-companies-aim-to-develop-small-nuclear-reactors.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">22 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Technology company Amazon recently said it is investing in small nuclear reactors to meet its increasing need for electricity.</p>
<p>Amazon's announcement came two days after a similar statement from technology company Google.</p>
<p>Nuclear power is gaining attention as the owner of the Three Mile Island nuclear power station in Pennsylvania announced last month that it will restart the reactor there.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="The Google logo, left, is displayed at the company's headquarters in Mountain View, Calif., on July 19, 2016, and the Amazon logo is displayed on the exterior wall of the Amazon OXR1 fulfillment center in Oxnard, Calif., on Aug. 21, 2024. (AP Photo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/63c656cf-7325-43af-ae40-4c50d92d93ce_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">The Google logo, left, is displayed at the company's headquarters in Mountain View, Calif., on July 19, 2016, and the Amazon logo is displayed on the exterior wall of the Amazon OXR1 fulfillment center in Oxnard, Calif., on Aug. 21, 2024. (AP Photo)</span></div>
<p>The goal is to sell the energy from the nuclear station to Microsoft to power its huge data centers.</p>
<p>All three companies, Microsoft, Amazon and Google, operate large data centers. They have been spending a lot of money on solar and wind power to create and use electricity that does not produce <strong>greenhouse gases</strong>. However, their energy needs are so great that they need to find other ways to produce clean energy. Nuclear energy does not create greenhouse gases.</p>
<p>The International Energy Agency in Paris predicts that data centers will use 1,000 terawatts of electricity in 2026. One terawatt is equal to 1 million <strong>megawatts</strong>. That is double the amount from 2022.</p>
<p>Data centers are important to artificial intelligence or AI systems. AI tools use huge amounts of information to “learn” to do things in a way that is almost human.</p>
<p>Kevin Miller is an official with Amazon Web Services. Miller told the Associated Press, “AI is driving a <strong>significant</strong> increase in the amount of data centers and power that are required on the <strong>grid</strong>.” He said adding nuclear power was very important.</p>
<p><strong>Small modular reactors</strong></p>
<p>Small modular reactors can generate up to one third of the power that a traditional nuclear reactor can. Recently, U.S. Energy Secretary Jennifer Granholm spoke at Amazon's second headquarters in Virginia. Speaking of energy production, Granholm said modular reactors are a “huge piece of how we're going to solve this <strong>puzzle</strong>.” Granholm said the department will provide $900 million to produce more reactors.</p>
<p>Developers say small reactors can be built faster and at a lower cost than large reactors. The developers say they will be able to produce electricity by the early 2030s if the Nuclear Regulatory Commission gives them permission.</p>
<p>Kathryn Huff is a nuclear engineering professor at the University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign and former official at the U.S. Department of Energy. Huff said, if new, clean power is not added as data centers expand, the U.S. risks “browning the grid,” or including more power from sources that are not clean: coal, oil and gas.</p>
<p>Small modular reactors are currently under development. They reportedly do not provide power to the U.S. grid. However, big investors can help them develop. Huff said the recent announcements could be an “inflection point” or a sign that things are changing.</p>
<p>A professor of nuclear engineering at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Jacopo Buongiorno, said the industry needs buyers who value dependable and clean energy. They only have to be willing to pay more for it at first until the cost comes down.</p>
<p>On October 14, Google said it signed an agreement with Kairos Power based in Alameda, California. Google said it would buy energy from several small, modular reactors.</p>
<p>Google said it expects the first modular reactors to start operations by 2030 with additional ones coming through the year 2035. The deal is expected to generate 500 megawatts of electricity. However, Google's own environmental <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.gstatic.com/gumdrop/sustainability/google-2024-environmental-report.pdf">report</a> estimated that the company used 24 terawatts of electricity last year.</p>
<p>Amazon's October 16 announcement said the company was working with Dominion Energy to study building modular reactors near the North Anna nuclear station in Virginia. The company said it is investing in X-energy, a reactor developer based in Maryland. Amazon is also working with Energy Northwest in Washington state.</p>
<p>The combined deals could produce 5000 megawatts of power by the late 2030s. However, that is likely a small part of Amazon's total power use, which it does not release to the public.</p>
<p>Doug True is an official with the Nuclear Energy Institute, an industry group. He said new reactor designs could meet industrial needs because of their small size and dependability.</p>
<p>“It seems like a really good fit to support those <strong>facilities</strong>, and for a lot of different applications depending upon the amount of power that's needed by the customer,” True said.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Alexa St. John and Jennifer McDermott reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>greenhouse gas </strong><em>–n.</em> a carbon-based gas that comes from burning or the breakdown of waste that scientists say can warm the atmosphere</p>
<p><strong>megawatt</strong> <em>–n. </em>a measure of power that is 1 million watts</p>
<p><strong>grid</strong><em> –n.</em> the network of lines, production stations and equipment that provide electricity for a large area</p>
<p><strong>generate </strong><em>–v.</em> to create something, especially electricity and power</p>
<p><strong>puzzle </strong><em>–n.</em> a problem that requires thought and effort</p>
<p><strong>facilities</strong> <em>–n. (pl.)</em> buildings and equipment for industrial use</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Deep Ocean Heatwaves Highly 'Under-reported' (2024/10/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/study-deep-ocean-heatwaves-highly-under-reported.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Periods of very high temperatures, or heatwaves, deep in the ocean might be highly “under-reported,” a recent study says. The study suggests such heatwaves could have worrying effects in the future.</p>
<p>Australia's national science agency (CSIRO) and the Chinese Academy of Sciences worked together to do the research, which appeared recently in the scientific publication <em><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-08051-2" target="_blank">Nature.</a> </em></p>
<p>Researchers found that 80 percent of marine heatwaves below 100 meters are independent of surface events.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Bleached corals are seen in a reef in Koh Mak, Trat province, Thailand, May 8, 2024. This year so far the country's weather recorded the highest temperature at 44.2 degrees Celsius affecting the seawater temperature as well. (REUTERS/Napat Wesshasartar/File Photo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/90783c6a-0760-4060-8597-08554d17ddfd_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Bleached corals are seen in a reef in Koh Mak, Trat province, Thailand, May 8, 2024. This year so far the country's weather recorded the highest temperature at 44.2 degrees Celsius affecting the seawater temperature as well. (REUTERS/Napat Wesshasartar/File Photo)</span></div>
<p>CSIRO scientist Ming Feng said, "These findings deepen our understanding of the <strong>frequency </strong>and <strong>intensity </strong>of extreme temperature events under the ocean surface and possible <strong>implications</strong>."</p>
<p>Marine heatwaves are temperature events that can cause severe damage to marine living environments. Such effects include damage to coral reefs and <strong>species</strong> displacement, the study said.</p>
<p>These heatwave events are becoming more common due to global warming, causing major environmental and socioeconomic effects, the study suggested.</p>
<p>The majority of previous studies on marine heatwaves have depended on surface signals based on widely available satellite observations of sea-surface temperature.</p>
<p>For this study, researchers used data from eight <strong>mooring</strong> sites. These locations permit a direct estimate of the occurrence of ocean temperature extremes.</p>
<p>The study also used observational data from more than two million ocean temperature profiles from global oceans.</p>
<p>The finding of separate, deeper warming was particularly worrying, the research found. Such warming is of concern because it affects the living area, or habitat, of so many creatures and the food they eat.</p>
<p>"Extreme temperature events below the sea surface are of greater ecological concern because they affect the habitat of most marine primary producers and consumers," the study said.</p>
<p>The research also highlighted the effects of ocean currents on marine heatwaves, in particular eddies.</p>
<p>Eddies are circular currents of water that are likely a major driver of subsurface events, CSIRO suggested.</p>
<p>Ocean eddies can affect acidity levels, oxygen levels and nutrient concentrations in the ocean.</p>
<p>The study suggested that understanding the drivers of subsurface marine heatwaves can help to improve assessment of these events in a warming climate and help to predict them in the future.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Farah Master reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>frequency</strong> <em>– n.</em> the number of repetitions of a periodic process in a unit of time</p>
<p><strong>intensity </strong><em>– n.</em> the magnitude of a quantity (such as force or energy) per unit (as of area, charge, mass, or time)</p>
<p><strong>implication</strong> <em> -- n</em>. a possible significance</p>
<p><strong>species</strong> <em>– n</em>. a class of individuals having common attributes and designated by a common name</p>
<p><strong>mooring</strong> <em>– n.</em> a place where or an object to which something (such as a craft or measuring device) can be fixed in place (or moored)</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Conservatives Want to Deny Migrant Children Right to Education (2024/10/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/conservatives-want-to-deny-migrant-children-right-to-education.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>For many years, children of families living in the United States illegally have had the right to attend public school based on a 1982 Supreme Court decision.</p>
<p>The justices said it is unconstitutional to deny children an education based on their immigration <strong>status</strong>.</p>
<p>But conservative politicians in states such as Oklahoma, Texas and Tennessee are now questioning that right. They also raise the possibility of <strong>challenging</strong> the decision known as <em>Plyler v. Doe</em>. The Supreme Court's conservative majority has already overturned previous decisions on abortion rights and the use of race for admissions<strong> </strong>in higher education.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Damien Salinas, center front, arrives at school on Sept. 7, 2023, in New York. Damien attends his first day of school in New York City after his family emigrated from Ecuador in June. (AP Photo/Andres Kudacki)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/dd3c774f-feb5-45cc-9bed-f694628f458b_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Damien Salinas, center front, arrives at school on Sept. 7, 2023, in New York. Damien attends his first day of school in New York City after his family emigrated from Ecuador in June. (AP Photo/Andres Kudacki)</span></div>
<p>Supporters of the 1982 decision fear it could become a national issue if former President Donald Trump wins a second term in the White House. Trump has made immigration a central part of his 2024 presidential campaign. He promises to carry out the largest operation in history to expel immigrants from the country if elected.</p>
<p><strong>Difficult requirements</strong></p>
<p>The debate over welcoming immigrant children into public schools has also reached the small town of Saugus, near Boston, Massachusetts.</p>
<p>At a recent meeting, the Saugus Public Schools Committee approved a new admissions policy. The policy requires new students to share immigration records. Families must sign a <strong>residency</strong> statement and provide housing and identity documents. It said the purpose was to simplify the process of registering students.</p>
<p>But, some are criticizing the policy's requirement for proof of "legal" residency and the threat of “criminal and civil” punishment for violators. They say it has another goal: keeping immigrants out of the small town's schools.</p>
<p>Civil rights lawyers say the Saugus requirements are too difficult for all to complete and violate federal law. They say the requirements unfairly harm students from immigrant families. They say even those living in the country legally may lack many of the required documents.</p>
<p>Vincent Serino is head of the Saugus school committee. He said during the August meeting that the policy is "tightening up" of existing residency rules and is not intended to keep out immigrants.</p>
<p>But a Nicaraguan woman told the Associated Press that it took six months to register her 8-year-old child because of the document requirements. The woman said the town would not accept her housing papers and the school did not answer when she spoke about the problems.</p>
<p><strong>Possibility of changes ahead</strong></p>
<p>In Saugus, the number of students who learn English has grown to 31 percent over the last ten years. In 2021, the national average for English learners in public schools was 10 percent, with the highest being Texas schools at 20 percent.</p>
<p>The increase in the number of immigrants in public schools makes it necessary to make changes in order to serve larger numbers of English learners.</p>
<p>But until recently, educators and officials would not have accepted the idea of denying children an education. Tom K. Wong is director of the U.S. immigration Policy Center at the University of California, San Diego. He said that now such ideas are becoming accepted in certain political circles.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, the conservative Heritage Foundation urged states to pass laws requiring public schools to ask families living in the country illegally to pay for their children to attend.</p>
<p>Over the summer, Ryan Walters, head of Oklahoma's State Department of Education, said his agency would ask schools to collect information on the cost of illegal immigration. Several school systems have pushed back, saying they will not check students' immigration status.</p>
<p>Chris Payne is a spokesperson for Union Public Schools in Tulsa, Oklahoma. He said federal law bans schools “from asking students or their families about their immigration status or to request documentation of their citizenship."</p>
<p>Attempts to limit children of immigrants in public schools have also failed in the states of Tennessee and Texas so far.</p>
<p>Back in Massachusetts, legal experts say the policy has been a problem for at least two immigrant families trying to register children in Saugus schools. And it took their involvement to get the students into the school.</p>
<p>"The policy itself is illegal," said Oren Sellstrom of Lawyers for Civil Rights. "Schools should be welcoming (all) children who are in the district and educating them."</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Michael Casey and Jocelyn Gecker reported</em><em> this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>status</strong> – <em>n.</em> the official position of a person or thing according to the law</p>
<p><strong>challenge</strong> – <em>v</em>. to say or show that (something) may not be true, correct, or legal</p>
<p><strong>residency</strong> – <em>n</em>. the state or fact of living in a place</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>AI Can Improve Weather Predictions if Used with Traditional Methods (2024/10/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/ai-can-improve-weather-predictions-if-used-with-traditional-methods.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p class="Body">Weather researchers are using artificial intelligence (AI) systems to improve existing weather prediction methods. But, experts say the AI tools currently face limitations and should be used along with traditional prediction methods to be most effective.</p>
<p class="Body">AI systems trained to predict, or forecast, weather events are now being used by many government agencies and organizations worldwide. Such systems aim to produce weather predictions faster and at a lower cost than traditional forecasting methods.</p>
<p class="Body">One weather predicting system that has shown promise is the Google-financed <a class="wsw__a" href="https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/graphcast-ai-model-for-faster-and-more-accurate-global-weather-forecasting/">GraphCast</a> method. This machine learning-based system trains directly on weather data that has already been collected and examined. Such methods have demonstrated an ability to outperform traditional forecasting systems.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file photo, a drone captures views of the Oder river during flooding in Wroclaw, Poland September 19, 2024. (Reuters)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/8b43a0ef-1ffd-4af6-93a6-5e70210646f7_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this file photo, a drone captures views of the Oder river during flooding in Wroclaw, Poland September 19, 2024. (Reuters)</span></div>
<p class="Body">The system works by combining past weather predictions with modern forecasting models to provide the most complete picture of weather and climate.</p>
<p class="Body">In Europe, the European Center for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts (ECMWF) has been using AI prediction tools since January. The organization provides detailed weather forecasts four times per day to nations across Europe.</p>
<p class="Body">The ECMWF technology is called the Artificial Intelligence/Integrated Forecasting System (AIFS). The group <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.ecmwf.int/en/newsletter/178/news/aifs-new-ecmwf-forecasting-system">describes</a> the system as a “data-driven" forecasting model. It is designed to make many predictions quickly, including for extreme events involving powerful storms and heatwaves.</p>
<p class="Body">AI-supported data from the ECMWF correctly predicted intense rains last month across parts of Europe that resulted in widespread flooding. But while the predictions were right, destruction caused by the flooding could not be avoided.</p>
<p class="Body">Experts told Reuters this is largely because it is still difficult to gather and fully <strong>utilize</strong> some collected weather data. In addition, there is a need to strengthen and improve current AI models used to predict weather.</p>
<p class="Body">Andrew Charlton-Perez is a professor of meteorology – the scientific study of weather processes – at the University of Reading in Britain. He told Reuters, "In some cases and for some <strong>variables</strong>, AI models can beat physics-based models, but in other cases <strong>vice versa</strong>."</p>
<p class="Body">Charlton-Perez said one problem is that the effectiveness of an AI model is based on the information it is given. Weather disasters can be harder to predict if there is too little data to enter into AI systems. This can also be true if extreme events happen repeatedly at different times of the year or in different areas.</p>
<p class="Body">Charlton-Perez said he thinks the best use of AI-based weather forecasts would be to use them in combination with traditional weather predicting tools. This, he noted, could utilize AI data to produce weather predictions based on large sets of information collected from multiple sources.</p>
<p class="Body">Thomas Wostal is with the weather observatory GeoSphere in Austria. He told Reuters his group's models correctly predicted 300 to 400 millimeters of local rains in September. And records show that same amount actually fell in the storms.</p>
<p class="Body">But scientists say even in cases where predictions are correct, effective communication is needed to get the information out to communities and local officials so they can effectively prepare.</p>
<p class="Body">Shruti Nath is a research assistant in weather prediction and climate at Britain's Oxford University. She told Reuters, "I think what happened with (the recent floods) ... is that it's so rare - a one in 150- to 200-year event - that even if the weather models capture it, there's a reasonable degree of uncertainty."</p>
<p class="Body">Nath said AI-supported forecasts need to be clearly communicated to the public in a way that warns of the severity and possible destruction of extreme events. This way, people might see the importance of taking action before severe weather happens in order to prevent costly cleanup and recovery efforts.</p>
<p class="Body">I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p class="Body"> </p>
<p class="Body"><em>Reuters reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p class="Body"><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p class="Body"> </p>
<p class="Body"><strong>utilize</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v</em><em>.</em><em> </em>to use something in an effective way</p>
<p class="Body"><strong>variable</strong><strong> </strong><em>–</em><em> </em><em>n. </em>a number, amount or situation that can change</p>
<p class="Body"><strong>vice versa</strong><strong> </strong><em>–</em><em> </em><em>adv. </em>used to say that what you have just said is also the true in the opposite way</p>
<p class="Body"> </p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Expect More Solar Storms, Northern Lights (2024/10/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/scientists-expect-more-solar-storms-northern-lights.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Space scientists say unusual lights in the sky, known as the northern lights, are more likely to appear because of intense activity on the sun.</p>
<p>The cause is the 11-year <strong>solar</strong> <strong>cycle</strong>. During a period of about 11 years, the sun's activity changes. The U.S. space agency, NASA, says changes in the sun's magnetic field cause the activity, which can result in sunspots.</p>
<p>Strong storms on the sun this year have created these “lights” in the sky called auroras. They look like moving waves of color filling the skies similar to what happens as <strong>dawn</strong> nears. Now, space scientists say these “light shows” are likely to be seen much farther south than usual.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - An aurora borealis, also known as the northern lights, is seen in the night sky along with the Big Dipper constellation on Thursday, Oct. 10, 2024, in Moscow, Idaho. (AP Photo/Ted S. Warren)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/d78331bb-fefc-44fa-a911-6246f7da1f19_cx0_cy14_cw93_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - An aurora borealis, also known as the northern lights, is seen in the night sky along with the Big Dipper constellation on Thursday, Oct. 10, 2024, in Moscow, Idaho. (AP Photo/Ted S. Warren)</span></div>
<p>The colors in the sky that people might see may be pink, purple, green or blue. The auroras are called the northern lights because they can usually only be seen in areas in the extreme north of the world near the Arctic Circle.</p>
<p>Space scientists who observe the sun through a special telescope can sometimes see darker places, called sunspots. The sunspots are areas where magnetic fields are stronger than in other places on the sun, NASA says.</p>
<p>The energy released from the interaction of these magnetic fields may cause a flare, a bright spot, which is an explosion of radiation from the sun. It shows up as a flash of light to observers.</p>
<p>Sometimes a large amount of solar material shoots away from the sun. This is called a coronal mass ejection, and it results in a geomagnetic storm when it arrives at the Earth.</p>
<p><strong>The solar cycle at a high point</strong></p>
<p>The sun is currently at the highest part of its 11-year cycle, making solar flares and northern lights more common. NASA and the U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, known as NOAA, say they expect this active period to last for at least another year. But they will not know until months later when solar activity was at its highest.</p>
<p>Kelly Korreck studies the stream of particles that come from the sun called the solar wind. Korreck led a project to develop an instrument to study the solar wind that was on NASA's Parker Solar Probe that got close to the sun in 2021.</p>
<p>The Parker Solar probe collected material and measured magnetic activity on the sun. Korreck said this solar cycle has provided more colorful auroras farther south and even more are likely. "We still could possibly get some good shows in the next few months," she added.</p>
<p><strong>Solar storms affect Earth</strong></p>
<p>Solar storms are powerful. They can temporarily <strong>disrupt</strong> electricity service and communications on Earth. NOAA follows space weather and warns operators of power stations and spacecraft in orbit.</p>
<p>In May, NOAA issued a rare severe geomagnetic storm warning. The radiation from the storm that arrived on Earth was the strongest in more than 20 years. It produced northern lights that people could see in many places in the Northern Hemisphere. That same month, scientists recorded the biggest flare <strong>erupting</strong> from the sun, but Earth was not in its path.</p>
<p>Earlier solar cycles have produced storms more intense than the one in May. Bill Murtagh is the Program Coordinator for the Space Weather Prediction Center at NOAA. He said space weather experts are keeping a close watch on the sun to prepare for any major problems.</p>
<p>Recently, a powerful solar storm gave those watching the sky a beautiful show far from the Arctic Circle. People could see auroras in Germany, Britain, and also in New England and New York City.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Adithi Ramakrishnan </em><em>reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English with additional information from NOAA and NASA. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>solar</strong> - <em>adj</em>. of or relating to the sun</p>
<p><strong>cycle </strong><em>–n.</em> repeated or regular events that happen over a set period of time</p>
<p><strong>dawn</strong> <em>–n. </em>when the sun rises above the horizon</p>
<p><strong>disrupt</strong> <em>–v.</em> to interfere with normal activities or processes</p>
<p><strong>erupt </strong><em>–v.</em> to explode or shoot out</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: How the Brain Cleans Itself (2024/10/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/study-how-the-brain-cleans-itself.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the Health &amp; Lifestyle report.</p>
<p>A rare look inside the human brain might help to explain how it clears away waste. Scientists say the failure to clear away such waste can lead to Alzheimer's disease and other brain disorders.</p>
<p>Brain cells use a lot of nutrients. This means they produce a lot of waste. Scientists believe the brain has special structures to take out this “cellular <strong>trash</strong>,” especially during sleep. They have reported observing this process happening in mice. But they had no clear evidence that this happens in humans.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This undated photo provided by the Oregon Health &amp; Science University in October 2024 shows Drs. Erin Yamamoto (L) and Juan Piantino, who used special imaging to spot a long-suspected pathway the human brain uses to clear waste. (Christine Torres Hicks/OHSU via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/cad1d2f1-b3c2-487d-8844-883dc04e4566_cx1_cy1_cw93_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This undated photo provided by the Oregon Health &amp; Science University in October 2024 shows Drs. Erin Yamamoto (L) and Juan Piantino, who used special imaging to spot a long-suspected pathway the human brain uses to clear waste. (Christine Torres Hicks/OHSU via AP)</span></div>
<p>Recently published research appears to have identified a system, or <strong>network</strong>, of very small waste-clearing <strong>channels</strong> in the brains of living humans. The researchers used a special kind of imaging technology to study the network.</p>
<p>One of the researchers was Dr. Juan Piantino of Oregon Health &amp; Science University. Piantino said the new research was important evidence. “We needed this piece to say this happens in humans, too,” he said.</p>
<p>His team recently published its findings in <em>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences.</em></p>
<p>The brain is very active during sleep. During sleeping hours, the brain appears to clean itself.</p>
<p>That idea has gotten the attention of researchers. Losing a good night's sleep can cause people's thinking to be unclear. But a continuous lack of sleep is believed to increase the risk of the brain disorder dementia.</p>
<p>How does the brain clean itself?</p>
<p>Over 12 years ago, scientists at the University of Rochester first reported finding a network they named the “glymphatic system.” Fluid from the brain, called cerebrospinal fluid, travels through channels surrounding <strong>blood vessels</strong> to carry waste out of the brain.</p>
<p>Beta-amyloids are substances linked to problems in the brain including Alzheimer's disease. When scientists injected mice with beta-amyloids, the substance left the brain faster when the animals were sleeping.</p>
<p>It is not clear exactly how the system works. However, some research has shown that the movement of blood vessels might help move the waste-clearing fluid where it needs to go.</p>
<p>Finding the system in humans is not easy. Regular <strong>MRI scans</strong> can show some of the fluid-filled channels. But Piantino said the scans do not show their purpose.</p>
<p>To find out more, his team at Oregon Health &amp; Science University injected a substance called a <strong>tracer</strong> into five patients. The tracer “lit up” during MRI scans. Twenty-four to 48 hours later, the tracer material was seen moving through the brain using the channels as in the earlier research on mice.</p>
<p>Rochester's Dr. Maiken Nedergaard predicts that the study will increase interest in how brain waste clearance connects to people's health.</p>
<p>But to test if better sleep or other treatments might really increase waste clearance and improve health, researchers "have to be able to measure glymphatic function in people,” said Dr. Jeff Iliff. He is with the University of Washington and has helped lead waste-clearance research. The question is whether the new study might point to ways of measuring the process.</p>
<p>Sleep is not the only question. For example, animal studies show that a blood pressure drug now used to treat the stress disorder called PTSD might improve glymphatic clearing. Iliff and Dr. Elaine Peskind plan to study this drug in a group of patients.</p>
<p>Larger studies in healthy people are also needed.</p>
<p>In addition, Piantino, who used tracer chemicals in people, wants to find an easier, <strong>noninvasive</strong> test to follow the waste clearance.</p>
<p>“We cannot study all the questions by injecting people,” he said.</p>
<p>And that's the Health &amp; Lifestyle report. I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Lauran Neergaard reported this story for The Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>trash </strong>–n. waste materials, especially household waste</p>
<p><strong>network </strong>–n. an interconnected group of pathways, wires or links</p>
<p><strong>channel </strong>–n. a pathway for fluid</p>
<p><strong>blood vessel </strong>–n. any of a group of tubes made from tissue that carry blood throughout the body</p>
<p><strong>MRI scan (magnetic resonance imaging) </strong>–n. a technology that uses electromagnetism to create images of tissue inside the body<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>tracer </strong>–n. a substance that has a chemical or radioactive property that permits it to be observed inside the body of a living thing</p>
<p><strong>noninvasive </strong>–n. a way of looking inside the body without using a medical operation or placing a device in the body</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Say They Have Bred Corals to Better Resist Warm Oceans (2024/10/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/scientists-say-they-have-bred-corals-to-better-resist-warm-oceans.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">20 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists say they have successfully reproduced <strong>corals</strong> to improve their resistance to warmer ocean temperatures.</p>
<p>The latest effort is one of many that seeks to prevent major coral destruction events known as bleaching. The scientists blame the bleaching on ocean warming caused by climate change.</p>
<p>Coral bleaching happens when the small ocean animals react to climate pressures by releasing <strong>algae</strong> organisms that provide them with energy and give them their color. If the bleaching is severe and long-lasting, corals can get sick and die.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image shows some of the selectively-bred coral at a nursery in the Pacific island nation of Palau. (Photo Credit: Jesse Alpert)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/fbf3b419-4132-4285-87ed-83f544b4ec03_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image shows some of the selectively-bred coral at a nursery in the Pacific island nation of Palau. (Photo Credit: Jesse Alpert)</span></div>
<p>Scientists and environmental officials have warned major bleaching events are currently affecting ocean coral collections in many areas across the world. Many researchers link the continued warming of Earth's oceans to climate changes related to human activities.</p>
<p>In April, the U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) and International Coral Reef Initiative said at least 53 countries, territories, or local economies <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/scientists-coral-bleaching-happens-around-the-world/7572317.html">reported</a> ongoing bleaching events since February 2023.</p>
<p>The latest research aimed to reproduce corals that can become more resistant to warm ocean temperatures. To do this, the researchers used a method known as selective breeding. Scientists have long used this method to produce animals and plants with more desirable <strong>characteristics</strong>.</p>
<p>This process can produce living things that are better able to deal with, or tolerate, different environmental conditions. Selective breeding is now a main method used by scientists to study how the process can prevent ocean warming from killing off corals.</p>
<p>The new research was led by scientists at Britain's Newcastle University. The team recently reported their findings <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-024-52895-1">in a study</a> appearing in the publication <em>Nature</em> <em>Communications</em>. The study said their selective breeding methods resulted in improved heat tolerance of adult corals, even within a single generation.</p>
<p>Scientists have for years been observing corals that show more heat-resistant qualities. These corals are used as the parents for new corals.</p>
<p>The researchers said their experiments showed that breeding heat-tolerant characteristics into different corals could be a useful tool “to improve population <strong>resilience</strong>.” However, the team noted the method would likely not be enough by itself to effectively protect corals. This is because increasingly intense ocean warming is expected to continue if additional steps are not taken to reduce the worldwide effects of climate change.</p>
<p>The scientists noted, therefore, that methods to reproduce heat-resistant corals must be a part of overall efforts that require “urgent climate action.”</p>
<p>The research team's experiments were carried out during a five-year project launched by Newcastle's James Guest. The effort received financial support from the European Research Council.</p>
<p>The team said it carried out selective breeding tests involving two different characteristics. The first sought to improve the tolerance to the release of a short, intense heat event – over 10 days with a temperature rise of 3.5 degrees Celsius. The second tested results for a less intense, but long-term temperature rise of 2.5 degrees Celsius over one month.</p>
<p>The study <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-024-52895-1">found</a> that “selecting parent colonies for high rather than low heat tolerance increased the tolerance of adult offspring." The result was observed for corals experiencing either a short, intense heat event or a long-term temperature rise.</p>
<p>The team <a class="wsw__a" href="https://theconversation.com/weve-bred-corals-to-better-tolerate-lethal-heatwaves-but-rapid-climate-action-is-still-needed-to-save-reefs-241298">estimated</a> that about 25 percent of the increased heat tolerance was linked to genes passed down from parents of the corals. These genes can also be influenced by other selective breeding methods to produce heat-tolerance characteristics, the researchers said.</p>
<p>Newcastle researcher Liam Lachs helped lead the study. He said in a statement the research clearly demonstrated that selective breeding can be a valuable tool in improving the health of corals influenced by warming oceans. However, he noted the tested methods are not a complete solution and that “more research is needed to <strong>maximize</strong>” breeding results.</p>
<p>The researchers said they plan next to lead efforts to carry out large experiments on corals in the wild to confirm the study results. These efforts would involve seeding selectively bred corals directly on ocean <strong>reefs</strong>, or deploying corals raised in a laboratory.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from Newcastle University, Nature and The Conversation. </em></p>
<p><strong>_________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>coral </strong><em>– n. </em>a hard, usually pink or white substance produced by a type of very small sea animal</p>
<p><strong>algae </strong><em>– n. </em>usually small plants that grow in or near water and do not have typical leaves of roots</p>
<p><strong>characteristic </strong><em>– n. </em>a typical quality that makes one person or thing different from others</p>
<p><strong>resilient </strong><em>– adj. </em>strong enough to get better quickly after suffering damage from illness, shock, etc.</p>
<p><strong>maximize </strong><em>– v. </em>to increase something as much as you can</p>
<p><strong>reef </strong><em>– n. </em>a collection of rocks or coral or a ridge of sand at or near the surface of water</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Has Human Life Expectancy Reached Its Limit? (2024/10/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/has-human-life-expectancy-reached-its-limit.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">20 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A new study says humanity is hitting the upper limit of life expectancy.</p>
<p>Developments in medical technology and genetic research are not leading to major increases in lifespan overall, the researchers said.</p>
<p>The study was published recently in <em>Nature Aging</em>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Emma Morano holds a cake with candles marking 117 years on the day of her birthday, Nov. 29, 2016, in Verbania, Italy. (AP Photo/Antonio Calanni)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e909286e-b832-4139-a6c5-79de5b3d5731_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Emma Morano holds a cake with candles marking 117 years on the day of her birthday, Nov. 29, 2016, in Verbania, Italy. (AP Photo/Antonio Calanni)</span></div>
<p>“We have to recognize there's a limit” and possibly change ideas about when people should retire and how much money they will need to live out their lives, said S. Jay Olshansky of the University of Illinois-Chicago. Olshansky was the lead writer of the study.</p>
<p>Mark Hayward of the University of Texas was not involved in the study. However, he called it “a valuable addition to the <strong>mortality</strong> <strong>literature</strong>.”</p>
<p>“We are reaching a <strong>plateau</strong>” in life expectancy, he said.</p>
<p>It is always possible that some new development could push survival to greater lengths, “but we don't have that now,” Hayward said.</p>
<p><strong>What is life expectancy? </strong></p>
<p>Life expectancy is an estimate of the average number of years a baby born in a particular year might expect to live. The measurement <strong>assumes </strong>death rates at the time of birth do not change.</p>
<p>Life expectancy is one of the world's most important health measures. Still the life expectancy measurement has problems. For example, life expectancy is an estimate that cannot include new developments or changes that might affect the length of people's lives.</p>
<p>These unknown developments could include pandemics or new treatments for diseases.</p>
<p>In the recent study, Olshansky and other researchers followed life expectancy estimates for the years 1990 to 2019. They took information from a database administered by the Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research.</p>
<p>The researchers paid special attention to eight of the places in the world where people live the longest: Australia, France, Hong Kong, Italy, Japan, South Korea, Spain and Switzerland.</p>
<p>The United States does not rank in the top 40, but it was included in the study because the researchers live in the U.S. Also, some experts have made estimates that life expectancy in the U.S. would increase greatly in the 2000s, Olshansky said.</p>
<p><strong>Who lives the longest? </strong></p>
<p>Women continue to live longer than men. Female life expectancy improvements are still happening — but at a slower rate, the researchers found. In 1990, the average amount of improvement was about 2.5 years every 10 years. In the 2010s, it was 1.5 years — but almost zero in the United States.</p>
<p>Life expectancy measurements in the U.S. are more difficult. The country is affected by a number of causes of early death. Examples include drug overdoses, shootings, weight problems and uneven health care services.</p>
<p>But in one calculation, the researchers estimated what would happen in all nine places if all deaths before age 50 were prevented. The increase at best was still only 1.5 years, Olshansky said.</p>
<p>The study suggests that there is a limit to how long most people live, and we have almost hit it, Olshansky said.</p>
<p>“We're squeezing less and less life out of these life-<strong>extending</strong> technologies. And the reason is, aging gets in the way,” he said.</p>
<p>It may seem common to hear of a person living to 100. Former U.S. President Jimmy Carter, for example, recently celebrated his 100th birthday.</p>
<p>In 2019, a little over two percent of Americans made it to 100, compared to about five percent in Japan and nine percent in Hong Kong, Olshansky said.</p>
<p>It is likely that the number of people who reach 100 will grow in the years ahead, experts say, but that is because of population growth. The percentage of people hitting 100 will remain limited, likely with fewer than 15 percent of women and 5 percent of men making it that long in most countries, Olshansky said.</p>
<p>I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>Mike Stobbe reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>mortality</strong> <em>-- n.</em> the death of large numbers of people</p>
<p><strong>literature </strong><em>-- n.</em> the body of writings on a particular subject</p>
<p><strong>plateau</strong> <em>-- n.</em> a relatively stable level, period, or condition</p>
<p><strong>assume</strong> <em>-- v.</em> to take as granted or true</p>
<p><strong>extend </strong><em>-- v.</em> to stretch out to fullest length</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Expressions Using Our Head and Shoulders (2024/10/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/expressions-using-our-head-and-shoulders.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Many English expressions and <strong>idioms</strong> use parts of the body to describe things unrelated to the body. For example, a <u>green thumb</u> means to be good at growing vegetables, flowers and other plants. And if something <u>costs an arm and a leg</u>, it is very <strong>expensive</strong>.</p>
<p>Well, today, we talk about your shoulder. This part connects your arm to your body. And the shoulder finds its way into many expressions.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Sheet Metal Union member Dan Hines carries Jackson Kin on his shoulders as he and Erica Kin march in the annual Labor Day Parade in Detroit, Michigan, U.S., September 2, 2024. (REUTERS/Rebecca Cook)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/aa66a232-63ee-45a7-a983-5aad0b4303ed_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Sheet Metal Union member Dan Hines carries Jackson Kin on his shoulders as he and Erica Kin march in the annual Labor Day Parade in Detroit, Michigan, U.S., September 2, 2024. (REUTERS/Rebecca Cook)</span></div>
<p>For starters, let's talk about “shoulder” as a verb. If you <u>shoulder</u> something, you accept it as your responsibility; you give support, or you take the blame.</p>
<p>Here is an example:</p>
<p><em>Since he was the leader of the project, he <u>shouldered</u> the blame for its failure.</em></p>
<p>And this is a great place to start. This idea of taking responsibility and giving support leads us to some other “shoulder” expressions.</p>
<p>For example, during difficult times in our lives, it is often necessary to have <u>a shoulder to <strong>lean</strong> <strong>on</strong></u> or <u>a shoulder to cry on</u>.</p>
<p>When we <u>lean on someone's shoulder</u>, we ask for their help. When we <u>cry on someone's shoulder</u>, they are there for support.</p>
<p>It is important to have at least one friend who has <u>a good shoulder to cry on</u>. These friends are great because they don't ask questions. They just listen and let us cry. You can also <u>put your head on someone's shoulder</u>. This means you are getting comfort and support from that person.</p>
<p>We call people who give us <u>a shoulder to lean on</u> or <u>cry on</u> our “support system.”</p>
<p>There is another way our shoulders give us support. If you are successful in your career but others have come before you, you can say you are <u>standing on the shoulders of <strong>giants</strong></u>. This means you have not succeeded on your own. You have learned from others in the same field who had earlier successes.</p>
<p>This expression is often used in science. This is an area where discoveries are often built upon the works of others. Because this expression uses the word “giant,” we often use it when talking about very well-known people. For example, in the world of science, the giants may include Isaac Newton or Albert Einstein.</p>
<p>Now, from our shoulders, let's move up to our heads. Our heads are centered between our shoulders. So, it should not be surprising that we have a couple of expressions that use both.</p>
<p>If you have <u>a good head on your shoulders,</u> you are thoughtful and smart. You do the right thing, and people can count on you. When you have <u>a good head on your shoulders</u>, you often achieve success in life.</p>
<p>This quality, people say, often puts you <u>head and shoulders above the rest</u>. This means you are much better than those in a similar field or competition.</p>
<p>Let's here it used in an example:</p>
<p><em>You have <strong>applied</strong> for a job. You have more education and much more experience than the job requires. You also have special skills that make you even more desirable. You feel these <strong>factors</strong> put you <u>head and shoulders above</u> the other candidates.</em></p>
<p>Here's another example:</p>
<p><em>You are preparing to run in a race. You have clocked the fastest time, and you have trained more than all the other runners. That certainly makes you <u>head and shoulders above</u> the rest.</em></p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>.</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>_______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>idiom </strong><em>-n</em>. an expression that cannot be understood from the meanings of its separate words but must be learned as a whole</p>
<p><strong>expensive </strong><em>-adj. </em>costly :<em> </em>having a high price</p>
<p><strong>lean on </strong><em>-v. to </em>depend on someone for support and encouragement</p>
<p><strong>giant </strong><em>-adj.</em> having extremely large size, proportion, or power</p>
<p><strong>apply </strong><em>-v. </em>to make an application : <em>apply for a job</em></p>
<p><strong>factor </strong><em>-n</em>. something that contributes to the production of a result</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Legal and Law (2024/10/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/legal-and-law.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Emmanuel in Zambia about the usage of the words “legal” and “law” in English.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/305dd1b7-d570-4785-8ec9-90bab77ef68b_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>Please help me understand the correct usage of the words "legal" and "law.” In the recent debate... I heard Donald Trump say "legal scholar.” I thought he was supposed to say, "law scholar.” Which one is the correct usage?</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Emmanuel.</p>
<p>The word “legal” is an adjective. That is why we can place it before the noun “scholar.” In the same way, we can use “legal” before many other nouns, as in these examples:</p>
<p><em>Legal system, legal documents, legal protections, </em>and <em>legal opinion.</em></p>
<p>The word “law” is a noun. We often use “the law” to discuss <strong>specific</strong> laws or to discuss the law in general. Let's look at an example of each. First, here is an example discussing a specific law about voting rules:</p>
<p><em>The law clearly states that persons under 18 years old are not permitted to vote.</em></p>
<p>Next, here is an example discussing the law in general:</p>
<p><em>Over the years, the law has changed to provide equal rights to women.</em></p>
<p><strong>Law: noun or adjective?</strong></p>
<p>The noun “law” can seem like an adjective when we place it before another noun to describe what a person does. For example:</p>
<p><em>Law professor, law school,</em> and <em>law student</em></p>
<p>However, the word “law” and the noun together form what is called a spaced compound noun. That is, we use the two words together to name one thing or person. “Police officer” is another example of a compound noun.</p>
<p>But this returns us to your question—if we can say “law professor,” why do we usually say “legal scholar” instead of “law scholar?”</p>
<p>One reason is that when we state what kind of legal scholar a person is, we can use an adjective and the word “law” before the word “scholar.” The following examples show this.</p>
<p><em>A busy law scholar</em></p>
<p><em>A constitutional law scholar</em></p>
<p>In these cases, the word “law” replaces the word “legal.” But if we are not stating what kind of scholar a person is, then we usually use the two words “legal scholar.”</p>
<p>Note, however, that we can also put an adjective before the words “legal scholar,” as in “international legal scholar.”</p>
<p>The above examples show that there are no strict rules for using “legal scholar” instead of “law scholar” when an adjective is placed before the two words. But keep in mind that we use the expression “legal scholar” more often than "law scholar” when there is no adjective before the two words.</p>
<p>Discussing the law and legal terms in English might seem difficult. But by reading and listening carefully, you can find the most common and correct ways to discuss this subject.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? We'd like to hear from you. Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please include where you are from in your email, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>specific </strong><em>-adj. </em>the exact example of something and not any of other similar things</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Huge Egyptian Museum Opens for Test Run (2024/10/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/huge-egyptian-museum-opening-for-test-run.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The <strong>Grand </strong>Egyptian Museum in Giza will open a limited number of <strong>exhibits </strong>about ancient Egypt starting this week. The limited opening will be a test run of the still-unannounced official opening of the museum, officials said.</p>
<p>Starting on October 16, 4,000 visitors per day will be permitted to view limited areas of the main <strong>galleries</strong>, said Al-Tayeb Abbas. He is assistant to Egypt's minister of <strong>antiquities</strong>.</p>
<p>Museum officials have repeatedly delayed the museum opening for many reasons, including the COVID-19 pandemic. Some areas have been open since 2022 for limited <strong>tours.</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="King Ramses II statue is displayed at the Grand Egyptian Museum in Giza, Egypt, Tuesday, Oct.15, 2024. (AP Photo/Khaled Elfiqi)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a9fab3f9-8f2e-4267-b9db-bebcfe866b67_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">King Ramses II statue is displayed at the Grand Egyptian Museum in Giza, Egypt, Tuesday, Oct.15, 2024. (AP Photo/Khaled Elfiqi)</span></div>
<p>The museum is a huge project near the famous Giza Pyramids. The building project began more than 12 years ago and has cost more than $1 billion so far.</p>
<p>The Egyptian government says more than 100,000 <strong>artifacts</strong> of Egypt's ancient treasures are on show at the site. Officials describe it as the world's largest archaeological museum.</p>
<p>The exhibits in the test run include 12 areas that explore issues related to society, religion, and philosophies of ancient Egypt, Abbas added. The areas are divided by <strong>dynasty</strong> and historical order.</p>
<p>Historical divisions include the Third Intermediate Period, Late Period, and Graeco-Roman Period. It also includes the New Kingdom, Middle Kingdom, and Old Kingdom periods. They all represent life thousands of years in the past.</p>
<p>One of the areas displays statues of the “Elite of the King.” These represent members of a king's family, and high-level officials who worked in the army, government or religious service.</p>
<p>Abbas told the AP that the test run would help prepare for the full opening by identifying operational issues. This includes finding out which parts of the museum might become overcrowded.</p>
<p>A reporter for the Associated Press spoke with some tourists at the museum.</p>
<p>Canadian visitor Aude Porcedda told the AP she was <strong>amazed</strong> by the museum. She said she believes it is important that the world know about Egyptian civilization.</p>
<p>Jorge Licano, a visitor from Costa Rica expressed similar praise.</p>
<p>“There is a lot of history and a lot of things we are not aware of, especially coming from the other side of the world, and seeing everything here and learning from the locals has been great,” he said.</p>
<p>The limited opening includes the museum's so-called Grand<strong> </strong>Staircase. It is six stories high with a view of the nearby pyramids. Also open to the public, are artifacts that include <strong>sarcophagi</strong> and statues. Other parts of the museum, including the King Tutankhamun treasure collection, are set to open at later dates.</p>
<p>All the exhibit space is equipped with high-level technology and permit different kinds of media presentations to help explain the lives of ancient Egyptians, including kings, said museum official, Eissa Zidan.</p>
<p>Some exhibits will use virtual reality to explain the history of burial and its development throughout ancient Egypt.</p>
<p>“The museum is not only a place to display antiquities, but it also aims to attract children to learn about ancient Egyptian history ... The museum is a gift to all the world,” Zidan told the AP.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Ahmed Hatem</em><em> and</em><em> Fatma Khaled reported this story for The Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>grand </strong><em>-adj. </em>great in size : marked by magnificence</p>
<p><strong>exhibit </strong><em>-n.</em><strong> </strong>an article or a collection shown in a public display</p>
<p><strong>gallery </strong><em>-n. </em>a room or building devoted to the exhibition of works of art</p>
<p><strong>antiquity </strong><em>-n. </em>objects or monuments from ancient times</p>
<p><strong>tour </strong><em>-n. </em>a journey for business, pleasure, or education often involving a series of stops and ending at the starting point</p>
<p><strong>artifact </strong><em>-n. </em>a usually simple object (as a tool or ornament) showing human work and representing a culture or a stage in the development of a culture</p>
<p><strong>dynasty </strong><em>-n. </em>a succession of rulers of the same line of descent</p>
<p><strong>amazed </strong><em>-adj.</em> <em>feeling or showing great surprise or wonder</em></p>
<p><strong>sarcophagus </strong><em>-n.</em><strong> </strong>a stone coffin : <em>plural </em><strong>sarcophagi</strong></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Unlicensed Gold Mines in Ghana Present Risks to People, Nature (2024/10/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/unlicensed-gold-mines-in-ghana-present-risks-to-people-nature.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p class="Body">Illegal gold mining operations in Ghana have reportedly increased in recent years. The activities present dangerous risks to the individuals involved as well as environmental harms. The Reuters news agency recently reported on the issue.</p>
<p class="Body">Reporters with the news agency visited such an operation in western Ghana. They found that workers were not using professional protective equipment as they mined for gold in muddy water filled with mercury. Groups of unofficial miners wore normal clothes and used only their hands to remove rocks.</p>
<p class="Body">The <strong>unlicensed</strong> mine is in the country's Prestea-Huni Valley district. It is an example of how increasing numbers of people are turning to illegal methods to find gold to earn money.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A drone view shows the excavated pits for illegal mining at the Prestea-Huni Valley Municipal District in the Western Region, Ghana August 17, 2024. (REUTERS/Francis Kokoroko)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/295e7358-0906-47ae-9c48-c5d29e6f1046_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A drone view shows the excavated pits for illegal mining at the Prestea-Huni Valley Municipal District in the Western Region, Ghana August 17, 2024. (REUTERS/Francis Kokoroko)</span></div>
<p class="Body">Mining officials in Ghana say such operations can harm miners' health, pollute waterways, destroy forests and farms, and increase crime rates.</p>
<p class="Body">One of the men working at the illegal mine told Reuters, “It's risky, but I just want to survive.” The man was a 24-year-old accounting student. He did not want to be named because he is involved in illegal activities. He told Reuters he had been missing classes to search for gold because he needs the money.</p>
<p class="Body">The unlicensed gold mining industry is known in Ghana as "galamsey.” The industry has grown quickly over the past year. One reason for the growth was a 30 percent rise in international gold prices.</p>
<p class="Body">Small mines produced 34 million grams of gold in the first seven months of this year, official government records show. That was more than in all of 2023.</p>
<p class="Body">About 40 percent of Ghana's total gold comes from small mines — those not owned by large international companies. And an estimated 70-80 percent of the small mines are unlicensed.</p>
<p class="Body">News reports and human rights groups say numerous miners have died from collapsing <strong>pits</strong> in recent years. Hospitals and health centers have reported high numbers of early deaths from heart-related diseases of miners and people living in towns and villages near mines.</p>
<p class="Body">The health problems are linked to breathing in dust that contains heavy metals such as lead. In addition, poisonous gas from the mercury and nitric acid are released during unlicensed mine activities. Such chemicals are also dumped on the ground or in rivers. Ghana's water <strong>authority</strong> says mercury and heavy metals from mining have poisoned about 65 percent of water sources.</p>
<p class="Body">The illegal operations have also harmed thousands of hectares of cocoa farms and forest areas, reports data-gathering group <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.globalforestwatch.org/">Global Forest Watch</a>.</p>
<p class="Body">Protesters have taken to the streets in Ghana's capital, Accra, in recent weeks. They have criticized President Nana Akufo-Addo's government over a lack of attention to the problems. Some demonstrators carried signs that said "Leaders, you've failed us!"</p>
<p class="Body">Aboubacar Sadekh took part in a protest on the issue September 22. He told Reuters, “Galamsey has to stop. We want to live long. We don't want to fall sick. We don't want to go to the hospital."</p>
<p class="Body">I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p class="Body"> </p>
<p class="Body"><em>Reuters reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p class="Body"><strong>_________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p class="Body"><strong>unlicensed</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj</em><em>.</em><em> </em>not having a license: an official document giving permission to do something</p>
<p class="Body"><strong>pit</strong><strong> </strong><em>–</em><em> </em><em>n. </em>a large hole in the ground, or a slightly low area in any surface</p>
<p class="Body"><strong>authority </strong><em>–</em><em> </em><em>n. </em> an official group or government department with power to control particular public services</p>
<p class="Body"> </p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Fossil Discovery in Brazil Could Help Explain Rise of Dinosaurs (2024/10/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/fossil-discovery-in-brazil-could-help-explain-rise-of-dinosaurs.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists in Brazil recently announced the discovery of one of the world's oldest reptile remains. They say the bones – dating back to around 237 million years ago – may help explain the rise of the dinosaurs.</p>
<p>The four-legged reptile species is called Gondwanax paraisensis, researchers recently announced in a statement. The animal is believed to have been near the size of a small dog, with a long tail.</p>
<p>The small reptile would have lived in the Triassic Period on land which is today southern Brazil. During this period – from 252 million to 201 million years ago – the world was much hotter.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Paleontologist from the Federal University of Santa Maria, Rodrigo Temp Muller, analyzes fossils called Gondwanax paraisensis, a species that lived 237 million years ago in Sao Joao do Polesine, Rio Grande do Sul state, Brazil, October 8, 2024. (REUTERS/Diego Vara)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/b5985c05-9f5e-40d9-a93f-d9bcbd5114e8_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Paleontologist from the Federal University of Santa Maria, Rodrigo Temp Muller, analyzes fossils called Gondwanax paraisensis, a species that lived 237 million years ago in Sao Joao do Polesine, Rio Grande do Sul state, Brazil, October 8, 2024. (REUTERS/Diego Vara)</span></div>
<p>The <strong>fossil </strong>was identified as a new silesaurid, a group of reptiles believed to have died off in a mass <strong>extinction</strong> event. Experts have debated whether silesaurids were true dinosaurs or if they came before dinosaurs.</p>
<p>"Understanding the <strong>characteristics</strong> of these <strong>precursors</strong> could shed light on what was crucial for the dinosaurs' evolutionary success," a statement from the researchers said.</p>
<p>In 2014, Pedro Lucas Porcela Aurelio, a medical doctor, found the remains in a piece of rock in the town of Paraiso do Sul. The town sits in Brazil's southernmost state of Rio Grande do Sul.</p>
<p>The Gondwanax paraisensis<strong> fossil</strong> comes from a time when dinosaurs as well as mammals, crocodiles, turtles and frogs first appeared.</p>
<p>Aurelio gave the remains to a local university in 2021, beginning three years of research.</p>
<p>"Being the first human to touch something from 237 million years ago is <strong>extraordinary</strong>," Aurelio told Reuters. "It's an indescribable feeling."</p>
<p>The research was led by Brazilian scientist Rodrigo Temp Müller, a paleontologist. His findings recently appeared <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1342937X24002764?via%3Dihub" target="_blank">in an article</a> in the publication <em>Gondwana Research</em>.</p>
<p>Müller said, "The most important part of this finding is its age. Because it's so old, it gives us clues as to how dinosaurs came to be."</p>
<p>Müller added that when Aurelio gave researchers the remains, they were covered by a thick layer of rock. At first, only parts of the backbone could be seen.</p>
<p>Gondwanax means "lord of Gondwana." The name suggests the Gondwana landmass in the southern area of the supercontinent Pangaea. Pangaea later broke apart into continents. The name paraisensis honors the town of Paraiso do Sul.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Sergio Queiroz and Diego Vara reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>fossil</strong> <em>– n.</em> a remnant of an organism that has been preserved in the earth's crust</p>
<p><strong>extinction</strong> <em>– n.</em> a situation in which a kind of animal no longer exists</p>
<p><strong>characteristic</strong> <em>– n.</em> a distinguishing trait, quality, or property</p>
<p><strong>precursor</strong> <em>– n.</em> one that comes before and indicates the approach of another; an animal from which another animal evolves from</p>
<p><strong>extraordinary</strong> <em>– adj.</em> going beyond what is usual or regular</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Recreate Head of Largest Ancient Bug (2024/10/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/scientists-recreate-head-of-largest-ancient-bug.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The largest bug to ever live was about 2.6 meters long and had many legs. However, the look and shape of its head remained a mystery until now.</p>
<p>The <strong>fossils</strong> of these creatures are often headless shells. When bugs drop their shells, a process called shedding, they move out of the head opening, leaving behind their <strong>exoskeleton</strong> but very little of the head.</p>
<p>Recently, scientists solved that mystery by re-creating the creature's head. They were able to do this after studying complete and well-kept fossils of younger bugs. The researchers published the new findings on October 10 in <em>Science Advances</em>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This illustration provided by researchers shows a young Arthropleura insect recreated using fossils discovered in Montceau-les-Mines, France. (Photo Credit supplied by Micka&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;235;l Lh&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;233;ritier, Jean Vannier, and Alexandra Giupponi, October 2024, via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/beebdc03-1c06-4746-9c00-60542577a08e_cx9_cy0_cw90_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This illustration provided by researchers shows a young Arthropleura insect recreated using fossils discovered in Montceau-les-Mines, France. (Photo Credit supplied by Micka<i>&amp;#</i>235;l Lh<i>&amp;#</i>233;ritier, Jean Vannier, and Alexandra Giupponi, October 2024, via AP)</span></div>
<p>What did the heads look like?</p>
<p>The huge bug's head was round with two short bell-shaped <strong>antennae. </strong>It had<strong> </strong>two eyes that stuck out like crab's eyes. Its mouth was fairly small and made for eating leaves and the outer covering of trees.</p>
<p>Its name is Arthropleura. This bug belonged to a group of crabs, spiders and insects called arthropods. But the bug was much, much bigger. It could grow as big as 2.6 meters and weigh as much as 50 kilograms.</p>
<p>The co-writer of the study is Mickael Lheritier. He is a <strong>paleobiologist</strong> at the University Claude Bernard Lyon in Villeurbanne, France. He said, “We discovered that it had the body of a millipede, but head of a centipede."</p>
<p>This large Arthropleura may have been the biggest bug to ever live. Although, not all scientists agree. Some say Arthropleura may be a close second to an <strong>extinct</strong> giant sea scorpion.</p>
<p>Researchers in Europe and North America have been collecting pieces and footprints of the huge bugs since the late 1800s.</p>
<p>“We have been wanting to see what the head of this animal looked like for a really long time,” said James Lamsdell. He is a paleobiologist at West Virginia University and was not involved in the study.</p>
<p>To produce a model<strong> </strong>of the head, researchers first used <strong>CT scans</strong> to study full-body fossils of younger bugs. These fossils were found in a French coal field in the 1980s.</p>
<p>This method permitted researchers to look closely for “hidden details like <strong>bits</strong> of the head” still in the rock without hurting the fossil, Lamsdell said.</p>
<p>The fossils are easily broken. He added that when you dig in the rock to remove the fossil, you do not know what part of the fossil “may have been lost or damaged.”</p>
<p>The fossils of younger bugs only measured about 6 centimeters. And it is possible they were a kind of Arthropleura that did not grow to a really large size.</p>
<p>But still, researchers said they are close enough to the huge Arthropleura to provide a picture of what adults looked like when they were alive 300 million years ago.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Christina Larson reported this story for the Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>fossil </strong><em>-n.</em><strong> </strong>a trace or print or the remains of a plant or animal of a past age preserved in earth or rock</p>
<p><strong>exoskeleton </strong><em>-n. </em>a hard supporting or protective structure (as of an insect, spider, or crustacean) on the outside of the body</p>
<p><strong>antenna </strong><em>-n.</em> one of a pair of slender movable organs of sensation on the head of an arthropod (as an insect or a crab) that are made up of segments</p>
<p><strong>paleobiologist </strong><em>-n.</em> a branch of paleontology concerned with the biology of fossil organisms<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>extinct </strong><em>-adj. </em>no longer existing</p>
<p><strong>CT scan </strong><em>-n. </em>cross-sectional, three-dimensional image of an internal body part produced by computed tomography chiefly for diagnostic purposes</p>
<p><strong>bit </strong><em>-n. </em>a small piece or amount</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>SpaceX Calls New Starship Test a Success, Captures Rocket at Landing (2024/10/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/spacex-calls-new-starship-test-a-success-captures-rocket-at-landing.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p class="Body">SpaceX has successfully completed a fifth test of its Starship rocket system. The uncrewed test was carried out Sunday at the American space company's launch center in Boca Chica, Texas.</p>
<p class="Body">During the flight, the 121-meter-tall Starship was successfully pushed into space by a SpaceX Super Heavy <strong>booster</strong> rocket. After reaching a height, or altitude, of about 70 kilometers, the booster separated from Starship's second stage, or top half,<strong> </strong>as planned.</p>
<p class="Body">The reuseable booster was then directed by ground controllers to return to the launch center. Before touching down on the landing <strong>pad</strong>, the rocket re-lit three of its 33 Raptor engines in order to slow the booster for a controlled landing.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image provided by SpaceX shows SpaceX's mega rocket booster returning to the launch pad to be captured during a test flight Sunday, Oct. 13, 2024, in Boca Chica, Texas. (SpaceX via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f9f61699-54ac-4013-921f-dcf62c772435_cx2_cy2_cw89_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image provided by SpaceX shows SpaceX's mega rocket booster returning to the launch pad to be captured during a test flight Sunday, Oct. 13, 2024, in Boca Chica, Texas. (SpaceX via AP)</span></div>
<p class="Body">The Super Heavy then positioned itself to land. For the first time, the booster was "caught“ and secured in place by a huge structure that includes large metal arms. Video of the landing provided by SpaceX showed the booster rocket being captured by the structure exactly as planned.</p>
<p class="Body">A short time later, Starship's second stage safely <strong>spashed down</strong> in the Indian Ocean. The test flight and successful landings demonstrated progress for SpaceX's Starship system.</p>
<p class="Body">The American space agency NASA is planning to use Starship to carry the next U.S. astronauts to the moon. Such a landing would be the first since NASA's Apollo 17 mission in 1972.</p>
<p class="Body">The next planned moon landing – which NASA officials have set for September 2026 – is part of NASA's Artemis program. Artemis will also seek to establish a permanent base around the moon to support ongoing lunar visits and possible future trips to Mars.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p class="Body">SpaceX was chosen to lead NASA's planned moon landing after numerous successful demonstrations and missions in recent years. The company's rockets and spacecraft have been dependably transporting astronauts and materials to the International Space Station (ISS) since 2020.</p>
<p class="Body">NASA also chose American aerospace company Boeing to serve as a possible partner in its Artemis program. But the company's Starliner rocket has faced major delays and difficulties during past test flights.</p>
<p class="Body">In the last one, Starliner successfully transported two American astronauts – Butch Wilmore and Suni Williams – to the ISS in early June. The two were expected to stay in space for only a week. But ongoing technical issues with the Starliner spacecraft prevented a return trip.</p>
<p class="Body">NASA recently decided to have Starliner return to Earth without the astronauts. The plan is for Wilmore and Williams to return home from the ISS in February on a SpaceX Dragon spacecraft.</p>
<p class="Body">Before SpaceX's latest mission, several Starship rockets exploded during the test flights. The last non-exploding test happened in June. During that flight, SpaceX reported some damage to heat-resisting <strong>tiles</strong> on the outside of Starship. But improvements made since then appeared to have succeeded.</p>
<p class="Body">After Sunday's flight, SpaceX chief Elon Musk said the rockets appeared to be generally in good condition, with just minor <strong>warping </strong>of some outer engine parts from intense heat. He noted that those parts could be fixed easily.</p>
<p class="Body">Musk is also chief of the social media service X. On the service, he expressed excitement when the Starship booster rocket returned to the launch area and was “caught” by the structure. SpaceX calls the huge metal arms that capture and secure the booster rocket on land “<strong>chopsticks</strong>” because they move similarly to the eating instruments.</p>
<p class="Body">“The <strong>tower</strong> has caught the rocket!!” Musk wrote <a class="wsw__a" href="https://x.com/elonmusk/status/1845446365717156265">in a message</a> on X. “Big step towards making life multiplanetary was made today,” he added.</p>
<p class="Body">The successful test flight was also praised on X by NASA Administrator Bill Nelson. “Congratulations to @SpaceX on its successful booster catch and fifth Starship flight test today!” Nelson wrote. He added that “continued testing” will prepare NASA and its partners for a series of “<strong>bold</strong> missions” to come in the future.</p>
<p class="Body">I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p class="Body"> </p>
<p class="Body"><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters, AFP and SpaceX. </em></p>
<p class="Body"><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p class="Body"> </p>
<p class="Body"><strong>booster</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n</em><em>.</em><em> </em>an engine on a spacecraft that gives extra power for the first part of a flight</p>
<p class="Body"><strong>pad </strong><em>–n.</em> a flat structure that is used by flying vehicles like rockets or helicopters to launch or to land</p>
<p class="Body"><strong>splash down </strong><em>–v. (phrasal)</em> when a spacecraft lands in the sea after returning from space</p>
<p class="Body"><strong>tile</strong><em> –</em><em> </em><em>n. </em>a flat piece of material that is used to cover surfaces such as floors, roofs or walls</p>
<p class="Body"><strong>warp </strong><em>–</em><em> </em><em>v. </em>to become bent into the wrong shape</p>
<p class="Body"><strong>chopsticks</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n</em><em>.</em><em> </em>Think sticks used for eating food in many parts of the world</p>
<p class="Body"><strong>tower</strong><strong> </strong><em>–</em><em> </em><em>n. </em>a very tall building or part of a building</p>
<p class="Body"><strong>bold </strong><em>–</em><em> </em><em>adj. </em>not frightened of taking risks</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Preschools Aim to Make Students ‘Better Citizens’ (2024/10/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/preschools-aim-to-make-student-better-citizens.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">15 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Early education expert Dan Gartrell says the most important civics lesson that preschools can teach is “social democracy.”</p>
<p>Gartrell wrote a book about teaching democracy to preschoolers. It is called <em>Education for a Civil Society</em>. The book is used by the ACCA Child Development Center near Washington, D.C. in Northern Virginia.</p>
<p>Gartrell said this teaching “starts with <strong>appreciating</strong> each member of the group as a <strong>worthy</strong> member and worthy of expressing thoughts and ideas.” He said after that, children can learn to treat others with kindness to solve conflicts and negotiate difficult situations by using words that do not hurt other people's feelings.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Preschool Executive Director Maria Isabel Ballivian, right, listens to her students on what characters of the TV show PAW Patrol they will vote for at the ACCA Child Development Center on Sept. 19, 2024, in Annandale, Virginia. (AP Photo/John McDonnell)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/0eeddce2-4eba-4b3d-a13f-74b795c7f41c_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Preschool Executive Director Maria Isabel Ballivian, right, listens to her students on what characters of the TV show PAW Patrol they will vote for at the ACCA Child Development Center on Sept. 19, 2024, in Annandale, Virginia. (AP Photo/John McDonnell)</span></div>
<p>Rachel Robertson is chief academic officer for Bright Horizons. The company operates preschool centers around the world. It uses democratic ideas in its education.</p>
<p>Robertson said that a child starts to be a “real community member” at around age three or four. She said the child starts “<strong>contributing</strong> to the classroom community and thinking a little bit broader about the world.”</p>
<p>At ACCA in Virginia, children are given a lot of <strong>autonomy</strong>. There are hours spent doing free play. Children vote on what they study and eat.</p>
<p>On a recent day, one classroom had just finished studying sand because the children wanted to know about it after they visited beaches over the summer. The children also tried different apples and voted on which apples the school should order.</p>
<p>The ACCA said the decision-making process is meant to <strong>affirm</strong> to children that their thoughts and the thoughts of their classmates are valuable.</p>
<p>Reporters with the Associated Press recently visited an ACCA classroom. The reporters found the children taking a vote on who the best <strong>character</strong> was on <em>Paw Patrol</em>, an <strong>animated</strong> TV series.</p>
<p>The three- and four-year-old children were choosing between two finalists: a German shepherd named Chase who wears a police uniform, and Skye, who wears a pink “pup pack.”</p>
<p>Educators at ACCA say they are teaching ideas of civics to students early. Their goal, they say, is to raise good citizens and strengthen democracy.</p>
<p>The students are not learning about the structure and rules of government. But teachers say they are working with students on how to solve problems with classmates, how to deal with anger or disappointment and how to think of the needs of others.</p>
<p>Mary Folks is a teacher at ACCA. She said, “We're all here to help develop these children to become better citizens...to be better problem-solvers and to be better equipped socially, emotionally...”</p>
<p>María-Isabel Ballivian is the preschool's executive director. She said she looks for ways to remind students that they are American. For example, she holds a large Fourth of July gathering.</p>
<p>Ballivian said, “If we give them now a sense of belonging, that's going to be a tool that they will have to become <strong>resilient</strong> once they face discrimination.”</p>
<p>Ballivian added, “I don't see how we can change the adults...But I do know, if we work hard, we can prepare our children for a better future.”</p>
<p>As for the class vote at ACCA, they narrowly supported Skye in their vote for best <em>Paw Patrol</em> character.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Moriah Balingit, Nathan Ellgren, and Almaz Abedje reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"> </h2>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>appreciate </strong><em>–v.</em> to be able to understand in some way</p>
<p><strong>worthy</strong> <em>–adj. </em>valued enough to merit a person's time, effort or concern</p>
<p><strong>contribute</strong> <em>–v.</em> to personally add to value to something or someone else</p>
<p><strong>autonomy</strong> <em>–n.</em> the ability to act independently without external help</p>
<p><strong>character </strong><em>–n.</em> a person or creature that appears in a movie, TV show, play or cartoon</p>
<p><strong>animated </strong><em>–adj</em>. relating to movie or TV cartoons which have the appearance of moving pictures rather than film or video</p>
<p><strong>resilient </strong><em>–adj.</em> able to recover from injury, damage or disease</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Blind Pianist Says Music Gives Him Energy, Hope (2024/10/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/blind-pianist-says-music-gives-him-energy-hope.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Takosangba Pongen could see until he was 14 years old. He has been blind for the 13 years since.</p>
<p>But, nobody would know that by watching Pongen perform on the piano.</p>
<p>Pongen said playing the piano helped him after he lost his sight. “It opened a window to see the world. It gives me energy and hope to go forward,” he said.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Takosangba Pongen, 27, a blind pianist, rehearses during the two-day Brillante Piano Festival in Bengaluru, India, Sunday, Sept. 29, 2024. (AP Photo/Aijaz Rahi) " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e6cfed63-fa38-4cf9-9487-f1eb344ee82b_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Takosangba Pongen, 27, a blind pianist, rehearses during the two-day Brillante Piano Festival in Bengaluru, India, Sunday, Sept. 29, 2024. (AP Photo/Aijaz Rahi) </span></div>
<p>Recently, he performed at the Brillante Piano Festival in Bengaluru, the capital of the southern Indian state of Karnataka.</p>
<p>Pongen plays by ear. He taught himself to play, assisted by piano play training on YouTube that he began using in 2020. He said he would like to be a professional musician someday.</p>
<p>But he is having difficulty finding a place that teaches piano to people with sight, or vision, problems.</p>
<p>Pongen first noticed his vision problems at school. He could not see clearly enough to read words on the<strong> blackboard </strong>in the room.</p>
<p>Then he remembers having difficulty seeing the small, glass balls called marbles that he liked to play with.</p>
<p>A medical operation to treat the problem failed, worsening his vision. By 14, Pongen was blind.</p>
<p>Pongen says that he sometimes wishes he could see but adds that he also accepts his condition as “God's plan.” He believes he is meant to serve as a model in how to face difficulty, lending support to others through example.</p>
<p>"If a blind man can do it, why can't others who are fully able,” Pongen said.</p>
<p>Brillante organizers said they believe in the “power of music as an agent of social development.” Pongen is a part of their “Specially Abled Musicians” program.</p>
<p>He played Nocturne in B Flat Minor, a work written by Frederic Chopin. Pongen said Chopin is one of his favorite writers of music.</p>
<p>“I love music that is expressive and emotional,” he said.</p>
<p>Pongen came more than 3,000 kilometers to Bengaluru. He traveled with his sister, Imlibenla, by his side to play at Brillante Festival, the fifth of its kind. His heart was racing, he said, when the program director, Khyochano TCK, presented him to the other musicians.</p>
<p>The nervousness returned as his performance time arrived. Pongen said he took a deep breath to calm himself.</p>
<p>Then, Imlibenla gently guided him onto the stage. She helped to seat him in front of the piano.</p>
<p>From there, he played beautifully.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Yirmiyan Arthur reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>_______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>blackboard</strong> <em>– n.</em> a hard smooth usually dark surface used especially in a classroom for writing or drawing on with chalk</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Nobel Prize Brings Attention to Worldwide Inequality (2024/10/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/nobel-prize-brings-attention-to-worldwide-inequality.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The Nobel Committee has brought attention to worldwide inequalities by awarding its economic prize to three Americans: Daron Acemoglu, Simon Johnson, and James A. Robinson.</p>
<p>The Nobel committee of the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences said the three won the 2024 Nobel Economics Prize “for studies of how <strong>institutions</strong> are formed and affect <strong>prosperity</strong>.”</p>
<p>Committee chair Jakob Svensson said, “Reducing the <strong>vast</strong> differences in income between countries is one of our time's greatest challenges.” He added that their research has provided “a much deeper understanding of the root causes of why countries fail or succeed.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences announces the Nobel Prize in economics, which goes to Daron Acemoglu, Simon Johnson and James A Robinson, in Stockholm, Sweden, October 14, 2024. (TT News Agency/Christine Olsson via REUTERS )" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/6d339d81-a7b6-4b57-acec-76b83da878b1_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences announces the Nobel Prize in economics, which goes to Daron Acemoglu, Simon Johnson and James A Robinson, in Stockholm, Sweden, October 14, 2024. (TT News Agency/Christine Olsson via REUTERS )</span></div>
<p>The wealthiest 20 percent of the world's countries are now around 30 times richer than the poorest 20 percent, the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences noted. The difference continues although poor countries have become relatively richer.</p>
<p>In 2021, the World Inequality Report said that the poorest half of the world's population owned just two percent of wealth while the richest 10 percent controlled 76 percent of wealth.</p>
<p>Acemoglu and Johnson work at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, while Robinson conducts his research at the University of Chicago.</p>
<p>Their findings are included in the 2012 book <em>Why Nations Fail: The Origins of Power, Prosperity, and Poverty </em>written by Acemoglu and Robinson.</p>
<p>In their work, the winners studied the city of Nogales, which sits on both sides of the U.S.-Mexico border.</p>
<p>Despite sharing the same geography, climate, many of the same ancestors and a common culture, life is different on either side of the border. In Nogales, Arizona, to the north, people are relatively wealthy and live long lives; most children complete high school. To the south, in Mexico's Nogales, Sonora, people are much poorer, and the city suffers from organized crime and corruption.</p>
<p>The difference, the economists said, is a U.S. system that protects property rights and gives citizens a say in their government.</p>
<p>The book includes evidence from ancient Rome to modern-day Nogales. It says that “inclusive institutions” make countries richer. It also says democracy, the rule of law and the protection of property rights prevent a small ruling class from owning most resources and wealth.</p>
<p>Reached by the academy in Athens, Greece, the Turkish-born Acemoglu said he was surprised and shocked by the award. He said the research honored by the prize underscores the value of democratic institutions.</p>
<p>“I think broadly speaking the work that we have done favors democracy,” he noted.</p>
<p>The Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences awards the prize in memory of Alfred Nobel. The prize was established after Nobel's death.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Hai Do adapted this story for VOA Learning English from Associated Press, Reuters and Nobel Prize reports. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>institution </strong><em>–n.</em> an established organization</p>
<p><strong>prosperity</strong> <em>–n. </em>a state of growing, improving and being successful</p>
<p><strong>vast</strong> <em>–adj.</em> very large in extent or size</p>
<p><strong>transitory </strong>–adj. taking place over a relatively short period of time; changing over time</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Map Fruit Fly Brain to Learn Its Functions (2024/10/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/scientists-map-fruit-fly-brain-to-learn-its-functions.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">14 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A group of international scientists recently announced they had made a map of the whole “brain” of an adult fruit fly.</p>
<p>They said the <strong>milestone</strong> would provide new knowledge about the brains of all animals including humans.</p>
<p>The research gives details of more than 50 million connections between 139,000 neurons, which are nerve cells in the brain of the fruit fly.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A handout microscopic image of a fruit fly released August 11, 2006. (REUTERS/CSIRO/Handout)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/50658aca-3e9c-45d2-b150-fcbd756a4c69_cx0_cy22_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A handout microscopic image of a fruit fly released August 11, 2006. (REUTERS/CSIRO/Handout)</span></div>
<p>The scientific name of the animal is Drosophila melanogaster. It is often used in scientific experiments, especially studies of nerve cells.</p>
<p>The researchers wanted to find out exactly how the brain cells operate when they are healthy and normal.</p>
<p>Sebastian Seung was one of the leaders of the research, which was published as a series of studies in <em>Nature</em>. Seung is a professor at Princeton University in New Jersey. He said, “You might be asking why we should care about the brain of a fruit fly. My simple answer is that if we can truly understand how any brain <strong>functions</strong>, it's bound to tell us something about all brains.”</p>
<p>The brain of a fruit fly is small — less than one millimeter wide. But some scientists are very interested in them. “It's beautiful,” said Cambridge researcher Gregory Jefferis.</p>
<p><strong>What the map showed</strong></p>
<p>The researchers created what they called a “wiring <strong>diagram</strong>” of an adult fruit fly. It is also called a “connectome” map. The goal was to create a map that shows how neurons connect to one another and how they operate.</p>
<p>Similar research has been done with simpler forms of life. For example, scientists have mapped the “brain” of a worm called Caenorhabditis elegans. They have also mapped the neural material of the <strong>larval</strong> form of the fruit fly. But the adult fruit fly was more complex. The idea was to link the neural connections to the behavior of the animal.</p>
<p>Mala Murthy was another co-leader of the research from Princeton. Murthy said, “One of the major questions we're addressing is how the wiring in the brain, its neurons and connections, can <strong>give rise to</strong> animal behavior.”</p>
<p>One of the studies in the series examined the brain <strong>circuits</strong> involved in walking. It discovered how flies halt. Another studied the fly's network of neurons associated with tasting and also grooming circuits. These circuits are behind the behavior in which a fly uses its leg to remove dirt from <strong>antennae</strong> on its head.</p>
<p>One of the studies examined how a fly processes motion and color information. And still another looked closely at how parts of the fly's brain were connected. That study discovered that a large group of neurons called “hub neurons” might help speed up the flow of information.</p>
<p>The researchers created the map by following how both sides of the brain were organized and linked the circuits they identified to behaviors. They also identified classes of cells in the fly's brain and examined the chemical connections between neurons known as synapses.</p>
<p>The international collaboration of scientists called FlyWire Consortium carried out the research.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Will Dunham reported this story for Reuters. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>milestone </strong><em>–n.</em> a sign that a major goal has been reached</p>
<p><strong>function</strong> <em>–n. </em>to purpose for something and the job that it does</p>
<p><strong>diagram</strong> –n. a simplified picture that shows how something works</p>
<p><strong>give rise to </strong><em>–v. (phrasal)</em> to cause; to bring about</p>
<p><strong>circuit </strong><em>–n.</em> a complete path by which electricity travels away from and returns to its source</p>
<p><strong>antenna (antennae pl.) </strong><em>–n.</em> the long structures attached to the heads of insects that help them feel and sense</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Pregnancy Changes the Brain (2024/10/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/study-pregnancy-changes-the-brain.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">14 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>When a brain scientist at the University of California, Irvine<strong> </strong>got pregnant at the age of 38, she saw a rare chance. <strong>Neuroscientist</strong> Liz Chrastil wanted to see how her brain changed while she was pregnant.</p>
<p>Chrastil was among a group of researchers who presented their findings in a new study. It offers the first detailed map of one woman's brain through the steps of pregnancy, also called <strong>gestation</strong>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A pregnant woman stands for a portrait in Dallas, May 18, 2023. (AP Photo/LM Otero, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/ff7d21d1-ad31-4ac5-bb8d-0ca31222ca4d_cx3_cy13_cw94_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A pregnant woman stands for a portrait in Dallas, May 18, 2023. (AP Photo/LM Otero, File)</span></div>
<p>Researchers say that motherhood affects nearly every part of the brain.</p>
<p>The researchers studied the effects of pregnancy in only one person: Chrastil. But their study has started a large international research project that aims to <strong>scan</strong> the brains of hundreds of women. The study could one day provide information about disorders<strong> </strong>like postpartum depression. Postpartum means after birth has taken place.</p>
<p>Chrastil said it has been a very long process. “We did 26 scans before, during and after pregnancy...” She said some of the findings were very noteworthy, or in her words “remarkable.” Chrastil is co-writer of the study that researchers published in <em>Nature Neuroscience </em>in September.</p>
<p>More than 80 percent of the parts of the brain studied had reductions in the amount of gray matter, where thinking takes place. This is an average of about four percent of the brain. This amount is nearly the same as the amount of reduction that happens during puberty. Puberty is the biological changes that cause a person to become a fertile adult.</p>
<p>However, the researchers said the reduction is probably not a bad thing. It might mean that networks of interconnected nerve cells called “neural circuits” are preparing for a new time in a woman's life.</p>
<p>The team began following Chrastil shortly before she became pregnant through <strong>in vitro fertilization</strong>. During the pregnancy and for two years after she gave birth, they continued doing <strong>MRI</strong> brain scans and blood tests to see how her brain changed. During this time, Chrastil's sex <strong>hormones</strong>, like estrogen, increased and decreased. Some of the changes continued past pregnancy.</p>
<p>Emily Jacobs is with the University of California, Santa Barbara and was also a co-writer of the study. Jacobs said earlier studies had taken scans of the brain before and after pregnancy. But she said, none had shown changes in the brain as they were taking place.</p>
<p>Unlike past studies, this one centered on many inner areas of the brain as well as the <strong>cerebral cortex</strong>, the outermost area, said Joseph Lonstein. He is a professor of neuroscience and <strong>psychology </strong>at Michigan State University and was not involved in the research.</p>
<p>Lonstein said it is “a good first step to understanding much more about whole-brain changes that could be possible in a woman across pregnancy and postpartum.”</p>
<p>Research in animals has linked some brain changes with qualities that could help the animal care for an infant. The new study does not deal with what the changes mean in terms of human behavior.</p>
<p>However, Lonstein said that it does describe changes in brain areas involved in social cognition, or thinking. This is how people act with others -- for example, how they understand their thoughts and feelings.</p>
<p>The researchers have partners in Spain, and they are developing what they call the <strong>Maternal</strong> Brain Project. The Ann S. Bowers Women's Brain Health <strong>Initiative</strong> and the Chan Zuckerberg Initiative support the project. The researchers say they hope scientists can use findings from more than one woman to predict problems such as postpartum depression.</p>
<p>“There is so much about the neurobiology of pregnancy that we don't understand yet,...” Jacobs said.</p>
<p>She added that this is not because women and pregnancy are too complex. More is not known about pregnancy and the brain, she said, because “biomedical sciences have historically ignored women's health.”</p>
<p>And that's the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Laura Ungar reported this story for the Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>neuroscientist </strong><em>–n.</em> a person who studies the nervous system including the brain</p>
<p><strong>gestation –</strong>n. the period of carry young in the uterus from conception to birth</p>
<p><strong>scan </strong><em>–n.</em> the process of using a device to make an image of the inside the body using sound, x-rays, or other radiation : also a <em>verb</em></p>
<p><strong>in vitro fertilization </strong><em>–adj.</em> fertilization of an egg in a laboratory dish or test tube <em>specifically</em> :<strong> </strong>fertilization by mixing sperm with eggs surgically removed from an ovary followed by uterine implantation of one or more of the resulting fertilized eggs —abbreviation <em>IVF</em></p>
<p><strong>MRI </strong><em>–n.</em> magnetic resonance imaging, also : the procedure in which magnetic resonance imaging is used</p>
<p><strong>hormone </strong><em>–n.</em> a product of living cells that circulates in body fluids (as blood) or sap and produces a specific and often stimulating effect on cells usually at a distance from the place where it is made</p>
<p><strong>maternal </strong><em>–adj. </em>of, relating to, belonging to, or characteristic of a mother</p>
<p><strong>initiative </strong><em>–n.</em> a plan or program intended to solve a problem</p>
<p><strong>cerebral cortex</strong> <em>–n.</em> the layer of gray matter that covers the outside of the cerebral hemispheres in the brain and is associated with higher cognitive functions, such as language, learning, perception, and planning.</p>
<p><strong>psychology </strong><em>–n. </em>the science of mind and behavior</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Some US Cities Use Sheep, Goats to Control Plant Growth (2024/10/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/some-us-cities-use-sheep-goats-to-control-plant-growth.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">14 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Some American communities and universities have been experimenting with sheep and goats to keep plant growth under control.</p>
<p>Along the Cumberland River near Nashville, Tennessee, visitors on boats watch the large buildings of the city in the distance. But they also can see something few expected: hundreds of sheep eating grass, or grazing, along the river.</p>
<p><strong>Sheep to remove unwanted plants </strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A flock of sheep called the Chew Crew move along the Cumberland River bank Tuesday, July 9, 2024, in Nashville, Tenn. The sheep are used to clear out overgrown weeds and invasive plants in the city's parks, greenways and cemeteries. (AP Photo/George Walker IV)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/321e07f5-4c67-44f0-9330-7b628243d8e3_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A flock of sheep called the Chew Crew move along the Cumberland River bank Tuesday, July 9, 2024, in Nashville, Tenn. The sheep are used to clear out overgrown weeds and invasive plants in the city's parks, greenways and cemeteries. (AP Photo/George Walker IV)</span></div>
<p>Zach Richardson oversees the sheep. His business is called Nashville Chew Crew. Richardson said sometimes the boats will go out of their way to let passengers get a closer look at his sheep. The group of sheep can be seen grazing a few hundred meters away from places where many people live and work.</p>
<p>The joy people get from watching sheep eat is partly why the creatures are becoming popular workers in some urban areas.</p>
<p>“Everybody that comes out here and experiences the sheep, they enjoy it more than they would someone...with a<strong> leaf blower</strong> or a <strong>weed eater</strong>,” Richardson said.</p>
<p>Using sheep to control plants is not a new method. But more American communities are choosing sheep to deal with problems such as invasive <strong>species</strong>, wildfire risks, native plant protection, and to keep historic places in good condition.</p>
<p>In 2017, Nashville's parks department paid for the Chew Crew to control unwanted plant growth at Fort Negley. The Union Army built the fort during the U.S. Civil War. Unwanted plants, or weeds, were growing between and along its stones. Tools like lawnmowers could easily damage the stones.</p>
<p>Sheep now graze in an area of about 61 hectares of city property yearly, including in the historic Nashville City Cemetery.</p>
<p>Jim Hester is assistant director of Metro Nashville Parks. Speaking about the sheep, he said, “It is a more environmentally <strong>sustainable</strong> way to care for the greenspace and oftentimes is cheaper than doing it with handheld equipment and <strong>staff</strong>."</p>
<p>Dogs watch over the Chew Crew's sheep. The dogs spend their whole lives with the sheep and keep visitors and animals from getting too close. The group of sheep, or flock, is made up of hair sheep, a kind of animal that naturally releases its hair fibers and is often used for meat.</p>
<p><strong>Santa Barbara fire protection </strong></p>
<p>Santa Barbara, California, has been using sheep for about seven years to protect land<strong> buffers</strong> that can slow or stop the spread of wildfires.</p>
<p>“The community loves the grazers and it's kind of a great way of community engagement,” said Monique O'Conner, open space planner for the city's parks and recreation.</p>
<p>The grazed areas can change how fire moves, said Mark vonTillow, the wildland specialist for the Santa Barbara City Fire Department.</p>
<p>VonTillow said that, if a fire hits a grazed area, “The fire behavior reacts <strong>drastically</strong> and drops to the ground.” He added, “That gives firefighters a chance to attack the fire.”</p>
<p>Some universities have tried using goats and sheep on their properties. In 2010, weeds were overtaking an area at the University of Georgia that was not used by students or staff. The weeds were pushing out native plants, said Kevin Kirsche, the school's director of sustainability.</p>
<p>Rather than using chemicals or mowers, Kirsche said the university hired Jennif Chandler to send in a<strong> herd</strong> of goats.</p>
<p>“Bringing the goats to the site was an <strong>alternative</strong> means of removing invasive plants in a way that was nontoxic to the environment and friendly to people,” Kirsche said.</p>
<p>At the time, Richardson, the owner of Chew Crew, was a student at the University of Georgia studying landscape architecture. He got the idea to create his own goat grazing business. The goats became the most popular four-legged creatures on campus, he said.</p>
<p>Richardson, who moved his company to Nashville after finishing his studies, now prefers sheep over goats. Sheep have closer group ties and are not as likely as goats to climb and explore.</p>
<p>“I'll never own another goat,” he admitted. “It's like trying to fence in water.”</p>
<p>But sheep are not an answer for all cities and their lands, O'Conner said. “We want to educate the public on why we're choosing to graze where we're grazing,” she added.</p>
<p>Hundreds of sheep can affect the environment by spreading seeds. The city of Santa Barbara does environmental studies before bringing in grazers since the process can also affect birds.</p>
<p>“Throwing like 500 sheep into an area is a much larger<strong> impact</strong> on the land and those soils than our native <strong>herbivores</strong> would have,” O'Conner said.</p>
<p>I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p>And I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Kristin M. Hall reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>leaf blower</strong> <em>–n. </em>a machine that uses a fan to blow away leaves</p>
<p><strong>weed eater </strong><em>–n.</em> a machine that cuts soft plants and grass</p>
<p><strong>species</strong><em> – n. </em>a class of individuals having common attributes and designated by a common name</p>
<p><strong>sustainable</strong> <em>– adj.</em> of, relating to, or being a method of harvesting or using a resource so that the resource is not depleted or permanently damaged</p>
<p><strong>staff</strong> <em>–n. </em>a regular employee</p>
<p><strong>buffer</strong> <em>– n.</em> any of various devices or pieces of material for reducing shock or damage due to contact</p>
<p><strong>drastically</strong> <em>– adv.</em> severely or seriously</p>
<p><strong>herd</strong> <em>–n. </em>a name for groups of certain animals such as cattle, sheep and goats</p>
<p><strong>alternative</strong> <em>– adj.</em> offering or expressing a choice</p>
<p><strong>impact</strong> <em>– n.</em> a significant or major effect</p>
<p><strong>herbivore</strong> <em>–n. </em>an animal that only eats plants</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: 610 Kinds of Birds Have Disappeared in Past 130,000 Years (2024/10/14)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/study-610-kinds-of-birds-have-disappeared-in-past-130-000-years.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">13 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>New research says that 610 bird <strong>species</strong> have died off over the past 130,000 years.</p>
<p>For instance, the Kaua'i 'ō'ō, a Hawaiian songbird, was declared <strong>extinct</strong> just last year.</p>
<p>The recent research also suggested that an “ongoing biodiversity crisis” that requires urgent study is taking place.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A flock of Common Teal fly across a wetland on a winter day on the outskirts of Srinagar on January 22, 2018. (REUTERS/Danish Ismail/File Photo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/c801f6d0-73e0-4b95-9fbf-57c1a7193cba_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A flock of Common Teal fly across a wetland on a winter day on the outskirts of Srinagar on January 22, 2018. (REUTERS/Danish Ismail/File Photo)</span></div>
<p>Bird species have a special purpose within the environment. When a bird species disappears, nothing remains to do its job, suggested Tom Matthews of the University of Birmingham in England. Matthews was the lead writer of the study that appeared recently in the publication Science.</p>
<p>Matthews said that birds do many important jobs in an environment. These jobs include spreading seeds, eating insects, or reusing dead material. Vultures, for example, eat the flesh of dead animals.</p>
<p>Matthews said a good example of the importance of birds is "on the islands of Mauritius and Hawaii, where all or almost all the native...birds that eat fruit...have gone extinct."</p>
<p>He explained, "In eating the fruits and then moving around, birds will <strong>disperse</strong> the seeds of the plants the fruits belong to.” The lack of seed spreading can have secondary effects, Matthews said. For example, Mauritius now has many threatened tree species.</p>
<p>Most of the documented extinctions have taken place on islands.</p>
<p>The loss of living areas for birds can have big effects given the limited area involved. Many island birds are flightless, meaning they cannot fly away to escape <strong>predators</strong>.</p>
<p>As a result, flightless birds are easily hurt by new predators, such as rats or cats, Matthews suggested.</p>
<p>Human hunting of birds was a big reason behind the disappearance of different bird species in the past. Bird hunting remains a big problem in some areas. Capturing birds for the songbird trade is a big problem, particularly in Southeast Asia, Matthews said.</p>
<p>Some areas and species had more exact reasons for bird disappearances. For example, avian malaria, introduced by people, has resulted in large numbers of extinctions in Hawaii where the birds possessed no natural immunity.</p>
<p>Matthews suggested that the effects of a changing climate on birds remains a “big unknown.”</p>
<p>Many birds have been lost over time.</p>
<p>The large flightless “elephant birds” were native to Madagascar. The bird is believed to have disappeared after people arrived. That includes Aepyornis maximus. It was about 3 meters tall and was possibly the largest bird that ever existed.</p>
<p>The flightless moa birds, native to New Zealand, including the South Island giant moa, also disappeared after humans came to the islands.</p>
<p>North America's passenger pigeon numbered in the billions but was hunted to extinction.</p>
<p>The researchers said the 610 bird species combined represented 3 billion years of evolutionary history. Each lost species is like cutting off a branch from the tree of life.</p>
<p>The number 610 is "likely a large underestimate" of avian extinctions, Matthews said. This is because of a lack of data from some areas and the fact some lost species may not have left behind bones or other evidence.</p>
<p>Matthews added, "the <strong>vast</strong> majority of extinctions over the last 50,000 years are <strong>attributable</strong> to human actions."</p>
<p>About 11,000 bird species now exist. The researchers projected future extinctions of more than 1,000 species over the next two hundred years.</p>
<p>"So even if you don't care about the moral and <strong>ethical</strong> concerns regarding the loss of species, these extinctions are important for other reasons, such as the loss of species that helped the environment to <strong>function</strong> effectively," Matthews added.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Will Dunham reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>species</strong> <em>– n.</em> a class of animals having common attributes and designated by a common name</p>
<p><strong>extinct</strong> <em>– adj.</em> no longer existing</p>
<p><strong>disperse</strong> <em>– v.</em> to cause to become spread widely</p>
<p><strong>predator</strong><em> –n.</em> an animal that hunts and eats other animals</p>
<p><strong>vast </strong>–<em>adj.</em> very great in size or extent</p>
<p><strong>attributable</strong> <em>– adj.</em> to be explained by indicating a cause</p>
<p><strong>ethical</strong> <em>–adj.</em> related to questions of right or wrong</p>
<p><strong>function</strong><em> – v.</em> to operate or be in action</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Europe Launches Spacecraft to Explore Asteroid Hit by NASA (2024/10/14)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/europe-launches-spacecraft-to-explore-asteroid-hit-by-nasa.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">13 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A European spacecraft has been launched to explore an <strong>asteroid</strong> struck in an earlier planetary defense mission by the American space agency NASA.</p>
<p>The European Space Agency (ESA's) Hera spacecraft launched October 7 from NASA's Cape Canaveral in Florida. The spacecraft, or probe, was carried to space aboard a SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket.</p>
<p>Hera is headed to the asteroid Dimorphos. NASA crashed its DART spacecraft into the space rock in 2022 in an area about 11 million kilometers from Earth. The NASA mission was an experiment to test a method for changing the orbit of asteroids that might one day threaten Earth.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="A SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket lifts off from the Cape Canaveral Space Force Station, Monday, Oct. 7, 2024 at Cape Canaveral, Fla., carrying a European spacecraft to an asteroid. (AP Photo/John Raoux)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4642df80-48c7-478d-8187-83c400c6f56b_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">A SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket lifts off from the Cape Canaveral Space Force Station, Monday, Oct. 7, 2024 at Cape Canaveral, Fla., carrying a European spacecraft to an asteroid. (AP Photo/John Raoux)</span></div>
<p>NASA has said its own studies of the crash <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/new-studies-show-nasa-s-asteroid-crash-test-was-highly-successful/6998173.html" target="_blank">showed it was successful</a> because the force of the strike changed the asteroid's orbit around a larger asteroid, called Didymos. Data showed the strike reduced the orbital period of Dimorphos by 33 minutes.</p>
<p>But the Hera mission seeks to closely examine Dimorphos to get more details on how the asteroid was changed in the strike by DART. Data collected by the ESA spacecraft will be used together with information gathered by NASA to develop future planetary defense plans.</p>
<p>American astronomer Derek Richardson, from the University of Maryland, told reporters before the launch, "The more detail we can <strong>glean</strong> the better as it may be important for planning a future <strong>deflection</strong> mission should one be needed.”</p>
<p>Officials from ESA have described the $400 million mission as a “crash <strong>scene</strong> investigation.” Hera project manager Ian Carnelli said the spacecraft was “going back to the crime site and getting all the scientific and technical information.”</p>
<p>Hera's trip to the asteroid is expected to take about two years. Next year, the probe plans to get a big gravitational push as it flies past Mars. It should arrive in the area around Dimorphos in December 2026.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p>Before it was hit by DART, Dimorphos circled a larger asteroid from about 1,189 meters out. Scientists believe the orbit is now closer and that Dimorphos changed its shape. Astronomers have also found evidence the asteroid is likely moving differently.</p>
<p>Examinations of the DART mission have suggested that rather than being a single hard rock, Dimorphos was more of a collection of <strong>rubble</strong> pieces held together by gravity. Investigators have said they believe the DART crash might have "completely deformed" the asteroid.</p>
<p>Ignacio Tanco is the flight director for the Hera mission. He told The Associated Press that some large rocks and other materials could still be following the asteroid. This, he said, could present a damage risk to the spacecraft.</p>
<p>“We don't really know very well the environment in which we are going to operate,” Tanco said. "But that's the whole point of the mission is to go there and find out.”</p>
<p>Hera will be equipped with two nanosatellites. One will land on Dimorphos and capture data on the asteroid with radar. The other will study the makeup of Dimorphos from farther out.</p>
<p>ESA and NASA will use the data to create plans for a possible asteroid strike that could cause wide destruction on Earth. Astronomers believe an asteroid wider than one kilometer – which could cause a worldwide disaster – is estimated to strike Earth about every 500,000 years.</p>
<p>An asteroid around 140 meters – which is a little smaller than Dimorphos but could still take out a major city – is predicted to hit Earth around every 20,000 years.</p>
<p>Currently there are no known 140-meter asteroids on a path to strike Earth. However, scientists have said only 40 percent of those space rocks are believed to have been identified.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>asteroid </strong><em>– n. </em>a rocky object that goes around the sun like a planet</p>
<p><strong>glean </strong><em>– v. </em>to discover something slowly or with difficulty</p>
<p><strong>deflect</strong><em> – v. </em>to make something change direction by hitting or touching it</p>
<p><strong>scene </strong><em>– n. </em>the place where something happens</p>
<p><strong>rubble </strong><em>– n. </em>pieces of broken rocks or bricks from a destroyed building or structure</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Italian Family Aims to Prove Its Painting Is a Picasso (2024/10/14)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/italian-family-aims-to-prove-its-painting-is-a-picasso.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">13 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A family in Italy hopes to prove that a painting found long ago on the island of Capri is the work of Spanish artist Pablo Picasso.</p>
<p>The family has been gathering scientific evidence to support the claim. It wants officials of the Picasso <strong>estate</strong> to confirm Picasso as the painting's creator.</p>
<p>A man found the painting in a load of waste he took possession of as a <strong>junk</strong> dealer more than 60 years ago. He hung the picture in his home for a long time. Later, it hung in a restaurant in Pompei, Italy.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A painting is seen at a restoration laboratory in Milan, Italy, Thursday, Oct. 3, 2024. (AP Photo/Antonio Calanni)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/3dd3f6c1-85ef-4b95-aa69-75819262b414_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A painting is seen at a restoration laboratory in Milan, Italy, Thursday, Oct. 3, 2024. (AP Photo/Antonio Calanni)</span></div>
<p>Then the man's son, Andrea Lo Russo, began to investigate the painting that, he said, his mother described as “<strong>ugly</strong>.”</p>
<p>He said he first came to think the painting was important after seeing a picture of a Picasso painting in a schoolbook. Later, as a young adult, Lo Russo and his brother took the painting to Paris. They showed it to experts at the Picasso Museum there.</p>
<p>“They looked, and they said, ‘it is not possible,'” Lo Russo remembered. The brothers refused the museum's offer to keep the painting for further study, he said.</p>
<p>Lo Russo said that his research into the painting's <strong>origin</strong> sometimes connected him with dishonest people. He said some people tricked<strong> </strong>him<strong> </strong>for money. One situation led officials to investigate him as a possible trafficker of false artwork.</p>
<p>That investigation ended after he produced paperwork confirming his effort to identify the family's painting.</p>
<p>After more than 20 years of trying, Lo Russo believes that recent tests carried out by the Swiss-based Arcadia Foundation prove that his painting is from Picasso.</p>
<p>Luca Marcante is a trained chemist who started the Arcadia Foundation in 2000 to investigate artwork. Marcante said laboratory tests show the paints used were like those Picasso used in one period of his career.</p>
<p>Most recently, a handwriting expert confirmed that the name written in the upper left corner of the painting is Picasso's handwriting, Marcante said.</p>
<p>For the art world, however, only one group can <strong>authenticate</strong> the painting as Picasso's work: the Picasso Administration in Paris. But, it has not answered a series of requests over the years.</p>
<p>Marcante said that he is preparing to share the most recent findings with them. He explains it this way: “You need to understand, they get dozens of inquiries every day from private people believing they have found a Picasso.”</p>
<p>The Picasso Administration chose not to speak to the Associated Press about the painting.</p>
<p><em><strong>Tete du femme </strong></em></p>
<p>Marcante said the painting is similar to <em>Tete du femme</em>,<em> </em>a 1949 painting that is believed to be a Picasso. It is part of a digital collection overseen by Sam Houston State University in Texas.</p>
<p>Adding to the mystery, Marcante said there is photographic evidence that Picasso visited the ruins of Pompeii in 1917. Marcante also said it is likely the artist visited Capri in the 1940s.</p>
<p>But expert Enrique Mallen doubts the painting is really Picasso's work. He said, “From what I know of studying Picasso for 30 years, he would never do an identical copy of his own work.”</p>
<p>The only record of <em>Tete du femme</em> is documentation from a 1967 book, which said the painting was in a private collection in Turin, Italy. Mallen said there is no other evidence of the painting.</p>
<p>Marcante called <em>Tete du femme</em> “a ghost painting, because no one has ever seen it.” He added, “The only real one is ours, that we have examined in a scientific manner...”</p>
<p>Lo Russo said that his family has not decided what to do with the painting if it is confirmed as a Picasso. Many people are asking about it now since news about the painting spread in recent weeks.</p>
<p>“We are <strong>confused</strong> ourselves,” he said.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Colleen Barry reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>estate</strong> <em>–n.</em> property left by its owner after the owner dies, which is administered by people who are appointed by the owner to do so into the future</p>
<p><strong>ugly </strong><em>–adj.</em> offensive to the sight</p>
<p><strong>origin</strong> <em>–n.</em> where something came from</p>
<p><strong>authenticate </strong><em>–v.</em> to go through a process to show that something is real or true legally or without a doubt</p>
<p><strong>confused </strong><em>–adj. </em>being perplexed or disconcerted</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>When in Rome … (2024/10/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/when-in-rome.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>One of the best things about traveling to a new country is learning about new traditions and customs. They can be very different from our own.</p>
<p>When visiting a foreign county, it is smart to follow the local social rules and customs of the people who live there. This can make your stay easier and more enjoyable.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A street vendor sells hats in front of the Colosseum in Rome, Monday, July 17, 2023. (AP Photo/Gregorio Borgia)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-d9e1-08db86e11944_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A street vendor sells hats in front of the Colosseum in Rome, Monday, July 17, 2023. (AP Photo/Gregorio Borgia)</span></div>
<p>Today we talk about <strong>fitting in </strong>with the way local people do things. We talk about an expression that goes all the way back to ancient Rome:</p>
<p><u>When in Rome, do as the Romans do.</u></p>
<p>This expression means that when we visit a place, we should follow the customs and norms of that place. This expression shows an <strong>attitude</strong> or <strong>mindset</strong>: You are willing to change your way of doing things to fit in with those around you.</p>
<p>The place does not have to be a new country. It can simply be a new situation or environment. For example, let's say you usually speak very loudly. But when visiting an art museum or library, you whisper in a low voice. You follow the rules of that place. <u>When in Rome ...</u></p>
<p>English speakers often shorten the expression to <u>“when in Rome...”</u></p>
<p>This expression has another meaning. When you are in an unfamiliar situation, you should follow the lead of those who know the rules. These people know how to <strong>behave </strong>with others. They know how to play the game. They know how to work within the system. They don't do things differently. They<strong> blend</strong><strong> in</strong>.</p>
<p>But what does Rome have to do with following other people's customs? Several websites describe how the expression may have begun. And if they are correct, this expression is very old.</p>
<p>Here is how the story goes:</p>
<p><em>During the time of the Roman Empire more than 1500 years ago, a Christian leader, Saint Augustine, moved from Rome to Milan. Once in the new city, he found some parts of religious life to be different. For example, in Rome he <strong>fasted,</strong> or did not eat, on Saturday. But in Milan, people did not fast on Saturday. Another church leader, Saint Ambrose, gave him some advice. St. Ambrose said that when he goes to Rome he fasts on Saturdays. But when he is in Milan, he does not. Problem solved.</em></p>
<p>This good advice, or proverb, has survived over the years. Some word experts say it first appeared in English around 500 years ago.</p>
<p>But we still use it to this day -- either to give advice or to describe a situation where we have to change our behavior to fit in.</p>
<p>Let's hear another example.</p>
<p><em>A: How was your trip to see your brother's family?</em></p>
<p><em>B: It was really fun. Different but fun. </em></p>
<p><em>A: How was it different?</em></p>
<p><em>B: Well, they live in the country and love to hunt and fish. So, that's what I did all week. It was great! </em></p>
<p><em>A: I am so surprised. I didn't think you were the <strong>outdoorsy</strong> type.</em></p>
<p><em>B: I'm not! But <u>when in Rome ...</u></em></p>
<p><em>A: With that attitude, it's <strong>no wonder</strong> you had a fun trip!</em></p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>.</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>__________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>fit in </strong><em>–v. (phrasal)</em> to behave in a way that is like other people near, so they do not form bad opinions about you</p>
<p><strong>attitude </strong><em>–n.</em> the way you think or feel about someone or something</p>
<p><strong>mindset </strong>–n. a way of thinking</p>
<p><strong>behave </strong>–v. the way a person acts</p>
<p><strong>blend</strong><strong> in </strong><em>–v. (phrasal)</em> to not bring attention to oneself</p>
<p><strong>fast </strong>–v. to not eat for a period of time, often for religious reasons<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>outdoorsy<em> </em></strong><em>–adj. (informal) </em>enjoying or accustomed to nature and wild areas</p>
<p><strong>no wonder<em> </em></strong><em>–interjection </em>it is not a surprise<em> </em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Weather Experts: ‘We Cannot Control Hurricanes’ (2024/10/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/weather-experts-we-cannot-control-hurricanes.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A series of powerful hurricanes have affected millions of people in the United States in recent weeks.</p>
<p>Some people are wondering if scientists could control extreme weather events. However, experts say hurricanes are far too powerful for humans to control.</p>
<p>Climate change is leading to increasingly powerful storms. This has led to greater attention on the possibilities of geoengineering.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A Bayou West resident and friend try to salvage items from her home after an apparent tornado touched down on the central beach community after Hurricane Milton in Vero Beach, Fla., Oct.11, 2024. (Kaila Jones/USA Today Network via Reuters)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f407c0c7-2c38-4f45-85bc-d1258491eddd_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A Bayou West resident and friend try to salvage items from her home after an apparent tornado touched down on the central beach community after Hurricane Milton in Vero Beach, Fla., Oct.11, 2024. (Kaila Jones/USA Today Network via Reuters)</span></div>
<p>Geoengineering involves futuristic ideas for <strong>reversing</strong> or lessening climate change. But many scientists have serious concerns about unwanted results.</p>
<p>Hurricanes are an example of the uncontrollable, disordered power of Earth's weather. Experts say there is no clear evidence from research to show humans might be able to control such strong storms.</p>
<p>Kristen Corbosiero is a professor of atmospheric and environmental sciences at the University at Albany. Corbosiero is a weather expert, or meteorologist. She said: "If meteorologists could stop hurricanes, we would stop hurricanes. If we could control the weather, we would not want the kind of death and destruction that's happened."</p>
<p><strong>Weather experts' opinions on controlling hurricanes</strong></p>
<p>National Hurricane Center tropical <strong>analysis</strong> chief Chris Landsea said that a fully developed hurricane releases heat energy that is the equal to a 10-megaton nuclear bomb every 20 minutes. That is more than all the energy used at a given time by human beings.</p>
<p>Chris Field is director of the Stanford Woods Institute for the Environment in California. He said scientists are learning of the many ways that climate change is making hurricanes more powerful and destructive. Warmer oceans add energy and more water to the warming atmosphere. That water becomes strong rainfall.</p>
<p>Colorado State University hurricane researcher Phil Klotzbac said the amount of energy a hurricane generates is much more than humans have the power to control. But people have still made attempts to control the storms.</p>
<p><strong>Historical efforts to control hurricanes</strong></p>
<p>Jim Fleming is a professor at Colby College in Maine. He has studied historical efforts to control the weather. He said humans do not even come close to having the practical technology to successfully control the weather.</p>
<p>Fleming described one attempt in 1947. The General Electric company partnered with the U.S. military to drop dry ice from Air Force planes into the path of a hurricane to try to weaken it. It did not work.</p>
<p>Some attempts or ideas could even make the storms worse or cause greater harm. One especially dangerous idea was to use a nuclear bomb, which would cause radiation and not be strong enough to change the storm, Kristen Corbosiero said.</p>
<p>Bringing cooling <strong>icebergs</strong> or adding chemicals to cause rain also are ideas that do not work, scientists say.</p>
<p><strong>Engineering the climate</strong></p>
<p>Modern geoengineers would operate differently. Today's geoengineers are thinking about how to <strong>reverse</strong> the damage humans have already caused.</p>
<p>Scientists in the field say one of the most promising ideas they see based on computer models is <strong>solar</strong> geoengineering. The method would involve lifting small particles into the upper atmosphere to return some of the sunlight back into space, cooling the planet a little. Still, supporters of the idea know that it comes with risks.</p>
<p>Two years ago, the American Geophysical Union (AGU) announced it was forming an <strong>ethics </strong>agreement for climate intervention. The AGU is the largest society of scientists who study climate issues.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Melina Walling and Seth Borenstein </em><em>reported this story for the </em><em>Associated Press</em><em>.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>geoengineering </strong>– <em>n</em>. large-scale manipulation of a specific process central to controlling Earth's climate for the purpose of obtaining a specific benefit</p>
<p><strong>reverse</strong> – <em>v. </em>to change (something) to an opposite state or condition</p>
<p><strong>analysis</strong> –<em> n.</em> a careful study of something to learn about its parts, what they do, and how they are related to each othe</p>
<p><strong>iceberg</strong> – <em>n.</em> a very large piece of ice floating in the ocean</p>
<p><strong>solar</strong> – n. of or relating to the sun</p>
<p><strong>ethics</strong> –<em> n</em>. n area of study that deals with ideas about what is good and bad behavior</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How to Improve Your Spelling (2024/10/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/how-to-improve-your-spelling.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Guillermo in Argentina about how to spell words in English.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4ec92eba-4c0f-40d5-9a0e-3106d24bba11_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>When I hear some new words in English, I can find their meaning, but for me, the spelling is always difficult. Can you please give me [some] advice?</p>
<p>Thank you,</p>
<p>Guillermo</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Guillermo.</p>
<p>English spelling can be difficult for several reasons. For many letters in the English alphabet, a letter can represent several sounds.</p>
<p>Let's listen to the sound the letter “A” makes in each of the following six words:</p>
<p><em>cat</em></p>
<p><em>day</em></p>
<p><em>father</em></p>
<p><em>ball</em></p>
<p><em>many</em></p>
<p><em>attack</em></p>
<p>Can you hear the difference between the two letters “A” of the last word? Let's listen again.</p>
<p><em>attack</em></p>
<p>The first syllable made the quick schwa sound “/<strong><i></i>601;/</strong>”.</p>
<p>Because an English letter can make different sounds, words that have similar spellings can sound different from each other, as in these examples:</p>
<p><em>lemon </em>and<em> demon</em></p>
<p><em>daughter </em>and<em> laughter</em></p>
<p><em>war </em>and<em> far</em></p>
<p>In addition, words that have different spellings can sound the same. These are called homophones, as in these examples:</p>
<p><em>pause </em>and<em> paws</em></p>
<p><em>rode </em>and<em> road</em></p>
<p><em>deer </em>and<em> dear</em></p>
<p>But that's not all. In many words, some letters are silent—they are not pronounced at all, like the letter “b” at the end of the word “climb”.</p>
<p>You can see from all of the above examples that you cannot only use the sounds of words to know how to spell them. So, what should you do?</p>
<p><strong>Spelling rules</strong></p>
<p>Fortunately, English does have some general rules for spelling.</p>
<p>For example, a famous rule that children learn in school is “<em>I</em> before <em>e</em> except after <em>c.”</em> This gives us the spelling of words such as:</p>
<p><em>piece</em></p>
<p><em>niece</em></p>
<p><em>receive</em></p>
<p>But be careful! There are still many words in English that break the spelling rules. The word “science,” for example, breaks the “I before e” rule. For words such as these, you simply have to memorize how to spell them. And how can you do that?</p>
<p><strong>Memorizing words</strong></p>
<p>The best way to help your memory is to read as much as possible and practice writing. Writing can test how well you know how to spell. Most computer programs also include a spell-checker, where misspelled words are underlined in a color. This helps you see any spelling mistakes you have made and also shows you the correct spelling.</p>
<p><strong>Recognizing patterns</strong></p>
<p>In addition to rules, there are spelling <strong>patterns</strong>. You can group words into the pattern they follow. For example, some words that have the spelling -ough include:</p>
<p><em>rough, tough, cough, though, </em>and <em>bought</em>.</p>
<p>Notice, however, that with these examples, the letters -ough made three different vowel sounds:</p>
<p><em>rough, cough, though</em></p>
<p>This again shows the need to memorize spellings because the sound of the word will not always tell you how to spell it.</p>
<p><strong>Having fun</strong></p>
<p>Lastly, becoming good at spelling can be enjoyable. Think of it like a game or other activity you enjoy. Over time, you will feel good as you learn to spell more and more words. There are many books, websites, and apps designed for spelling practice. Try to use these and practice your spelling.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? We'd like to hear from you. Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please include where you are from in your email, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>pattern </strong>–n. a regular or repeated happening</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Han Kang, First South Korean Writer to Win Nobel in Literature (2024/10/11)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/han-kang-first-south-korean-writer-to-win-nobel-in-literature.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">10 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>South Korean writer Han Kang won the 2024 Nobel Prize in Literature on Thursday. The Swedish Academy's Nobel Committee said her work “confronts historical <strong>traumas</strong> and exposes the <strong>fragility</strong> of human life.”</p>
<p>Born in 1970, Han Kang is the first South Korean to win the literature prize. Kang began her career in 1993 with the publication of several poems in <em>Literature and Society</em>. She published her first story in 1995 with <em>Love of Yeosu.</em></p>
<p>In 2016, Kang won the Man Booker International Prize for <em>The Vegetarian.</em> It tells the story of a woman's decision to stop eating meat and her family's worry about her mental health. The <strong>novel</strong> was the first of her books to be translated into English and was seen as her major international breakthrough.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Han Kang speaks to the media after winning the Man Booker International prize for fiction for her book 'The Vegetarian' in London, Tuesday, May, 16, 2016. Kang has won the Nobel Prize for Literature. (AP Photo/Alastair Grant, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01e877c5-133c-4c36-8e44-b7776aa637a0_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Han Kang speaks to the media after winning the Man Booker International prize for fiction for her book 'The Vegetarian' in London, Tuesday, May, 16, 2016. Kang has won the Nobel Prize for Literature. (AP Photo/Alastair Grant, File)</span></div>
<p>In a talk with the Booker Prizes, published last year, Kang said the book was written during a difficult period in her life. She questioned whether she could finish the story or even survive as a writer.</p>
<p>"I was suffering from severe <strong>arthritis</strong>...To this day, I feel awkward when I hear about the novel's ‘success,'” she said.</p>
<p>In the novel <em>Human Acts</em>, Kang explored the 1980 killing of hundreds of students and unarmed civilians by the South Korean military in the city of Gwangju, where she grew up.</p>
<p>"In seeking to give voice to the victims of history, the book confronts this episode with <strong>brutal</strong> actualization and, in so doing, approaches the <strong>genre</strong> of witness literature," the Academy said.</p>
<p><strong>One of two South Korean Nobel winners</strong></p>
<p>Kang is the second South Korean to win a Nobel Prize. Former South Korean President Kim Dae-jung received the Nobel Peace Prize in 2000 for his efforts to restore democracy in the South and improve relations with North Korea.</p>
<p>The literature prize has long faced criticism that it is too centered on European and North American writings. It has also been awarded mainly to male writers. Kang is only the 18th woman to receive the award among more than 100 winners.</p>
<p>Past winners of the prize include well-known writers like Irish poet W.B. Yeats, American writer Ernest Hemingway and Colombia's Gabriel Garcia Marquez. In 2016, American singer Bob Dylan also received the prize “for having created new poetic expressions within the great American song tradition”</p>
<p>Mats Malm is Permanent Secretary of the Swedish Academy. He told reporters, “I was able to talk to Han Kang over the phone. She was having an ordinary day, it seems, she had just finished <strong>supper</strong> with her son."</p>
<p>The prize comes with a money award of $1.1 million.</p>
<p>I'm Mario J. Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Jill Robbins adapted the story for Learning English based on reports from Reuters and The Associated Press.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>trauma </strong>– <em>n.</em> a very difficult or unpleasant experience that causes someone to have mental or emotional problems usually for a long time</p>
<p><strong>fragile</strong> – <em>adj</em>. easily broken or damaged</p>
<p><strong>novel</strong> <em>– n.</em> a long written story usually about imaginary characters and events</p>
<p><strong>arthritis</strong><strong> </strong>– <em>n.</em> a disease that causes the joints of the body to become swollen and painful</p>
<p><strong>brutal</strong> – <em>adj</em>. very direct and accurate in a way that is harsh or unpleasant</p>
<p><strong>genre</strong> - <em>n</em>. a particular type or category of literature or art</p>
<p><strong>supper</strong> – <em>n</em>. the evening meal — used especially to refer to an informal meal that you eat at home</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>UN: Crime Groups in Southeast Asia Find Success on Telegram (2024/10/11)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/un-crime-groups-in-southeast-asia-find-success-on-telegram.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">10 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Powerful crime groups in Southeast Asia use the messaging app Telegram widely, the United Nations said in a report on Monday. It said the app's use led to major changes in the way such groups carry out large criminal operations.</p>
<p>The U.N. Office on Drugs and Crime (UNODC) produced the report. The investigators say stolen data, including credit card information, passwords and <strong>browser</strong> history, are openly traded on the app. The app has many channels and little content supervision, the report said.</p>
<p>Criminals on the app also sell tools used for cybercrime, including so-called <strong>deepfake</strong> software and data-stealing <strong>malware</strong>. And, criminal <strong>cryptocurrency</strong> exchanges carry out business on Telegram also, the report said.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Telegram app logo is seen in this illustration taken, August 27, 2024. (REUTERS/Dado Ruvic/Illustration)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4b0d8111-f03c-44a1-b2cc-c8cfacb24f2a_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Telegram app logo is seen in this illustration taken, August 27, 2024. (REUTERS/Dado Ruvic/Illustration)</span></div>
<p>"We move 3 million USDT stolen from overseas per day," the report quoted one advertisement as saying in Chinese.</p>
<p>There is "strong evidence of underground data markets moving to Telegram and <strong>vendors</strong> actively looking to target transnational organized crime groups based in Southeast Asia," the report said.</p>
<p>Southeast Asia has emerged as a center for a multibillion-dollar online crime industry that targets victims across the world. Many industry members are Chinese criminal groups that operate from large, protected complexes using trafficked workers. The industry makes between $27.4 billion to $36.5 billion yearly, the UNODC said.</p>
<p>In August, French police arrested Telegram's leader Pavel Durov in Paris. Officials charged him with permitting criminal activity on the site, including the online spread of sexual images of children.</p>
<p>Telegram, which has close to 1 billion users, did not immediately answer a request for comment</p>
<p>Following his arrest, Durov said the app would surrender users' IP addresses and phone numbers to French officials making legal requests. He also said the app would remove some tools that have been abused for illegal activity.</p>
<p>The report said the huge amount of profit earned by criminal groups in the area led them to change their operating methods. They established new business models and added technologies to their systems, including malware, generative artificial intelligence and deepfakes, officials say.</p>
<p>The UNODC said it had identified more than ten deepfake software service providers “targeting criminal groups involved in cyber-enabled <strong>fraud</strong> in Southeast Asia."</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Reuters reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong><strong> </strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>browser - </strong><em>n. </em>a computer program used for accessing sites or information on a network (such as the World Wide Web)</p>
<p><strong>deepfake - </strong><em>n. </em>an image or recording that has been convincingly altered and manipulated to misrepresent someone as doing or saying something that was not actually done or said</p>
<p><strong>malware - </strong><em>n. </em>software designed to interfere with a computer's normal functioning</p>
<p><strong>cryptocurrency - </strong><em>n.</em><strong> </strong>any form of currency that only exists digitally, that usually uses a decentralized system for issuing new units and reording transactions, and that relies on cryptography to prevent fraudulent transactions</p>
<p><strong>vendor - </strong><em>n. </em>seller</p>
<p><strong>fraud - </strong><em>n. </em>the use of dishonest methods to cheat another person of something valuable</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: US Hurricanes Much Deadlier Than Government Estimates (2024/10/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/study-us-hurricanes-much-deadlier-than-government-estimates.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A new study says hurricanes in the United States are hundreds of times deadlier than government estimates say. In fact, the research finds, they result in more American deaths over the long term than car accidents or wars.</p>
<p>The study found the average storm that hits the U.S. <strong>contributes</strong> to the early deaths of 7,000 to 11,000 people over a 15-year period.</p>
<p>Solomon Hsiang is a climate economist at Stanford University in California. Hsiang co-wrote the study with Rachel Young of the University of California Berkeley.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This GOES-16 GeoColor satellite image taken at 12:15 p.m. EDT and provided by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shows Hurricane Milton in the Gulf of Mexico, off the coast of Mexico's Yucatan Peninsula on Oct. 8, 2024. (NOAA via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/744bf985-5557-411a-bd23-eb4d9cd90b7e_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This GOES-16 GeoColor satellite image taken at 12:15 p.m. EDT and provided by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shows Hurricane Milton in the Gulf of Mexico, off the coast of Mexico's Yucatan Peninsula on Oct. 8, 2024. (NOAA via AP)</span></div>
<p>“After each storm there is sort of this surge of additional <strong>mortality</strong> in a state that's been <strong>impacted </strong>that has not been <strong>previously</strong> documented or<strong> associated</strong> with hurricanes in any way,” Hsiang said.</p>
<p><em>Nature</em> magazine published the study.</p>
<p><strong>Researchers take a wider look </strong></p>
<p>The research considers hurricane deaths in a new way: through examination of long-term public health and economic effects of what is called <strong>excess</strong> mortality. The investigators looked at individual state death rates following 501 separate storms in the United States between 1930 and 2015. Their research shows a sudden rise or “bump” in death rates after each storm.</p>
<p>Similar examinations are done for heat waves and other health threats like pollution and disease, Hsiang said. They compare death rates to pre-storm times while accounting for other influences that could be causing change to those rates, he said.</p>
<p>Hsiang said additional research is needed to learn how storms contribute to deaths after the bad weather passes. But he theorized that storms cause major stress as well as environmental changes, including the spread of poisonous substances. He also said the economic cost of storms can leave people unable to pay for health care and other necessities.</p>
<p><strong>Early deaths</strong></p>
<p>“When someone dies a few years after a hurricane hit them, the cause will be recorded as a heart attack, stroke or respiratory failure,” said Texas A&amp;M University climate scientist Andrew Dessler. He was not part of the study but has done similar research on heat and cold deaths.</p>
<p>Hsiang said he and Young were surprised when they examined hundreds of bumps and found they stretch out over 15 years.</p>
<p>It's “almost like a <strong>trickle</strong> of mortality, like each month we're talking about five to 10 individuals who are dying earlier than they would have otherwise," Hsiang said.</p>
<p>These deaths are of people who did not realize their health issues were connected to storms that took place years earlier. But, Hsiang said, that is what the data shows: "They would not have died at those times had the storm not arrived.”</p>
<p>The numbers proved so high that the researchers kept looking for mistakes in their work. “It took years for us to really fully accept that this was happening," Hsiang said.</p>
<p><strong>How big are the numbers?</strong></p>
<p>Storms are a factor in between 55,000 to 88,000 excess deaths each year, the study found. Over the 85 years included in the study, the team found that between 3.6 million and 5.2 million people died in connection with storm experience. That is more than the two million car accident deaths over that same period, the study said.</p>
<p>Hsiang said he and Young saw a <strong>trend</strong> of increasing hurricane-connected deaths, mostly as a result of population growth. Beginning in 2000, there was a big jump in the total volume of storms hitting large populations, he said.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong><strong> </strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>contribute </strong><em>– v. </em>to have a part in bringing about something</p>
<p><strong>mortality</strong> <em>– n. </em>the death of large numbers (as of people or animals)</p>
<p><strong>previously</strong> <em>– adv. </em>going before in time or order</p>
<p><strong>associate </strong><em>– v. </em>to link or connect</p>
<p><strong>trickle </strong><em>– n. </em><strong> </strong>to move or go one by one or little by little</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Tech Tip: Instagram’s New Tools to Protect Young Users (2024/10/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/tech-tip-instagram-s-new-tools-to-protect-young-users.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Meta's Instagram service recently introduced some built-in tools designed to protect young users. The changes also give parents more control over their children's accounts to improve safety and limit the amount of time spent on the social networking <strong>app</strong>.</p>
<p>Instagram <a class="wsw__a" href="https://about.fb.com/news/2024/09/instagram-teen-accounts/#:~:text=Teens%20under%2016%20will%20need%20their%20parent's%20permission%20to%20use,to%20turn%20on%20parental%20supervision.">says</a> the new tools aim to “<strong>reassure</strong> parents that teens are having safe experiences.” The main change was the establishment of Teen Accounts, which Meta says was developed “with parents and teens in mind.”</p>
<p>The Associated Press offers the following tips as a guide for parents to get the most out of the new tools.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file photo, students use their cellphones as they leave for the day the Ramon C. Cortines School of Visual and Performing Arts High School in downtown Los Angeles, Aug. 13, 2024. (AP Photo/Damian Dovarganes, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/170a62cc-b678-4c17-bb1e-a11dbfe92812_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this file photo, students use their cellphones as they leave for the day the Ramon C. Cortines School of Visual and Performing Arts High School in downtown Los Angeles, Aug. 13, 2024. (AP Photo/Damian Dovarganes, File)</span></div>
<p><strong>What limits will young users have? </strong></p>
<p>Instagram already restricts anyone under 13 from signing up for the service. Now, teen accounts will <strong>automatically</strong> be set to private. That means they will have to accept or reject requests from new followers. Other users will not be able to see a teen user's posts and videos or communicate with the account.</p>
<p>Teens will also face messaging restrictions. They can only receive direct messages from people they are following or who follow them. But they can still send messages to other accounts.</p>
<p>Teen Accounts will also restrict certain kinds of material, or content. This will include sensitive subjects such as videos of people fighting or content that pushes methods to improve appearance. In addition, Instagram's anti-bullying tools will be set to the highest level to prevent offensive words and phrases in comments and direct message requests.</p>
<p>To restrict usage time, teens will get a message to stop using the app after it has been open for more than an hour. This message can be ignored, however.</p>
<p><strong>Can the new limits be changed?</strong></p>
<p>The new limits will be turned on automatically for all teens. But 16 and 17-year-olds will have the ability to turn them off. Children under 16 will need parental permission to do so.</p>
<p>Teens might also seek to lie about their age to get around the restrictions. But Meta has made it more difficult for them to do so. Young users are required to confirm their ages by uploading an identification card or by sending a short video of themselves.</p>
<p>Instagram says it will also begin testing artificial intelligence (AI) software early next year that will aim to prevent false birth dates from being accepted.</p>
<p><strong>New controls for parents </strong></p>
<p>If a parent does not think the limits for their child are strong enough, they can add more protective controls. For example, a parent has the ability to see who their teen has traded messages with within the past seven days.</p>
<p>The new tools also provide controls for parents to set daily limits for Instagram use. A parent can also block a teen from using Instagram during specific times of the day and follow subjects they are seeing.</p>
<p><strong>How to set up parental controls</strong></p>
<p>To set up additional controls, a parent first needs to set up family <strong>supervision</strong> on his or her account. On the mobile app, this can be done by going into settings and scrolling to find the family center to activate the tools.</p>
<p>Next, the Teen Account will have to invite a parent. This will be in the form of a link the teen can send by text message to the parent. After accepting the invite, the teen user has 48 hours to confirm the parent's response.</p>
<p><strong>Can I use the teen settings right away?</strong></p>
<p>The restrictive tools will be automatically activated for anyone under 18 who now signs up for Instagram in the U.S., Britain, Canada and Australia. For existing accounts, the restrictions will be put in place by mid-November.</p>
<p>The protections will be available for teens in the European Union's 27 countries beginning later this year. And the rest of the world will get Teen Accounts for Instagram in January. Meta says it will also bring the changes to other services like Facebook next year.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English, with additional information from Meta.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>app </strong><em>– n. </em>a small computer program that can be put onto a mobile phone or other electronic device</p>
<p><strong>reassure </strong><em>– v. </em>to say something to stop someone from worrying</p>
<p><strong>automatic </strong><em>– adj.</em><em> </em>working by itself with little human control</p>
<p><strong>supervise </strong><em>– v. </em>to watch a person or activity to make sure things are being done correctly, safely, etc.</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Win Nobel in Chemistry for Predicting, Designing Proteins (2024/10/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/scientists-win-nobel-in-chemistry-for-predicting-designing-proteins.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">09 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Three scientists who developed methods to predict the structure of proteins and build new ones have won the Nobel Prize in Chemistry.</p>
<p>The winners were American David Baker, a professor at the University of Washington; Briton Demis Hassabis, head of Google's DeepMind research laboratory in London; and American John Jumper, a top researcher at DeepMind. The lab centers on artificial intelligence (AI) methods.</p>
<p>Protein is one of the most important substances to life on Earth. Baker succeeded in building new kinds of proteins. Hassabis and Jumper solved a problem that had existed for 50 years. They were finally able to use AI to predict the structure of proteins.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This combo of pictures show American biochemist David Baker, from left, American researcher John Jumper and Demis Hassabis, CEO of DeepMind Technologies, the AI division behind Gemini. (UW Medicine/Google DeepMind via AP/AP Photo/Jeff Chiu)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e4fa581a-667d-405e-a799-0eb7806b00c9_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This combo of pictures show American biochemist David Baker, from left, American researcher John Jumper and Demis Hassabis, CEO of DeepMind Technologies, the AI division behind Gemini. (UW Medicine/Google DeepMind via AP/AP Photo/Jeff Chiu)</span></div>
<p>The Nobel Committee for Chemistry said the discoveries “hold enormous potential.”</p>
<p>For example, committee members said the ability to build new proteins could lead to the discovery of new drugs and vaccines. It could also help scientists develop extremely small materials, called nanomaterials, and small sensors.</p>
<p>Heiner Linke is Chair of the Nobel Committee for Chemistry. He said the award honored research that made connections for the first time between amino acid sequences and protein structures.</p>
<p>“That was actually a grand challenge in chemistry, and in particular biochemistry” for many years, Linke said.</p>
<p><strong>Designing and predicting proteins</strong></p>
<p>Baker first designed a new protein in 2003. Since then, his research group has produced many different proteins. “It seems that you can almost construct any type of protein now with this technology,” said Professor Johan Aqvist of the Nobel committee.</p>
<p>The committee said Hassabis and Jumper created an AI model called AlphaFold2. It has been able to predict the structure of nearly all 200 million proteins researchers have identified.</p>
<p>Linke said, “Proteins are the molecules that enable life. Proteins are building blocks that form bones, skin, hair and tissue.” He added, “To understand how life works, we first need to understand the shape of proteins.”</p>
<p>Linke said that in 2020, Hassabis and Jumper were able to use AI methods to finally “<strong>crack the code</strong>.” That made it possible to predict the complex structure of “any known protein in nature.”</p>
<p>There are many possible uses for the technology. Researchers should be able to use it to better understand how organisms develop resistance to antibiotics. They might also be able to create images of chemical substances called enzymes that can break down plastic.</p>
<p>The committee said Baker had developed “computational tools” that enable scientists to design new proteins with new shapes and <strong>functions</strong>.</p>
<p>Baker noted that Hassabis and Jumper's work in AI had greatly helped his team.</p>
<p>“The <strong>breakthroughs</strong> made by Demis and John on protein structure prediction really highlighted to us the power that AI could have,” he said. “And that led us to <strong>apply</strong> these AI methods to protein design and that has greatly increased the power and <strong>accuracy</strong>.”</p>
<p>Baker was asked during a phone call with Nobel officials and reporters if he had a favorite protein. He said it would be difficult to choose. But he noted that one designed during the pandemic proved to be effective in protecting against the coronavirus.</p>
<p>“And I've been very excited about the idea of a <strong>nasal spray</strong>, of little designed proteins, that would protect against all possible pandemic viruses.” Baker said.</p>
<p>Hassabis is a leader in Britain's technology industry. He received a knighthood earlier this year for his work in AI. He helped establish DeepMind in 2010. Google later bought the lab.</p>
<p>DeepMind first gained wide attention by developing an AI system that was able to defeat the human world champion in the Chinese game of Go faster than expected.</p>
<p>This year's Nobel Prize in Chemistry is worth about $1 million. Half of the prize will go to Baker. Hassabis and Jumper will share the other half.</p>
<p>Award ceremonies for the 2024 Nobel Prize winners will be held on December 10.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Daniel Niemann and Mike Corder reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>to crack the code </strong>–idiom to discover something that is hidden or very difficult to know</p>
<p><strong>function</strong> <em>–n. </em>the job that something does</p>
<p><strong>breakthrough</strong> <em>–n.</em> a sudden jump in knowledge or ability</p>
<p><strong>apply </strong>–v. to use a method or practice to carry out a task or operation</p>
<p><strong>accuracy </strong>–n. exactly showing the true value or condition of something</p>
<p><strong>nasal spray </strong>–n. a liquid that is sprayed into the nose to ease discomfort or support health</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>In Changing Climate, Scientists Develop Stronger Seeds for India (2024/10/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/in-changing-climate-scientists-develop-stronger-seeds-for-india.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Unpredictable rains and increasing heat are making life more difficult for the people of Rayanpet, a village in southern India. The conditions are also damaging the rice crops grown there.</p>
<p>P. Ravinder Reddy, a former soldier, started farming on his family's land 16 years ago. He said, "We used to know when it would rain and for how long.”</p>
<p>That meant they used to know when to plant. Now, he said, it is not so predictable. Sometimes there is too much rain. Sometimes there is no rain at all.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="P. Ravinder Reddy, a farmer, applies fungicide to peanut seeds before sowing in Rayanpet village of Telangana state, India, Wednesday, Sept. 25, 2024. (AP Photo/Mahesh Kumar A.)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f1ae7734-ed23-441a-92cd-cab78bc29044_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">P. Ravinder Reddy, a farmer, applies fungicide to peanut seeds before sowing in Rayanpet village of Telangana state, India, Wednesday, Sept. 25, 2024. (AP Photo/Mahesh Kumar A.)</span></div>
<p>Agricultural research organizations in India have been working for years to engineer rice seeds that can survive in a changing climate. Reddy has been experimenting with new kinds of rice for the past five years. The new rice plants are producing more grain with less water. They are also more disease resistant.</p>
<p>Reddy says he has planted them across part of his 10-hectare field. He still grows some of the older kinds because there is a demand for them. But he said, “I think in a few years, we will use only these <strong>tougher</strong> seeds."</p>
<p>India is one of the world's largest producers and <strong>consumers</strong> of wheat and rice. Research organizations in that country and around the world have worked for years to produce seeds that are better able to handle <strong>drought</strong>, unseasonal rains, plant diseases and more.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, a United Nations report said more than 700 million people suffered from hunger last year. More than one-third of the worldwide population does not have the money to buy healthy foods.</p>
<p><strong>Defending against climate shocks</strong></p>
<p>India has nearly 120 million farmers. Most have less than two hectares of land. Unpredictable rainfall, rising temperatures and increased <strong>pest </strong>problems all threaten their ability to grow food.</p>
<p>Experts say the dangers to rice include increasing salt content in groundwater, heavy rainfall over short periods, long periods of drought and increasing nighttime temperatures.</p>
<p>Some farmers are turning to methods of natural farming to deal with climate change. But that can mean reduced <strong>yields</strong>. India's federal government is also urging the use of climate-<strong>resilient </strong>seeds that result in better yields.</p>
<p><strong>Government research support</strong></p>
<p>Ashok Kumar Singh is former director of New Delhi-based Indian Agriculture Research Institute. He has overseen the creation of many successful rice varieties that withstand pests and plant diseases. His organization has helped release more than 2,000 climate-resilient kinds of seed in the last 10 years.</p>
<p>"We really need these seeds to deal with these multiple <strong>issues </strong>created by global warming," Singh said.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi released 109 climate-resilient seeds for several different crops. India's federal government has announced plans to make sure at least 25 percent of rice-growing fields in the country will be planted with climate-resilient seeds in the coming winter crop season.</p>
<p>In Rayanpet village, Reddy is preparing to plant rice seeds for the winter season in a few weeks.</p>
<p>"It is good to keep trying new seeds, as after some time all of them will have some issue or the other," Reddy said. “If the government can also make sure we get good prices for our crops after harvest, that would help farmers like us a great deal.”</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Sibi Aras </em><em>reported this story for the </em><em>Associated Press</em><em>.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>tough</strong> – <em>adj</em>. strong and not easily broken or damaged</p>
<p><strong>consumer</strong> – <em>n</em>. a person who buys goods and services</p>
<p><strong>drought</strong> – <em>n</em>. a long period of time during which there is very little or no rain</p>
<p><strong>pest </strong>– <em>n</em>. an animal or insect that causes problems for people</p>
<p><strong>yield</strong> – <em>n. </em>the amount of something that is produced by a plant, farm, or the like</p>
<p><strong>issue –<em> </em></strong><em>n</em>. problem or concern</p>
<p>especially by damaging crops</p>
<p><strong>resilient </strong>– <em>adj</em>. able to become strong, healthy, or successful again after something bad happens</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Developers of AI Methods Win Nobel Prize in Physics (2024/10/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202410/developers-of-ai-methods-win-nobel-prize-in-physics.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By </span><br/><span class="datetime">08 October, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Two early developers of artificial intelligence (AI) have won this year's Nobel Prize in Physics.</p>
<p>American John Hopfield is with Princeton University in New Jersey. Geoffrey Hinton is a citizen of Canada and Britain who works at the University of Toronto.</p>
<p>The Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences honored them for helping “to develop methods that are the foundation of today's powerful machine learning.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="The 2024 Nobel Prize winners in Physics, professor John Hopfield, left, of Princeton University, and professor Geoffrey Hinton, of the University of Toronto, Tuesday, Oct. 8, 2024. (Princeton University via AP and Noah Berger/AP Photo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/71730729-6d5b-4062-aebb-7eccfce76f73_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">The 2024 Nobel Prize winners in Physics, professor John Hopfield, left, of Princeton University, and professor Geoffrey Hinton, of the University of Toronto, Tuesday, Oct. 8, 2024. (Princeton University via AP and Noah Berger/AP Photo)</span></div>
<p>The 76-year-old Hinton is known as the Godfather of artificial intelligence for his part in developing machine learning. However, he also has warned that AI has created threats to humanity.</p>
<p>Ellen Moons is a member of the Nobel committee at the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences. Moons said the two scientists “used fundamental <strong>concepts</strong> from <strong>statistical</strong> physics to design artificial <strong>neural</strong> networks that <strong>function</strong> as <strong>associative memories</strong> and find <strong>patterns</strong> in large data sets.”</p>
<p>Moons added that their research has been used to make progress in physics but has also become part of people's daily lives. Technologies like facial recognition and language <strong>translation</strong> are used every day.</p>
<p>Hinton predicted that AI would have a “huge influence” on civilization and will bring improvements to productivity and health care. He told reporters and Royal Academy officials that, “It would be comparable to the Industrial Revolution.”</p>
<p>The Industrial Revolution was a period of intensive development of machines and manufacturing that started more than 250 years ago in Britain.</p>
<p>Hinton said, “Instead of exceeding people in physical strength, it's going to exceed people in intellectual ability.” But Hinton also expressed concern about the possible bad results of AI, especially noting, in his words, “the threat of these things getting out of control.”</p>
<p>The Nobel committee also recognized the possible damage the discoveries that it was honoring could cause. Moons said AI's “development has also raised concerns about our future. Collectively, humans carry the responsibility for using this new technology in a safe and ethical way for the greatest benefit of humankind.”</p>
<p><strong>What they did</strong></p>
<p>In the 1980s, Hinton helped to develop a method known as backpropagation, which is used to “train” computers to learn.</p>
<p>Later, he headed a team at the University of Toronto that won the ImageNet computer competition in 2012 for designing a “neural network.”</p>
<p>Hinton and AI scientists Yoshua Bengio and Yann LeCun won the Turing Award in 2019. It is the top award in computer science. That year, Hinton told the Associated Press about the reaction he and his fellow researchers received over their work.</p>
<p>“They thought we were very misguided and what we were doing was a very surprising thing for apparently intelligent people to waste their time on. My message to young researchers is, don't be put off if everyone tells you what you are doing is silly.”</p>
<p>Hopfield is now 91 years old. The Nobel committee said he “invented a network that uses a method for saving and recreating patterns.”</p>
<p>Hinton used Hopfield's network to create a new network using a different method known as the Boltzmann machine. The committee said this “machine” can learn to recognize elements in a particular kind of data.</p>
<p>“What fascinates me most is still this question of how mind comes from machine,” Hopfield said in a video posted online by The Franklin Institute after it awarded him a physics prize in 2019.</p>
<p>The Nobel Prize in Physics is valued at $1 million. Swedish inventor Alfred Nobel created the prizes to honor discoveries that help humanity. The first prizes were awarded in 1901.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, the prize in chemistry will be announced, on Thursday, the prize for literature, and Friday, the peace prize. And, the Nobel for economics will be announced on Monday.</p>
<p>The winners receive their prizes in ceremonies held on December 10.</p>
<p>I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>Daniel Niemann and Mike Corder reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>concept</strong> <em>–n.</em> a general idea</p>
<p><strong>statistical</strong> <em>–adj. </em>related to facts or information that is in the form of numbers</p>
<p><strong>associative</strong> <em>–adj. </em>of or relating to association, connection or linkage</p>
<p><strong>memory</strong> <em>–n. </em>the power or process of reproducing or recalling what has been learned and retained especially through associative mechanisms</p>
<p><strong>neural</strong> <em>–adj.</em> like a brain or nerve cells</p>
<p><strong>function </strong><em>–n.</em> the job or task that something does</p>
<p><strong>pattern </strong><em>–n.</em> images, objects or elements that are repeated in a recognizable way</p>
<p><strong>translation </strong><em>–n.</em> to take writing in one language and recreate its meaning in another language</p>
<p><strong>consequence </strong><em>–n.</em> the results of an action</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
