<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>VOA Special English</title>
        <link>https://www.21voa.com/special_english/</link>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <itunes:category>ESL</itunes:category>
        <itunes:author>VOA</itunes:author>
        <description>美国之音（以下称VOA）的英语节目，按播音速度可分为两种：Standard English （标准英语）和 Special English（特别英语）。

Special English 又叫“慢速英语”，是VOA 专为全世界非英语国家初学英语的听众安排的一种简易、规范的英语广播节目。该节目创始于50年代末期，是VOA 的专家们研究如何与世界各地的英语学习者进行交际的产物。它正式开播于1959年10月。当时只面向欧洲和中东，但由于这个节目适合许多国家英语学习者的需要，所以它的广播对象不久就扩大到世界其他地区，并很快在全世界范围内产生了广泛的影响。现在这个节目对欧洲、非洲和拉丁美洲每晚广播一次，对加勒比地区每晚广播一次（星期天除外），对东南亚广播次数最多，每天上午两次，晚上三次。

30多年来，VOA 为了办好Special English节目，进行了大量的调查研究工作，对播音速度、内容及用词范围都作了具体规定，基本上达到了既能为英语学习者提供信息，又不损害英语本身风格的目的，使之成为VOA 独具特色，拥有最大量听众的节目。

美国著名词汇学家S. B. Flexmer 指明了Special English的三条标准，也就是它所“特别”的地方：

1、它是一种由美国人最常用的1500个基本单词为主体构成的美国英语；

2、它用简短、明晰的句子写作和广播；

3、它以每分钟90个单词的速度，即2/3的Standard English（标准英语）速度进行广播。

Special English的节目可分为两大类：一类是新闻节目；一类是专题节目。

1．新闻节目

VOA Special English 的新闻广播向听众提供世界范围内的政治、经济、军事、外交、国际关系、宗教、天气以及各种重大事件和珍闻奇事等各个方面的信息，每天向东南亚地区广播五次，早上两次，晚上三次，每逢半点播出。

Special English新闻节目每次长约十分钟，大都播出十条左右新闻，近一千个单词，每条新闻多为一分钟，但偶尔也有长达两分钟的要闻。除头条新闻外，每条新闻都由一个电头引导，这样显得结构分明，条理清晰，适宜初学英语的人收听。在节目结束之前，播音员常常用三四句话重播其中三条新闻的提要以加深听众对要闻的印象。

Special English新闻中70%左右的内容与同时整点播出的Standard English新闻相同，但相同新闻的先后次序有所变动。每次节目的开头和结尾大同小异，格式比较固定。

2．专题节目（一）

Special English的专题节目（Feature Programs）,从时间上看，可分为两大类：一是每五分钟一次的专题，二是每十五分钟一次的专题。本节先介绍每项五分钟一次的专题材节目。

Special English五分钟一次的专题材节目安排在Special English新闻节目之后和（或）每十五分钟一次的专题材节目之前播出，每星期播七次。根据内容，可分为三个小类，即：Science Report（科学报道），逢星期一、三、五播出，每天播六遍；Agriculture Report（农业报道），逢星期二、四播出，每天播六遍；Words And Their Stories（词语掌故），逢星期六和星期天播出，每天播五遍。这三个专题材各具特色，具有相对的独立性，听众每听完一个节目，都会获得一个完整的印象。

Science Report（科学报道）这一专题材节目每周向听众介绍三篇有关现代科学技术最新发展情况的报道，涉及物理、化学、天文至高无上理、生物、环卫、心理、教育、医学和计算机等方面。适宜理工科大学生和科技工作者收集信息，积累资料，学习科技英语。

Agriculture Report（农业报道） Agriculture Report是为农业科技工作者和生产者安排的一个专题。它专门报道世界各国，特别是美国现代农业生产的最新成文汇报总务科 学家对农业生产某一方面的研究进展，以及他们对影响农业生产的某一自然现象进行分析和研究的近况。此外，它还经常向听众介绍发展中国家家业生产的一些有益经验等内容。

Words And Their Stories（词语掌故）这一专题节目，旨在向学习英语的听众介绍美国英语中生动有趣的词语和惯用法，并从科学研究和通俗词源学的角度来解释它们的含意、产生的背景及其在使用过程中的演变情况等。它通过讲故事的形式讲解每一个词语。这是VOA Special English中的优秀节目之一，是学习美国英语的极好材料。通过收听这一节目，听众不仅能学到娓娓动听的掌故和地道的美国英语，而且能增加美国的社会文化背景知识，历史传统与现状的了解。

VOA 为了更好地办好这个节目，便于听众收听学习，于1978年编辑出版了一本名为Words And Their Stories的书，共收集一百篇故事，作者是Herbert Sutcliffe, Harold Bermen 及VOA 该节目的部分编辑人员。在每次的实际广播中，播音员都以此书为蓝本，再根据需要对原稿进行适当增删。按每周两个故事计算，此书的一百个故事还不能满足一年的播音需要。于是编辑们就是重播部分词语掌故的同时，不断增加许多新的词语掌故，及时将词源学家的最新研究成果和不断增加的新词汇介绍给听众。收听实践证明，初学者在收听过程中必然会遇到许多人名、地名和一些较难的句子，有时甚至在听完之后还很难理解所播词语的确切含义及其汉语意思，为此，听众可参看1983年由中国对外翻译出版公司出版的该书英汉对照本中的有关部分。

3．专题节目（二）

VOA Special English的专题节目，除上节谈的五分钟一次的以外，还有本节要介绍的每十五分钟一次的节目。这类节目共有七个不同的小专题，以星期为单位循环，每天分四次复播出一个专题，但星期日和星期六的两个专题材每晚只播三遍，每次节目约十分钟，继每次五分钟的专题节目之后播出。

这类专题节目的基本结构是，在特定的伴声中先报告当次节目的名称，并扼要介绍其主要内容，然后播送节目正文。最后，在伴乐声中报告节目主持人和撰稿人的姓名，以邀请听众在下周的这个时间继续收听该节目而结束。

People in America（美国人物志） 这是有关美国历史名人的一个专题节目，每逢星期天晚上播出。它向听众介绍在美国历史上产生过重大影响、起过重要作用、作出了突出贡献的科学、文学、政治、或其他各方面的历史人物。节目一般都对他们的生平事迹进行简要的叙述，对其贡献作出评介，类似人物小传。有的重要人物事迹很多，必须用两次或几次的节目时间进行联播。对这样的节目要坚持收听，才会获得完整的印象。

TThis is America（今日美国） This Is America向听众介绍美国人民的生活、学习、工作和娱乐情况，是英语学习者解美国社会的一条渠道。该专题大都一个节目一个整体，每逢星期一晚播出。

Science in the News（科学新闻） 这一专题材主要对新近的科学技术新闻进行综述或摘要广播。向听众介绍世界各国在自然、医学、疾病、原子能、航天等方面的科研动态、成果、突破性进展及存在的困难。涉及当今世界人们普遍关心的重大问题，如核事故、航天飞机爆炸、自然灾害、环境污染和爱滋病等等。每逢星期二播出，每次播一到五条新闻摘要。

Explorations（自然探索） 每逢星期三晚上，听众可以收听到Explorations这一专题节目。该专题既涉及人类遨游太空、探索原子、研究自身、改造自然的现代技术，也报道发展中国家开发新资源，利用新工艺改善人民生活等方面的成就，其侧重点在各种科技实验和简易实用技术方面。该节目一般安排一段时间播一个系列，每次播出一个主题，以便能将某项新技术的研究和应用的全过程介绍给听众，电台还乐意为感兴趣的听众提供所需的文字材料。

The Making of a Nation（建国史话） 这一专题节目向听众介绍美利坚合众国从十三个殖民地区域到现代工业国的孕育、诞生以及形成超级大国的历史过程，并以历史为线索，特定的历史时期为单位，以重大的历史事件为主题材来叙述各个党派、各届总统和政府的历史作用与贡献。这是每个英语学习者都应了解的基本知识。The Making of a Nation每逢星期四播出。这是个系列节目，坚持收听，则有助于系统了解美国的历史概况。

American Mosaic（美国万花筒） American Mosaic是一个radio magazine（广播杂志）节目。该节目题材广泛、内容丰，展示着美国社会文化生活中比较轻松愉快的生活画面；听众收听该节目就如同在阅读一本图文并茂的杂志。它每次有三到五个小节目，涉及音乐、图书、技术和教育等方面的内容。我们既可以从中欣赏到著名歌唱的优秀歌曲，对美国音乐有所了解，又可以获取一些生动有趣的现代美国社会生活知识，随着播音员那亲切悦耳的声音步入美国风景如画的大好河山；同时还能听到世界各地的听众提出的有关英语语方文学等方面的问题和电台的解答。

American Stories（美国故事） 这一专题材节目安排在每星期六晚上播出。这样能使听众在学习和工作之余，得以轻松一下头脑。我们可以通过这一美国文学的“窗口”，接触各种流派、各类名家的文学作品。了解美国英语的时代特色，欣赏、学习美国人民运用语方的技巧，并从那些佳作名篇中获得艺术享受。该节目对短篇故事采取一次播一篇的方式，对中、长篇小说则先进行简写加工，再分几次播出全文。在播出故事正文之前，播音员常常先介绍故事的主要情节。对需要分几次节目时间播出的中长篇，在播第二或以后各部分之前，主持人还先重述已播部分的故事梗概，以唤起听众的回忆，使故事听起来更加连贯。</description>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          <item>
            <title>Near a New Jersey Highway, a Large Statue of Buddha (2024/12/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/near-a-new-jersey-highway-a-large-statue-of-buddha.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In the eastern American state of New Jersey, a large statue of Buddha has become a gathering place for people of many religious faiths.</p>
<p>The nine-meter-high statue has stood among the woods in Franklin Township since 2009. It was built under the leadership of the Venerable Hungampola Sirirathana Nayaka Thera, a Buddhist monk from Sri Lanka. He says his dream is to unite people of all faiths.</p>
<p>The statue is on the grounds of the New Jersey Buddhist Vihara and Meditation Center. The center has become a spiritual place for Buddhists, Hindus, and Christians.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Carol Kruhen lifts up her pressed palms next to a statue of the Buddha after meditating at the New Jersey Buddhist Vihara and Meditation Center in Franklin Township, N.J. on Sunday Nov. 30, 2024. (AP photo/Luis Andres Henao)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/3676030c-37ed-48be-b3eb-a86eb3c01bdd_cx6_cy2_cw87_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Carol Kruhen lifts up her pressed palms next to a statue of the Buddha after meditating at the New Jersey Buddhist Vihara and Meditation Center in Franklin Township, N.J. on Sunday Nov. 30, 2024. (AP photo/Luis Andres Henao)
</span></div>
<p>Among those who praise the center are a Princeton University professor who grew up in a Korean Christian church and who follows Tibetan Buddhism; a leader of the local Nepali community who organizes interfaith gatherings; and a woman who became a Buddhist after living near the statue.</p>
<p>“It just seems to be a <strong>nexus</strong> where a lot of people connect,” said Daniel Choi. He follows Tibetan Buddhism and teaches writing at Princeton. He has been <strong>meditating</strong> in front of the Buddha statue since 2015.</p>
<p>Choi said that the center is open to the public. He said that is unlike most Buddhist centers in the U.S. which are run by private organizations, “where you wouldn't be able to go in for open practice,” he said.</p>
<p>He also noted that the center is in an unexpected place. Thera built the statue and meditation center behind a house close to a highway.</p>
<p>“You hear traffic; you hear cars rushing by; you hear airplanes flying above...You hear the <strong>construction</strong> work going on,” Choi said.</p>
<p>The meditation center follows Theravada, the main form of Buddhism observed in Sri Lanka, Burma and Thailand. But it welcomes all Buddhist traditions and other faiths.</p>
<p>When Choi first visited, he was surprised to find a statue of Kuan Yin, the Buddhist goddess of <strong>compassion</strong>. The goddess is important in Mahayana Buddhism observed in China and Korea.</p>
<p>“For me that was very welcoming because I thought: 'OK, so there's something for me as well,'” Choi said.</p>
<p>Local students have painted a wall in the center with images showing different world religions, from Baha'i and Christianity to Sikhism and Zoroastrianism. All of these religions are practiced in New Jersey.</p>
<p>Tulsi Maharjan is director of the nonprofit organization Friends of Nepal - New Jersey. He has led projects involving more than one religion, including the wall painting and a peace garden.</p>
<p>He said that when he first came to New Jersey 35 years ago, he had to drive almost three hours to go to a Buddhist temple. But now, people from all over the world live near the Vihara Meditation center and statue.</p>
<p>“Now, within ten minutes...from my home, I can go to the Buddhist temple. But there are so many others,” he said listing nearby Jain, Sikh and Hindu temples that make him proud of the religious diversity in central New Jersey.</p>
<p>Maharjan said that anybody who comes to the temple “feels so <strong>calm and collected</strong> once they see that big Buddha.”</p>
<p>Carol Kuehn is a 76-year-old retired high school teacher who lives next to the Buddhist center. Kuehn said: “It's the first thing I look at in the morning.”</p>
<p>Kuehn grew up in a Christian family and became interested in Buddhism after reading Herman Hesse's novel <em>Siddhartha</em>.</p>
<p>She became a Buddhist after the leader of the temple arrived in 2002. Buddhism, she said, helped her deal with <strong>grief</strong> after the death of her husband.</p>
<p>“The whole point of Buddhism is to live in the moment,” she said.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Luis Andres Henao wrote this story for The Associated Press. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>nexus </strong><em>–n.</em> a point where people or things meet or join together</p>
<p><strong>meditate </strong><em>–v.</em> to spend time in quiet thought with the aim of easing tension or considering spiritual issues</p>
<p><strong>construction </strong><em>–n.</em> the process of building structures such as homes and buildings</p>
<p><strong>compassion </strong><em>–n.</em> a desire to help people who are suffering</p>
<p><strong>(cool,) calm and collected </strong><em>–adj.</em><em> (idiomatic) </em>to be at ease and thoughtful</p>
<p><strong>grief </strong><em>–n.</em> severe sadness usually because of a bad or difficult event</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Tech Tip: How to Protect Communications through Encryption (2024/12/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/tech-tip-how-to-protect-communications-through-encryption.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>U.S. cybersecurity officials are advising people to use <strong>encryption</strong> in their communications after a major <strong>hacking</strong> campaign.</p>
<p>Federal officials released a list of security suggestions for U.S. telecommunications companies that were targeted.</p>
<p>The advice includes one suggestion that everyone can use: “Ensure that traffic is end-to-end encrypted to the maximum <strong>extent </strong>possible.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - An attendee at the Microsoft Ignite conference records an address on Nov. 19, 2024, in Chicago. (AP Photo/Charles Rex Arbogast, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/5ab9677b-ca52-4218-b328-45e322bc50da_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - An attendee at the Microsoft Ignite conference records an address on Nov. 19, 2024, in Chicago. (AP Photo/Charles Rex Arbogast, File)</span></div>
<p>End-to-end encryption, also known as E2EE, means that messages are protected so that only the sender and receiver can see them. If anyone else gets the message, all they will see is disordered information that cannot be understood without the <strong>key</strong>.</p>
<p>Law enforcement officials had until now resisted encryption. This resistance is because the encryption means the technology companies themselves will not be able to look at the messages. In addition, the companies will not be able to respond to law enforcement requests to turn the data over.</p>
<p>The Associated Press (AP) recently offered some ways that normal people can use for end-to-end encryption :</p>
<p><strong>Texting </strong></p>
<p>Officials said the hackers targeted the <strong>metadata</strong> of a large number of people. That included information on the dates, times and <strong>recipients </strong>of calls and <strong>texts</strong>. The hackers also got to see the information from texts from a much smaller number of people.</p>
<p>If you are an iPhone user, information in text messages that you send to someone else who also has an iPhone will be encrypted end-to-end. Look for the blue text bubbles which mean that the messages are encrypted iMessages.</p>
<p>The same goes for Android users sending texts through Google Messages. There will be a lock next to the timestamp on each message to show that the encryption is on.</p>
<p>But there is a weakness. When iPhone and Android users text each other, the messages are encrypted only using Rich Communication Services (RCS). That is a common method for messaging that has replaced the older SMS and MMS methods.</p>
<p>Apple notes that RCS messages “aren't end-to-end encrypted, which means they're not protected from a third party reading them while they're sent between devices.”</p>
<p>Samsung, which sells Android smartphones, also indirectly described the issue in a small area at the bottom of a press release last month. Samsung said about RCS, “Encryption only available for Android-to-Android communication.”</p>
<p><strong>Chat apps </strong></p>
<p>To avoid getting caught out when exchanging texts, experts recommend using encrypted messaging <strong>apps</strong>.</p>
<p>Privacy supporters are big fans of Signal, which uses end-to-end encryption on all messages and voice calls. Signal is an app that is run by an independent nonprofit group based in Mountainview, California. It promises never to sell customer data. The group has also made its source code publicly available so that it can be examined by anyone “for security and correctness.”</p>
<p>Signal's encryption method is so respected that it has been included into competitor WhatsApp.</p>
<p>End-to-end encryption is also the normal mode for Facebook Messenger, which like WhatsApp is owned by Meta Platforms.</p>
<p><strong>What about Telegram? </strong></p>
<p>Telegram is an app that can be used for one-on-one discussions, group chats and broadcast “channels.” But Telegram does not use end-to-end encryption normally. Users have to turn on end-to-end encryption. And Telegram's end-to-end encryption does not work with group chats.</p>
<p>Cybersecurity experts have warned people against using Telegram for private communications.</p>
<p><strong>Making calls </strong></p>
<p>Instead of using your phone to make calls through a wireless cellular network, you can make voice calls with Signal and WhatsApp. Both apps encrypt calls with the same technology that they use to encrypt messages.</p>
<p>There are other choices. If you have an iPhone, you can use Facetime for calls, while Android owners can use the Google Fi service. Both are end-to-end encrypted.</p>
<p>However, with all these choices, the person on the other end will also have to have the app.</p>
<p>WhatsApp and Signal users can choose the privacy setting they want in the settings. Such choices include hiding an IP address during calls to prevent your general location from being guessed.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Kelvin Chan reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>encryption</strong><em> – n.</em> changing something (such as data) into a code</p>
<p><strong>hack </strong><em>– v.</em> to gain illegal access to a computer network, computer system, phone, etc.</p>
<p><strong>extent</strong> <em>– n.</em> a degree, point, or limit to which something goes to</p>
<p><strong>key</strong><em> –n.</em> information that permits a computer application to un-encrypt a message permitting the receiver to read it</p>
<p><strong>metadata</strong> <em>-- n.</em> data that gives information about other data</p>
<p><strong>recipient</strong> <em>– n.</em> someone who receives something</p>
<p><strong>text (message)</strong> <em>–n.</em> a short message sent through a computer program from one person to another which can contain a written message, links or pictures</p>
<p><strong>app (application)<em> </em></strong><em>–n.</em> a computer program that is designed to do one task or several linked tasks</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Winter Work for the Gardeners (2024/12/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/winter-work-for-the-gardeners.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>For people in parts of the world with seasons — especially cold ones — winter might seem like a time to rest and to take a break from <strong>garden</strong> work.</p>
<p>But it is not, says Associated Press gardening expert Jessica Damiano.</p>
<p>Autumn and winter are the best times to attend to your garden's needs and prepare for the next growing season. There is much to do for both outdoor and indoor plants.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This Dec. 5, 2024, image provided by Jessica Damiano shows a thick layer of fallen leaves serving as mulch to protect spring bulbs planted in a Long Island, New York, garden bed. (Jessica Damiano via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/0043f07c-2958-42c0-b929-da9acf869f82_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This Dec. 5, 2024, image provided by Jessica Damiano shows a thick layer of fallen leaves serving as mulch to protect spring bulbs planted in a Long Island, New York, garden bed. (Jessica Damiano via AP)</span></div>
<p><strong>Outdoor care</strong></p>
<p>For people who want flowers like tulips in the early spring plant the <strong>bulbs</strong> that produce them if your soil is not frozen. If you can still dig, plant tulips, daffodils and other bulbs.</p>
<p>Cover them with about eight centimeters of <strong>mulch</strong>, leaves or dried grass. This will prevent freezing and melting temperatures from forcing them out of the ground over the winter.</p>
<p>During winter months, even in more temperate areas, some plants need protection from the cold. These include some fruit trees, like citrus, dahlias and many plants that <strong>bloom</strong> in the spring. In winter conditions, a cloth cover called burlap can help limit the damaging effects of wind.</p>
<p>If snow builds up on the branches of evergreen trees and shrubs, remove it. The heavy weight can damage branches.</p>
<p>Keep a record of plants you mean to move from one place to another in your garden. The notes will guide you in early spring: a time that is best to move plants that bloom early in the season.</p>
<p>if you have extra seeds, consider trading them with gardening friends or at a gardening event. Store and organize seeds for the future in glass containers in cool places without light. Make sure to write down what they are and when they were collected.</p>
<p>If insects or diseases were a problem during the growing season, use winter months to read about <strong>companion</strong> plants that can ease the problem in the coming year.</p>
<p><strong>Indoor care</strong></p>
<p>The cold winter months also affect houseplants. Bring houseplants near a south-facing or west-facing window to get the most sunlight possible. Turn the houseplants about one fourth of a turn each time you water them. This will support more even growth.</p>
<p>If you are buying poinsettias for the holidays, be sure to examine them for whiteflies before bringing them home. If you do not, you could bring home insects.</p>
<p>If you plant Amaryllis bulbs indoors now, they will bloom during the coldest months of the winter. Plant them with their pointed ends reaching out of the potting soil and place them in a warm, sunny spot, watering them well.</p>
<p>After they bloom, keep them in a cooler place to extend the life of their flowers but keep them away from children and pets. Amaryllis bulbs are poisonous to eat.</p>
<p><strong>Remember the birds</strong></p>
<p>Damiano also advises to remember that non-migrating birds need food because most of their food sources are gone during the winter months. High quality birdseed and water can help.</p>
<p>These same birds will repay the effort by feeding on thousands of insects that threaten your garden during the warm growing season.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Jessica Damiano reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>garden</strong><strong> </strong>–n. an area where trees and plants grow in a way designed by a gardener to produce flowers and small crops for food</p>
<p><strong>bulb</strong> <em>–n. </em>a round piece of plant tissue that becomes a flowing plant when grown in the ground</p>
<p><strong>bloom</strong> <em>–n. </em>the flowering state</p>
<p><strong>mulch</strong> <em>–n.</em> broken down plant material such as leaves and bark that is put on the ground to enrich the soil and protect existing plants</p>
<p><strong>delicate</strong><strong> </strong>–adj. very fine and sensitive to difficult conditions</p>
<p><strong>companion</strong><strong> </strong>–n. someone or something that goes well with another</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Youth Church Orchestra Aims to Help Musicians of Color (2024/12/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/youth-church-orchestra-aims-to-help-musicians-of-color.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>For more than two years, Ebonie Vazquez searched to find a music teacher of color for her son, Giovanni. He is 11 years old and loves to play the violin. Now, she has found that teacher at New Hope Presbyterian Church, a Christian religious center, near Los Angeles, California.</p>
<p>Chineta Goodjoin, a Black <strong>pastor, </strong>leads New Hope. She started a string orchestra at the church in April to help children of color have a better chance to learn classical music.</p>
<p>Goodjoin and the orchestra's leaders think it is important for the music teachers to look like their students and share similar life experiences. That is why the orchestra's director, Charles Dickerson and all its music teachers are people of color.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Giovanni Vazquez plays the violin during a string orchestra rehearsal at New Hope Presbyterian Church on Wednesday, Oct. 16, 2024, in Anaheim, California. (AP Photo/William Liang)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/dcb9f483-89e9-4534-b7ba-c39840f9051d_cx13_cy0_cw83_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Giovanni Vazquez plays the violin during a string orchestra rehearsal at New Hope Presbyterian Church on Wednesday, Oct. 16, 2024, in Anaheim, California. (AP Photo/William Liang)</span></div>
<p>Dickerson is also the director of the Inner City Youth Orchestra of Los Angeles, which he founded in 2009. After Goodjoin's daughter Nyla began playing in that orchestra, Goodjoin decided to build a similar group at her church.</p>
<p>The church's orchestra now has about 18 members, aged nine to 20. They play the violin, viola, bass and cello. The orchestra accepts all students who want to join.</p>
<p>Ebonie Vazquez says having teachers of color has helped the orchestra members feel like they fit in well.</p>
<p>“It's important they don't feel like <strong>outsiders</strong>, but are supported and feel like they belong,” she said. “It has definitely helped my son connect more to the music and the <strong>craft</strong>.”</p>
<p>Her son Giovanni said that in the church orchestra, he could play classical music or popular modern music. He values being part of the church orchestra because “it's a piece of our community.”</p>
<p>“They <strong>encourage</strong> young musicians of color and everyone gets a chance to play and maybe use it as <strong>a stepping stone</strong> to get better or even turn this into a career,” he said.</p>
<p>Elizabeth Moulthrop is executive director of El Sistema, an international network of music education programs that was founded in Venezuela.</p>
<p>She said programs like the church orchestra can help students go to life-changing summer music camps, receive college scholarships, and find connections to jobs.</p>
<p>Goodjoin said she and her husband, Reggie Goodjoin, see a future for the orchestra where “African American kids play classical music and play it well.” Reggie Goodjoin is a jazz musician and the church's music director.</p>
<p>The group plays a mix of both classical and popular music. “I like to say they play everything from Bach to Beyonce,” added Goodjoin. They also learn music by famous African American jazz composers such as Count Basie and Duke Ellington.</p>
<p>Goodjoin said she believes the church is a great place to start talking about fairness<strong> </strong>in music. “Music is freedom,” Goodjoin added.</p>
<p>The pastor is already getting praise from parents. One boy who plays the upright bass was about to quit playing because no one in his school orchestra looked like him.</p>
<p>“His mom said that when he came here, the pressure to play and compete was taken off and that it's a <strong>delight</strong> to now watch her son light up feeling a sense of worthiness,” she said.</p>
<p>Dickerson said he started the Los Angeles orchestra when a group of students told him they wanted to play closer to where they live.</p>
<p>“They would have to drive long distances to be in these orchestras where they didn't know the other kids,” he said. “The young kids from our communities were always put in the back row and the back row was right next to the door.”</p>
<p>“It's easy to walk out that door,” he added, “when you don't really feel accepted and when you know you're probably not as skilled as the others.” He added that those other students usually had more music lessons and started playing at a younger age.</p>
<p>Dickerson said the Black Church has at times been the only place the African American community could organize services they needed, such as banks and newspapers.</p>
<p>“If we can come together in the church and create a symphonic orchestra, all I can say is all praise to God,” he added.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith. And I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Deepa Bharath wrote this story for The Associated Press. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>_________________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>pastor </strong><em>-n. </em>a leader of a church</p>
<p><strong>outsider </strong><em>-n. </em>a person who does not belong to a particular group</p>
<p><strong>craft </strong><em>-n. </em>an activity that involves doing something skillfully</p>
<p><strong>encourage</strong><em> -v. </em>to help people want to do things</p>
<p><strong>a stepping stone </strong><em>-noun phrase -- </em>an experience that can help you make progress, especially in your career</p>
<p><strong>delight </strong><em>-n. </em>something that brings happiness</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Geothermal Development Faces Barriers in Southeast Asia (2024/12/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/geothermal-development-faces-barriers-in-southeast-asia.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Indonesia and the Philippines aim to increase their use of geothermal energy to move away from highly polluting fossil fuels.</p>
<p>However, money issues, governmental rules, and community protests have slowed the growth of geothermal energy production.</p>
<p>Geothermal energy uses heat from underground <strong>reservoirs</strong> of hot water to produce electricity. Environmental experts see geothermal as a good source of clean energy because it can provide power 24 hours a day. Geothermal power plants also require little <strong>maintenance</strong> and can last for many years.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Cars drive on a road as steam rises from a geothermal power plant in Dieng, Central Java, Indonesia, Nov. 15, 2024. (AP Photo/Beawiharta)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/86617547-029e-4e25-ac87-d4342ea88fa7_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Cars drive on a road as steam rises from a geothermal power plant in Dieng, Central Java, Indonesia, Nov. 15, 2024. (AP Photo/Beawiharta)
</span></div>
<p>Countries with high geothermal possibilities — such as the United States, Indonesia and the Philippines — have areas where volcanic activity naturally carries hot water or steam to the Earth's surface. The hot water or steam can also be reached by <strong>drilling</strong> into the ground.</p>
<p>Marit Brommer is head of the International Geothermal Association based in Germany. She told The Associated Press, “We're essentially standing on our own sun, which we can get clean, reliable energy from.”</p>
<p><strong>Geothermal energy in Southeast Asia</strong></p>
<p>In Southeast Asia, geothermal energy production is expected to increase ten times greater from 2020 to 2050, reaching 276 million megawatt-hours, the International Energy Agency says.</p>
<p>After the U.S., Indonesia and the Philippines are the second and third-largest users of geothermal energy in the world.</p>
<p>Still, Indonesia uses less than one-tenth of its large reserves of geothermal energy. Six percent of the country's power supply comes from geothermal sources.</p>
<p>And the Philippines has only developed about eight percent of its geothermal resources. It makes up 14.6 percent of the country's energy use.</p>
<p>Both countries plan to expand their production of geothermal energy. Indonesia aims to increase geothermal production by at least 8 percent by 2030. The Philippine government is targeting several projects to increase geothermal <strong>capacity</strong> by nearly 1.5 gigawatts, nearly doubling its current use.</p>
<p><strong>Facing difficulties</strong></p>
<p>However, developing new geothermal projects is costly and sometimes risky for companies when they test and drill to look for reservoirs. That makes it hard to get money for development, said Shigeru Yamamura. He is an energy specialist at the Asia Development Bank.</p>
<p>“That's the most difficult part of developers, because (in terms of money) they cannot take 100 percent of the exploration risk themselves,” Yamamura said.</p>
<p>The Philippine government has announced plans to <strong>auction</strong> for developing geothermal projects. The government is also preparing a “smart green <strong>grid</strong> plan” that centers on renewable energy. The plans may make it more likely that banks will give loans to private companies seeking to develop geothermal projects.</p>
<p>The Indonesian Ministry of Energy and Mineral Resources says it is working to shorten the wait time to get permits for new geothermal projects. It is also considering ways to increase the amount of money companies could make from the projects.</p>
<p>The World Bank is providing a $150 million loan to increase Indonesian investments in geothermal energy. And the Green Climate Fund and the Clean Technology Fund are providing $127.5 million.</p>
<p>Still, community pushback can slow development even when there is enough money.</p>
<p>In Indonesia, villagers have protested geothermal projects. They say the projects are not safe and can harm the environment. Several geothermal projects in Indonesia have had deadly gas leaks in the past five years.</p>
<p>In the Philippines, protests have led at least one company to pay money to <strong>Indigenous</strong> groups for the use of their lands.</p>
<p>Brommer, of the International Geothermal Association, thinks governments and businesses should work with nearby communities.</p>
<p>“We need to show that this development benefits all people, not just a company,” she said. “It's not about being a good neighbor; it's about being the best neighbor and really working with communities to respect their concerns.”</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith. </p>
<p>And I'm Jill Robbins. </p>
<p><em>Vitoria Milko wrote this story for The Associated Press. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>reservoir </strong><em>-n. </em>a large natural or manmade lake used as a source of water supply</p>
<p><strong>maintenance </strong><em>-n. </em>the act of keeping property or equipment in good condition by making repairs</p>
<p><strong>drill </strong><em>-v. </em>to make a hole in the ground or some other surface</p>
<p><strong>capacity </strong><em>-n. </em>the largest amount or number something can hold</p>
<p><strong>auction </strong><em>-v. </em>to make a public sale where something is sold to the person or group that offers the highest price</p>
<p><strong>grid </strong><em>-n. </em>the physical system that delivers electricity in a country</p>
<p><strong>Indigenous </strong><em>-adj. </em>native to an area; groups of people who are descended from the first people to ever live in an area or country</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Spanish Scrabble Winner Does Not Speak Spanish (2024/12/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/spanish-scrabble-winner-does-not-speak-spanish.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A New Zealand man recently won an international Spanish Scrabble competition although he does not speak Spanish.</p>
<p>Scrabble is a board game in which players form words from letters to gain points.</p>
<p>Nigel Richards is a professional Scrabble player. He holds five English-language world championships in the board game. But in November, he won the Spanish world Scrabble championship in Granada, Spain. In the competition, he lost one game out of 24.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - National SCRABBLE Champion Nigel Richards spells F-O-V-E-A-E (a part of the eye) in the final game of the competition at the Royal Pacific Resort in Orlando, Florida, on July 29, 2008. (Joe Kaleita/AP Images/SCRABBLE)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/cdd950c3-f6b2-49ed-946f-c4f62faa8003_cx1_cy3_cw93_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - National SCRABBLE Champion Nigel Richards spells F-O-V-E-A-E (a part of the eye) in the final game of the competition at the Royal Pacific Resort in Orlando, Florida, on July 29, 2008. (Joe Kaleita/AP Images/SCRABBLE)</span></div>
<p>Many people are wondering how Richards could win without speaking Spanish.</p>
<p>Liz Fagerlund is a New Zealand Scrabble official and a friend of Richards. She recently told the Associated Press that Richards started memorizing the Spanish language Scrabble word list one year ago.</p>
<p>She said, “He can't understand why other people can't just do the same thing.” Fagerlund added, “He can look at a <strong>block</strong> of words together, and once they go into his brain as a picture he can just <strong>recall</strong> that very easily.”</p>
<p>In second place was defending champion Benjamín Olaizola of Argentina. He won 18 of his games.</p>
<p>Nothing like the New Zealander's win had ever happened in Spanish Scrabble, said Alejandro Terenzani, an organizer of the competition.</p>
<p>“It was impossible to react <strong>negatively</strong>, you can only be <strong>amazed</strong>,” Terenzani said. “We certainly expected that he would perform well, but it is perhaps true that he <strong>surpassed </strong>our expectations.”</p>
<p>However, the recent Scrabble competition is not the first that Richards has won in a language that he does not speak.</p>
<p>In 2015, he became the French language Scrabble world champion although he does not speak French. He studied the French language word list for nine weeks. He won the French championship again in 2018.</p>
<p>Richards is known in the world of international Scrabble as the greatest player of all time. He has been playing in competitions for about 30 years. But other players have said his Spanish language victory was notable even by his <strong>standards</strong>.</p>
<p>Playing Spanish Scrabble required some different methods to win. The wooden pieces, or tiles, used in the word game have different values in English and Spanish Scrabble. Richards also had to consider thousands of additional seven-, eight- and nine-letter words in the Spanish language.</p>
<p>In 2008, Richards was the first player ever to hold the world, U.S., and British titles at the same time. He had to “forget” 40,000 English words that do not appear in the American Scrabble word list to win in the U.S.</p>
<p>His victories are famous in the Scrabble community. Tens of thousands of people have watched and <strong>analyzed</strong> his games in YouTube videos.</p>
<p>Scrabble does not require players to know the definitions of words. Players only need to know what combinations of letters can be used in a country's version of the game.</p>
<p>Native speakers have “a huge <strong>leg up</strong>,” American Scrabble player Will Anderson said in a video explaining Richards' Spanish win.</p>
<p>In 2010, Richards' mother, Adrienne Fischer, told a New Zealand newspaper that he was not a great English student in school. He never attended university. And he took a mathematical approach to the game rather than a <strong>linguistic</strong> one.</p>
<p>“I don't think he's ever read a book,” she said, “apart from the dictionary.”</p>
<p>Fagerlund said Richards <strong>impressed</strong> her when he arrived at his first Scrabble club meeting at age 28. Two years later, in 1997, he rode a bicycle 350 kilometers from Christchurch to the city of Dunedin where he won the New Zealand championship on his first try. Then he rode the bicycle home again.</p>
<p>At the Spanish event, he was <strong>shy</strong> and <strong>modest</strong>, organizer Terenzani said. But he happily had his picture taken and spoke with fans who sought him out.</p>
<p>“Although he did so in English, of course,” Terenzani joked.</p>
<p>Richards now lives in Malaysia. He never speaks to reporters. What drives him is a mystery.</p>
<p>“I get lots of requests from journalists wanting to interview him, and he's not interested,” Fagerlund said.</p>
<p>She added that he does not understand what all the <strong>fuss</strong> is about.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Charlotte Graham-Mclay reported this story for the Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>________________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>block</strong> <em>–n.</em> a group or a set of something</p>
<p><strong>recall </strong><em>–v.</em> to remember</p>
<p><strong>negatively </strong><em>–adv.</em> in a bad, unhelpful or unhappy way</p>
<p><strong>amazed </strong><em>–adj.</em> to be filled with wonder or admiration</p>
<p><strong>surpass </strong><em>–v.</em> to go beyond something</p>
<p><strong>standards </strong><em>–n. (pl.)</em> a level of expectations involving several qualities or conditions</p>
<p><strong>linguistic</strong> <em>–adj.</em> related to languages</p>
<p><strong>leg up </strong><em>–idiom</em> something that helps a person do better at something than other people</p>
<p><strong>impressed</strong> <em>–adj.</em> causing a person to remember something about you</p>
<p><strong>shy </strong><em>–adj.</em> unwilling or afraid to talk to other people for some reason</p>
<p><strong>modest </strong><em>–adj.</em> unwilling to bring attention to oneself or to show excessive concern for one's appearance</p>
<p><strong>fuss </strong><em>–n. </em>a show of too much praise or interest that might not seem real or honest</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>In Uganda, Cost of Attending School Keeps Children Home (2024/12/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/in-uganda-cost-of-attending-school-keeps-children-home.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The World Bank said last year that 54 percent of adults in Africa south of the Sahara Desert ranked the issue of paying school costs higher than medical or other costs.</p>
<p>The aid organization said school fees were the biggest financial worry for 40 percent of people in Uganda. In that country, a top government-supported school reportedly costs $700 for a three-month term. That is a lot of money in a country where yearly economic activity per person was $864 in 2023.</p>
<p>World Bank information shows that African countries in the area also have the highest rates of children out of school in the world. Parents in Uganda report unpredictable increases in the cost of attending school, or tuition, as a cause of tension. Some critics are calling for laws to protect parents from exploitation.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A teacher gives a lesson to his students at Wampewo Ntakke Secondary School in Kawempe tula village, Kampala, Uganda on Nov. 4, 2024. (AP Photo/Hajarah Nalwadda)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/cce01551-1243-4617-aa6c-dd120d6db408_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A teacher gives a lesson to his students at Wampewo Ntakke Secondary School in Kawempe tula village, Kampala, Uganda on Nov. 4, 2024. (AP Photo/Hajarah Nalwadda)</span></div>
<p>The Equal Opportunities Commission is a government agency that reports on the issues of inequality and discrimination. It released a report in September that called for punishment against government-supported schools that demand fees that are too high. It warned that <strong>arbitrarily</strong> raising fees can force children to drop out of school.</p>
<p>The Uganda Bureau of Statistics says that children's attendance in early grades is about 68 percent. But the percentage falls to 22 percent for secondary school. The main reason given is financial difficulty.</p>
<p>Uganda has a program of secondary education for all students. It was introduced in 2007. However, schools are not in good condition. The schools usually do not require <strong>tuition</strong>, but parents must pay for <strong>uniforms</strong>, textbooks and other costs.</p>
<p>Private schools are more popular but also more costly. Spokesperson for the Ministry of Education Dennis Mugimba said the government is not interested in making rules about prices. Mugimba said setting private school <strong>fees</strong> is “purely administrative and it is <strong>adjusted</strong> according to the business environment.” But he said costs linked to “capital development” should not be the responsibility of parents.</p>
<p>The number of private schools across Uganda has increased. The Associated Press (AP) reports that they are now a majority of the country's schools. But some people with ties to education say placing importance on the profitability of education as a business is worrying.</p>
<p>Fagil Mandy is a former inspector of schools. Mandy said there should be standardized rules to make school fees predictable for everyone.</p>
<p>It is normal for both private and government-supported schools to request money for many projects. These can include buying a bus or purchasing laboratory equipment.</p>
<p><strong>One student's story</strong></p>
<p>Shalom Mirembe is a student who spoke to the AP. Her mother takes care of four children. Her father recently died.</p>
<p>The school Mirembe attends near Kampala costs $300 per term. But her mother sends Mirembe to school without paying. She is depending on the <strong>mercy</strong> of officials.</p>
<p>But Joanita Seguya, a teacher at Wampewo Ntakke Secondary, said schools are taking measures to bar students from school if their parents do not pay. Seguya said of the school's 2100 students, 400 are from families that struggle to pay fees.</p>
<p>Twenty-year-old Mirembe is taking her final exams this year. At one point, school officials were going to bar her from school because her mother had failed to pay the fees. But when school administrators found out that her father had died recently, they permitted her to return. Some of her teachers attended the funeral.</p>
<p>But other families are not so fortunate.</p>
<p>Moses Serikomawa is jobless with seven children. He said paying $200 in school fees each term is too much when the family lacks food sometimes. But he added, “The children still want to go back to school.”</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Rodney Muhumuza reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>arbitrarily</strong><strong> </strong><em>–adj.</em> not based on a plan or for a specific or good reason</p>
<p><strong>tuition</strong> <em>–n. </em>the stated cost of attending a school or education program</p>
<p><strong>uniform</strong> <em>–n.</em> identical clothing that is worn by people in some professions or by students at certain schools</p>
<p><strong>fee</strong><strong> </strong><em>–n.</em> an amount that must be paid sometimes in addition to other costs</p>
<p><strong>adjust</strong><strong> </strong><em>–v.</em> to change a value or a piece of equipment so that it is correct or is enough</p>
<p><strong>mercy </strong><em>–n.</em> willingness to forgive or to do something because it appears to be kind or good</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>NASA’s James Webb Confirms Continued Expansion of the Universe (2024/12/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/nasa-s-james-webb-confirms-continued-expansion-of-the-universe.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Data collected by the James Webb Space Telescope has confirmed earlier information suggesting the universe is expanding at a faster rate than scientists had expected.</p>
<p>The new finding is based on measurements collected by the Webb over the past two years. The telescope is operated by the American space agency NASA.</p>
<p>Researchers say the new readings show that our universe is growing faster today than it did in the period after it first formed billions of years ago. The data suggests the distances between nearby stars and galaxies are increasing. This confirms earlier studies based on data collected by other telescopes.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Spiral galaxy NGC 628, located 32 million light-years away from Earth, is seen in an undated image from the James Webb Space Telescope. (NASA, ESA, CSA, STScI, Janice Lee (STScI), Thomas Williams (Oxford), and the PHANGS team/Handout via REUTERS)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/aefe56cf-bed5-4209-94cc-7479821e730e_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Spiral galaxy NGC 628, located 32 million light-years away from Earth, is seen in an undated image from the James Webb Space Telescope. (NASA, ESA, CSA, STScI, Janice Lee (STScI), Thomas Williams (Oxford), and the PHANGS team/Handout via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>The finding that today's universe is expanding faster than expected was first made in the 1990s by data gathered by NASA's Hubble Space Telescope. In 1998, data examinations led a group of scientists to first conclude that our universe is expanding at an ever-increasing rate.</p>
<p>That finding was based on studies of huge explosive events called supernovas. NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://spaceplace.nasa.gov/supernova/en/#:~:text=A%20supernova%20is%20the%20biggest,that%20humans%20have%20ever%20seen.">describes</a> a supernova as an “extremely bright, super-powerful explosion of a star.” A supernova takes place at the end of a star's life.</p>
<p>The 1990s research on supernovas and the universe's continued expansion resulted in three scientists winning the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/physics/2011/press-release/">2011 Nobel Prize in Physics</a>. One of the winners – Adam Riess of Johns Hopkins University in Maryland – was the lead writer of a study on the new data collected by the Webb telescope.</p>
<p>The study notes the idea of the universe expanding at an unexpected rate – and the mysterious reasons behind the growth – has long been known as <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/missions/webb/nasas-webb-hubble-telescopes-affirm-universes-expansion-rate-puzzle-persists/">Hubble Tension</a>. The Nobel winners were awarded the prize in part for showing evidence that Hubble Tension may be caused by forces they describe as “dark energy.”</p>
<p>NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/universe/dark-matter-dark-energy/">says</a> astronomers believe dark energy makes up about 68 percent of the universe, while dark matter makes up around 27 percent. But beyond that, very little is known about these two “dark” elements.</p>
<p>Riess – a professor of physics and astronomy – wrote about the new data produced by the Webb telescope observations. He said in a statement, "The <strong>discrepancy</strong> between the observed expansion rate of the universe and the predictions of the standard model suggests that our understanding of the universe may be incomplete."</p>
<p>Riess noted that data from both the Webb and Hubble instruments had confirmed the earlier findings linked to the Hubble Tension problem. He said the ongoing mysteries of how dark energy might affect faster universe expansion presents a major “<strong>challenge</strong>” for scientists. However, the new data also provides new possibilities “to learn more about our universe.”</p>
<p>The researchers used three different methods to measure a specific value – the distances from Earth to galaxies where a kind of <strong>pulsating</strong> star called a Cepheid had been identified.</p>
<p>The universe's expansion rate is measured in kilometers per second as megaparsecs, a distance equal to 3.26 million light-years. A light-year is the distance light travels in a year, about 9.5 trillion kilometers.</p>
<p>The researchers said the Webb's observations appear to rule out the idea that the earlier Hubble data might have returned false information because of possible instrument errors. The team's findings recently appeared <a class="wsw__a" href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ad8c21">in a study</a> in the publication <em>The Astrophysical Journal</em>.</p>
<p>Siyang Li is a doctoral student in astronomy at Johns Hopkins who was a co-writer of the study. He told Reuters news agency the Webb results could mean “there may be a need to <strong>revise</strong> our model of the universe.” However, Li added that such a revision would be very difficult to make currently with existing data.</p>
<p>Li also noted a great improvement in the Webb data compared to the older Hubble information. "The Webb data is like looking at the universe in <strong>high-definition</strong> for the first time and really improves the signal-to-noise of the measurements,” he said.</p>
<p>The researchers suggested more work is needed to possibly unlock the Hubble Tension mystery. Riess said more data observations will be necessary to learn about what forces are continuing to drive expansion of the universe. And the team will next try to capture more detailed data on the rate of expansion, as well as seek to establish timelines for the growth.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from Reuters, NASA and Johns Hopkins University. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>discrepancy</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a difference between two things that should be the same</p>
<p><strong>challenge </strong><em>– n.</em> something difficult that tests one's ability or determination</p>
<p><strong>pulsate</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to beat or move with a strong, regular rhythm</p>
<p><strong>revise</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to change something so that it is more correct</p>
<p><strong>high-definition</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj.</em> a system for showing very clear pictures on a television or computer screen</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Highly Effective HIV Drug to Be Offered at Low Cost to Poor Countries (2024/12/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/highly-effective-hiv-drug-to-be-offered-at-low-cost-to-poor-countries.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A yearly two-shot treatment shown to be highly effective in preventing HIV infections is to be offered at low cost to people in 120 poor nations.</p>
<p>Experts have called the treatment the closest the world has ever come to developing a vaccine against HIV. HIV stands for human immunodeficiency virus. It is an infection that destroys cells of a person's <strong>immune</strong> <strong>system</strong> and makes it difficult for them to fight off diseases.</p>
<p>The HIV virus can progress to the related disease AIDS. The World Health Organization (WHO) <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.who.int/news-room/questions-and-answers/item/hiv-aids">explains</a> that AIDS is a term used to describe “the most <strong>advanced</strong> stages of HIV infection.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file image, a pharmacist holds a vial of lenacapavir, the new HIV prevention injectable drug, at a health research center in Cape Town, South Africa, Tuesday, July 23, 2024. (AP Photo/Nardus Engelbrecht, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/0694c119-3073-45b3-ac6a-ac94300ef2dc_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this file image, a pharmacist holds a vial of lenacapavir, the new HIV prevention injectable drug, at a health research center in Cape Town, South Africa, Tuesday, July 23, 2024. (AP Photo/Nardus Engelbrecht, File)</span></div>
<p>American-based drugmaker Gilead is the developer of the medication, called lenacapavir. The drug is already sold under the name Sunlenca to treat HIV infections in the U.S., Canada, Europe and elsewhere. But Gilead plans to seek approval soon for the medication to be used to prevent HIV infection.</p>
<p>Studies have shown the twice-yearly injection was 100 percent effective in preventing HIV infections in a study of women. And another recent study found the drug worked nearly as well in men.</p>
<p>Winnie Byanyima is the executive director of UNAIDS. She told The Associated Press that the shots had worked so well, she sees them as an “<strong>unprecedented</strong>” treatment. Byanyima praised Gilead for developing the drug. But she noted that the world's ability to stop HIV/AIDS also depends on its use in at-risk countries.</p>
<p>Gilead has said it plans to offer low-cost, <strong>generic</strong> versions of lenacapavir for sale in numerous poor countries with high HIV rates. These are mostly in Africa, Southeast Asia and the Caribbean.</p>
<p>However, the company does not plan on launching the drug in most of Latin America. HIV infection rates are far lower in Latin America than Gilead's targeted countries. But critics of the drug company's deployment plans say HIV in these countries is increasing. So several groups have called on Gilead to reconsider its plans to include sales in Latin America.</p>
<p>In a recent report, the United Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS, UNAIDS, noted the number of AIDS death last year — an estimated 630,000 — was the lowest since 2004, when AIDS deaths were at their highest. The organization suggested the decreasing numbers mean the world is now at “a historic <strong>crossroads</strong>,” with a chance to end the epidemic.</p>
<p>There are other methods to protect against HIV infection. These include <strong>condoms</strong>, daily pills and bi-monthly shots. But experts say the Gilead twice-yearly shots would be especially useful for underrepresented groups. These could include people fearful of seeking care, including <strong>gay</strong> men, sex workers and young women.</p>
<p>Byanyima told the AP, the treatment “would be a <strong>miracle</strong> for these groups because it means they just have to show up twice a year at a <strong>clinic</strong> and then they're protected.”</p>
<p>A collection of 15 activist groups – in Peru, Argentina, Ecuador, Chile, Guatemala and Colombia – recently wrote to Gilead to voice their concerns. They are asking for the generic version to be made available in Latin America. They say there is “alarming” <strong>inequity</strong> there in providing new HIV prevention tools with infection rates rising.</p>
<p>Countries including Norway, France, Spain and the U.S. have been paying more than $40,000 per year for Sunlenca. But experts have said it could be produced for as little as $40 a treatment once generic production expands.</p>
<p>In a statement, Gilead said it has “an ongoing commitment to help enable <strong>access</strong> to HIV prevention and treatment <strong>options</strong> where the need is the greatest.” Among the 120 countries approved for the generic version are 18 mostly African nations that make up about 70 percent of the world's HIV cases.</p>
<p>The drugmaker said it is also working to establish “fast, <strong>efficient </strong>pathways to reach all people who need or want lenacapavir for HIV prevention.”</p>
<p>Dr. Chris Beyrer is the director of the Global Health Institute at Duke University in North Carolina. He said it will be greatly useful to have the Gilead shots available in the hardest-hit countries in Africa and Asia. But he added that rising HIV rates among groups including gay men and <strong>transgender</strong> populations represents “a public health emergency” in Latin America.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>immune system</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> the cells and tissues in the body that fight against infection</p>
<p><strong>advanced </strong><em>– adj.</em> having developed to a late stage</p>
<p><strong>crossroads</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a time when you have to make an important decision that will affect your future life</p>
<p><strong>condom </strong><em>– n. </em>a thin rubber covering worn by a man to stop a woman from becoming pregnant</p>
<p><strong>gay</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj.</em> being attracted to others of the same sex</p>
<p><strong>miracle</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> something that is very surprising or difficult to believe</p>
<p><strong>clinic </strong><em>– n. </em>a place where people go to see doctors or receive medical treatment</p>
<p><strong>inequity </strong><em>– n.</em> the state of being unfair, or something that is unfair</p>
<p><strong>access</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> the ability to get or use something</p>
<p><strong>option </strong><em>– n. </em>a choice among things</p>
<p><strong>efficient</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj.</em> working well and not wasting time or energy</p>
<p><strong>transgender</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj.</em> used to describe someone whose gender does not match the body they were born with</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Mayans Ask Mexican Court to Recognize Lakes as Legal Persons (2024/12/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/mayans-ask-mexican-court-to-recognize-lakes-as-legal-persons.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In the Mexican state of Yucatan, hundreds of underground lakes form a semicircular shape in the northwestern part of Yucatan state. They are called the Ring of Cenotes. The lakes provide water for the area, but they are also part of a dispute between local people and pig farmers.</p>
<p>The cenotes are also important to local people who earn a living by leading foreign visitors into the <strong>caverns</strong> to swim and explore.</p>
<p>Maribel Ek lives in the community of Homun, near the cenote known as Santa Maria. To native Mayans like Ek, cenotes are holy. She calls the Sant Maria cenote her "neighbor."</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Maribel Ek, guardian of the cenotes, rests inside the Santa Maria cenote, in Homun, Mexico, Monday, March 4, 2024. (AP Photo/Rodrigo Abd)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1955184f-5b8a-4a58-ae00-4127608fccdc_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Maribel Ek, guardian of the cenotes, rests inside the Santa Maria cenote, in Homun, Mexico, Monday, March 4, 2024. (AP Photo/Rodrigo Abd)</span></div>
<p>That belief is behind a legal action, or lawsuit, that aims to have the Ring of Cenotes legally recognized as a person. Personhood would give the lakes the same rights and protections of law that human citizens have.</p>
<p>A Mayan organization called Guardians of the Cenotes has brought the lawsuit. It aims to keep large pig farms out of the area because they are affecting the water quality of the underground lakes.</p>
<p>If the group wins, the lakes will become the first <strong>ecosystem</strong> in Mexico to be considered a person. There have been other such cases worldwide, such as the Whanganui River in New Zealand or the Komi Memem River in the Brazilian Amazon.</p>
<p>Ek is a member of the Guardians group.</p>
<p><strong>Polluting the waters</strong></p>
<p>The threats to cenotes have been growing. Cities in Yucatan are growing and there are new <strong>breweries</strong> and soybean fields in the area. But what most worries the Guardians of the Cenotes are the pig farms.</p>
<p>Mexico's Ministry of the Environment reports that 507 pig farms are operating near the Ring of Cenotes. There is little to no control over what happens to the thousands of liters of water containing pig waste from the farms.</p>
<p>Yameli Aguilar is a biologist from the Autonomous University of Yucatan. He said the polluted water goes into the <strong>aquifer</strong>.</p>
<p>A study carried out last year by the Ministry of the Environment found E. coli bacteria in 20 cenotes near pig farms.</p>
<p>The state has named the land a natural protected area, and it is an important wetland. Lourdes Medina is a lawyer who represents the Guardians in the legal case. She said the government still has failed to prevent “serious <strong>contamination</strong>” from taking place.</p>
<p>Ek and others created the Guardians of the Cenotes group to lead the fight against one pig farm built near Homun in 2017. They organized protests and legal actions without any effect. A year later, six children from Homun brought a case demanding their right to water and a healthy environment. A judge ordered the farm closed.</p>
<p>In 2022, the group began its personhood legal action. If successful, it would affect 52 communities within the Ring of Cenotes. A Yucatan state judge has ordered officials not to give permission to any project that could affect the area until the lawsuit is settled.</p>
<p>That could happen at the beginning of next year.</p>
<p><strong>What do the pig farmers say?</strong></p>
<p>Pig farms and other large industries come to the area because of the availability of water. The farms use a lot of water to cool the animals and clean their waste.</p>
<p>The industry says it is not causing the contamination. Carlos Ramayo Navarrete is director of the Pig Farmers Association in Merida. It represents the largest pig farms in Yucatan. He said the problem comes from a lack of <strong>drainage</strong> systems in cities and small pig farmers. Navarrete said small pig farms are not as officially <strong>regulated</strong> as the big farms he represents.</p>
<p>He said around half the water the farms use is reused. In addition, he said all of the farms have treatment systems to reduce pollution in their wastewater. The remaining water is then used as fertilizer.</p>
<p>However, both the Ministry of the Environment and Aguilar, the biologist, have said that the measures taken by the industry are still not enough.</p>
<p><strong>What will the future bring?</strong></p>
<p>Back in Homun, Maribel Ek enjoys swimming in the waters of the cenote. She said that she has learned the cenote is "a blessing, a dark hole that becomes a friend," and she added "That's why we demand rights for our cenotes."</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Teresa de Miguel reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>cavern</strong> – <em>n</em>. a large cave</p>
<p><strong>ecosystem</strong> – <em>n</em>. everything that exists in a particular environment</p>
<p><strong>brewery</strong> – <em>n</em>. a company that makes beer</p>
<p><strong>aquifer </strong>- <em>n</em>. a layer of rock or sand that holds a lot of water</p>
<p><strong>contamination </strong>–n. when a substance, like pollution, gets into places where it is not supposed to be</p>
<p><strong>drainage </strong><em>–n. </em>related to systems that carry rain or wastewater away from streets and buildings</p>
<p><strong>regulate</strong> – <em>v.</em> to make rules or laws that control activities like business or travel</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Google Announces Solution to a Big Problem in Quantum Computing (2024/12/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/google-announces-solution-to-a-big-problem-in-quantum-computing.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Google recently said that it had solved a major problem in supercomputing with a new generation of processor called Willow.</p>
<p>Along with other technology companies such as Microsoft and International Business Machines (IBM), Google, whose parent company is Alphabet, is working on <strong>quantum</strong> computing. The new development promises to increase computing speeds while limiting mistakes, or errors, which are a problem with quantum computing systems.</p>
<p>Scientists at the company's Santa Barbara, California quantum laboratory announced they had at least partly solved the error problem on December 9. On the same day, the scientific publication <em>Nature </em>published their paper on error correction.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A person shows Google Quantum AI's " by="" chip="" december="" handout="" in="" obtained="" on="" photo="" reuters="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/b9e503d9-3cc7-4766-8a3b-8507989df74c_w268_r1.jpg" this="" undated="" via="" willow=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A person shows Google Quantum AI's "Willow" chip, in this undated handout photo obtained by Reuters on December 6, 2024. (Handout via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>Google said that the Willow processor carried out a <strong>computation</strong> in under five minutes that would have taken a fast supercomputer longer than the current age of the universe to complete.</p>
<p>The work of the Google researchers, however, does not have any <strong>commercial</strong> uses yet. But Google hopes quantum computers will one day solve problems in medicine, battery chemistry and artificial intelligence (AI) that today's computers cannot solve.</p>
<p><strong>The Willow chip</strong></p>
<p>The Willow processor, or chip, runs on units of data called “quantum bits” or “qubits” for short. Qubits permit fast computing but can easily create errors. Google researchers have a theory that qubits might be affected by subatomic particles from events in space.</p>
<p>As more qubits are placed onto a chip, however, the errors can increase to make the chip no better than today's usual computer chips. As a result, scientists have been working on quantum error-correction since the 1990s.</p>
<p>Hartmut Neven, who leads Google's Quantum AI group, said that Willow has 105 qubits.</p>
<p>In the paper recently published in <em>Nature</em>, Google researchers said they have found a way to connect the Willow chip's qubits so that error rates go down as the number of qubits goes up. Neven also said Willow can correct errors in “real time.” That is an important step toward making quantum computers useful.</p>
<p>"We are past the break even point," Neven told Reuters. In a blog post, he said it was an unmistakable sign that “error correction is improving overall.”</p>
<p>In 2019, IBM challenged the claim that Google's quantum chip solved a problem that would take a normal computer 10,000 years to complete. IBM said the problem could be solved in two-and-a-half days using different <strong>assumptions</strong> about computer system design.</p>
<p>Google said in its blog post that it considered some of those concerns in its newest estimates. Even under the best conditions, Google said a computer of today would still take a billion years to get the same results as its latest chip.</p>
<p>Some of Google's competitors are producing chips with more qubits than Willow. But Anthony Megrant, who is also with Google Quantum AI, told Reuters that Google is trying to make the most dependable qubits possible.</p>
<p>Google produced its earlier chips in a shared building at the University of California, Santa Barbara. But for the Willow chips, Google built its own special laboratory. Megrant said that the new lab will speed up the process of making future chips.</p>
<p>One major problem is that quantum chips must be kept at low temperatures in machines that can produce extremely low temperatures called cryostats. The new laboratory permits the researchers to work more quickly.</p>
<p>"If we have a good idea, we want somebody on the team to be able to...get into that clean room and into one of these cryostats as fast as possible, so we can get lots of <strong>cycles</strong> of learning," Megrant said.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Stephen Nellis</em> <em>reported this story for Reuters news agency. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English with additional information from Google and Nature. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>quantum</strong> – <em>adj</em>. of, relating to, or using the principles of quantum theory</p>
<p><strong>computation </strong><em>–n</em>. an operation carried out by a computing device that is mathematical and digital in nature</p>
<p><strong>commercial </strong>–adj. related to business activity</p>
<p><strong>assumption </strong>–n. one of the basic conditions that is accepted in making a computation, but which might not exist in reality</p>
<p><strong>cycle </strong>– <em>n.</em> a repeating series of events or actions</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Europe Launches Mission to Create Simulated Solar Eclipse (2024/12/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/europe-launches-mission-to-create-simulated-solar-eclipse.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Two European satellites were recently launched on a mission that will include a <strong>simulated</strong> total solar eclipse.</p>
<p>The European Space Agency (ESA) launched the satellites on December 5 from southern India aboard an Indian-built rocket.</p>
<p>ESA says its Proba-3 mission aims to demonstrate <strong>precision </strong>formation flying abilities as the two satellites travel together in a fixed position.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This artist illustration shows one of two satellites - part of the European Space Agency's Proba-3 mission - positioned for a simulated total solar eclipse.
(Image Credit: CREDIT - ESA-P. Carril, 2013)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a624d48f-1a3a-46c6-afe3-13cf2ebaee4f_cx0_cy11_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This artist illustration shows one of two satellites - part of the European Space Agency's Proba-3 mission - positioned for a simulated total solar eclipse.
(Image Credit: CREDIT - ESA-P. Carril, 2013)</span></div>
<p>The two satellites are set to separate and fly 150 meters apart in about a month when they reach their target area high above Earth.</p>
<p><strong>Creating simulated solar eclipse</strong></p>
<p>In one of the mission's major experiments, the two spacecraft will carry out a series of <strong>artificial</strong> total solar eclipses. A shadow created by one satellite will permit the other to observe sun activity while blocking out the sun itself.</p>
<p>The goal of this operation is to give scientists the chance to study the sun's outermost atmosphere, known as the corona. The corona is difficult to observe because of the brightness of the sun.</p>
<p>Scientists have repeatedly tried to study this part of the sun from observations on Earth during real total solar eclipses. But those eclipses do not happen often and usually only last up to five minutes. The Proba-3 team plans to carry out total eclipses at least twice a week, with each lasting up to six hours.</p>
<p>Scientists say repeated studies of the corona can help provide new information about how solar activity influences Earth. For example, the project could help scientists better understand why the corona is so much hotter than the sun itself, and how the sun's energy output changes over time.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p>Sometimes, intense solar activity can result in geomagnetic storms, which can cause difficulties for power and communication systems on Earth.</p>
<p>"For six hours at a time, it will be able to see the sun's <strong>faint </strong>atmosphere, the corona, in the hard-to-observe region between the sun's edge and 1.4 million kilometers from its surface," ESA said in a pre-launch statement.</p>
<p>Mission leaders say the eclipse experiments will require extreme precision – within just one millimeter – to effectively position the spacecraft. To keep their position, the satellites will depend on <strong>GPS</strong>, laser systems and radio links.</p>
<p>ESA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.esa.int/Enabling_Support/Space_Engineering_Technology/Proba-3/Proba-3_Flying_two_spacecraft_is_harder_than_one">said</a> in a statement, “Proba-3 is very different because our satellites will be flying just one-and-a-half football fields away from each other during active formation flying.”</p>
<p>Esther Bastida Pertegaz is a systems engineer on the Proba-3 mission. She said in a video, "The corona of the sun ... has been very poorly investigated. One of the things we really want to understand is ... how do coronal mass ejections or solar wind <strong>originate</strong> in this area."</p>
<p>The $210 million project is being supported by over 40 European companies, Reuters news agency reports. These include SENER Aerospace, Redwire Space, and Airbus Defence and Space.</p>
<p>ESA says Proba-3 will aim for at least 1,000 hours of “on demand” totality during its two-year operation. Once the mission is complete, both satellites will continually drop lower until they burn up in the atmosphere. Officials said that would likely happen within five years.</p>
<p>ESA has said other orbits of Proba-3 – besides the eclipse experiments – will be carried out to demonstrate a range of precise formation flying to help support future missions.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters and the European Space Agency. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>simulate</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to do or make something that behaves or looks like something real but is not</p>
<p><strong>precise </strong><em>– adj.</em> exact</p>
<p><strong>artificial</strong><strong> </strong><em>–</em> <em>adj. </em>something created by a machine and not a natural process</p>
<p><strong>faint</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj. </em>very light; hard to see</p>
<p><strong>GPS</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a system built to follow the movements of something with an electronically-powered piece of equipment</p>
<p><strong>originate</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> where something begins</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Oldest Pet Burial Ground in America Is Final Resting Place for Thousands (2024/12/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/oldest-pet-burial-ground-in-america-is-final-resting-place-for-thousands.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>On most days, Mark Lindenberg either drives or walks over to visit with Boots, his beloved cat who died in 2020 at 17 years old. The New York man had the animal buried at the Hartsdale Pet Cemetery, a burial place on small grassy hills near the main road.</p>
<p>The words on Boots' <strong>tombstone</strong> read, “You taught me how to love and be loved.”</p>
<p>Other tombstones include <strong>phrases </strong>such as “A truer friend we never had” and “Our beloved queen.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="The pet cemetery was established in 1896, when veterinarian Samuel Johnson allowed a client to bury her dog in his apple orchard. (VOA)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/7f181b9a-2e80-41ef-b608-cb91367c2d76_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">The pet cemetery was established in 1896, when veterinarian Samuel Johnson allowed a client to bury her dog in his apple orchard. (VOA)</span></div>
<p>“Human cemeteries are sad,” Lindenberg said. “This is one of the most <strong>cheerful </strong>places.”</p>
<p>He added, “I can't think of a better place.”</p>
<p>Hartsdale is America's oldest pet cemetery in operation. It was added to the National Register of Historic Places in 2012. Lindenberg says he paid about $7,000 to bury Boots at Hartsdale. Those costs cover the individual site, burial, burial container, tombstone, and grounds<strong> </strong>care.</p>
<p>“What have I worked for if I'm not going to do the things that matter most, and this mattered most,” Lindenberg said. “I got <strong>instant</strong> closure the day I decided I was going to bury her here.”</p>
<p>Pet burials started in Hartsdale in 1896 when animal doctor Samuel Johnson let a woman bury her dog on his property of apple trees. The place is about 30 kilometers north of New York City.</p>
<p>Since that time, about 70,000 animals have been laid to rest in the two-hectare cemetery. Most of the pets buried at Hartsdale are cats and dogs, but several other kinds of animals are also there.</p>
<p>“There's reptiles that are buried here. Mice,” said Edward Martin III, vice president of the Hartsdale Pet Cemetery. “There's a lion <strong>cub</strong> that was buried here in 1912 by a Russian <strong>princess</strong>. There's the ashes of Ming, who's a Bengal tiger that was buried here a few years ago. There are some m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s.”</p>
<p>There is also Hudson the horse, some birds and singer Mariah Carey's cat, Clarence. The oldest headstone, dating to 1898, remembers the life of a dog named Blague.</p>
<p>Martin operates the place with his father Edward Martin Jr., who purchased the cemetery in 1974. The younger Martin is a lawyer and accountant who decided later in his career to help run the cemetery. He had worked there also as a teenager.</p>
<p>“I've seen what people go through, and they lose their pets, and I feel like I'm in a good position where I can help them,” he said. “And I have helped them, and it makes me want to continue helping them.”</p>
<p>Between 250 and 300 burials take place at Hartsdale each year. The cemetery never runs out of space because not all of the burial sites are permanent. People can make a one-time forever maintenance payment of $3,500 or a yearly payment of $105. If the yearly payments stop, that gravesite is offered for sale.</p>
<p>“The pet in the grave will be removed from that plot so someone else who wants it can pay the maintenance. And the pets are taken out, and they're <strong>cremated</strong>, and they don't leave the cemetery,” said Martin Jr., Hartsdale's president. “Their remains are scattered over the cemetery grass.”</p>
<p>A centerpiece at the cemetery is the war dog memorial at the top of a hill. Established in 1923, the memorial honored World War I service dogs. But these days, the memorial honors service dogs of all kinds.</p>
<p>Although Hartsdale is mostly a resting place for animals, the cremated remains of about 800 humans are buried here with their pets. There is a Martin family plot, where the elder Martin plans to be laid to rest when he dies.</p>
<p>“I have to be buried somewhere. And why would I go to any place other than this?” he said. “My mother and father, and my mother-in-law or father-in-law are buried here, and so, that's a good reason by itself to do it.”</p>
<p>Lindenberg also likes the idea. He has already prepared to be cremated and buried alongside Boots when the time comes.</p>
<p>“I'm single. I don't know if I'll ever get married, and I can't think of a better place,” he said. “I lived with my cat every day for almost 17 years. Why stop now?”</p>
<p>In the meantime, Lindenberg, who lives a 10-minute walk away, will continue to visit his old friend almost daily.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Dora Mekouar reported this story for VOA News. Caty Weaver adapted the story for Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"> </h2>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in this Story</h2>
<p><strong>tombstone </strong><em>– n.</em> a marker attached to an individual burial place</p>
<p><strong>cheerful </strong><em>– adj.</em> pleasantly bright</p>
<p><strong>instant </strong><em>– n</em>. produced or happening with, or as if with, extreme quickness and ease</p>
<p><strong>cub </strong><em>– n</em>. a kind of baby animal</p>
<p><strong>princess </strong><em>– n.</em> a daughter or granddaughter of a king or queen:<strong> </strong>a female member of a royal family</p>
<p><strong>cremate </strong><em>– v.</em> to burn (as a dead body) to ashes</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>For Words of the Year: Brat, Brain Rot, Polarization (2024/12/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/for-words-of-the-year-brat-brain-rot-polarization.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/><span class="datetime">14 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From “brat” to “brain rot” and “polarization,” word experts agree that social media and politics have driven conversations that use these terms. Here are their <strong>selections</strong> for word of the year.</p>
<p><strong>Polarization</strong></p>
<p>The American dictionary publisher Merriam-Webster selected <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/wordplay/word-of-the-year">polarization</a> as its word of the year for 2024. The dictionary publisher defines <u>polarization</u> as “division into two sharply <strong>distinct</strong> opposites; especially, a state in which the opinions, beliefs, or interests of a group or society...become concentrated at opposing extremes.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This cover image released by Atlantic Records shows " ap="" brat="" by="" charli="" records="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/96a5ce05-f6b6-4cfe-81f7-76c6a8e8dbae_cx0_cy23_cw0_w268_r1.jpg" via="" xcx.=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This cover image released by Atlantic Records shows "brat" by Charli XCX. (Atlantic Records via AP)</span></div>
<p>As divided as Americans appear, Merriam-Webster says <u>polarization</u> “happens to be one idea that both sides of the political <strong>spectrum</strong> agree on.”</p>
<p>The word was widely used in news stories and broadcasts to describe the presidential election in the United States. Supporters of both candidates, president-elect Donald Trump and Vice President Kamala Harris, voiced the opinion that the opposing candidate was a threat to the nation.</p>
<p>The U.S. election also brought attention to two other words: <u>pander</u> and <u>weird</u>. Trump's supporters accused Harris of <u>pandering</u>, in other words, changing her policy positions to get votes. And Democratic vice-presidential candidate Tim Walz called his opponents <u>weird</u>, meaning strange or unusual.</p>
<p><strong>Brain rot</strong></p>
<p>The editors at Britain's Oxford University Press say usage of its word of the year selection, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://corp.oup.com/news/brain-rot-named-oxford-word-of-the-year-2024/">brain rot</a><u>,</u> increased by 230 percent from 2023 to 2024.</p>
<p>Oxford defines brain rot as “the supposed <strong>deterioration</strong> of a person's mental or intellectual state, especially viewed as the result of overconsumption of material (now particularly online content) considered to be trivial or unchallenging.”</p>
<p>The phrase likely first appeared in written form in Henry David Thoreau's 1854 book <em>Walden</em> about his experiences living a simple lifestyle. He wrote: “While England <strong>endeavors</strong> to cure the potato rot, will not any endeavor to cure the brain-rot – which prevails so much more widely and fatally?”</p>
<p>In 2024, the phrase has been used to describe concerns about the harm of overconsuming, or watching and reading too much, online material.</p>
<p>Casper Grathwohl, President of Oxford Languages, noted, “I find it fascinating that the term ‘brain rot' has been adopted by Gen Z and Gen Alpha, those communities largely responsible for the use and creation of the digital content the term refers to.”</p>
<p><strong>Brat</strong></p>
<p>Politics and social media come together in the Collins Dictionary's selection of <a class="wsw__a" href="https://blog.collinsdictionary.com/language-lovers/a-year-when-hedonism-and-anxiety-combine/">brat</a> as its word of the year.</p>
<p>The most recent usage of <u>brat</u> started as the title of an album by pop singer Charli XCX. Then it went <strong>viral</strong> as a campaign <strong>slogan</strong> “Kamala IS <u>Brat</u>” for the Democratic presidential candidate.</p>
<p>The word means different things to different people.</p>
<p>Traditionally, <u>brat</u> describes an immature person or an unruly child. But Collins says it is now used to describe a person with “confident, independent, and <strong>hedonistic attitude</strong>.”</p>
<p>Collins says the term <u>brat</u> “has clearly captured something of the spirit of the age.” And for a short time, the word <u>brat summer</u> even “established itself as an aesthetic and a way of life.”</p>
<p><strong>Demure</strong></p>
<p>The online Dictionary.com selected <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.dictionary.com/e/word-of-the-year-2024/">demure</a> as its word of the year for 2024. Between January and the end of August, Dictionary.com<em> </em>said the word “saw a nearly 1200 percent increase in usage in digital web media alone.”</p>
<p>The sharp rise is credited to several videos on TikTok by Jools Lebron. “You see how I do my makeup for work?” she asked. “Very <u>demure</u>, very mindful.”</p>
<p><u>Demure</u> is another example of how popular word usage changes over time. In the 14th century, <u>demure</u> was used to describe people who avoid bringing attention to themselves. Today, the word is used to describe someone who brings attention to themselves with “refined and <strong>sophisticated</strong> appearance or behavior.”</p>
<p>And those are the Words of the Year for 2024.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Hai Do wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>selection </strong><em>–n.</em> a choice that is made from several possibilities</p>
<p><strong>distinct </strong><em>–adj.</em> different in an observable way</p>
<p><strong>spectrum </strong><em>–n.</em> a complete set of small differences that can exist within one thing: for example, the spectrum of light or of popular opinion</p>
<p><strong>deterioration </strong><em>–n.</em> the condition of being broken down and becoming worse and less effective</p>
<p><strong>endeavor </strong><em>–v.</em> to try to do something with continuous effort</p>
<p><strong>viral </strong><em>–adj. (social media)</em> something that is seen many times and is considered popular</p>
<p><strong>slogan </strong><em>–n.</em> an easily remembered phrase that is meant to build support for something or someone</p>
<p><strong>hedonistic</strong> <em>–adj.</em> interested only in pleasure</p>
<p><strong>attitude </strong><em>–n. </em>a way of acting that shows the way one thinks</p>
<p><strong>sophisticated </strong><em>–adj.</em> knowledgeable in worldly matters; complex is a way that appeals to people with a certain kind of knowledge</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Chicken Little (2024/12/14)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/american-stories-chicken-little.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/><span class="datetime">13 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now an American Children's Story from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Today's story probably had its start long before it was published in Europe long ago.</p>
<p>It might have first been known as “Henny Penny.” But the story has been told to American children at least since the mid-1800s under a title similar to “Chicken Little.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e9b8d234-737f-4e19-8c46-ee5932263831_w100_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>Generations have heard and thought about the lessons of the little chicken who causes big problems for a group of well-meaning but not-so-thoughtful birds.</p>
<p>Today's version is based on two examples of the story. One is called <em>Remarkable Story of Chicken Little</em>. John Green Chandler had it published in the city of Boston, Massachusetts in 1842. Katharine Pyle published her 1918 version in <em>Mother's Nursery Tales</em>.</p>
<p>The story has taken on its own American qualities and is a little like a parable, a story that teaches a moral lesson. Later retellings including a few movie versions have made changes to some of the characters or aimed to teach different ideas.</p>
<p>Here is the story <em>Chicken Little</em> in VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>One day, Chicken Little fell asleep under some flowers.</p>
<p>Cow wandered by, reached over the fence and bit off some flowers.</p>
<p>The noise wakened Chicken Little just as a flower <strong>petal</strong> fell on her tail.</p>
<p>"Squawk! Squawk!” cried Chicken Little, frightened by the petal's landing.</p>
<p>“The sky is falling,” she continued, her call rising louder with her terror. “Squawk! Squawk!”</p>
<p>And, she jumped up and began to run, moving as fast as her two legs would carry her. She did not stop running until she came to the barnyard. There, she found Henny Penny scratching in the dirt of the barnyard.</p>
<p>“Oh, Henny Penny, do not scratch—run!” cried Chicken Little. “The sky is falling.”</p>
<p>The scratching stopped. Then Hen called out: “How do you know that, Chicken Little?”</p>
<p>“I saw it with my eyes, I heard it with my ears, and part of it fell on my tail. Let us run, until we get some place.”</p>
<p>“Squawk! Squawk,” cried Hen in return, a look of shock on her face. Then, run she did, speeding away from the barnyard.</p>
<p>Chicken Little followed close behind.</p>
<p>They almost ran right past the little lake, just as Ducky Lucky was going in for a swim.</p>
<p>“Oh, Ducky Lucky! Ducky Lucky! Do not try to swim,” cried Henny Penny. “The sky is falling.”</p>
<p>“Seriously, Henny Penny? Why do you think that?” asked Ducky Lucky.</p>
<p>“Chicken Little told me.”</p>
<p>“How do you know the sky is falling, Chicken Little?”</p>
<p>“I saw it with my eyes, I heard it with my ears, and part of it fell on my tail. Oh, let us run until we get some place.”</p>
<p>Ducky Lucky was persuaded.</p>
<p>“Yes, we had better run,” he yelled.</p>
<p>And the three took off, Ducky Lucky <strong>waddling</strong> faster than he ever had before. The birds ran and ran until they came to a green <strong>meadow</strong>, and there was Goosey Loose eating the green grass.</p>
<p>“Oh, Goosey Lucy, Goosey Lucy, do not eat; run,” cried Ducky Lucky.</p>
<p>“Why should I run?” asked Goosey Lucy.</p>
<p>“Because the sky is falling.”</p>
<p>“How do you know that, Ducky Lucky?”</p>
<p>“Henny Penny told me.”</p>
<p>“How do you know that, Henny Penny?”</p>
<p>“Chicken Little told me.”</p>
<p>“How do you know that, Chicken Little?”</p>
<p>“Because I saw it with my eyes, and heard it with my ears, and part of it fell on my tail. Oh, let us run some place.”</p>
<p>“Yes, we had better run,” cried Goosey Lucy.</p>
<p>Away they all ran, Goosey Lucy in the lead, and they ran and ran until they came to the turkey <strong>yard</strong>, and there was Turkey Lurkey <strong>strutting</strong> and <strong>gobbling</strong>.</p>
<p>“Oh, Turkey Lurkey! Do not strut!” cried Goosey Lucy.</p>
<p>“Why should I not strut?” asked Turkey Lurkey.</p>
<p>“Because the sky is falling.”</p>
<p>“How do you know it is?”</p>
<p>“Ducky Lucky told me!”</p>
<p>“How do you know, Ducky Lucky?”</p>
<p>“Henny Penny told me!”</p>
<p>“How do you know, Henny Penny?”</p>
<p>“Chicken Little told me!”</p>
<p>“Chicken Little, how do you know this for a fact?”</p>
<p>“I could not help knowing! I saw it with my eyes, I heard it with my ears, and a part of it fell on my tail. Oh, let us run until we get some place.”</p>
<p>“Yes, it would be best to run,” said Turkey Lurkey, so away they all ran, first Turkey Lurkey, and then Goosey Lucy, and then Ducky Lucky, and then Henny Penny and then Chicken Little.</p>
<p>They ran and ran until they came to Foxy Loxy's house.</p>
<p>Foxy Loxy was resting, spread out across the doorway. She kept <strong>yawning</strong>, opening her mouth wide so that all her sharp teeth showed. But, her mouth snapped shut at the sudden arrival of the frightened birds, Turkey Lurkey and Goosey Lucy and Ducky Lucky and Henny Penny and Chicken Little.</p>
<p>Her eyes softened and her ears stood up. She was so very happy to see them all and smiled sweetly.</p>
<p>“Well, well,” the fox said, “what brings you all here?”</p>
<p>“Foxy Loxy, prevent yourself from yawning,” cried old Turkey Lurkey, “Indeed, the sky is falling.”</p>
<p>“How do you know that, Turkey Lurkey?” asked the fox.</p>
<p>“Goosey Lucy informed me.”</p>
<p>“How do you know that, Goosey Lucy?”</p>
<p>“Ducky Lucky told me.”</p>
<p>“How do you know that, Ducky Lucky?”</p>
<p>“Henny Penny told me.”</p>
<p>“How do you know that, Henny Penny?”</p>
<p>“Chicken Little.”</p>
<p>“How do you know that, Chicken Little?”</p>
<p>“I could not help knowing, for I saw it with my eyes, and I heard it with my ears, and part of it fell on my tail. Oh, where shall we run? We ought to go someplace.”</p>
<p>“Well,” said the Fox, “you come right into my house, and I will protect you and take such good care of you that, even if the sky falls, you will not know anything about it.”</p>
<p>So, in ran Turkey Lurkey and Goosey Lucy and Ducky Lucky and Henny Penny and — Chicken Little.</p>
<p>Foxy Loxy waited for a while and then shut the door firmly behind her. She would not let the falling sky threaten her guests, you see. She was going to take special care of them all.</p>
<p>And, maybe she did. But no one ever saw Chicken Little or her friends again.</p>
<p><em>Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted this story for VOA Learning English from stories in the public domain.</em></p><p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>petal</strong> <em>–n. </em>a flat, soft colorful part of a flower</p>
<p><strong>waddle</strong> <em>–v.</em> to walk with short steps while moving from side to side like a duck</p>
<p><strong>meadow </strong>–n. a wide flat area covered with grass that is often surrounded by forest</p>
<p><strong>strut </strong>–v. to walk in a confident or proud way</p>
<p><strong>yawn </strong>–v. to open the mouth wide and take a deep breath usually as a reaction to being tired or bored</p>
<p><strong>curl </strong>–v. to form into a rounded shape</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Using the Phonetic Alphabet (2024/12/14)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/using-the-phonetic-alphabet.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">13 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Mouhammed in Egypt about using the phonetic alphabet.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/d81a33a8-a0ed-4bc3-8954-e67593f8e401_w268_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>I want to ask about the most important sources through which I can learn to improve the [pronunciation] of English letters, [for] trying to master the American accent.</p>
<p>Thank you,</p>
<p>Mouhammed</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Mouhammed.</p>
<p><strong>Understanding phonemes and the phonetic alphabet</strong></p>
<p>You can use the phonetic alphabet to help you know each sound of American English. Let's start by looking at what the phonetic alphabet is.</p>
<p>Each separate sound we make when we talk is called a phoneme. For example, the word “cat” has three phonemes: /k/, /<i></i>230;/, /t/ --“cat.”</p>
<p>For every phoneme we say, in any language, we can show that phoneme by using a special symbol, or sign. Those symbols are what make The International Phonetic Alphabet, or IPA. Notice that in the example with “cat,” only the phonetic symbol for the letter “t” looks the same as the English letter for that sound.</p>
<p>For many phonemes, the phonetic symbol does not look the same as the letters of the English alphabet that make the sound of the phonemes. Consider the word “need,” for example. It is spelled N-E-E-D but the phonetic symbol signifying the vowel looks like the English letter “i.”</p>
<p><strong>Using the phonetic alphabet</strong></p>
<p>How can you use the phonetic alphabet? Try to identify the phonemes that are difficult for you. For example, small differences between some vowel sounds in American English may be difficult for some non-native speakers to hear. Consider the following example:</p>
<p><em>bit bet</em></p>
<p>Did you clearly hear the difference between the two words? Hearing the sounds more clearly can help you pronounce them.</p>
<p>The <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.vocabulary.com/resources/ipa-pronunciation/">IPA Pronunciation Guide</a> on the website Vocabulary.com has an audio element so you can listen to the sound of each symbol. It also provides example words that contain the sound of each symbol. So, you can use the guide to practice hearing and saying any phoneme in American English.</p>
<p>The VOA Learning English video series <em>How to Pronounce </em>has many lessons that use IPA symbols to help learners practice the sounds of American English. The 21 lessons <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/7120228.html">“Games with Vowel Sounds”</a> and the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/7070516.html" target="_blank">"Listening Practice”</a> lessons are good places to start.</p>
<p>On the VOA Learning English website, you can play a short piece of audio and listen for phonemes you want to <strong>practice</strong>. You can hear words pronounced clearly and look at the way English spelling represents the phonemes you hear.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? We want to hear from you! Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please let us know where you are from, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Ancient Americans Depended Heavily on Mammoth for Food (2024/12/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/study-ancient-americans-depended-heavily-on-mammoth-for-food.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A new study finds that the first humans to live in North America depended heavily on mammoths and other large animals for food.</p>
<p>The finding is based on examinations of the diet of a woman who lived about 13,000 years ago during the last Ice Age. She belonged to a culture called the Clovis. They were among the first Native Americans to arrive on the continent.</p>
<p>The woman was still breast-feeding her 18-month-old son when he died. The boy's remains were discovered back in 1968 in an ancient burial ground in the western U.S. state of Montana. Scientists examined his bones to learn more about his mother's diet.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Illustration of a group of Western Clovis people at a site in Montana. as seen in this handout image released on December 4, 2024. (Ben Potter of the University of Alaska Fairbanks and Jim Chatters of McMaster University/Handout via REUTERS)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/b33d06e9-8bd5-4a22-9d1a-92e6f16ed19b_cx0_cy11_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Illustration of a group of Western Clovis people at a site in Montana. as seen in this handout image released on December 4, 2024. (Ben Potter of the University of Alaska Fairbanks and Jim Chatters of McMaster University/Handout via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>They found that the woman ate mostly meat from mammoths and other very large animals. The finding supports scientific theories that Clovis people specialized in hunting large animals instead of seeking plants or small animals to eat.</p>
<p>At the time the Clovis people lived, large animals like mammoths lived in areas covering the Americas, as well as parts of northern Asia. The researchers noted that mammoths traveled very long distances during this period. This made them a target for migrating humans seeking protein-rich foods to eat.</p>
<p>The team examined isotope data collected from the boy's bones to estimate the Clovis woman's dietary intake. An isotope is a kind of atom that has a different atomic weight than similar atoms, but the same chemical structure. The isotope experiments centered on the elements carbon and nitrogen.</p>
<p>Mat Wooller is a professor and director of the Alaska Stable Isotope center at the University of Alaska Fairbanks. He was a co-writer of the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.adr3814">study</a> describing the research in the publication <em>Science Advances</em>.</p>
<p>Wooller told Reuters news agency isotope examinations can provide “a chemical fingerprint” of parts of an ancient human's diet. "We are all made of elements, like carbon and nitrogen, and so is our food," he said.</p>
<p>James Chatters is a professor of Earth, Environment and Society at Canada's McMaster University. He helped lead the research. Chatters <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.uaf.edu/news/study-reveals-mammoth-as-key-food-source-for-ancient-americans.php">said</a> in a statement that centering on mammoths “helps explain how Clovis people could spread throughout North America and into South America in just a few hundred years.”</p>
<p>The scientists estimated the woman mostly ate meat from a group of animals called megafauna, the largest creatures that existed at the time. The study showed megafauna made up about 96 percent of her diet, with mammoth accounting for about 40 percent of the total.</p>
<p>Chatters said one mammoth could support “a dependent community of children, care-giving women, and less <strong>mobile </strong>elders for days or even weeks while the hunters sought their next kill." Mammoths stood to about four meters tall at the shoulder and weighed as much as 11 tons.</p>
<p>Chatters said the Clovis people were known to be highly skilled hunters with a 10,000-year history of hunting megafauna over wide areas of territory. He added that the great dependence of the Clovis on megafauna likely led to the pressures that later caused the <strong>extinction</strong> of large ice age animals.</p>
<p>Chatters noted the latest finding supports past studies that provided "indirect evidence” that Clovis people mainly depended on mammoths and other large animals for food. This evidence included examinations of different <strong>artifacts</strong> – such as stone tools or the ancient remains of large animals, he said.</p>
<p>Ben Potter was also a co-writer of the study. He is an archeologist at the University of Alaska Fairbanks. Potter told Reuters, "These results also help us understand megafauna extinctions at the end of the last Ice Age.” He added the findings suggest that humans may have played a more important part in the extinctions than is sometimes thought.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Reuters reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English, with additional information from the University of Alaska Fairbanks and Science Advances. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>mobile </strong><em>– adj. <strong> </strong></em>capable of moving or being moved</p>
<p><strong>artifact </strong><em>– n.</em> an object showing human work and representing a culture or a stage in the development of a culture</p>
<p><strong>extinct</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj.</em> no longer in existence</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Peace Brings Big Changes to Kabul's Luxury Housing Market (2024/12/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/peace-brings-big-changes-to-kabul-s-luxury-housing-market.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The capital city of Kabul, Afghanistan, has seen big changes in its high-end housing market. Peace, it seems, is driving up property prices.</p>
<p>Omidullah, a <strong>real estate</strong> agent, is selling a white-and-gold house with nine bedrooms and nine bathrooms in the Afghan capital. The house is on the market for $450,000, a surprising number in a country where more than half of the population depends on humanitarian aid to survive.</p>
<p>Most Afghans do not have bank accounts. And it is rare to borrow money from banks to buy property. Yet the offers are coming in.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A man waters flowers outside a luxury house in the city of Kabul, Afghanistan, Sept. 29, 2024. (AP Photo/Siddiqullah Alizai)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/bb75cc0c-9bea-4398-b7fc-ec5762f4c409_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A man waters flowers outside a luxury house in the city of Kabul, Afghanistan, Sept. 29, 2024. (AP Photo/Siddiqullah Alizai)</span></div>
<p>“It's a <strong>myth </strong>that Afghans don't have money,” Omidullah said. “We have very big businessmen who have big businesses abroad. There are houses here worth millions of dollars.”</p>
<p><strong>Afghans coming home </strong></p>
<p>People who spent years living and working abroad are returning home. They are drawn by the country's much-improved security and stability after years of war and destruction. Those returning include Afghans escaping <strong>deportation</strong> campaigns in Iran and Pakistan.</p>
<p>Banks rarely have enough money for lending. So, Afghans buy properties with their own money or employ what is called “geerawi.” It is when someone provides a fixed amount to a property owner in return for living in his place. And the person stays until the property owner returns the money.</p>
<p>Before the Taliban takeover, people were afraid to invest in Kabul, said another real estate agent, Ghulam Mohammed Haqdoost.</p>
<p>But the Taliban have created better conditions for the property market. The city is less violent since the Taliban changed from an insurgency to a government. Foreign forces left the country, although <strong>armored</strong> vehicles, checkpoints and military buildings remain common sights.</p>
<p>The Taliban have promised to end corruption and establish order. That means no more dealing with militia chiefs or paying officials for land purchases or building projects.</p>
<p>Haqdoost is happy with how easily and quickly things are getting done under the new administration.</p>
<p>“House prices have risen by almost 40 percent,” he said. “In the last three years, we have sold almost 400 properties. It wasn't like that before.”</p>
<p><strong>Good times for builders </strong></p>
<p>Business is good for Haqdoost. He employs 1200 workers, including women who only deal with female buyers.</p>
<p>Haqdoost said most purchasers bring their wives along because women often make decisions when it comes to real estate purchases — even in a nation that critics say oppresses women. “They decide whether to buy the house or not,” he said.</p>
<p>Afghans often host visiting friends or family in their homes. So wealthy buyers want houses with a garden, gym, swimming pool, rooms for visitors and at least one kitchen.</p>
<p>Since most of Haqdoost's buyers are from overseas, their tastes are influencing the homes. They want houses with central heating, <strong>double-pane</strong> windows and <strong>elevators</strong>, and things like dining tables and beds.</p>
<p>Kabul's population was around 500,000 in the year 2000. Now it is more than 5 million. To make Kabul more livable, city officials are busy building and repairing roads, putting in streetlights, planting trees and removing <strong>trash</strong>. They are also developing plans for less costly housing and increased home ownership.</p>
<p>Just outside of Kabul, Arash Asad is trying to sell his uncle's property, which sits on around 4,000 square meters of land. He wants to sell the property for $800,000.</p>
<p>“People think this country has no jobs and no economy,” Asad said. “But Afghans have made their money, illegally or legally, over the years. You wouldn't believe it.”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Riazat Butt reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>real estate </strong><em>-- n.</em> property (buildings and land)</p>
<p><strong>myth</strong> <em>– n.</em> a false idea or notion</p>
<p><strong>deport</strong> <em>– v.</em> to send (a person) out of the country</p>
<p><strong>armored</strong> <em>-- adj. </em>protected with a defensive covering </p>
<p><strong>double-pane </strong><em>-- adj. </em>describes a kind of window with two panes or layers of glass </p>
<p><strong>elevator</strong><em> -- n.</em> a platform or cage that moves people up and down </p>
<p><strong>trash </strong><em>-- n.</em> objects that are no longer wanted or needed and are thrown away </p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>European Climate Agency: 2024 Is Likely Hottest Year on Record (2024/12/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/european-climate-agency-2024-is-likely-hottest-year-on-record.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A recent report by the European climate service Copernicus says that November was the second-warmest November for which the agency has records.</p>
<p>The finding means that Copernicus will likely declare 2024 the hottest year ever measured using its sets of data.</p>
<p>Copernicus called last year the hottest on record. But after this summer, scientists involved in the effort were expecting that 2024 would set a new record.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Women cool themselves with fans in the Rastro flea market during a heatwave in Madrid, Spain, Aug. 15, 2021. (AP Photo/Andrea Comas, file)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/207d73c9-1299-4303-9983-16fefb6af150_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Women cool themselves with fans in the Rastro flea market during a heatwave in Madrid, Spain, Aug. 15, 2021. (AP Photo/Andrea Comas, file)</span></div>
<p>In November, the global temperature average was 14.10 Celsius. Through November, this year's average global temperature is 0.14 Celsius above the same period last year.</p>
<p>Jennifer Francis is a climate scientist at the Woodwell Climate Research Center in the northeastern U.S. state of Massachusetts. Francis, who was not involved in the report, said the big story about November is that “like 2023, it beat out previous Novembers by a large <strong>margin</strong>.”</p>
<p>The report said 2024 will likely be the first year in which the average temperature was more than 1.5 degrees Celsius above pre-industrial times. In earlier publications, Copernicus calls pre-industrial times the period between 1850 and 1900.</p>
<p>The 2015 Paris Agreement says human-caused warming should be limited to 2 degrees Celsius.</p>
<p>In the years following 2015, the world's top climate scientist said it was important to limit the rise in temperature to 1.5 degrees Celsius to prevent the worst effects of climate change. The scientists said these effects could include increasingly destructive and <strong>frequent</strong> extreme weather events.</p>
<p>Copernicus Deputy Director Samantha Burgess said in a news release that “<strong>ambitious</strong> climate action is more urgent than ever.”</p>
<p>Many scientists say the main cause of climate change is the burning of fuels like coal, oil and natural gas.</p>
<p>Francis said the new records are “terrible news for people and ecosystems.”</p>
<p>Francis predicted bad effects from the quickly changing climate. These include the possibility of animals dying off and changes to the natural food webs that the animals are part of.</p>
<p>She added that coastal communities may face problems because of rising sea levels.</p>
<p>Experts said heat waves over the oceans and a loss of sea ice and snow cover probably played a part in the temperature increase this year. Copernicus, the European agency, said the area of Antarctic sea ice in November was 10 percent below average, a record.</p>
<p>The Associated Press reports that oceans absorb about 90 percent of the heat trapped by greenhouse gases. They then release heat and water vapor back into the atmosphere.</p>
<p>Last year's record heat was caused partly by an El Ni<i></i>241;o — a temporary natural warming of parts of the central Pacific that affects weather worldwide.</p>
<p>But that ended earlier this year and an effect that often follows, called La Ni<i></i>241;a, failed to take place. This left the scientific community “a little perplexed by what's going on here...why temperatures are staying high,” said Jonathan Overpeck.</p>
<p>Overpeck is a climate scientist at the University of Michigan.</p>
<p>One theory is that an El Ni<i></i>241;o releases more heat to the atmosphere because of warmer ocean waters. Overpeck said, “we're not getting the cooling effect that often in decades gone by helps bring the temperature back down.”</p>
<p>This year, he said, “is such a big jump following yet another jump...”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Tammy Webber reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>margin </strong><em>– n.</em> a measure or degree of difference</p>
<p><strong>frequent</strong> <em>– adj.</em> acting or returning regularly or often</p>
<p><strong>ambitious</strong> <em>– adj.</em> hoping to reach a particular goal</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>TikTok Asks Court to Block US Ban, Seeks US Supreme Court Hearing (2024/12/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/tiktok-asks-court-to-block-us-ban-seeks-us-supreme-court-hearing.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">11 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>TikTok has asked a U.S. appeals court to temporarily block a law requiring its parent company, ByteDance, to <strong>divest</strong> itself of the popular video sharing service, or face a U.S. ban.</p>
<p>The legal request comes after the same federal appeals court last week upheld a law that forces ByteDance to sell TikTok by January 19 or face the ban. Lawyers for ByteDance and TikTok are seeking to temporarily block the law to give the U.S. Supreme Court a chance to rule on the case.</p>
<p>The companies said the Supreme Court had “an established historical record of protecting Americans' right to free speech.” They added their opinion that they expected the high court to “do just that on this important constitutional issue."</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file photo, a man carries a Free TikTok sign in front of the courthouse where a trial of Donald Trump was underway on April 15, 2024, in New York. (AP Photo/Ted Shaffrey, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/634230ad-7808-4e9f-b14c-d240f3e648aa_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">In this file photo, a man carries a Free TikTok sign in front of the courthouse where a trial of Donald Trump was underway on April 15, 2024, in New York. (AP Photo/Ted Shaffrey, File)</span></div>
<p>In the legal request, the companies warned that, without court intervention, the law would take effect next month leading to the closure of TikTok in the U.S. They called the service, or app, “one of the nation's most popular speech <strong>platforms</strong>,” noting it currently has more than 170 million monthly users in the U.S.</p>
<p>TikTok also warned that, if the law takes effect, it would affect “services for tens of millions of TikTok users outside the United States.”</p>
<p>The companies asked the appeals court to act on their request by December 16. They noted that President-elect Donald Trump has suggested he may try to prevent a U.S. ban on TikTok. Trump is set to take office on January 20.</p>
<p>A temporary block on the law could “give the incoming administration time to <strong>determine</strong> its position,” they said. The new administration's position, the companies argued, could make the Supreme Court hearing of the case unnecessary.</p>
<p>Unless the Supreme Court rules, a decision about whether to delay the TikTok ban would rest with President Joe Biden. He could approve a 90-day extension past January 19. However, experts have noted it is not clear whether ByteDance could meet a series of requirements needed to permit an extension.</p>
<p>In its ruling, the appeals court recognized that “170 million Americans use TikTok to create and view all sorts of free expression.”</p>
<p>Reuters news agency reports that it is not yet clear whether the Supreme Court will consider the case. But some legal experts have said the high court is likely to agree to hear it. The law is considered by some a test to see how far the U.S. government should be permitted to go in acting against technology companies using national security as a reason.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press, Reuters and Agence France-Presse reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>divest</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to sell something, especially a business or part of a business</p>
<p><strong>platform </strong><em>– n.</em> a kind of computer system, smartphone or social media service</p>
<p><strong>determine</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to decide something</p>
<p><strong>essential</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj.</em> necessary or needed</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Looking Back on Mispronounced Names and Words (2024/12/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/looking-back-on-mispronounced-names-and-words.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Vice President Kamala Harris and pop singer Chappell Roan were among the year's most talked-about people. Their names were also among those people said incorrectly, or mispronounced.</p>
<p>In early December, the language-learning company Babbel and The Captioning Group released a list of words that people in the U.S. struggled with the most in 2024. The list also provides a look back at the year's most discussed subjects and people, from pop culture to politics.</p>
<p>Esteban Touma is a linguistic and cultural expert at Babbel. He said, "It's a nice way to kind of look back into the year and see everything that has happened."</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Los Angeles Dodgers' Shohei Ohtani brings his dog Decoy to deliver the ceremonial first pitch before a baseball game between the Dodgers and the Baltimore Orioles, Aug. 28, 2024, in Los Angeles, California. (AP Photo/Mark J. Terrill, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/cee80e45-a025-4b9f-8974-29ac985caa81_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Los Angeles Dodgers' Shohei Ohtani brings his dog Decoy to deliver the ceremonial first pitch before a baseball game between the Dodgers and the Baltimore Orioles, Aug. 28, 2024, in Los Angeles, California. (AP Photo/Mark J. Terrill, File)</span></div>
<p>Chappell Roan became famous this year and is <strong>nominated</strong> for six Grammy awards. But people still do not know how to say her name correctly. The list says her name is pronounced CHAP-uhl ROHN, not SHA-pel ROW-an.</p>
<p><strong>Help with pronouncing names</strong></p>
<p>During Harris' campaign for president this year, two of her young relatives spoke at the Democratic National Convention to teach the crowd how to say her first name, pronounced COM-a-la.</p>
<p>Also making the list was U.S. Transportation Secretary Pete Buttigieg, whose last name still causes some problems. During his 2020 presidential run, his campaign made shirts with the pronunciation "Boot-Edge-Edge" to help.</p>
<p>Other words on the list include:</p>
<p>— Dutch Kooikerhondje, pronounced COY-ker-HUND-che, is a breed of dog that became known this year. That is because Los Angeles Dodgers baseball player Shohei Ohtani has a Kooikerhondje called Decoy that appeared with him at an opening game.</p>
<p>— The name of the actress Zendaya is often mispronounced as zen-DIE-uh, but it should be zen-DAY-a.</p>
<p>— Online fast-<strong>fashion</strong> business Shein is SHE-in, not SHEEN.</p>
<p>— Newly discovered exoplanet Speculoos-3b is pronounced SPEK-yuh-lohss three bee.</p>
<p>— Phryge, the <strong>mascot</strong> of the Paris Olympics, is pronounced FREE-je.</p>
<p>— Semaglutide, the drug in weight-loss medications Ozempic and Wegovy, is pronounced sem-ah-GLOO-tide, not SEE-mah-gloo-tide.</p>
<p>— The last name of Irish actor Barry Keoghan, who starred in "Saltburn," is pronounced key-OH-gin.</p>
<p>Nancy Niedzielski is chair of the linguistics department at Rice University in Houston. She points out that most of the words on the list are not English, so it is not surprising that they would be mispronounced in the U.S. The key to pronouncing them correctly, she said, would probably just be hearing them spoken.</p>
<p>Touma, a native Spanish speaker, said if you cannot pronounce a word, it is important to just keep trying. "One of the problems we have is our mouths are not trained to do those sounds that come from different languages," he said.</p>
<p>Touma admitted even he struggles with some words, including Harris' first name. Even though he knows the correct pronunciation, he said, it is hard to get it right in a conversation.</p>
<p>As Roan's music gained popularity, it was an interesting cultural moment to watch as people learned to pronounce her first and last name, he said.</p>
<p>"The way we create understanding with each other is just trying to do these things," Touma said.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jamie Stengle </em><em>reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>nominate</strong> – <em>v.</em> to formally choose (someone) as a candidate for a job, position, office, or award</p>
<p><strong>fashion</strong> – <em>n</em>. a popular way of dressing during a particular time or among a particular group of people</p>
<p><strong>mascot</strong> - <em>n</em>. a person, animal, or object used as a symbol to represent a group (such as a sports team) and to bring good luck</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Saving Sea Turtles on Northeastern US Coast (2024/12/11)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/saving-sea-turtles-on-northeastern-us-coast.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">10 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Over the last 20 years, the number of <strong>stranded </strong>sea turtles has increased in the waters off the northeastern coast of the United States. As a result, special animal hospitals in the New England area are now treating many sea turtles. Some kinds of these animals are highly endangered.</p>
<p>The turtles enter waters such as Cape Cod Bay when the weather is warm. But when temperatures drop, they cannot escape to head south, said Adam Kennedy. He is the director of rescue and <strong>rehabilitation</strong> at the New England <strong>Aquarium</strong>.</p>
<p>The aquarium operates a turtle hospital in Quincy, Massachusetts. On December 3, Kennedy said more than 200 young turtles needed to be treated there. The animals had been <strong>stunned</strong> by the cold.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Biologist Sammi Chaves, right, examines a Kemp's ridley sea turtle at a New England Aquarium marine animal rehabilitation facility, in Quincy, Mass., Tuesday, Dec. 3, 2024. (AP Photo/Steven Senne)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/72f1d803-3cad-4060-a8d2-6ae85ef97d13_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Biologist Sammi Chaves, right, examines a Kemp's ridley sea turtle at a New England Aquarium marine animal rehabilitation facility, in Quincy, Mass., Tuesday, Dec. 3, 2024. (AP Photo/Steven Senne)</span></div>
<p>The cold-stunned sea turtles wash up on the shores of Cape Cod every fall and winter. Kennedy said aquarium workers expect the number of turtles that they rescue to climb to at least 400. He said the average in 2010 was 40.</p>
<p>Kennedy said, “Climate change certainly is <strong>allowing</strong> those numbers of turtles to get in where normally the numbers weren't very high years ago.” He added that high winds and falling temperatures caused the recent strandings.</p>
<p>In the early 2010s, the five-year average of cold-stunned sea turtles in Massachusetts was around 200. In recent years, that number has grown to more than 700. These numbers come from the U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</p>
<p>All the turtles at the New England Aquarium's hospital are young. Most are<strong> </strong>the highly endangered Kemp's ridley turtles. The <strong>migration </strong>of these turtles often causes them to become stranded in the New England area. But some are green turtles or loggerheads which are not as endangered.</p>
<p>Kemp's ridley is the world's smallest sea turtle. The turtles mostly live in the Gulf of Mexico. But they travel into the northern Atlantic Ocean when young. A 2019 study in the scientific publication <em>PLoS One</em> said ocean warming increases the chance that turtles will become stunned by the cold in the waters of the Northwest Atlantic. The study said warmer water might push the turtles north in a way that makes stranding more likely.</p>
<p>Melissa Joblon is director of animal health at the New England Aquarium. She said most turtles that arrive at the center are sick: “The majority of the turtles arrive with serious <strong>ailments</strong> such as pneumonia, dehydration, traumatic injuries, or sepsis.”</p>
<p>The turtle hospital treats the animals so they can be returned to the wild. Kennedy said they are put in local waters or even taken south to warmer waters. He said about 80 percent survive.</p>
<p>“At the end of the day," Kennedy said, "getting these turtles back to the wild is what we are doing and what we want. We want them back in the ocean.”</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Patrick Whittle reported this story for the Associated Press from Portland, Maine. Anna Matteo adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>stranded </strong><em>–adj.</em> to be unable to leave a place</p>
<p><strong>rehabilitation </strong><em>–n.</em> the process of bringing a person or any living thing back to health after an accident or sickness</p>
<p><strong>aquarium </strong><em>–n</em>. a place that shows and takes care of fish and other sea life</p>
<p><strong>stun </strong><em>–v.</em> to make senseless, groggy, or dizzy by or as if by a blow</p>
<p><strong>allow </strong><em>–v.</em> to let something happen</p>
<p><strong>migration </strong><em>–n.</em> to regular movement of animals from one place to another to find food or better weather conditions</p>
<p><strong>ailment </strong><em>–n.</em> a sickness or condition that causes pain or poor health</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Power Outages Threaten Ice Cream Industry in Ecuadorean Town (2024/12/11)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/power-outages-threaten-ice-cream-industry-in-ecuadorean-town.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">10 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In Ecuador, power outages threaten ice cream businesses in the small town of Salcedo in the country's central highlands.</p>
<p>Ice cream production in Salcedo began in the middle of the 1900s. Women working in a Roman Catholic religious center there would make a fruit drink with milk from the area's dairy farms. One of the female religious workers, called nuns, began collecting the unused drink mixture. She turned it into creamy popsicles, frozen <strong>treats</strong> that quickly became popular.</p>
<p>The nuns sold the popsicles in town to gather money for the poor. But the people of Salcedo saw a business opportunity and began trying new <strong>flavors</strong> and methods. Soon ice cream lovers came to support the industry in the town.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A worker packages popsicles at an artisanal factory in Salcedo, Ecuador, Thursday, Nov. 28, 2024, amid a wave of power outages, triggered by a prolonged dry spell. (AP Photo/Dolores Ochoa)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a5971131-f931-4e57-8289-fc1433bbb3bd_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A worker packages popsicles at an artisanal factory in Salcedo, Ecuador, Thursday, Nov. 28, 2024, amid a wave of power outages, triggered by a prolonged dry spell. (AP Photo/Dolores Ochoa)</span></div>
<p>However, a recent wave of power outages is threatening Salcedo's ice-cream industry. The daily loss of electrical power, began earlier this year. Each outage can last up to 14 hours. The problem is a long period without rain. Ecuador gets much of its power from hydroelectric centers which depend on lakes and rainwater.</p>
<p>Gabriel Pumasunta is part owner, with his two brothers, of the Polar Bear ice-cream factory. He said that if the power outages continue this month, they will have to shut down the factory. Pumasunta said that much of his product has melted because of power outages.</p>
<p>Before September, Polar Bear was producing 60,000 popsicles per month. Now, the small company makes 10,000 popsicles per month. The business has been forced to let go of eight of its 10 employees. Pumasunta is spending the company's savings and those of his family. He now works on the plant's machines himself. His parents are helping to run the factory.</p>
<p><strong>Severe business losses from power outages</strong></p>
<p>Ecuador's President Daniel Noboa has not been able to solve the electricity crisis. The chamber of commerce in Guayaquil, Ecuador's largest city, estimates that power outages are creating weekly losses of $700 million for Ecuadorian businesses.</p>
<p>Germán Soria is president of the association of <strong>artisanal</strong> ice-cream makers. He said that before the power crisis, Salcedo had 80 small- and medium-sized ice-cream makers and three large factories. Now, 30 of these smaller businesses have had to close. Even the large factories are slowing production.</p>
<p>Soria's own ice-cream business is no longer operating. He said he stopped production three weeks ago and had to sell some equipment, as well as some land to pay his debts.</p>
<p>He said that the outages happen at unexpected times. That means buyers, like small stores, are unwilling to purchase ice cream because they are unsure whether it will melt.</p>
<p>Local officials say the power crisis has cost 300 jobs in Salcedo. The town is known for its fruit-flavored ice-cream, including flavors such as blackberries and taxo, a kind of tropical fruit.</p>
<p><strong>New sources of power</strong></p>
<p>The Ecuadorian government has bought some large electric <strong>generators</strong> that run on oil or gas. But as Marco Acu<i></i>241;a, the president of Ecuador's national guild of engineers, said: "They do not have the <strong>capacity</strong> to make up for the current deficit."</p>
<p>In Salcedo, the collapse of the ice-cream industry has hurt the local economy. Dairy farms, fruit growers, transporters and small stores that sell popsicles all feel the effects.</p>
<p>"Before (the power cuts) we would buy up to 150 popsicles a day," said Maria Juliette López, who owns a small store on the Panamerican highway where <strong>tourists</strong> and truck drivers stop to buy <strong>snacks</strong>. "Now we can only take up to 40 popsicles a day, because any product that is left over will melt,” she said.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Gonzalo Solano reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>treat</strong> – <em>n</em>. something that tastes good and that is not eaten often</p>
<p><strong>flavor</strong> – <em>n.</em> the quality of something that you can taste</p>
<p><strong>artisanal</strong> – <em>adj</em>. made by a person who is skilled at making things by hand</p>
<p><strong>generator</strong> – <em>n</em>. a machine that makes electricity by burning gas or oil</p>
<p><strong>capacity</strong> – <em>n.</em> the ability to do something</p>
<p><strong>tourist</strong> – <em>n</em>. a person who travels to a place for pleasure</p>
<p><strong>snack</strong> – <em>n</em>. a small amount of food eaten between meals</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Deep Breathing Can Reduce Stress, Anxiety (2024/12/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/deep-breathing-can-reduce-stress-anxiety.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>At Myosin Marketing in Austin, Texas, the group employee meeting begins with an uncommon activity for a workplace. The members gather on Zoom and the head of the company, Sean Clayton, leads them through a deep-breathing exercise.</p>
<p>Clayton says the activity helps his employees <strong>relax</strong> and to be willing to take creative risks.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A woman meditates on the beach in Miami, Florida, April 28, 2010. According to a study published on Nov. 9, 2022 in the journal JAMA Psychiatry, mindfulness meditation worked as well as a standard drug for treating anxiety. (AP Photo/Lynne Sladky, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1dabb073-c37b-4b77-bdd5-19cf18b12302_cx0_cy12_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A woman meditates on the beach in Miami, Florida, April 28, 2010. According to a study published on Nov. 9, 2022 in the journal JAMA Psychiatry, mindfulness meditation worked as well as a standard drug for treating anxiety. (AP Photo/Lynne Sladky, File)</span></div>
<p>“At first they thought it was really <strong>weird</strong>,”<strong> </strong>he said, adding that most people turned off their cameras. But, after a couple of weeks, there was a change. The employees said the deep breathing felt good.</p>
<p>Studies show that deep breathing can be an effective way to reduce tension, or stress, at work. But people may not think about their breathing while on the job.</p>
<p>Workers who sit at computers for long periods tend to take <strong>shallow</strong> breaths as their shoulders slowly rise. Workers who spend the day on their feet in retail or health care may be too busy to center their attention on breathing.</p>
<p>But there is good reason to stop what you are doing and take deep breaths, research suggests.</p>
<p>Long-lasting stress can increase the risk of heart disease and stroke. Experts at the American Heart Association say it can be as harmful as secondhand smoke. Research suggests deep-breathing exercises can lower a person's blood pressure and reduce <strong>anxiety</strong>.</p>
<p>There are many <strong>benefits</strong> to deep breathing. For starters, it is free. It can be done anywhere. And unlike a 30-minute <strong>meditation</strong> practice, most deep breathing exercises do not take much time.</p>
<p>Also, it gives you something to <strong>focus</strong> on – your breathing. Experts say that this can help to calm racing thoughts.</p>
<p>Focusing on breathing for one to five minutes can help you clear your mind and let you “get back to focusing on the one thing you want to <strong>accomplish</strong>,” said Glenn Levine. He is a heart and blood system doctor and professor at Baylor College of Medicine in Houston, Texas.</p>
<p>A good way to do deep breathing exercises is outside, Levine said. However, if that is not possible, doing them at a desk works.</p>
<p>“Instead of focusing on the screen or work, just focus on your breathing. If possible,” Levine said, “close your eyes.”</p>
<p>Even very busy people can find time for daily breathing exercises.</p>
<p>Lisa Marie Deleveaux is a marketing professional and mother of five. She lost her job several months ago and has struggled to find a new one. Deleveaux wakes early most mornings before her children, to do breathing exercises.</p>
<p>“If you set a <strong>priority</strong> for yourself ... you can make the time,” Deleveaux said.</p>
<p>With one breathing exercise, she breaths in through one nostril and then out through the other. She uses a thumb or forefinger to hold one nostril closed at a time.</p>
<p>“It relaxes my mind. It makes my mind so full of ease. It brings you back to the present moment,” she added.</p>
<p>To get ahead of anxiety before starting her workday, sales representative Lindsay Carlisle of Michigan does breathing exercises with her seven-year-old daughter during their drive to school. They breathe in for seven counts, hold their breath for five, and then breathe out for seven counts. They repeat this several times.</p>
<p>“Throughout that process, my shoulders start to drop on their own, and it really is calming,” Carlisle said.</p>
<p>Suze Yalof Schwartz was an overworked magazine editor when her mother-in-law taught her a three-minute meditation method.</p>
<p>Yalof Schwartz says it changed her life. She left her career and founded Unplug Meditation, a Santa Monica, California, company with a meditation studio, an app, and programs for corporate customers.</p>
<p>“When we slow down our breath, we send a signal to our brain that everything's OK, even when it's not,” she said.</p>
<p>Another 16-second breathing exercise is called box breathing. You breathe in for four counts, hold for four, breathe out for four counts and hold for another four. Yalof Schwartz has taught it to people in stressful jobs including firefighters, police and doctors.</p>
<p>“It is the best thing that you can do at work before you have a meeting, before you send out an email that you wish you didn't send, before you have a difficult conversation, because it just calms you down, gets rid of your <strong>negative </strong>energy,” she said.</p>
<p>Employers such as Coca-Cola, Mattel and Netflix have used Unplug Meditation to teach breathing or meditation.</p>
<p>It is not always easy for workers to find space for deep breathing exercises. For example, salespeople often work alongside their customers. Yalof Schwartz suggests doing breathing exercises when making a sale or organizing items.</p>
<p>Carlisle, the sales representative, sets a timer on her phone telling her to breathe deeply. She also keeps a note near her computer that simply says “Breathe.”</p>
<p>“The anxiety is always going to be there,” Carlisle said. “But at least I know I have one small tool. ... It sounds so simple and <strong>silly</strong>, but it works.”</p>
<p>And that's the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo. And I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Cathy Bussewitz</em><em> reported this story for the Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>relax </strong><em>–v. </em>to make less tense or rigid</p>
<p><strong>weird </strong><em>–adj. </em>of strange or extraordinary character</p>
<p><strong>shallow </strong><em>–adj. </em>having little depth</p>
<p><strong>anxiety </strong><em>–n. </em>fear or nervousness about what might happen</p>
<p><strong>benefit </strong><em>–n. </em>something that produces good or helpful results or effects or that promotes well-being</p>
<p><strong>meditate </strong><em>–v. </em>to spend time in quiet thinking and breathing : <strong>meditation </strong><em>–n. </em>the act of meditating</p>
<p><strong>focus </strong><em>–n. </em>a center of activity, attraction, or attention</p>
<p><strong>accomplish </strong><em>–v. </em>to succeed in reaching (a stage in a progression)</p>
<p><strong>priority</strong> <em>–n. </em>precedence in exercise of rights in the same subject matter</p>
<p><strong>negative </strong><em>–adj. </em>not positive or helpful</p>
<p><strong>silly </strong><em>–adj. </em>playfully lighthearted and amusing</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Handwriting Might Have Identified Famous Byzantine Artist (2024/12/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/handwriting-might-have-identified-famous-byzantine-artist.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Crime-solving methods might have provided an answer to an ancient mystery — the identity of a leading Byzantine painter.</p>
<p>The artist Giotto who lived in Italy about 700 years ago is often considered the father of Western painting. But at the same time that Giotto lived, Manuel Panselinos was equally important to a different tradition: the art of Byzantium.</p>
<p>The art of Byzantium can be found in Eastern Orthodox churches across Greece, Serbia and other Orthodox countries. Byzantium is an ancient name for the modern city of Istanbul.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Christina Sotirakoglou a handwriting expert, observes Byzantine paintings based on photographs prints, at her office, in Thessaloniki, northern Greece, Saturday, Nov. 30, 2024. (AP Photo/Giannis Papanikos)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/5f11a40f-724f-4bce-a3db-57ceaaba34e7_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Christina Sotirakoglou a handwriting expert, observes Byzantine paintings based on photographs prints, at her office, in Thessaloniki, northern Greece, Saturday, Nov. 30, 2024. (AP Photo/Giannis Papanikos)</span></div>
<p><strong>Who was Panselinos? </strong></p>
<p>Nothing is known of Panselinos' life. Historians now believe Panselinos was a <strong>nickname</strong>. They now suspect his real name was likely Ioannis Astrapas. He was from the northern Greek city of Thessaloniki.</p>
<p>Work said to be made by Panselinos, from the late 1200s and early 1300s, is considered the finest produced in the Byzantine empire. That ancient empire covered parts of Europe and Asia. It lasted from the fall of the Roman Empire until the capture of the capital Constantinople by the Ottoman Turks in 1453.</p>
<p>Art historians had long suspected that “Panselinos” could have been a nickname, or a pseudonym, for a member of the Macedonian School of painting in Thessaloniki. The name means “full moon” in Greek.</p>
<p>Recent research by a Greek <strong>monk </strong>and a language expert have linked Panselinos with Macedonian School painter Astrapas.</p>
<p>Now <strong>handwriting</strong> expert Christina Sotirakoglou has found new evidence. She matched lettering on a document thought to be by Astrapas with writing on a church painting at Mount Athos in northern Greece. The Protaton church painting has been considered Panselinos' best work.</p>
<p>Father Cosmas Simonopetritis is a former administrator at Mount Athos; the religious community is where the Protaton church stands. He said Sotirakoglou's and his own research “clearly prove” Panselinos' real identity.</p>
<p>“Panselinos was a real person, and (the name) was just the nickname by which Ioannis Astrapas became known,” Simonopetritis told the Associated Press (AP).</p>
<p>Constantinos Vafiadis is a professor of Byzantine art who was not involved in the research. Vafiadis said he found strong points in the nickname theory and naming Astrapas as the true artist. However, he added that it appeared more than one painter had created the art at the Protaton church.</p>
<p>“I agree with <strong>attributing</strong> part of the paintings to Ioannis Astrapas,” Vafiadis said. “But again there remains much ground for future research into that person, because other Mount Athos monuments from the same period have not yet been sufficiently published.”</p>
<p>“Panselinos” and his fellow artists at the time are linked with a rebirth in Eastern Orthodox art. Their work brought back forms and skills inherited from ancient times. Facial expressions got a deeper humanity, and greater attention was paid to proportion and depth of field in composition.</p>
<p>Simonopetritis said Astrapas was an “extremely gifted painter” with deep knowledge. He added that Astrapas mixed “the ancient, classical world with Orthodox Byzantine spirituality.”</p>
<p><strong>How they did it </strong></p>
<p>The trail started with linking Astrapas to the person who wrote a book called the Marcian Codex GR 516 from the early 1300s. The book contains artwork and is handwritten in Greek. Among the painted pictures, or illustrations, is a full moon.</p>
<p>“For me ... that was the main proof,” Simonopetritis said.</p>
<p>With a name found for the person who produced the manuscript, the next step was to compare it to the writing on the painting in the Protaton church that has been traditionally linked with “Panselinos.”</p>
<p>“Mrs. Sotirakoglou, who is a handwriting expert, filled in that blank,” Simonopetritis said.</p>
<p>But women have for more than 1,000 years been banned from entering the Mount Athos religious community.</p>
<p>“I was forced to study the Protato paintings based on photographs,” Sotirakoglou told the AP. Sotirakoglou works as a court expert who examines handwriting in criminal cases.</p>
<p>The first clue came from the Greek letter “Phi,” the English “F,” in the Marcian codex manuscript.</p>
<p>“It's a Phi that stands out, and is similar” in both the manuscript and the Protato painting, she said. “Matches also followed with other letters, T, with its proportions, which is bigger, covering the other letters and is topped with a curve, the proportions of the K.”</p>
<p>“But when the Phi was revealed, the code of the writing was broken and the job became much easier,” she added.</p>
<p>Father Cosmas said that during his duties on Mount Athos he attended services at the Protaton church every day.</p>
<p>“That's where my desire was born...to explore the mystery around the name and the identity of Panselinos,” he said, adding that he thinks the artist has now gotten “his true identity.”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Costas Kantouris and Nicholas Paphitis reported this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>nickname</strong><em> – n.</em> a usually descriptive or familiar name given instead of the one belonging to a person</p>
<p><strong>monk</strong> <em>–n.</em> a male member of a religious group in certain religions who lives in a community apart from the rest of society and does not marry or hold much property</p>
<p><strong>handwriting</strong> <em>– n.</em> writing done by hand</p>
<p><strong>attribute</strong> <em>– v.</em> to consider or reckon as made in an indicated fashion</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Report: Wealth Held by Billionaires Jumped in 2024 (2024/12/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/report-wealth-held-by-billionaires-jumped-in-2024.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The Union Bank of Switzerland (UBS) Billionaire Ambitions Report for 2024 said the total number of <strong>billionaires</strong> worldwide had risen to 2,682 from 2,544 a year earlier.</p>
<p>Their worth increased to $14 trillion from $12 trillion. In 2015, their total wealth stood at $6.3 trillion.</p>
<p>The World Bank says that the world's population was just over 8 billion, and its gross domestic product, or GDP, was about $105.4 trillion last year. GDP is a measure of all the goods and services produced in a year. This shows that a very small group of people holds about 13 percent of the world's GDP.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - SpaceX CEO Elon Musk (L) shakes hands with Japanese billionaire Yusaku Maezawa who was introduced as the first SpaceX private passenger to circle the moon, in Hawthorne, California September 17, 2018. (REUTERS/Gene Blevins)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/A8DDDFCD-BAB3-4F09-AEE9-1B1EB83017F6_cx3_cy8_cw96_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - SpaceX CEO Elon Musk (L) shakes hands with Japanese billionaire Yusaku Maezawa who was introduced as the first SpaceX private passenger to circle the moon, in Hawthorne, California September 17, 2018. (REUTERS/Gene Blevins)</span></div>
<p><strong>Self-made billionaires</strong></p>
<p>The UBS report for 2023 showed that new billionaires gained more wealth through <strong>inheritance</strong> than through <strong>entrepreneurship</strong>. But most of the year's new billionaires were self-made.</p>
<p>The 2024 report was based on a study of billionaires between June and September and wealth data on the super-rich. It showed the risk of international conflict and inflation were their main worries. The study also showed that most billionaires see North America as offering the best investment returns over the next year.</p>
<p>In the United States, the number of billionaires jumped to 835 from 751, led by industrial and tech entrepreneurs, with their total wealth climbing to $5.8 trillion from $4.6 trillion.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: 9pt;">India, the world's most populous country, saw its number of billionaires increase during the past year by over a fifth to 185. Their wealth rose by more than 40 percent to almost $906 billion, UBS said.</span></p>
<p>In Western Europe, Switzerland passed Britain to become the country with the second-highest number of billionaires after Germany, increasing its total by 10 to 85. The British total dropped by one to 82, UBS said.</p>
<p>Germany with 117 (or 8 more), France with 46 (or 12 more), Italy with 62 (or 6 more) and Spain with 27 (or 3 more), all gained billionaires. The combined wealth of France's billionaires was highest among Europeans.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Jill Robbins adapted this story for Learning English from a Reuters report. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>billionaire</strong> – <em>n</em>. a rich person who has at least a billion dollars, pounds, or other currency</p>
<p><strong>inheritance</strong> – <em>n.</em> money, property, etc., that is received from someone when that person dies</p>
<p><strong>entrepreneur</strong> – <em>n</em>. a person who starts a business and is willing to risk loss in order to make money</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Rare Birth Gives Hope to Endangered Deer (2024/12/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/rare-birth-gives-hope-to-endangered-deer.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Recently, a rare pudu was born in an Argentinian zoo. The birth has given scientists and <strong>conservationists</strong> a chance to study and collect data on the small deer.</p>
<p>Pudus are one of the smallest deer <strong>species</strong> in the world. They can grow up to 50 centimeters tall and weigh up to 12 kilograms. At birth, the white-spotted male pudu weighed just 1.21 kilograms.</p>
<p>Workers at the conservation organization Temaiken Foundation named it Lenga after a tree species in the Andean Patagonian Forest of Chile and Argentina.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A rare pudu fawn born earlier this month is seen next to its mother, at the Temaiken Foundation, in Buenos Aires, Argentina, Nov. 22, 2024. (REUTERS/Alessia Maccioni)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e83c31f7-075b-44c5-9de6-a8365eb7abb7_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A rare pudu fawn born earlier this month is seen next to its mother, at the Temaiken Foundation, in Buenos Aires, Argentina, Nov. 22, 2024. (REUTERS/Alessia Maccioni)</span></div>
<p>"It's a very <strong>enigmatic</strong> animal. It's not easy to see," said Maximiliano Krause. He is Lenga's caretaker at the nonprofit organization.</p>
<p>Krause says Lenga is spending his days exploring the park with his mother, Chalten, and father, Nicolino. Lenga is breastfeeding for the first two months until he can eat plants on his own.</p>
<p>After that, Lenga will lose his white spots and the spotty skin color that helps small deer hide from both daytime and nighttime <strong>predators</strong>. At about one year, pudus develop antlers and reach up to 10 centimeters.</p>
<p>Pudus are very elusive animals. In other words, they are hard to find and difficult to see in the wild. When chased by predators, they escape in a <strong>zig-zag</strong> manner. The small deer also face threats from wild dogs and species introduced into southern Argentina and Chile.</p>
<p>Only about 10,000 pudus remain in the wild. They are <strong>classified</strong> as near-threatened by the International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN).</p>
<p>"This pudu birth is obviously a joy for us," said Cristian Guillet. He is the director of zoological operations at the Temaiken Foundation.</p>
<p>Guillet said that Lenga will help them research and gather data that will help conservation efforts for pudus and other Patagonian deer, like the huemul.</p>
<p>"(This) offers hope of saving them from <strong>extinction</strong>," Guillet said.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Lucila Sigal and Alexander Villegas reported this story for Reuters. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>conservationist </strong><em>– n.</em><strong> </strong>a person who is in favor of conservation especially of natural resources (as forests)</p>
<p><strong>species </strong><em>– n. </em>a category of living things that ranks below a genus, is made up of related individuals able to produce fertile offspring, and is identified by a two-part scientific name</p>
<p><strong>enigmatic </strong><em>– adj. </em>of, relating to, or resembling a puzzle or enigma : mysterious</p>
<p><strong>predator </strong><em>– n.</em> an animal that obtains food mostly by killing and eating other animals</p>
<p><strong>zig-zag </strong><em>– adv. </em>one of a series of short sharp turns, angles, or alterations in a course</p>
<p><strong>classify </strong><em>– v. </em>to consider (someone or something) as belonging to a particular group : to arrange in classes that have systematic relations usually founded on common properties</p>
<p><strong>extinction </strong><em>– n. </em>the process of no longer existing : an act of extinguishing or an instance of being extinguished</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>New Study Examines Whether Venus Had Liquid Water (2024/12/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/new-study-examines-whether-venus-had-liquid-water.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A new study suggests that Venus likely never had water flowing on its surface. The research was based on data related to the chemical makeup of the planet's atmosphere.</p>
<p>Scientists have long considered whether Venus once held liquid water, even possibly large oceans. Such research was based on the fact that Venus is like our own planet in many ways. It is a rocky planet similar in structure and size to Earth and is also our closest planetary neighbor.</p>
<p>But the latest study provides evidence that Venus has likely always been the hot, extremely dry planet it remains today. Researchers from Britain's University of Cambridge led the study. It recently <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41550-024-02414-5">appeared</a> in the publication <em>Nature Astronomy</em>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This file photo, provided by NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory, shows a computer-generated 3D model of Venus' surface. (NASA/JPL/Handout via REUTERS)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/29dfc8bd-80f6-481a-a39e-d0065ce57aec_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This file photo, provided by NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory, shows a computer-generated 3D model of Venus' surface. (NASA/JPL/Handout via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>The researchers' data examinations led them to conclude that both the surface and interior of Venus remain dry. The team said the strongest evidence that Venus once had large amounts of water would be the discovery of some water inside the planet today. But the study provided no evidence of that.</p>
<p>Since water is considered an important element for supporting life, the researchers also suggest that Venus was likely never habitable, or able to support life.</p>
<p>The lead writer of the study was Tereza Constantinou, a doctoral student at the University of Cambridge's Institute of Astronomy. She told Reuters news agency, "We suggest that a habitable past would be associated with Venus' present interior being water-rich, and a dry past with Venus' present interior being dry.”</p>
<p>The researchers <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cam.ac.uk/research/news/researchers-deal-a-blow-to-theory-that-venus-once-had-liquid-water-on-its-surface">explained</a> they attempted to measure the current destruction rate of molecules in water, carbon dioxide and carbonyl sulfide in Venus' atmosphere. The state of the planet's atmosphere is linked to volcanic activity, the team said.</p>
<p>“Volcanism, through its supply of gases to the atmosphere, provides a window into the interior of rocky planets like Venus,” the researchers wrote <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cam.ac.uk/research/news/researchers-deal-a-blow-to-theory-that-venus-once-had-liquid-water-on-its-surface">in a statement</a>. “As <strong>magma</strong> rises from the <strong>mantle</strong> to the surface, it releases gases from the deeper portions of the planet.</p>
<p>Volcanic explosions, or eruptions, can provide information on the amount of water contained deep below a planet's surface, the scientists said.</p>
<p>On Earth, for example, volcanic eruptions mostly release steam, a <strong>vapor</strong> created when water gets heated. Measurements of volcanic gases on Earth have shown they release about 60 percent water vapor.</p>
<p>But the researchers said their examinations suggested volcanic gases released on Venus were less than 6 percent water vapor. This persuaded the team to conclude that the planet's interior – the source of the magma that releases volcanic gases – must be very dry.</p>
<p>The team noted that scientists have had two leading theories on the history of water on Venus. The first is that the planet had a moderate climate for billions of years, with liquid water flowing over areas of the surface. Over time, widespread volcanic activity likely led to extreme heat and dry conditions that made the water disappear.</p>
<p>The second theory imagined Venus as being very hot from the beginning, preventing liquid water from ever forming on the surface.</p>
<p>Constantinou said, “Both of those theories are based on climate models, but we wanted to take a different <strong>approach</strong> based on observations of Venus' current atmospheric chemistry.” She added that the team did not find evidence that any chemicals being removed from the atmosphere were later being restored.</p>
<p>This provides strong evidence that Venus has a very dry interior today, the scientists concluded. "The atmospheric chemistry suggests that volcanic eruptions on Venus release very little water, <strong>implying</strong> that the planet's interior...is equally dry,” Constantinou said.</p>
<p>She added that her team “would have loved to find that Venus was once a planet much closer to our own.” However, Constantinou noted the finding suggests that researchers should center their searches “on planets that are mostly likely to be able to support life – at least life as we know it.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from Reuters and the University of Cambridge. </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>magma</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> hot liquid rock found just below the surface of the Earth</p>
<p><strong>mantle </strong><em>– n.</em> a layer of something that covers a surface</p>
<p><strong>vapor</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> many small drops of liquid that form in the air</p>
<p><strong>approach </strong><em>– n. </em>the way something is done</p>
<p><strong>imply</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to communicate an idea or feeling without saying it directly</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>California Proposes Plan to Protect Its Famous Joshua Trees (2024/12/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/california-proposes-plan-to-protect-its-famous-joshua-trees.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The California Department of Fish and Wildlife has released a proposed plan to protect the state's famous Joshua trees. Environmentalists say the trees are threatened by wildfires, human development and climate change.</p>
<p>An early version of the plan calls for avoiding or reducing direct and indirect effects of <strong>overgrazing</strong>, insect-killing chemical use and <strong>off-roading</strong> activity. The plan advises moving trees when projects require their removal or could harm them. It also calls for identifying and protecting lands where the trees could survive if the climate in southern California becomes drier and hotter.</p>
<p>“In many ways, it's a good <strong>comprehensive</strong> plan of the things we need to do if the western Joshua tree is going to survive the very, very difficult <strong>decades</strong> ahead,” said Brendan Cummings. He is conservation director with the Center for Biological Diversity based in Tucson, Arizona. The nonprofit group asked the California government in 2019 to list the western Joshua tree as threatened under the state's Endangered Species Act.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A Joshua tree is silhouetted in front of the Bobcat Fire at sunset Saturday, Sept. 19, 2020, in Juniper Hills, California. (AP Photo/Marcio Jose Sanchez, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/0c078bdf-94cd-4a36-82c1-b900d89b9dec_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A Joshua tree is silhouetted in front of the Bobcat Fire at sunset Saturday, Sept. 19, 2020, in Juniper Hills, California. (AP Photo/Marcio Jose Sanchez, File)</span></div>
<p>The conservation plan is a requirement by the Western Joshua Tree Conservation Act. California lawmakers passed the act last year. It is the first law in the state to protect a species from the threats of climate change. The law also bars anyone from killing, damaging, or removing a tree without state permission.</p>
<p>The proposed plan lists ways to help identify land that should be recognized as most important for conservation. This includes large areas with Joshua trees or areas with a high density of healthy and adult trees. The plan suggests placing restrictions on areas where there is low risk of such threats as fires, invasive plants and animals, development and where <strong>pollinators</strong> and seed-spreading animals exist. It aims to identify these lands by December 2025 and place permanent restrictions on 70 percent of them by 2033.</p>
<p>The plan also calls on land <strong>managers</strong> and wildfire workers to create methods to reduce and fight wildfires that threaten the trees and lessen effects from <strong>rehabilitating</strong> burned areas. That includes protecting trees, replanting them, planting other native species, and controlling invasive ones.</p>
<p>The proposed plan says, its effectiveness and the survival of the trees will mainly depend on whether reductions can be made in the release of heat-trapping gases. Such emissions come mainly from burning coal, oil and gas.</p>
<p>Cummings said climate change could destroy most, if not all, of the areas where the trees live if the situation does not change.</p>
<p>If emissions are limited as planned, Cummings said, “we have a very good chance of saving the species if all the things outlined in this plan are carried out. And primarily that's doing what we can to protect as many of them as possible."</p>
<p>Approval from California's Fish and Game Commission is necessary for the proposed plan to go into effect.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted the story for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>over-grazing </strong><em>– n.</em> the act of permitting animals to graze (an area, such as a field) to the point of damaging vegetational cover</p>
<p><strong>off-roading</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n</em>. the activity of driving a vehicle in a place where there is no road</p>
<p><strong>comprehensive</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj</em>. covering completely or broadly</p>
<p><strong>decade</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a period of 10 years</p>
<p><strong>pollinator</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> an agent (such as an insect) that pollinates flowers</p>
<p><strong>rehabilitate </strong><em>– v. </em>to restore or bring to a condition of health or useful and constructive activity</p>
<p><strong>manager</strong> <em>– n.</em> a person who runs a business or organization</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>'Show Your Hand', other Card Idioms (2024/12/8)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/show-your-hand-other-card-idioms.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">07 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Playing cards is a popular <strong>pastime</strong> for people of all ages. Some games are easy, while others are complex. And people of <u>all walks of life</u> play cards. A set of playing cards is called a deck. A deck of cards is not costly and can be bought almost anywhere.</p>
<p>With one deck of 52 cards, you can play many different games. Some of the games include poker, blackjack, bridge, rummy, 500, snap, hearts, and crazy eights ... just to name a few.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Finance professionals learn how to play guandan, a poker-like card game, during a training session in Beijing, China, August 6, 2023. (REUTERS/Yew Lun Tian)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-ae30-08dbad65d3e9_cx17_cy17_cw82_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Finance professionals learn how to play guandan, a poker-like card game, during a training session in Beijing, China, August 6, 2023. (REUTERS/Yew Lun Tian)</span></div>
<p>The deck of cards also gives the English language many <strong>idioms</strong>. Today we will talk about a few of them.</p>
<p>To win at many card games, you must keep your cards hidden from the other players. In many games, the cards you are <strong>dealt </strong>and play with are called your “hand.” If your opponents know your hand, they can easily beat you. Some players keep their cards hidden by holding them to their chest.</p>
<p>In life, you might need to keep some parts of a plan hidden or secret for them to succeed. You might need to <u>keep your cards close to your chest</u>. This idiom means to keep your plans, <strong>intentions</strong> or methods secret.</p>
<p>However, with most card games, players must show their cards to the other players at some point, sometimes at the end of the game.</p>
<p>This gives us two similar idioms – <u>to show your hand</u> and <u>to lay your cards on the table</u>.</p>
<p>As an idiom, to <u>show your hand</u> or your cards means to tell people your plans or intentions that you had kept hidden.</p>
<p>The same is true of <u>laying your cards on the table</u>. In many card games, the players must show their cards by placing them face up on the table for everyone to see. When we put our cards on the table, we show something that we have kept hidden. These can be things like our reasons for doing something, our intentions or our opinions.</p>
<p>Now, in a game of cards, luck or chance plays an important part. You must play with the cards you are dealt. This is the case in life, too. Not everything is a choice. Sometimes we must deal with things that are out of our control. We must <u>play with the cards we are dealt</u>. We can also say <u>play the hand we are dealt</u>.</p>
<p>So, luck is part of the game. We cannot know or predict<strong> </strong>the cards we are dealt. But sometimes other players cheat. They can do this by <strong><u>stacking</u></strong><u> the deck</u>. When you <u>stack the deck</u>, you add cards to the deck that will help you win. This gives you an unfair <strong>advantage</strong>.</p>
<p>In life, we can sometimes feel that things are <u>stacked against us</u>. This means that no matter how hard we try, we still struggle. We feel as though life has <u>dealt us a bad hand,</u> and we must struggle and fight to gain anything at all.</p>
<p>For example, if the <u>deck is stacked</u> against you, the <strong><u>odds</u></strong><u> are not in your <strong>favor</strong></u>. You might have to struggle against all odds to succeed.</p>
<p>These are just a few of the idioms English gets from a deck of cards. There are many more.</p>
<p>But that's all the time we have today. Keep listening to <em>Words and Their Stories </em>to learn more!</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>_____________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>pastime </strong>–n. an activity done for enjoyment in one's free time</p>
<p><strong>idiom </strong>–n. an expression in language that has a meaning different from the words' literal meaning</p>
<p><strong>intention </strong>–n. what someone means to do but which might not be clear from what they say or do</p>
<p><strong>stack </strong>–v. to place on thing on top of another</p>
<p><strong>advantage </strong>–n. a positive or good result that is gained from an action</p>
<p><strong>odds </strong>–n. (pl.) the likelihood that something will or will not happen</p>
<p><strong>favor </strong>–n. something that happens to help or support a person</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Peruvian Women Heal Themselves with Song, Art (2024/12/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/peruvian-women-heal-themselves-with-song-art.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The 36-year-old Peruvian artist Sadith Silvano makes creations born of ancient songs.</p>
<p>Brush in hand, eyes on the cloth, the Peruvian woman paints as she sings. And through her voice, her ancestors speak.</p>
<p>“When we paint, we listen to the inspiration that comes from the music and connect to nature, to our elders,” said Silvano.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Sadith Silvano, from Paoyhan, a Shipibo-Konibo Indigenous community in the Amazon, puts on an earring at her home and workshop where she hand-paints textiles in Lima, Peru, Saturday, Oct. 19, 2024. (AP Photo/Guadalupe Pardo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/0c0d2e78-757b-4beb-8d0f-15b030e4ebda_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Sadith Silvano, from Paoyhan, a Shipibo-Konibo Indigenous community in the Amazon, puts on an earring at her home and workshop where she hand-paints textiles in Lima, Peru, Saturday, Oct. 19, 2024. (AP Photo/Guadalupe Pardo)</span></div>
<p>The artist now lives and works in Lima, Peru, where she moved 20 years ago from Paoyhan. It is a Shipibo-Konibo Indigenous community located in the Amazon.</p>
<p>“These pieces are sacred,” she added. “We bless our work with the energy of our songs.”</p>
<p>Official data says close to 33,000 Shipibo-Konibo people live in Peru. They are believed to come from the surroundings of the Uyacali river. Many moved to urban areas like Cantagallo, the Lima neighborhood where Silvano lives.</p>
<p>Hand-painted textiles like the ones she makes have slowly gained recognition. Known as “kené,” these works were declared part of the “Cultural Heritage of the Nation” by the Peruvian government in 2008.</p>
<p>Each kené is special, Shipibo craftswomen say. Every design speaks of a woman's community, her worldview and beliefs.</p>
<p>“Every design tells a story,” Silvano said while dressed in traditional clothing. “It is a way in which a Shipibo woman distinguishes herself.”</p>
<p>Paoyhan, where Silvano was born, is far from Lima. To get there requires an airplane flight and a 12-hour boat trip.</p>
<p>In her hometown, locals rarely speak languages other than Shipibo. Doors and windows there have no locks.</p>
<p>Adela Sampayo, a 48-year-old healer who was born not too far from Paoyhan, moved to Cantagallo in 2000.</p>
<p>But she says that all her skills come from the Amazon River area.</p>
<p>“Since I was a little girl, my mom treated me with traditional medicine,” said Sampayo. “She gave me plants to become stronger, to avoid getting sick, to be courageous,” she added. “That's how the energy of the plants started growing inside me.”</p>
<p>Sampayo, too, communicates her worldview through her textiles. Though she does not paint, she embroiders, and each thread tells a tale from home.</p>
<p>“Each plant has a spirit,” said the healer, pointing to the leaves embroidered in the cloth. “And medicinal plants come from God.”</p>
<p>The plants painted by Silvano also bear meaning. One of them represents pure love. Another represents a wise man. And another, a serpent.</p>
<p>“The anaconda is special for us,” Silvano said. “It's our protector, like a god that cares for us and provides food and water.”</p>
<p>In ancient times, she said, her people believed that the sun was their father, and the anacondas were their guardians. Colonization brought Catholicism and their worldview changed.</p>
<p>“Nowadays we have different religions...but we respect our other beliefs too,” Silvano said.</p>
<p>For many years, after her father took her to Lima hoping for a better future, she thought of her time in the jungle. Life in Paoyhan was not easy, but she learned to be strong at a young age.</p>
<p>“When we encounter difficult times, we overcome them with our therapy: designing, painting, singing,” Silvano said. “We have a song that is melodic and heals our soul, and another one that is inspiring and brings us joy.”</p>
<p>Few Shipibo girls are told to study or make a living of their own, Silvano said. Instead, they are taught to wait for a husband. And once married, they are taught to deal with problems, difficulties, or bad treatment.</p>
<p>“Even though we suffer, people tell us: Take it, he's the father of your children. Take it, he is your husband,” Silvano said. “But deep inside, we are wounded. So what do we do? We sing.”</p>
<p>The lesson is taught by mothers to daughters: If you are hurt at home, grab your cloth, your brush and leave. Go far away, alone, and sit. Connect with your kené and paint. And while you paint, sing.</p>
<p>“That's our healing,” Silvano said. “Through our songs, our kenés, we are free.”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Maria Teresa Hernandez reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>brush</strong> <em>– n</em>. a device with bristles typically set into a handle and used especially for painting</p>
<p><strong>inspiration </strong><em>– n.</em> a divine influence or action on a person believed to qualify him or her to receive and communicate sacred revelation</p>
<p><strong>sacred</strong> <em>– adj. </em>of or relating to religion, worthy of respect</p>
<p><strong>courageous</strong> <em>–adj.</em> showing the ability to do difficult things</p>
<p><strong>textile </strong><em>– n.</em> a woven or knit cloth</p>
<p><strong>craftswoman</strong> <em>–n.</em> a woman who is skilled in a craft</p>
<p><strong>distinguish </strong><em>– v. </em>to mark as separate or different</p>
<p><strong>embroider</strong> <em>– v.</em> to decorate with needlework</p>
<p><strong>anaconda<em> </em></strong><em>– n. </em>a large kind of constricting snake</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How the Animals Lost Their Tails by Carl Sandburg (2024/12/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/american-stories-how-the-animals-lost-their-tails-by-carl-sandburg.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p><strong>Introduction:</strong></p>
<p><em>Today's story is How the Animals Lost Their Tails and Got Them Back Traveling from Philadelphia to Medicine Hat. It appeared in the book Rootabaga Stories by Carl Sandburg, published in 1922.</em></p>
<p><em>Sandburg was a very famous American poet. He wrote Rootabaga Stories for his three daughters Margaret, Janet and Helga. The stories make liberal use of repetition and nonsense language, a fun form of word play.</em></p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e9b8d234-737f-4e19-8c46-ee5932263831_w100_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p><em>Listen closely to the language of this story about talking animals with a big problem.</em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<p>Far up in North America, near the Saskatchewan River in Winnipeg wheat country not far from the town of Moose Jaw, where nobody works unless they have to, and they nearly all have to, there is a place known as Medicine Hat.</p>
<p>There, on top of a high tower in a high chair, sits the Head Spotter of the Weather Makers.</p>
<p>When the animals lost their tails, it was because the Head Spotter got careless.</p>
<p><strong>How all the animals lost their tails</strong></p>
<p>You see, the tails of the animals were hard and dry because of a stretch of hot, dusty weather. Then, at last, came a rain. It poured down on the animals' tails and softened them.</p>
<p>But then a cold wind came and froze all the tails solid. A big wind followed and blew and blew and blew until all the animals' tails flew off their bodies.</p>
<p>It was easy for the hogs with their short tails. But it was not so easy for the blue fox, who uses his tail to run and to write secret letters in the snow.</p>
<p>It was easy for the rabbit and her little white tail. But it was hard for the yellow flongboo who lights up her home in the hollow tree with her bright tail.</p>
<p>The animals decided to choose a committee of representatives to represent them in parleyhoo to see what steps could be taken by talking to do something.</p>
<p>There were 66 representatives on the committee. They decided to call it the Committee of Sixty Six.</p>
<p>For a chairperson they picked the top flongboo. When there was a fight among the flongboo families, she was the one who would say who was right and who was wrong.</p>
<p>She was from Chappaquiddick and lived there in a horse chestnut tree between South Hadley and Northampton.</p>
<p>After her nomination and election, she brought the Committee of Sixty Six to order.</p>
<p>“It is <strong>no picnic</strong> to lose your tail and we are here for business,” she said banging the <strong>gavel</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>The blue fox's proposal</strong></p>
<p>Then a blue fox from Waco, Texas stood up and said, “Madam Chairwoman, do I have the floor?”</p>
<p>That is a way of saying, “May I speak?”</p>
<p>“I <strong>make a motion</strong>,” said the blue fox.</p>
<p>“I <strong>move</strong> that this committee get on a train at Philadelphia and ride on the train until it stops and then take another train until we get to Medicine Hat where the Head Spotter of the Weather Makers sits. There, we will ask if he will bring back our tails.”</p>
<p>The Chairwoman said, “All in favor of the motion will clean their right ears with their right paws.”</p>
<p>And all the blue foxes and yellow flongboos began cleaning their right ears with their right paws.</p>
<p>“All who oppose the motion will clean their left ears with their left paws,” said the chairwoman.</p>
<p>And all the blue foxes and yellow flongboos began cleaning their left ears with their left paws.</p>
<p>“The motion is carried both ways, it's a <strong>razzamatazz</strong>,” said the chairwoman.</p>
<p>“Once again, all in favor of the motion will stand up on their toes.”</p>
<p>And all the blue foxes and all the yellow flongboos stood up.</p>
<p>“And now,” said the chairwoman, “all who are against the motion will stand on the top of their heads, stick their hind legs up in the air, and make a noise like woof, woof.”</p>
<p>No one opposed the motion.</p>
<p>“The motion is carried,” said the chairwoman.</p>
<p>So the committee went to Philadelphia to get the train to Medicine Hat.</p>
<p>The Chairwoman asked a policeman there: “Would you be so kind as to tell us the way to the Union Depot.”</p>
<p>“It pays to be <strong>polite</strong>,” said the policeman.</p>
<p>“May I ask you again if you would kindly direct us to the Union Depot where the train is?” asked the flongboo again.</p>
<p>“Polite persons and angry persons are different kinds,” said the policeman.</p>
<p>The flongboo's eyes changed their light, and a slow fire burned from where her tail used to be.</p>
<p>She said, “Sir, I must inform you that we are The Committee of Sixty Six. We are <strong>distinguished</strong> representatives from places you do not know. This committee is going to ride to Medicine Hat with a special message and a secret <strong>errand</strong> for the Head Spotter of the Weather Makers.”</p>
<p>“I am a polite friend of all respectable people,” said the policeman touching the star on his chest.</p>
<p>“This is the first time ever in the history of the United States that a committee of sixty-six has ever visited a city in the United States,” said the flongboo.</p>
<p>“I beg to be mistaken,” finished the policeman. “The Union Depot is under that clock.” And he pointed to a big clock nearby.</p>
<p><strong>The train trip to Medicine Hat</strong></p>
<p>Over to Union Depot train station they went, all sixty-six, half foxes, half flongboos.</p>
<p>“They are speaking in some strange language from where they come from,” said one passenger.</p>
<p>“They have secrets to keep among each other, and never tell us,” said another passenger.</p>
<p>“We will find out all about it in the newspapers tomorrow,” said a third passenger.</p>
<p>Then the foxes and flongboos climbed into a special car.</p>
<p>The train left the station. It came to the Horseshoe Curve near Altoona where the tracks bend in a half circle. Then it went on toward Ohio.</p>
<p>Two baby blue foxes, the youngest on the committee, sat at the front of the car.</p>
<p>Crossing Ohio and Indiana at night the flongboos took off the top of the car. The conductor told them, “I must have an explanation.” “It is between us and the stars,” they told him.</p>
<p>The train ran on to Chicago. There were pictures in the newspapers that afternoon showing foxes and flongboos eating pink ice cream with iron <strong>axes</strong>.</p>
<p>Each blue fox and yellow flongboo got their own newspaper.</p>
<p>Crossing to the north the sky began to fill with the snow ghosts of Minnesota. Again the foxes and flongboos lifted the top off the car so they would not miss the show.</p>
<p>Some went to sleep but the two baby blue foxes stayed up watching the snow ghosts and telling snow ghost stories to each other.</p>
<p>Early in the night the first baby blue fox said to the second, “Who are the snow ghosts the ghosts of?” The second baby blue fox answered, “Snow men, snow foxes and snow fishes, everybody has a snow ghost.”</p>
<p>And that was only the beginning of their talk. They would talk until morning about where the snow ghosts go on Christmas morning and how the snow ghosts watch the New Year.</p>
<p>Somewhere between Winnipeg and Moose Jaw, they stopped the train and all ran out in the snow. The white moon was shining down a valley of birch trees.</p>
<p>At last they came to Medicine Hat, near the Saskatchewan River in Winnipeg wheat country not far from the town of Moose Jaw, where nobody works unless they have to, and they nearly all have to.</p>
<p>There they ran to the place where the Head Spotter of the Weather Makers sits in a high chair on a high tower watching the weather.</p>
<p>“Let loose another big wind to blow back our tails, let loose a big freeze to freeze our tails back on, and let us get back our lost tails,” they said to the Head Spotter.</p>
<p>Which was just what he did, giving them exactly what they wanted, so they all went back home satisfied.</p>
<p><em>Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted this public domain story by Carl Sandburg for VOA Learning English.</em></p><p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>no picnic </strong><em>– idiom </em>a difficult thing to do or an unpleasant experience</p>
<p><strong>gavel</strong> <em>– n.</em> a small hammer that is used for getting attention in a court or a formal meeting of officials or lawmakers</p>
<p><strong>have the floor </strong>– <em>idiom</em> have the right to speak at a public meeting</p>
<p><strong>make a motion </strong>– <em>idiom</em> to formally propose something in a debate or formal proceedings</p>
<p><strong>move </strong>– <em>v</em>. (formal) to propose that something be done</p>
<p><strong>razzamatazz </strong>– <em>n</em>. noisy and excited activity meant to attract attention</p>
<p><strong>hind legs </strong>– n<em>. (pl.)</em> the two back legs of a four-legged animal</p>
<p><strong>polite </strong>– <em>adj.</em> showing good manners and respect for others</p>
<p><strong>distinguished </strong>– <em>adj.</em> known by many people for some special quality or something done in the past</p>
<p><strong>errand </strong>– <em>n</em>. a short trip aimed at getting something done</p>
<p><strong>ax</strong> - <em>n.</em> a tool used for cutting wood</p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<p><em>We have a new comment system. Here is how it works: </em></p>
<ol>
<li><em>Write your comment in the box.</em></li>
<li><em>Under the box, you can see four images for social media accounts. They are for Disqus, Facebook, Twitter and Google.</em></li>
<li><em>Click on one image and a box appears. Enter the login for your social media account. Or you may create one on the Disqus system. It is the blue circle with “D” on it. It is free.</em></li></ol>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Notes about ‘Being’ (2024/12/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/notes-about-being.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Tayyab in Pakistan about a form of the verb “be” in English.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/499c6236-13c1-4ee9-90c9-d6b651dac57c_w268_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>I am always confused when it comes to the usage of “being.”</p>
<p>Thank you,</p>
<p>Tayyab</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Tayyab.</p>
<p>Let's start by considering a basic way we use the <strong>verb</strong> “be” in English. We commonly use this verb to link, or join, a subject with its description. The description will often be a noun or an <strong>adjective</strong>. The following two examples show this:</p>
<p><em>That man is a farmer.</em></p>
<p><em>That man is rich. </em></p>
<p>Expanding on this use of the verb “be,” we can call a description of how a person feels and experiences his or her life as a “state of being.” A state of being can last for a short or a long time. However, a state of being is longer than a momentary feeling. The following examples show this usage:</p>
<p><em>In retirement, her <u>state of being</u> became more relaxed.</em></p>
<p><em>His <u>state of being</u> has not been good in recent months. </em></p>
<p>We can also use the word “being” to begin a description. This can help us describe something or someone in one sentence instead of two. For example, we could use two sentences to describe a man who does not speak very much with other people:</p>
<p><em>Mr. Jones was someone who spoke very little. He sat quietly while others did the talking</em>.</p>
<p>But if we use the word “being,” we can express this idea in one sentence, as in the following example:</p>
<p><em><u>Being a man of few words</u></em><em>, Mr. Jones sat quietly while others did the talking. </em></p>
<p>Here is another example of changing a description from two sentences to one sentence:</p>
<p><em>Manut was very tall. That is why he decided to play basketball instead of football. </em></p>
<p><em><u>Being very tall</u></em><em>, Manut decided to play basketball instead of football. </em></p>
<p>We can also use the word “being,” combined with the noun or adjective that follows it, as the subject of a sentence. Consider the following examples:</p>
<p><em><u>Being a parent</u></em><em> has helped me better understand my own parents. </em></p>
<p><em><u>Being open to criticism</u></em><em> will help you improve your work. </em></p>
<p>In these examples, the phrases “being a parent” and “being open to criticism” are the subjects of the sentences.</p>
<p>Lastly, we can use the word “being” as a noun to describe a highly intelligent form of life. Humans are beings, and somewhere in the universe, other intelligent beings might exist.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? We'd like to hear from you. Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please include where you are from in your email, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>verb </strong><em>–n.</em> a word that describes action or existence</p>
<p><strong>adjective </strong><em>–n.</em> a word that gives additional information about or modifies a noun</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Vienna Sausage Stand Gets UNESCO Recognition (2024/12/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/vienna-sausage-stand-gets-unesco-recognition.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">05 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A popular kind of sausage stand in Vienna, Austria has been recognized by the United Nations for its cultural value.</p>
<p>The street stands – called “Würstelstands” in German – are a famous part of the Austrian capital's history. In addition to selling food, they are known for being a place where many different kinds of people can come together to eat and spend social time.</p>
<p>UNESCO is the United Nations' Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization. It seeks to recognize and help save cultural treasures and traditions around the world.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="Customers line up at a traditional sausage stand (Wuerstelstand), which are named as intangible cultural heritage by the Austrian UNESCO Commission, in Vienna, Austria, Thursday, Nov. 28, 2024. (AP Photo/Heinz-Peter Bader)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/7bf267af-b0e8-43c0-a48d-30d528a0b887_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">Customers line up at a traditional sausage stand (Wuerstelstand), which are named as intangible cultural heritage by the Austrian UNESCO Commission, in Vienna, Austria, Thursday, Nov. 28, 2024. (AP Photo/Heinz-Peter Bader)</span></div>
<p>Vienna's Würstelstands were recently added to a list of the country's “<strong>intangible</strong> cultural <strong>heritage</strong>.” The Austrian UNESCO Commission oversees the list.</p>
<p>Among other things on the list are Vienna's traditional wine establishments – called “Heurigen” – which were recognized in 2019. In addition, the city's famous coffee house culture was honored in 2011.</p>
<p>The Associated Press reports the history of Würstelstands goes back generations. And they are known for much more than the tasty sausages they serve. They have been bringing people of many different backgrounds together for many years. The stands have also developed some of their own terms.</p>
<p>These include the “Haasse,” a special kind of boiled sausage. Another unusual stand offering is known as the “Kasekrainer” – a smoked creation filled with cheese. And there is “Oaschpfeiferl,” a spicy peperoni version, as well as the <strong>pickled</strong> “Krokodü.”</p>
<p>Josef Bitzinger runs the Bitzinger Würstelstand. He told the AP that sausage stands have a long history in Vienna." His stand enjoys a favorable spot, next to the city's Albertina museum and just behind the Vienna State Opera.</p>
<p>“<strong>Originally</strong> it was just a bucket with hot water in which the sausages used to swim," Bitzinger said. He added that the stands began with small vehicles pulled by dogs or horses. Later, they were transported by cars or big trucks.</p>
<p>The tradition of Würstelstand goes back to the pre-World War I days of the Austro-Hungarian Empire. At that time, former soldiers set up movable cooking shops to make a living.</p>
<p>The city's longest-serving stand in a fixed spot is Würstelstand Leo. It has been serving up sausages since 1928. The stands started to develop quickly in 1969, when the government decided to begin approving fixed stands.</p>
<p>Vienna's mayor, Michael Ludwig, said he thinks the UNESCO recognition “honors the tradition, the <strong>hospitality</strong> and the <strong>diversity</strong> of our city.” He added that the stands remain a big part of the city's culture.</p>
<p>Bitzinger said he and other owners had long campaigned for the UNESCO recognition. “The special thing about it is that it's a form of <strong>gastronomy</strong> everybody can <strong>afford</strong>."</p>
<p>Bitzinger added, "Here the general director and, during the opera ball, a <strong>celebrity</strong> stands next to a worker and the street sweeper who just finished cleaning the street. That unites people.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>intangible</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj.</em> a quality that exists but is difficult to describe or prove</p>
<p><strong>pickled </strong><em>– adj.</em> a process by which food is put into vinegar or salt water and stored for a long time</p>
<p><strong>heritage</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> the buildings, paintings, customers, etc. that have existed for a long time and are important in a culture or society</p>
<p><strong>original </strong><em>– adj.</em> existing since the beginning</p>
<p><strong>hospitality </strong><em>– n.</em> the foods, drinks and entertainment provided by or organization or business</p>
<p><strong>diversity </strong><em>– n.</em> the fact that there are many different kinds of things or people included in something</p>
<p><strong>gastronomy</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> the art and knowledge used in preparing and eating good food</p>
<p><strong>afford </strong><em>– v.</em> able to pay for something</p>
<p><strong>celebrity</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a famous person</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>People on Island Near Singapore Face Uncertain Future (2024/12/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/people-on-island-near-singapore-face-uncertain-future.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A short boat ride from the wealthy city-state of Singapore is something rare – a small, quiet island.</p>
<p>People living on Pulau Ubin still talk about the arrival of solar power 11 years ago. They call it a “<strong>miracle</strong>.”</p>
<p>Although the electricity was expensive, Chu Yok Choon said he loved the <strong>convenience</strong>. He could just press a button, and a pump would send water to his home from the village well. Until 2013, Chu had to carry water from the well by hand and use <strong>generators</strong> to provide electricity.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A visitor leaves Changi ferry terminal on a boat to visit Singapore's Pulau Ubin island, November 1, 2024. (REUTERS/Edgar Su)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/bba78e9f-d4cf-4877-b560-5863da0765a0_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A visitor leaves Changi ferry terminal on a boat to visit Singapore's Pulau Ubin island, November 1, 2024. (REUTERS/Edgar Su)</span></div>
<p>Chu is one of 30 people living on Pulau Ubin. The island measures only 10 square kilometers. He spoke to Reuters recently and compared life on the island to life in Singapore, or as he calls it, the mainland.</p>
<p>"Life on the mainland doesn't feel natural," said the 79-year-old. "Life here is quieter."</p>
<p>Pulau Ubin includes forest areas and wetlands. The wetlands were once under threat from development until the plans were postponed.</p>
<p>The island offers visitors walks along thick greenery and lakes that were formed from rock <strong>quarries</strong>. They can ride bicycles on roads free of vehicles and eat seafood meals by the water's edge.</p>
<p>For those living in Singapore, the island is an escape. It can be reached in about 10 minutes by ferry. But for those who live on the island, those ferry rides can be inconvenient. Trips to the mainland to buy food and other necessities can be delayed.</p>
<p>Also, ferries can be costly. For visits to the city, Chu said he would have to wait until the ferry filled up with 12 passengers. Each person pays $3. This cost is similar to Singapore's public transportation. But if he is in a hurry, he would have to pay $36 for the whole boat.</p>
<p>Still, the residents stay. They say they are enjoying a life different from the busy, <strong>stressful </strong>conditions in the city.</p>
<p>"The energy is so <strong>fantastic</strong>," said 54-year-old Koh Bee Choo. She lives in a house on top of wooden supports that extends out over the water.</p>
<p>"I go for morning walks and I <strong>absorb</strong> the energy in the jungle," added Koh. She lived in Singapore for nearly five years but returned to the island to run a bicycle rental shop.</p>
<p>While the older generation enjoys island life, their children have moved to the city after going there to attend school.</p>
<p>This has left an aging population. The island's youngest residents are in their 50s. <strong>Conservation</strong> experts worry about the island's future. No one is permitted to move to the island from the city. In 2001, the government said the island was safe from changes until changes are required for development.</p>
<p>At the height of its popularity, almost 4,000 people lived on the island. They worked in granite quarries and on farms. But the largest quarry closed in 1970. Then, many people moved to the city where a policy to develop industry grew the economy and covered a once-struggling nation in new developments, roads and factories.</p>
<p><strong>A disappearing way of life</strong></p>
<p>Each June for the past nine years, Singaporean officials have celebrated "Ubin Day." The goal is to help people value and love the island's heritage and ecosystem, the National Parks Board says on its website.</p>
<p>Games and enrichment <strong>booths </strong>mark the celebration. So do plans for the island's future.</p>
<p>In 1991, the government stopped a plan to extend the subway to the island. Now there are talks about saving the island for future generations. But there will come a day when no one will live there anymore.</p>
<p>"The old people have died off, one by one...,” said Chu. He told Reuters that young people do not want to stay.</p>
<p>Koh said she hoped officials would let more people stay in <strong>guesthouses</strong>. "Not the high-end ones but the kampung-type," she added, using the Malay term for a village.</p>
<p>Lim Csye See is a 69-year-old who runs a bicycle rental shop. Lim said he did not want the island to become like Sentosa, Singapore's <strong>theme park</strong> island which is crowded with costly hotels and homes.</p>
<p>"If this place becomes like Sentosa, then that's the end," said Lim.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Xinghui Kok reported this story for Reuters. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>miracle </strong>–n. a wondrous or amazing event</p>
<p><strong>convenience </strong>–n. a quality or situation in which things are easy and do not involve hard work</p>
<p><strong>generator </strong>–n. a machine that produces electricity usually from burning fuel</p>
<p><strong>quarry </strong>–n. an open place where rock is cut to use for building purposes</p>
<p><strong>stressful </strong>–adj. something that causes tension and worry</p>
<p><strong>fantastic </strong>–adj. wonderful or especially good</p>
<p><strong>absorb </strong>–v. to take in</p>
<p><strong>conservation </strong>–n. marked by a desire to save maintain and save something for the future</p>
<p><strong>guesthouse </strong>–n. a place where visitors can stay, usually for a modest price and with modest rooms and accommodations</p>
<p><strong>theme park</strong> –n. a place with many mechanical rides and exciting events that are meant to entertain people</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>As Space Traffic Grows, UN Calls for More International Cooperation (2024/12/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/as-space-traffic-grows-un-calls-for-more-international-cooperation.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>As the amount of space traffic continues to grow, the United Nations is calling for increased international cooperation to improve safety.</p>
<p>Continued deployment of satellites and sharp increases in space <strong>debris</strong> over the years have resulted in the crowding of low Earth orbit. Space experts and industry leaders say this has created safety risks that will worsen if the problem is not dealt with.</p>
<p>A U.N. gathering of experts in October called for more sharing of information about orbital space objects, as well as creation of an international process to follow and <strong>manage</strong> them. The meeting was organized by the U.N.'s Office for Outer Space Affairs.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This illustration provided by NASA depicts the non-operating RHESSI (Reuven Ramaty High Energy Solar Spectroscopic Imager) solar observation satellite.(NASA via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/da396372-a847-4c24-b021-e2060a754541_cx0_cy12_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This illustration provided by NASA depicts the non-operating RHESSI (Reuven Ramaty High Energy Solar Spectroscopic Imager) solar observation satellite.(NASA via AP)</span></div>
<p>Data from the American-based company Slingshot Aerospace suggests there are more than 14,000 satellites around the world in low Earth orbit. That number includes about 3,500 satellites that are currently inactive, Reuters news agency reports.</p>
<p>In addition, there are about 120 million pieces of orbital debris left over from spacecraft launches, crashes or other causes. Only a few thousand of those are large enough to follow, or track.</p>
<p>"There's no time to lose on space traffic <strong>coordination</strong>,” the director of the U.N.'s Office for Outer Space Affairs, Aarti Holla-Maini, told Reuters. She added, “With so many objects being launched into space, we have to do everything we can to ensure space safety, and that means <strong>facilitating </strong>the sharing of information between operators.”</p>
<p>Holla-Maini explained that such coordination should involve both public and private organizations. The goal is to take steps to avoid crashes between space objects orbiting in low Earth orbit. She added that this area of space must remain safe to prevent costly difficulties to technologies that drive worldwide communication, <strong>navigation</strong> and scientific exploration.</p>
<p>Currently, there is no centralized system to help prevent such problems. It has also been difficult for organizations to agree on a set of guidelines aimed at improving safety in low Earth orbit. While some countries are willing to share data, others object because of security or privacy concerns.</p>
<p>There have been several examples of these issues over the past year. A Chinese launcher rocket exploded in August, creating thousands of pieces of debris in low Earth orbit. In June, an unused Russian satellite exploded, releasing thousands of metal pieces. That incident forced astronauts on the International Space Station to briefly take shelter.</p>
<p>Low Earth orbit is the most crowded area of space. This is because it offers a balance between cost and <strong>proximity</strong>, making it a popular target for the quickly growing private space industry.</p>
<p>It is estimated that many more satellites – tens of thousands more – will enter low-Earth orbit in the coming years. One prediction by Canada-based space tracking company NorthStar Earth &amp; Space suggests the possible financial risk of space object collisions is likely to reach $556 million over five years.</p>
<p>NorthStar's chief executive, Stewart Bain, told Reuters the situation had reached "a critical point” for establishing rules to cover space objects in low Earth orbit. Bain noted that SpaceX's Starlink is launching thousands of satellites per year and China and others are preparing to follow. Such expansion could threaten the load <strong>capacity </strong>of objects in low Earth orbit, he said.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Reuters reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>debris</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> broken pieces of something</p>
<p><strong>manage </strong><em>– v.</em> to deal with something</p>
<p><strong>coordinate</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to organize all the different parts of something</p>
<p><strong>facilitate </strong><em>– v.</em> to make something possible or easier</p>
<p><strong>navigate</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to find directions by using maps or other equipment</p>
<p><strong>proximity </strong><em>– n.</em> how near one thing is to another, or the fact of being near something</p>
<p><strong>capacity</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> the largest amount or number something can hol</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Five Things to Know about Notre Dame Cathedral (2024/12/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/five-things-to-know-about-notre-dame-cathedral.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Notre Dame Cathedral in the French capital of Paris is set to reopen to the public Sunday after a five-year-long rebuilding project. The Cathedral had been badly damaged in a fire in 2019.</p>
<p>The Roman Catholic religious center is considered a jewel of Gothic building design, a <strong>symbol</strong> of Paris and is a popular site to visit.</p>
<p>The cathedral took 182 years to build between the 12th and 14th centuries. It holds some surprising stories. Here are five special things to know about this famous Parisian site:</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="French President Emmanuel Macron, center left, and his wife Brigitte Macron, third right, visit the restored interiors of Notre-Dame Cathedral, Friday, Nov.29, 2024 in Paris. (Christophe Petit Tesson, Pool via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/47d79232-3e69-4e7f-a599-2bcc234ad808_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">French President Emmanuel Macron, center left, and his wife Brigitte Macron, third right, visit the restored interiors of Notre-Dame Cathedral, Friday, Nov.29, 2024 in Paris. (Christophe Petit Tesson, Pool via AP)</span></div>
<p><strong>The cathedral is considered France's geographic center. </strong></p>
<p>In front of the cathedral, a metal and stone marker in the road describes the place as the "starting point of the roads of France.'' This sign marks the starting point for measuring distances between Paris and other cities across the country.</p>
<p>The marker was placed in 1924, but the idea of the cathedral as the center of the nation dates to 1769. King Louis XV thought there should be a central site for France's growing system of roads. That idea tied the nation's <strong>geography</strong> to its heart in Paris.</p>
<p><strong>Its famous statues were added in the 19th century</strong></p>
<p>Those frightening stone statues on Notre Dame might seem ancient, but not all of them are what they appear. The <strong>gargoyles</strong> are <strong>monster</strong>-shaped elements used to direct rainwater away from the building. They have been around since the time of the cathedral's <strong>construction</strong>. But the monster-like creatures often seen in <strong>photos</strong> and movies are <strong>chimera</strong>, and they are much newer.</p>
<p>In 1841, the French government asked the architects Eugène Viollet-le-Duc and Jean-Baptiste Lassus to repair the then-collapsing building. Viollet-le-Duc added these frightening-looking statues to make the cathedral seem more mysterious. He drew ideas for the chimera from Victor Hugo's famous book <em>The Hunchback of Notre Dame.</em></p>
<p>How to tell them apart? Gargoyles <strong>resemble horizontal spikes</strong> coming out of the<strong> facade</strong> and have <strong>spouts </strong>to permit rainwater to flow out.</p>
<p><strong>During the French Revolution, protesters changed Notre Dame.</strong></p>
<p>During the French Revolution, there were protests of religious centers.</p>
<p>In 1793, revolutionaries took away the cathedral's religious symbols and renamed it "Notre-Dame de la Raison," or, in English, “Our Lady of Reason.”</p>
<p>During that time, the cathedral held events celebrating science and new ideas and, for a short time, it was even used to store the alcoholic drink called wine.</p>
<p>Religious services started again in 1795 under the rule of Napoleon I.</p>
<p><strong>Statues without heads were found and repaired.</strong></p>
<p>In 1792, revolutionaries also cut the heads off 28 statues from the front of Notre Dame, thinking the statues were of French <strong>royalty</strong>. They were really representations of ancient kings of Judah, from stories in the Bible, the Christian holy book.</p>
<p>The heads were thought lost forever.</p>
<p>But in 1977, workers working in a <strong>courtyard</strong> in Paris uncovered hundreds of pieces of stone sculptures. Experts confirmed they were the missing heads of Notre Dame's kings of Judah statues.</p>
<p>Today, 22 of the heads have been repaired and are shown at the Cluny Museum in Paris.</p>
<p><strong>The 2019 fire exposed a worldwide lack of outdoor lead pollution guidelines.</strong></p>
<p>The 2019 fire that almost destroyed Notre Dame caused a serious health risk. When the<strong> flames</strong> melted the top of the building, large amounts of harmful lead dust were released into the air and came down across Paris.</p>
<p>Officials found there were no rules to measure the danger of outdoor lead dust. This was not just a Paris issue — major cities like London and Rome, and even the World Health Organization — do not have guidelines for outdoor lead pollution.</p>
<p>The Notre Dame fire forced officials to take a closer look at their safety standards. It took four months for the city to complete an extensive cleaning of the city's streets even as visitors and the citizens of Paris walked around the cathedral every day.</p>
<p>Now that you know these five things, you can enjoy seeing the photos of the new Notre Dame when it opens to the public.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p>Tom Nouvian<em> reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>symbol</strong> –<em> n</em>. an action, object, event, etc., that expresses or represents a particular idea or quality</p>
<p><strong>gargoyle </strong>– <em>n</em>. a strange or ugly human or animal figure that sticks out from the roof of a building (such as a church) and is used to cause rainwater to flow away from the sides of a building.</p>
<p><strong>chimera</strong> – <em>n</em>. a monster from Greek mythology that breathes fire and has a lion's head, a goat's body, and a snake's tail</p>
<p><strong>resemble </strong>– <em>v</em>. to look or be like</p>
<p><strong>horizontal </strong>– <em>adj</em>. positioned from side to side rather than up and down; parallel to the ground</p>
<p><strong>spike</strong> – <em>n</em>. a long, thin rod that ends in a point and is often made of metal</p>
<p><strong>fa<i></i>231;ade</strong> – <em>n.</em> the front of a building</p>
<p><strong>spout</strong> –<em> n</em>. a tube, pipe, or hole out of which a liquid flows</p>
<p><strong>royalty </strong>–<em> n.</em> members of a royal family</p>
<p><strong>courtyard</strong> –<em> n</em>. an open space that is surrounded completely or partly by a building or group of buildings</p>
<p><strong>flame</strong> – <em>n</em>. the hot, glowing gas that can be seen when a fire is burning</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What to Know about South Korea’s Short Period of Martial Law (2024/12/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/what-to-know-about-south-korea-s-short-period-of-martial-law.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>South Korea's parliament moved to <strong>impeach</strong> President Yoon Suk Yeol after he declared <strong>martial law</strong> and sent troops into the streets on Tuesday night.</p>
<p>For several hours, armed forces with helicopters and <strong>armored</strong> vehicles surrounded the parliament. Lawmakers had to climb walls to get into the building and used <strong>fire extinguishers</strong> to hold off the troops.</p>
<p>The lawmakers who were able to reenter the building rejected Yoon's martial law declaration with a 190-0 vote. Eighteen lawmakers from Yoon's party also voted against the declaration. The vote forced Yoon to lift martial law about six hours after it began.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Members of main opposition Democratic Party stage a rally against South Korean President Yoon Suk Yeol at the National Assembly in Seoul, South Korea, Wednesday, Dec. 4, 2024. (AP Photo/Ahn Young-joon)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/9d8822a1-59c8-4cd9-a66c-e56ccadcf44a_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Members of main opposition Democratic Party stage a rally against South Korean President Yoon Suk Yeol at the National Assembly in Seoul, South Korea, Wednesday, Dec. 4, 2024. (AP Photo/Ahn Young-joon)</span></div>
<p>Opposition parties then began the process of impeachment.</p>
<p>Impeachment is a way for lawmakers to charge a public official with a crime while they are in office. Impeaching Yoon requires the support of two-thirds of the National Assembly and at least six of the nine Constitutional Court justices. The liberal opposition Democratic Party holds a majority in the 300-seat parliament and has called for Yoon's resignation.</p>
<p>A vote on the impeachment motion could be held as early as Friday, Democratic Party lawmaker Kim Yong-min said.</p>
<p><strong>Yoon said there was a plan to rebel </strong></p>
<p>Yoon ordered martial law without warning in a speech late Tuesday. He promised to remove "anti-state" forces he said were planning to rebel. He accused the main opposition parties of supporting North Korea.</p>
<p>Yoon gave no direct evidence when he pointed to North Korea as a threatening force. Yoon has long held that a hard line is the only way to stop the North from following through on its nuclear threats against the South.</p>
<p>In the late 1980s, several South Korean strongmen spoke of the threat from the North when struggling to control protesters and political opponents in the South.</p>
<p>As president, Yoon has struggled to get his proposals through the opposition-controlled parliament. At the same time, Yoon and his wife have faced charges of corruption.</p>
<p><strong>What is martial law?</strong></p>
<p>South Korea's constitution gives the president power to use the military to keep order in "wartime, war-like situations or other comparable national emergency states.” That can include suspending civil rights and temporarily limiting the powers of the courts and government agencies.</p>
<p>But it also gives the National Assembly power to lift the declaration with a majority vote.</p>
<p>Some experts say the way Yoon declared martial law went far beyond his lawful powers. The constitution does not permit a president to use the military to suspend parliament. And many question whether the country really faces a situation comparable to war.</p>
<p>The opposition said Yoon's actions were “illegal and unconstitutional.” The sudden declaration was also opposed by the leader of Yoon's own conservative party. Han Dong-hoon called the decision wrong and promised to "stop it with the people."</p>
<p>South Korea became a democracy only in the late 1980s, and military intervention in civilian affairs is still a sensitive subject. South Koreans were in shock with the actions. And many expressed surprise and worry on social media over Yoon's announcement.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Foster Klug reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>impeach</strong> – <em>v</em>. to charge (a public official) with a crime done while in office</p>
<p><strong>martial law </strong>– <em>n</em>. control of an area by military forces rather than by the police</p>
<p><strong>armored</strong> – <em>adj</em>. covered in flat pieces of metal to protect against attack</p>
<p><strong>fire extinguisher</strong> – <em>n</em>. a metal container filled with chemicals that is used to put out a fire</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Tips for Better Writing (2024/12/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/tips-for-better-writing.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By VOA</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the Education Report.</p>
<p>Today we continue our series of expert suggestions for academic writing. Our guest is Jennifer Ahern-Dodson, assistant professor of the Practice in Writing Studies at Duke University in North Carolina.</p>
<p>Ms. Ahern-Dodson starts a <strong>conversation </strong>with both students and professors planning to write a paper or essay. She asks about their earlier writing <strong>experiences.</strong> Were they <strong>negative or positive</strong>?</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Students at the University of Texas-Southmost College work on a writing assignment in an English as a Second Language class in 2006. (AP Photo/Brad Doherty)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/ffa53382-773c-42f8-be66-ab08da38659e_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Students at the University of Texas-Southmost College work on a writing assignment in an English as a Second Language class in 2006. (AP Photo/Brad Doherty)</span></div>
<p>She advises that you are not alone if you have had problems with your writing. She says everyone struggles with writing.</p>
<p>“Writing is hard. All writers struggle at some point. And even if writing has come easily for you, at some point in your work as a student, that eventually you're going to <strong>hit a roadblock</strong>. And so part of what I like to get folks thinking about is -- besides writing's hard for everybody – is to really take a moment to think about their past writing experiences. And when the writing is going well, what was happening? When the writing wasn't going well, what was happening?”</p>
<p>She says most people's negative writing experiences happened because a very specific <strong>formula </strong>is required for a paper including an exact length.</p>
<p>“And so they primarily focus on, and worry about, what the final product has to look like, like how many pages for a research essay? Or if it is in the second or third language, you know, punctuation and grammar, like whether it gets communicated in the right language.</p>
<p>“And so focusing on the end makes it really hard to get started.”</p>
<p>Another problem can arise when the need to do well on a paper is extremely important.</p>
<p>“...like a timed essay exam, or a college application essay, or a research paper that is at the end of the semester, and it's tied to the entire grade for the class. So worrying about what will happen if they don't do well – get bad grades, don't get into college -- creates, of course, significant anxiety<strong>.</strong> And that can make it harder to get the writing done.”</p>
<p>Then she and the people she's helping move to more <strong>positive</strong> projects. She says usually when writing comes easily, the writers feel they have something important to say.</p>
<p>The teacher advises asking yourself questions. What personal understanding of the subject can you bring to your paper? Why is this subject important? For whom is it meaningful? Who will be reading it?</p>
<p>“...Think about who your<strong> audience</strong> is, and what it is that you really want to say to them. And what that can do is help you switch from the final product and what it can look like (to) really more on what you have to offer, your particular <strong>perspective.” </strong></p>
<p>She says that is an important change for all writers.</p>
<p>And that's the VOA Learning English Education Report. Coming soon: Jennifer Ahern-Dodson talks about doing research, sitting down to write and sharing your writing with others.</p>
<p>I'm Jeri Watson.</p>
<p>__________________________________________________<strong> </strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in this Story</h2>
<p><strong>conversation - </strong><em>n.</em> an informal talk involving two people or a group of people</p>
<p><strong>experiences - </strong><em>n.</em> the processes of doing and seeing things and having things happen to you</p>
<p><strong>negative - </strong><em>adj. </em> unpleasant, unproductive</p>
<p><strong>positive</strong><em> - n. </em>pleasant, productive</p>
<p><strong>hit a roadblock</strong><em> - idiom, </em>encountering a situation that blocks one's progress</p>
<p><strong>audience - </strong><em>n.</em> the people who watch, read, or listen to something</p>
<p><strong>perspective </strong>- <em>n.</em> the way you view something; point of view</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>South Korean Man Guilty of Gaining Weight to Avoid Military Service (2024/12/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/south-korean-man-guilty-of-gaining-weight-to-avoid-military-service.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A South Korean court has found a man guilty of purposefully gaining weight to avoid completing required service in the country's military.</p>
<p>Seoul's Eastern District Court sentenced the 26-year-old man to one year in prison for violating the country's military service act. The Associated Press reports that the court suspended the sentence for two years. The court said the man did not appeal the November 13 ruling against him.</p>
<p>The court said the man had gained more than 20 kilograms in an effort to get released from a government requirement to serve in the military.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file photo, South Korean army soldiers carry out an anti-terror drill as part of the Ulchi Taeguk exercise at a park in Seoul, South Korea, May 27, 2019. (AP Photo/Ahn Young-joon, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/c8a2881a-9139-4638-a725-50ad478100fb_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this file photo, South Korean army soldiers carry out an anti-terror drill as part of the Ulchi Taeguk exercise at a park in Seoul, South Korea, May 27, 2019. (AP Photo/Ahn Young-joon, File)</span></div>
<p>South Korea requires all able-bodied men to serve in the military for 18-21 months. However, some individuals with health issues can instead perform service in non-military positions. Such service can be carried out at welfare centers or at other approved places within communities.</p>
<p>People with serious health problems are not required to serve in the military at all.</p>
<p>A health examination in 2017 found the man was physically able to become an active-duty soldier while weighing 83 kilograms. But the court said the man received advice that he could get permission to serve a non-military, social service position if he was overweight. This led him to start gaining weight.</p>
<p>The court said that in three physical exams carried out in 2022 and 2023, the man weighed 102-105 kilograms, a weight that made him fit for social service.</p>
<p>The AP reported it was not clear how the crime was discovered nor if the man began his military duty before he was tried. The court said only that he had promised to meet his military service requirement.</p>
<p>South Korea operates a <strong>compulsory</strong> military service system to deal with<strong> </strong>possible military threats from North Korea. But the policy is widely debated in the country. Some critics of the system point to the fact that requiring military service forces young men to suspend their studies or professional careers.</p>
<p>South Korea's Military Manpower Administration is responsible for operating the country's compulsory military service system. It says that each year, about 50-60 cases of <strong>dodging</strong> military duties have been reported.</p>
<p>The organization notes the most common ways to avoid military duties are to gain or lose large amounts of weight or to not complete necessary medical treatments before physical exams.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>compulsory</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj.</em> an official requirement to do something</p>
<p><strong>dodge </strong><em>– v.</em> to avoid something, often in a dishonest way</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Microsoft’s AI ‘Agents’ Aim to Take over Many Human Duties (2024/12/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/microsoft-s-ai-agents-aim-to-take-over-many-human-duties.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Microsoft is expanding its artificial intelligence (AI) tool offerings to include “personal <strong>agents</strong>” which are designed to take over different human processes.</p>
<p>The American software company said the new offerings are designed to help users complete certain business activities with little or no human involvement. The agents are expected to be offered to some users starting in the coming weeks. A full release is expected sometime next year.</p>
<p>Microsoft has said its agents are designed to expand on so-called chatbots. A chatbot is an AI tool that can work by itself to produce human-level writing or discussion. Such systems – also known as generative AI – can also produce images and videos based on short text descriptions.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Microsoft CEO Satya Nadella introduces the Azure Boost DPU at the company's Ignite conference Tuesday, Nov. 19, 2024, in Chicago. (AP Photo/Charles Rex Arbogast)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/7e2f7f13-2575-43ff-b39d-83e1ff5bd902_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Microsoft CEO Satya Nadella introduces the Azure Boost DPU at the company's Ignite conference Tuesday, Nov. 19, 2024, in Chicago. (AP Photo/Charles Rex Arbogast)</span></div>
<p>While chatbots perform some functions on their own, they also depend heavily on humans to operate and guide them. The idea behind AI agents is to give them the ability to take over whole business processes with little or no guidance from people.</p>
<p>In a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2024/10/21/new-autonomous-agents-scale-your-team-like-never-before/">statement</a> last month, Microsoft said it was preparing for a world where every organization would have a collection of AI agents to perform different business activities.</p>
<p>In <a class="wsw__a" href="https://news.microsoft.com/source/features/ai/ai-agents-what-they-are-and-how-theyll-change-the-way-we-work/">another statement</a> issued last week, the company said the agents being developed are designed to “operate around the clock” to ease the workload of human workers. Examples of agent duties include processing <strong>customer</strong> orders or returns and examining shipping records to prevent errors.</p>
<p>Microsoft has moved quickly to offer AI technologies to everyday users of its business software products. The methods are largely based on models built by AI developer OpenAI, creator of the ChatGPT chatbot. Microsoft has invested about $13 billion in OpenAI.</p>
<p>Microsoft's Chief Marketing Officer, Jared Spataro, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2024/10/21/new-autonomous-agents-scale-your-team-like-never-before/">said</a> the public should “think of agents as the new apps for an AI-powered world.”</p>
<p>The company added that its customers will be able to use its Copilot Studio service to create their own AI agents to meet specific needs. Copilot is Microsoft's existing AI chatbot tool. In addition, the company said it has introduced 10 ready-to-use agents to carry out <strong>routine</strong> business activities.</p>
<p>Charles Lamanna is the corporate vice president of business and industry for Copilot. He told Reuters news agency, "The idea is that Copilot is the user <strong>interface</strong> for AI." He added, "Every employee will have a Copilot, their personalized AI agent. And then they will use that Copilot to interface and interact with the sea of AI agents that will be out there."</p>
<p>In an online explanation of the AI tools, Microsoft said “instead of just assisting you, agents can work alongside you or even <strong>on your behalf</strong>.” This could include “a range of things, from responding to customer questions to more (complex) or multistep assignments,” the company added.</p>
<p>The abilities of AI agents remain limited for now. But ongoing development of the tools has raised concerns about certain risks linked to the technology. Microsoft officials have said the company had developed responsible AI guidelines to protect users from possible security or privacy problems.</p>
<p>Other big technology companies also aim to develop such agents. These include Salesforce, Nvidia, Google and Oracle. Industry experts have said the tools could provide companies with an easier path to earn money from the billions of dollars they are investing in AI systems.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press, Reuters and Agence France-Presse and Microsoft reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>agent </strong><em>– n.</em> a person or system whose job it is to deal with business for someone else</p>
<p><strong>customer </strong><em>– n.</em> a person or organization that buys goods or services from a shop or business</p>
<p><strong>routine </strong><em>– adj</em>. a regular task that gets repeated over and over again</p>
<p><strong>interface </strong><em>– n. </em>a connection between a person and a computer system</p>
<p><strong>on behalf (of someone) </strong><em>– phrase</em> acting for someone else</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Ancient Footprints Suggest 2 Human Species Were Neighbors in Kenya 1.5 Million Years Ago (2024/12/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/ancient-footprints-suggest-2-human-species-were-neighbors-in-kenya-1-5-million-years-ago.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists say ancient footprints left in wet dirt on a Kenyan lakeside suggest that two early human ancestors were neighbors about 1.5 million years ago.</p>
<p>Two separate <strong>species</strong> made the sets of footprints “within a matter of hours, or at most days,” said paleontologist Louise Leakey, a writer of the research published recently in the journal <em>Science</em>. Paleontologists study <strong>fossils</strong> to learn about the history of life on Earth.</p>
<p>Scientists already knew from earlier fossil finds that these two <strong>extinct </strong>lines of human development – called Homo erectus and Paranthropus boisei – lived about the same time in the Turkana Basin.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="An aerial view shows a research team standing alongside the fossil footprint trackway at the excavation site on the eastern side of Lake Turkana in northern Kenya, 2022. (Louise Leakey via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/08ad1e64-92bb-4ece-affc-d0bc2dd71073_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">An aerial view shows a research team standing alongside the fossil footprint trackway at the excavation site on the eastern side of Lake Turkana in northern Kenya, 2022. (Louise Leakey via AP)</span></div>
<p>But dating fossils is not exact. “It's plus or minus a few thousand years,” said paleontologist William Harcourt-Smith of Lehman College and the American Museum of Natural History in New York. He was not involved in the study</p>
<p>Yet with fossil footprints, “there's an actual moment in time <strong>preserved</strong>,” he said. “It's an amazing discovery.”</p>
<p>Researchers found the fossil footprints in 2021 in what is today Koobi Fora, Kenya, said Leaky, who is based at Stony Brook University in New York.</p>
<p>Study co-writer Kevin Hatala is a paleoanthropologist at Chatham University in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. He said the two species likely knew of each other's existence whether they left the prints at the same time or a day or two apart.</p>
<p>“They probably saw each other, probably knew each other was there and probably influenced each other in some way,” Hatala said.</p>
<p>Scientists were able to tell the difference between the two species because of the shape of the footprints. The shape of each informed researchers about the structure of the foot and how it was being used at the time.</p>
<p>Homo erectus appeared to be walking similarly to how modern humans walk – striking the ground heel first, then moving weight over the ball of the foot and toes and pushing off again.</p>
<p>The other species, which was also walking upright, was moving “in a different way from anything else we've seen before, anywhere else,” said co-writer Erin Marie Williams-Hatala, a human development <strong>anatomist</strong> at Chatham.</p>
<p>Among other details, the footprints suggest greater ability of movement in their big toe, compared to Homo erectus or modern humans, said Hatala.</p>
<p>Our common <strong>primate</strong> ancestors probably had hands and feet fit for grasping branches. But, over time, the feet of human ancestors developed to permit walking upright, researchers say.</p>
<p>The new study adds to a growing amount of research that suggests the change to walking on two feet did not happen at a single moment, in a single way.</p>
<p>Instead, there may have been a number of ways that early humans learned to walk, run and slide on prehistoric muddy hills.</p>
<p>“It turns out, there are different gait mechanics – different ways of being <strong>bipedal</strong>,” said Harcourt-Smith.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted the story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>species </strong><em>– n.</em> <strong> </strong>a class of things of the same kind and with the same name</p>
<p><strong>fossil </strong><em>– n.</em> a trace or print or the remains of a plant or animal of a past age preserved in earth or rock</p>
<p><strong>extinct </strong><em>– adj</em>. no longer existing</p>
<p><strong>preserve </strong><em>– v</em>. <strong> </strong>to keep or save from decomposition</p>
<p><strong>anatomist </strong><em>– n.</em> a scientist who studies the structural makeup of a living organism or any of its parts</p>
<p><strong>bipedal </strong><em>– adj.</em> of, or relating to, walking on two feet</p>
<p><strong>primate</strong> <em>– n.</em> any of an order of mammals that are characterized by hands and feet that grasp, a relatively large complex brain, and vision in which objects are seen in three dimensions and that includes human beings, apes, m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s, and related forms (such as lemurs and tarsiers)</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: More Than 800 Million Have Diabetes Worldwide, Many Untreated (2024/12/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/study-more-than-800-million-have-diabetes-worldwide-many-untreated.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A new study reports that more than 800 million adults have diabetes worldwide. And more than half of those aged over 30 who have the condition are not receiving treatment.</p>
<p>Diabetes is a disease in which your blood sugar level is too high. If untreated, it can damage the heart, blood vessels, nerves and other organs.</p>
<p>The study, recently published in the publication <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(24)02317-1/fulltext"><em>Lancet</em></a>, found that around 828 million people aged 18 and older had diabetes worldwide in 2022. Among those 30 and older, the study said 445 million, or 59 percent, were not receiving treatment.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A person receives a blood sugar test for diabetes in Dhaka, Bangladesh on November 14, 2024. (REUTERS/Mohammad Ponir Hossain)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a853c27d-6ac4-4712-ae84-e8a44a59a070_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A person receives a blood sugar test for diabetes in Dhaka, Bangladesh on November 14, 2024. (REUTERS/Mohammad Ponir Hossain)</span></div>
<p>The study was done by the NCD Risk Factor Collaboration and the World Health Organization (WHO). It is the first worldwide <strong>evaluation</strong> based on more than 1,000 studies involving more than 140 million people.</p>
<p><strong>Shocking increase</strong></p>
<p>The WHO <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/diabetes">estimated</a> that the number of people living with diabetes worldwide rose from 200 million in 1990 to about 830 million in 2022. The study's researchers say the increase has been caused largely by rising cases in low- and middle-<strong>income</strong> countries. Treatments in those countries have not kept up with the rise, while the situation has improved in some higher-income countries.</p>
<p>WHO Director-General Dr. Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus said in a statement that the increase shown in the study was shocking. “To bring the <strong>global</strong> diabetes epidemic under control, countries must urgently take action," he said. Those actions should include policies supporting healthy diets and physical activity, as well as health systems that can prevent, identify and treat the condition.</p>
<p><strong>Treating the disease is costly</strong></p>
<p>Jean Claude Mbanya is a professor at the University of Yaounde I in Cameroon. He said that in parts of sub-Saharan Africa, only 5-10 percent of those estimated to have diabetes were getting treatment. He added that treating diabetes, either with <strong>insulin</strong> or drugs, can be costly. "A huge number (are) at risk of serious health complications," he said.</p>
<p>Some of the largest improvements, 25 to 37 percentage points, happened in countries in Latin America, central and western Europe, Canada, South Korea, Russia, Seychelles, and Jordan.</p>
<p>The WHO says the number of deaths caused by diabetes has been increasing since 2000. In 2021, the disease was the direct cause of 1.6 million deaths.</p>
<p><strong>Symptoms and prevention</strong></p>
<p>The health agency says <strong>symptoms</strong> of diabetes may happen suddenly or take many years to be noticed. They include:</p>
<ul>
<li>feeling very thirsty</li>
<li>needing to urinate more often than usual</li>
<li>blurred vision</li>
<li>feeling tired</li>
<li>losing weight</li>
</ul>
<p>The best way to prevent or delay the illness, the WHO says, is to make lifestyle changes. For example:</p>
<ul>
<li>keeping a healthy body weight</li>
<li>staying active with at least 150 minutes of exercise each week</li>
<li>eating a healthy diet and avoiding sugar and saturated fat</li>
<li>not smoking tobacco.</li>
</ul>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jennifer Rigby reported this story for Reuters.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted the story for Learning English with additional information from The Lancet and the WHO.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>evaluate</strong> – <em>v</em>. to judge the value or condition of (someone or something) in a careful and thoughtful way</p>
<p><strong>income</strong> – <em>n</em>. money that is earned from work, investments, business, etc.</p>
<p><strong>global</strong> – <em>adj</em>. involving the entire world</p>
<p><strong>insulin</strong> – <em>n.</em> a substance that your body makes and uses to turn sugar into energy</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Research of Galaxies Supports Einstein’s General Theory of Relativity (2024/12/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/research-of-galaxies-supports-einstein-s-general-theory-of-relativity.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>An international group of scientists has been studying how the structure of the universe has grown over the past 11 billion years.</p>
<p>These researchers recently announced findings about how gravity behaves at a very large scale. What they found supports a prediction physicist Albert Einstein made in his 1915 theory of general relativity.</p>
<p><strong>Dark energy and gravity </strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - The Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument at Kitt Peak National Observatory in Arizona is operated imaging the night sky in 2022, in Kitt Peak, Arizona, U.S. (Kitt Peak National Observatory/NOIRLab/U.S. National Science Foundation/AURA/T. Slovinsky/Handout via REUTERS)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/c5a9df68-7c1f-4dc7-a5ac-eb7d15b066fc_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - The Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument at Kitt Peak National Observatory in Arizona is operated imaging the night sky in 2022, in Kitt Peak, Arizona, U.S. (Kitt Peak National Observatory/NOIRLab/U.S. National Science Foundation/AURA/T. Slovinsky/Handout via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>The findings are part of a years-long study of the history of the universe that has <strong>focused</strong> on dark energy. Dark energy is an invisible and mysterious force that is accelerating, or speeding up, the ongoing expansion of the universe.</p>
<p>The study's researchers used a year of observations by the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) at Kitt Peak National Observatory in Arizona.</p>
<p>Gravity is one of the universe's <strong>fundamental</strong> forces. Einstein's theory linked space, time and gravity. The theory holds that large amounts of mass and energy <strong>curve</strong> the structure of space-time, influencing the motion of whatever passes nearby.</p>
<p>Dragan Huterer of the University of Michigan was co-leader of the working group that examined the data from DESI.</p>
<p>Huterer said: "Einstein's theory of general relativity describes the motion of <strong>massive </strong>objects in a gravitational field that they create. It is one of the most successful physical theories that we have.”</p>
<p>But the announcement in 1998 that the universe's expansion was speeding up raised doubts about Einstein's model.</p>
<p>“The discovery of the accelerating universe...led to suggestions that maybe general relativity needs to be modified,” Huterer said.</p>
<p>The new DESI findings revealed gravity is behaving as Einstein predicted that it would.</p>
<p>Scientists say the Big Bang event 13.8 billion years ago began the universe, which has been expanding ever since. They say experiments show the expansion was actually accelerating and dark energy is a possible cause.</p>
<p>The new DESI findings focused on the growth of what is called the cosmic structure. It dates to when the universe was about 20 percent of its current age.</p>
<p>This cosmic structure has a direct connection to the large-scale organization of matter. Galaxies, galaxy clusters and even larger galaxy superclusters form a cosmic web or connected networks with large areas of space existing in between.</p>
<p>This structure results from the gravitational pull of matter throughout the universe.</p>
<p>The new study was based on DESI observations of almost 6 million galaxies and their centers, dating back 11 billion years.</p>
<p>The DESI scientists in April released the largest three-dimensional map of the cosmos. They announced findings suggesting that dark energy may not be an unchangeable force. Instead, it might change over time. Those findings focused on a specific behavior of galaxy clusters. The new research expanded what is known about that behavior.</p>
<p>Mustapha Ishak-Boushaki of the University of Texas at Dallas was a co-leader of the working group. He said, "Our DESI data shows that it is in agreement with Einstein's theory of gravity but still favors a <strong>dynamical</strong> dark energy - and finding these <strong>simultaneously </strong>is new."</p>
<p>The universe includes ordinary matter: stars, planets, gas, dust. It also contains dark matter. Dark matter is invisible material that might make up about 27 percent of the cosmos. In addition to that, scientists also believe there is dark energy which might make up 68 percent of the cosmos.</p>
<p>"Dark energy is responsible for the accelerated expansion of the universe. The physical nature of dark energy is at present unknown," Huterer said.</p>
<p>The new findings appear to support the current “standard model” of cosmology that includes the theory of general relativity.</p>
<p>The DESI working group involves more than 900 researchers from more than 70 organizations worldwide. It is overseen by the U.S. Department of Energy's Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory. The new research was published in the arXiv online database before undergoing the process of<strong> peer review</strong>.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Will Dunham reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>focus</strong> <em>– v.</em> to concentrate attention or effort</p>
<p><strong>fundamental </strong><em>–adj.</em> ideas that form the basis of other ideas or theories</p>
<p><strong>curve </strong><em>–n.</em> a shape that is similar to a circle or a rounded line</p>
<p><strong>massive</strong> <em>– adj.</em> forming or consisting of a large mass; very large</p>
<p><strong>dynamical </strong><em>– adj. </em>of or relating to physical force or energy</p>
<p><strong>simultaneously </strong><em>– adv.</em> existing or happening at the same time</p>
<p><strong>peer review<em> </em></strong><em>– n.</em> a process for publishing scholarly research in which academic people with similar positions and jobs as the writers' offer criticism of a research paper before it is officially published in a scholarly journal</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Publish Version of a Map of Human Body Cells (2024/12/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/scientists-publish-version-of-a-map-of-human-body-cells.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Researchers have created an early version of a map of some of the human body's cells.</p>
<p>The human body has an estimated 37.2 trillion cells. Each <strong>type</strong> of cell has a <strong>unique</strong> job. Knowing each cell's job can help scientists better understand health and diseases such as cancer.</p>
<p>The work is part of the Human Cell Atlas<strong> </strong>project. The effort began in 2016. It involves researchers around the world. The group, called a consortium, plans to release a more complete <strong>atlas</strong> in 2026 by mapping cells from 18 organs and body systems. These include the skin, heart, and breasts.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image provided by Ana-Maria Cujba shows blood vessels in a portion of the human small intestine, March 21, 2024. (Ana-Maria Cujba/Wellcome Sanger Institute via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/5f5045b6-c127-4964-8d33-63b8056263c8_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image provided by Ana-Maria Cujba shows blood vessels in a portion of the human small intestine, March 21, 2024. (Ana-Maria Cujba/Wellcome Sanger Institute via AP)</span></div>
<p>Some of the researchers published their findings on bone development in embryos. The study appeared in <em>Nature </em>on November 20.</p>
<p>Aviv Regev is a founding co-chair of the project. Regev is currently executive vice president and head of research and early development at U.S. biotech company Genentech. She said the work is important in two ways.</p>
<p>First, the project relates to <strong>curiosity</strong>. Humans have long wanted to know what they are made of. “And, in fact, <strong>biologists</strong> have been mapping cells since the 1600s for that reason," Regev added.</p>
<p>Second, Regev said knowing how cells work is critical for understanding how to treat disease.</p>
<p>"Cells are the basic unit of life, and when things go wrong, they go wrong with our cells, first and foremost," she added.</p>
<p>"<strong>Fundamentally</strong>, these studies tell us how tissues, organs and humans are built," said Muzlifah Haniffa of Wellcome Sanger Institute and Newcastle University in Britain. Haniffa was a member of the project's organizing committee.</p>
<p><strong>What is the Human Cell Atlas?</strong></p>
<p>Scientists are<strong> focusing</strong> on certain organs. They are mapping the jobs of cells in the mouth, stomach and intestines. They are researching cells that guide how bones and joints develop. They also are exploring which cells group into tissue, where they are found in the body and how they change over time.</p>
<p>The <strong>high-resolution,</strong> <strong>open-access</strong> atlas is considered a first version. The scientists say they hope it will help researchers fight diseases that damage human cells.</p>
<p>The current cell map not only shows many types of human cells. It also shows the relationships between cells, said Dr. Timothy Chan. Chan is a cancer expert at the Cleveland Clinic who was not involved in the project. Chan said the atlas project is a “<strong>deep dive </strong>into human biology” that is sure to help identify and treat cancer cells.</p>
<p>Scientists are also creating other atlases that could show more about the foundations of health and disease in specific parts of the body.</p>
<p>For example, researchers working on a brain atlas are seeking to understand the structure, <strong>location</strong> and function of the many types of brain cells. A new gut microbiome atlas is meant to show the collection of microorganisms in the intestines. Those organs play important parts in digestion and immune system health.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Adithi Ramakrishnan and Laura Ungar reported this story for The Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English with additional information from Reuters and other sources. </em></p>
<p><em>______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>type </strong><em>–n.</em> a particular kind of thing that is like others in the same group</p>
<p><strong>unique </strong><em>–adj.</em> something that is unlike anything else</p>
<p><strong>atlas </strong><em>–n.</em> a detailed map of a place or a thing that include picture or images</p>
<p><strong>curiosity </strong><em>–n.</em> the condition of being interested in something and wanting to learn more about it</p>
<p><strong>biologist </strong><em>–n.</em> a scientist who studies the processes of life and the living structures involved in it</p>
<p><strong>focus </strong><em>–v.</em> to place special attention on something or someone</p>
<p><strong>high-resolution </strong><em>–adj.</em> usually related to a kind of image that is very rich or high in detail showing very small or complex things clearly</p>
<p><strong>open-access </strong><em>–adj.</em> available to anyone and not requiring payment</p>
<p><strong>deep dive </strong><em>–n.</em> a complete investigation into something</p>
<p><strong>location </strong><em>–n.</em> the place where something is</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Mysterious Creature from Argentina Has Made Its Home in Dubai (2024/12/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/mysterious-creature-from-argentina-has-made-its-home-in-dubai.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Dubai in the United Arab Emirates is known for its tall, modern buildings rising high above the desert. But an unusual animal from Argentina, the Patagonian mara, can be found there, too.</p>
<p>The animal, like a rabbit, has long legs and ears and a body larger than most other rodents. They have been found near the Al Qudra Lakes, which are usually home to gazelle and other desert creatures found in the Emirates, or UAE.</p>
<p>How they got there remains a mystery. But in the UAE, <strong>exotic</strong> animals have ended up in the private homes and farms of the wealthy.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A Patagonia mara is seen at Al Qudra Lakes in Dubai, United Arab Emirates, Thursday, Nov. 21, 2024. (AP Photo/Jon Gambrell)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/57b429f6-d892-4742-b7f6-01e618b337ab_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A Patagonia mara is seen at Al Qudra Lakes in Dubai, United Arab Emirates, Thursday, Nov. 21, 2024. (AP Photo/Jon Gambrell)</span></div>
<p>The UAE's Climate Change and Environment Ministry and officials in Dubai did not answer questions from the Associated Press (AP) about the Patagonian maras. But one estimate suggests that as many as 200 could be <strong>thriving</strong> in the area of the Al Marmoom Desert Conservation Reserve nearby. Few dead maras have been found.</p>
<p>An AP reporter found at least five maras on a recent visit to the Al Qudra Lakes, a wide desert area 40 kilometers south of Dubai. On another visit, the reporter saw several <strong>packs</strong> of the animals, including one mother still <strong>nursing</strong> a baby.</p>
<p>Al Qudra is at the end of a long bicycle path. It is popular in the winter months. Campers and others come to enjoy the outdoors in the cooler weather among the area's lakes. Some of the lakes have been engineered into shapes like a moon, two hearts or as an advertisement for Dubai's Expo 2020.</p>
<p>The Patagonian maras first appeared publicly in 2020 during the height of the coronavirus pandemic. A request for information on their sightings was first published in an issue of the Dubai Natural History Group's monthly newsletter. Volunteers described seeing them in Al Qudra and on Saadiyat Island near the UAE's capital of Abu Dhabi.</p>
<p>“This large rodent is a common <strong>species</strong> in zoological collections and undoubtedly found its way out from captivity,” wrote Jacky Judas, who has long studied mammals in the UAE.</p>
<p>“They can regularly be seen sleeping or eating grass in the middle of <strong>roundabouts</strong> at Al Qudra...it can possibly survive in highly modified <strong>habitats</strong> with tree plantations, lawns and ponds,” Judas wrote.</p>
<p>Those words describe the environment found at Al Qudra and are probably the reason for the maras' continued survival. But temperatures in the UAE regularly reach 45 degrees Celsius in the summer, making it a difficult environment.</p>
<p>The number of maras at Al Qudra suggests that they are breeding. Patagonian maras mate for life, and females can get pregnant only a few times a year. They can give birth to one to three babies at a time. In Argentina, the animals can be hunted and eaten, their fur used for rugs and blankets.</p>
<p>The Patagonian maras eat plants and are no threat to humans. There are few animals that might hunt them at Al Qudra. Arabian red fox do live and hunt in the area.</p>
<p>Patagonian maras normally live in central and southern Argentina. But they have been trafficked into areas as <strong>exotic</strong> pets in the past. In the United States, the appearance of one was covered by the local news in Denver, Colorado. In August, a Patagonian mara was found in a car about to enter Turkey from Greece. Officials discovered other animals in the suspected trafficking attempt.</p>
<p>It is illegal to keep endangered or threatened wildlife in the Emirates. But there have been many reports and social media videos of Emirati men in <strong>luxury</strong> cars with pet lions along for the ride.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Jon Gambrell reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>thrive</strong> <em>–v.</em> to not only survive but to live well and to reproduce</p>
<p><strong>pack</strong> <em>–n. </em>a group of certain kinds of animals like dogs, hyenas, and some rodents</p>
<p><strong>nurse</strong> <em>–v.</em> when mother mammals provide milk to their young</p>
<p><strong>species</strong><strong> </strong><em>–n.</em> a kind of animal or plant that is like others of its kind and can reproduce with them</p>
<p><strong>roundabout</strong><strong> </strong><em>–n</em>. a circular roadway where two or more roads meet</p>
<p><strong>habitat </strong><em>–n.</em> an environment in which a plant or animal lives</p>
<p><strong>luxury </strong><em>–adj.</em> market by being very costly or excessive</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What Does ‘Like Gangbusters’ Mean? (2024/12/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/what-does-like-gangbusters-mean.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">30 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>With a new project, you may want to start with energy and excitement. If that is the case, you could say you want to start <u>like gangbusters.</u></p>
<p>To start <u>like gangbusters</u> means you start a project <u>on the right foot</u> – an exciting one! You begin with energy, speed, and sometimes, attention-getting success.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - John Dillinger (C), a well-known gangster, is handcuffed and guarded in court awaiting his trial on Feb. 9, 1934. (AP PHOTO)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/14F4B16C-9315-45BE-A9FD-96C3EF88CB4D_cx1_cy16_cw96_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">FILE - John Dillinger (C), a well-known gangster, is handcuffed and guarded in court awaiting his trial on Feb. 9, 1934. (AP PHOTO)</span></div>
<p>Let's hear some examples:</p>
<p><em>She works <u>like gangbusters</u> and gets the job done quickly. </em></p>
<p><em>The wildflowers are spreading <u>like gangbusters</u>.</em></p>
<p>We can use this expression to describe something that starts with a lot of <strong>enthusiasm</strong>. It can also mean someone or something is having great effect -- usually in a good way. Whatever the attempt is, it is successful.</p>
<p>To start something <u>like gangbusters</u> can also mean it involves great force or <strong>aggressiveness</strong>. For example, the partners worked <u>like gangbusters</u> to open their business before their <strong>rivals</strong> in the city.</p>
<p><u>Like gangbusters</u> can simply mean something is growing very fast. For example, if the economy is growing <u>like gangbusters,</u> it is growing very fast.</p>
<p>Sometimes we add the phrasal verb “come on,” making the expression <u>to come on like gangbusters.</u> The expression <u>to come on like gangbusters</u> can also mean to work hard and in an energetic, forceful manner to get something done.</p>
<p>Here are some examples:</p>
<p><em>When I gave the lesson to my students, they <u>came on like gangbusters</u> to try to solve the mystery.</em></p>
<p><em>The new employee <u>came on like gangbusters</u> during her first few months on the job. </em></p>
<p>But why <u>gangbusters</u>?</p>
<p>As a noun, <u>gangbuster</u> is a term for a law-enforcement officer who breaks up organized crime. <u>Gangbusters</u> often use forceful or aggressive means.</p>
<p>Word experts say the expression <u>like gangbusters</u> comes from a popular radio show called <em>Gang Busters</em> broadcast in the United States from 1935 to 1957. This crime-fighting radio drama started with a lot of noise and excitement – police sirens, screams, gun fire and exciting music.</p>
<p><u>Gangbuster</u> is also an adjective. It can describe something that is excellent or successful. For example, experts are reporting of a <u>gangbusters</u> housing market in rural areas.</p>
<p>It can also describe someone who is energetic or <strong>eager</strong> to do something. For example, if someone asks you to volunteer during the weekend you can say, “I'm not really <u>gangbusters</u> over that idea." However, this usage is not as common as <u>to come on like gangbusters.</u></p>
<p>And if you do not want to use <u>gangbusters</u>, you could say you <u>started something with a bang</u>. To <u>start or begin something with a bang </u>means you start in an exciting and noticeable way. You can also say to <u>be back with a bang.</u></p>
<p>Here's an example using that expression:</p>
<p><em>The singer took a year off. But with her new <strong>album</strong>, she's <u>back with a bang.</u></em></p>
<p>And that's end of this Words and Their Stories. Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>enthusiasm </strong><em>–n.</em><strong> </strong>strong excitement of feeling</p>
<p><strong>aggressiveness </strong><em>–n. </em>being forceful in getting things done</p>
<p><strong>rival </strong><em>–n. </em>one of two or more trying to get what only one can have</p>
<p><strong>eager </strong><em>–adj.</em><strong> </strong>marked by enthusiastic or impatient desire or interest</p>
<p><strong>album </strong><em>–n. </em>a collection of one or more audio recordings that is presented as a single unit and is typically longer than a single</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What Is GivingTuesday? (2024/11/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/what-is-givingtuesday.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Since its start in 2012, GivingTuesday, the Tuesday after Thanksgiving, has become one of the biggest money-raising days of the year for nonprofits in the United States.</p>
<p>In 2022 and 2023, GivingTuesday raised $3.1 billion for charity, or aid, organizations, as estimated by GivingTuesday.</p>
<p>This year, GivingTuesday is on December 3.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - N.C. State defensive end Davin Vann works among the donations collected to help Hurricane Helene victims in western North Carolina, Wednesday, Oct. 2, 2024 in Raleigh, N.C. (AP Photo/Aaron Beard)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/92e09aab-cba2-4a35-9147-5a51d5ee79b5_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - N.C. State defensive end Davin Vann works among the donations collected to help Hurricane Helene victims in western North Carolina, Wednesday, Oct. 2, 2024 in Raleigh, N.C. (AP Photo/Aaron Beard)</span></div>
<p><strong>How did GivingTuesday start?</strong></p>
<p>The #GivingTuesday <strong>hashtag</strong> started as a project of the 92nd Street Y in New York City in 2012. It became an independent organization in 2020. It has grown into a worldwide organization of local groups that support giving in their communities, often on different dates that have local importance, like holidays.</p>
<p>Now, GivingTuesday, the nonprofit, also gathers researchers studying everyday giving. It also collects data from wide sources like payment processors, <strong>crowdfunding</strong> sites, employee giving software and organizations that offer charitable giving.</p>
<p><strong>What is the purpose of GivingTuesday?</strong></p>
<p>For nonprofits, the point of GivingTuesday is to raise money and engage their supporters. Many nonprofits will organize fundraising campaigns with email and mail appeals that arrive on the Tuesday after Thanksgiving.</p>
<p>Nonprofits do not have to be linked in any way with GivingTuesday, the organization, to run a fundraising campaign. GivingTuesday will still provide them with <strong>graphics </strong>and advice. In that way, it remains a grassroots effort with groups and donors taking part as they like.</p>
<p><strong>Has GivingTuesday been successful?</strong></p>
<p>GivingTuesday has grown far beyond its early days when it mainly pushed for giving on social media. The day has become a well-known event that seeks to center charitable giving and volunteering in the U.S. and around the world.</p>
<p>For years, GivingTuesday has been a major <strong>focus</strong> of fundraising for nonprofits, with many seeking to organize <strong>matching</strong> donations from major donors. It is the beginning of the end-of-year fundraising race as nonprofits seek to reach their budget targets for the following year.</p>
<p>Donations on GivingTuesday in 2022 and 2023 reached $3.1 billion, an increase from $2.7 billion in 2021. While that is a lot to raise in a single day, the <strong>trend</strong> last year was flat and fewer donors were giving. The organization says that is a worrying sign.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted the story for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>hashtag </strong><em>– n.</em> a word or phrase preceded by the symbol # that classifies or categorizes the accompanying text (such as a tweet)</p>
<p><strong>crowdfunding </strong><em>– n</em>. the practice of obtaining needed funding (as for a new business) by soliciting contributions from a large number of people especially from the online community</p>
<p><strong>graphics </strong><em>– n</em>. <strong> </strong>graphic media such as images, maps, charts, etc.</p>
<p><strong>focus </strong><em>– n.</em> special attention you give something</p>
<p><strong>matching </strong><em>– adj.</em> equal in amount</p>
<p><strong>trend </strong><em>– n. </em>a general movement</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
