<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>VOA Special English</title>
        <link>https://www.21voa.com/special_english/</link>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <itunes:category>ESL</itunes:category>
        <itunes:author>VOA</itunes:author>
        <description>美国之音（以下称VOA）的英语节目，按播音速度可分为两种：Standard English （标准英语）和 Special English（特别英语）。

Special English 又叫“慢速英语”，是VOA 专为全世界非英语国家初学英语的听众安排的一种简易、规范的英语广播节目。该节目创始于50年代末期，是VOA 的专家们研究如何与世界各地的英语学习者进行交际的产物。它正式开播于1959年10月。当时只面向欧洲和中东，但由于这个节目适合许多国家英语学习者的需要，所以它的广播对象不久就扩大到世界其他地区，并很快在全世界范围内产生了广泛的影响。现在这个节目对欧洲、非洲和拉丁美洲每晚广播一次，对加勒比地区每晚广播一次（星期天除外），对东南亚广播次数最多，每天上午两次，晚上三次。

30多年来，VOA 为了办好Special English节目，进行了大量的调查研究工作，对播音速度、内容及用词范围都作了具体规定，基本上达到了既能为英语学习者提供信息，又不损害英语本身风格的目的，使之成为VOA 独具特色，拥有最大量听众的节目。

美国著名词汇学家S. B. Flexmer 指明了Special English的三条标准，也就是它所“特别”的地方：

1、它是一种由美国人最常用的1500个基本单词为主体构成的美国英语；

2、它用简短、明晰的句子写作和广播；

3、它以每分钟90个单词的速度，即2/3的Standard English（标准英语）速度进行广播。

Special English的节目可分为两大类：一类是新闻节目；一类是专题节目。

1．新闻节目

VOA Special English 的新闻广播向听众提供世界范围内的政治、经济、军事、外交、国际关系、宗教、天气以及各种重大事件和珍闻奇事等各个方面的信息，每天向东南亚地区广播五次，早上两次，晚上三次，每逢半点播出。

Special English新闻节目每次长约十分钟，大都播出十条左右新闻，近一千个单词，每条新闻多为一分钟，但偶尔也有长达两分钟的要闻。除头条新闻外，每条新闻都由一个电头引导，这样显得结构分明，条理清晰，适宜初学英语的人收听。在节目结束之前，播音员常常用三四句话重播其中三条新闻的提要以加深听众对要闻的印象。

Special English新闻中70%左右的内容与同时整点播出的Standard English新闻相同，但相同新闻的先后次序有所变动。每次节目的开头和结尾大同小异，格式比较固定。

2．专题节目（一）

Special English的专题节目（Feature Programs）,从时间上看，可分为两大类：一是每五分钟一次的专题，二是每十五分钟一次的专题。本节先介绍每项五分钟一次的专题材节目。

Special English五分钟一次的专题材节目安排在Special English新闻节目之后和（或）每十五分钟一次的专题材节目之前播出，每星期播七次。根据内容，可分为三个小类，即：Science Report（科学报道），逢星期一、三、五播出，每天播六遍；Agriculture Report（农业报道），逢星期二、四播出，每天播六遍；Words And Their Stories（词语掌故），逢星期六和星期天播出，每天播五遍。这三个专题材各具特色，具有相对的独立性，听众每听完一个节目，都会获得一个完整的印象。

Science Report（科学报道）这一专题材节目每周向听众介绍三篇有关现代科学技术最新发展情况的报道，涉及物理、化学、天文至高无上理、生物、环卫、心理、教育、医学和计算机等方面。适宜理工科大学生和科技工作者收集信息，积累资料，学习科技英语。

Agriculture Report（农业报道） Agriculture Report是为农业科技工作者和生产者安排的一个专题。它专门报道世界各国，特别是美国现代农业生产的最新成文汇报总务科 学家对农业生产某一方面的研究进展，以及他们对影响农业生产的某一自然现象进行分析和研究的近况。此外，它还经常向听众介绍发展中国家家业生产的一些有益经验等内容。

Words And Their Stories（词语掌故）这一专题节目，旨在向学习英语的听众介绍美国英语中生动有趣的词语和惯用法，并从科学研究和通俗词源学的角度来解释它们的含意、产生的背景及其在使用过程中的演变情况等。它通过讲故事的形式讲解每一个词语。这是VOA Special English中的优秀节目之一，是学习美国英语的极好材料。通过收听这一节目，听众不仅能学到娓娓动听的掌故和地道的美国英语，而且能增加美国的社会文化背景知识，历史传统与现状的了解。

VOA 为了更好地办好这个节目，便于听众收听学习，于1978年编辑出版了一本名为Words And Their Stories的书，共收集一百篇故事，作者是Herbert Sutcliffe, Harold Bermen 及VOA 该节目的部分编辑人员。在每次的实际广播中，播音员都以此书为蓝本，再根据需要对原稿进行适当增删。按每周两个故事计算，此书的一百个故事还不能满足一年的播音需要。于是编辑们就是重播部分词语掌故的同时，不断增加许多新的词语掌故，及时将词源学家的最新研究成果和不断增加的新词汇介绍给听众。收听实践证明，初学者在收听过程中必然会遇到许多人名、地名和一些较难的句子，有时甚至在听完之后还很难理解所播词语的确切含义及其汉语意思，为此，听众可参看1983年由中国对外翻译出版公司出版的该书英汉对照本中的有关部分。

3．专题节目（二）

VOA Special English的专题节目，除上节谈的五分钟一次的以外，还有本节要介绍的每十五分钟一次的节目。这类节目共有七个不同的小专题，以星期为单位循环，每天分四次复播出一个专题，但星期日和星期六的两个专题材每晚只播三遍，每次节目约十分钟，继每次五分钟的专题节目之后播出。

这类专题节目的基本结构是，在特定的伴声中先报告当次节目的名称，并扼要介绍其主要内容，然后播送节目正文。最后，在伴乐声中报告节目主持人和撰稿人的姓名，以邀请听众在下周的这个时间继续收听该节目而结束。

People in America（美国人物志） 这是有关美国历史名人的一个专题节目，每逢星期天晚上播出。它向听众介绍在美国历史上产生过重大影响、起过重要作用、作出了突出贡献的科学、文学、政治、或其他各方面的历史人物。节目一般都对他们的生平事迹进行简要的叙述，对其贡献作出评介，类似人物小传。有的重要人物事迹很多，必须用两次或几次的节目时间进行联播。对这样的节目要坚持收听，才会获得完整的印象。

TThis is America（今日美国） This Is America向听众介绍美国人民的生活、学习、工作和娱乐情况，是英语学习者解美国社会的一条渠道。该专题大都一个节目一个整体，每逢星期一晚播出。

Science in the News（科学新闻） 这一专题材主要对新近的科学技术新闻进行综述或摘要广播。向听众介绍世界各国在自然、医学、疾病、原子能、航天等方面的科研动态、成果、突破性进展及存在的困难。涉及当今世界人们普遍关心的重大问题，如核事故、航天飞机爆炸、自然灾害、环境污染和爱滋病等等。每逢星期二播出，每次播一到五条新闻摘要。

Explorations（自然探索） 每逢星期三晚上，听众可以收听到Explorations这一专题节目。该专题既涉及人类遨游太空、探索原子、研究自身、改造自然的现代技术，也报道发展中国家开发新资源，利用新工艺改善人民生活等方面的成就，其侧重点在各种科技实验和简易实用技术方面。该节目一般安排一段时间播一个系列，每次播出一个主题，以便能将某项新技术的研究和应用的全过程介绍给听众，电台还乐意为感兴趣的听众提供所需的文字材料。

The Making of a Nation（建国史话） 这一专题节目向听众介绍美利坚合众国从十三个殖民地区域到现代工业国的孕育、诞生以及形成超级大国的历史过程，并以历史为线索，特定的历史时期为单位，以重大的历史事件为主题材来叙述各个党派、各届总统和政府的历史作用与贡献。这是每个英语学习者都应了解的基本知识。The Making of a Nation每逢星期四播出。这是个系列节目，坚持收听，则有助于系统了解美国的历史概况。

American Mosaic（美国万花筒） American Mosaic是一个radio magazine（广播杂志）节目。该节目题材广泛、内容丰，展示着美国社会文化生活中比较轻松愉快的生活画面；听众收听该节目就如同在阅读一本图文并茂的杂志。它每次有三到五个小节目，涉及音乐、图书、技术和教育等方面的内容。我们既可以从中欣赏到著名歌唱的优秀歌曲，对美国音乐有所了解，又可以获取一些生动有趣的现代美国社会生活知识，随着播音员那亲切悦耳的声音步入美国风景如画的大好河山；同时还能听到世界各地的听众提出的有关英语语方文学等方面的问题和电台的解答。

American Stories（美国故事） 这一专题材节目安排在每星期六晚上播出。这样能使听众在学习和工作之余，得以轻松一下头脑。我们可以通过这一美国文学的“窗口”，接触各种流派、各类名家的文学作品。了解美国英语的时代特色，欣赏、学习美国人民运用语方的技巧，并从那些佳作名篇中获得艺术享受。该节目对短篇故事采取一次播一篇的方式，对中、长篇小说则先进行简写加工，再分几次播出全文。在播出故事正文之前，播音员常常先介绍故事的主要情节。对需要分几次节目时间播出的中长篇，在播第二或以后各部分之前，主持人还先重述已播部分的故事梗概，以唤起听众的回忆，使故事听起来更加连贯。</description>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          <item>
            <title>Deep Breathing Can Reduce Stress, Anxiety (2024/12/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/deep-breathing-can-reduce-stress-anxiety.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>At Myosin Marketing in Austin, Texas, the group employee meeting begins with an uncommon activity for a workplace. The members gather on Zoom and the head of the company, Sean Clayton, leads them through a deep-breathing exercise.</p>
<p>Clayton says the activity helps his employees <strong>relax</strong> and to be willing to take creative risks.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A woman meditates on the beach in Miami, Florida, April 28, 2010. According to a study published on Nov. 9, 2022 in the journal JAMA Psychiatry, mindfulness meditation worked as well as a standard drug for treating anxiety. (AP Photo/Lynne Sladky, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1dabb073-c37b-4b77-bdd5-19cf18b12302_cx0_cy12_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A woman meditates on the beach in Miami, Florida, April 28, 2010. According to a study published on Nov. 9, 2022 in the journal JAMA Psychiatry, mindfulness meditation worked as well as a standard drug for treating anxiety. (AP Photo/Lynne Sladky, File)</span></div>
<p>“At first they thought it was really <strong>weird</strong>,”<strong> </strong>he said, adding that most people turned off their cameras. But, after a couple of weeks, there was a change. The employees said the deep breathing felt good.</p>
<p>Studies show that deep breathing can be an effective way to reduce tension, or stress, at work. But people may not think about their breathing while on the job.</p>
<p>Workers who sit at computers for long periods tend to take <strong>shallow</strong> breaths as their shoulders slowly rise. Workers who spend the day on their feet in retail or health care may be too busy to center their attention on breathing.</p>
<p>But there is good reason to stop what you are doing and take deep breaths, research suggests.</p>
<p>Long-lasting stress can increase the risk of heart disease and stroke. Experts at the American Heart Association say it can be as harmful as secondhand smoke. Research suggests deep-breathing exercises can lower a person's blood pressure and reduce <strong>anxiety</strong>.</p>
<p>There are many <strong>benefits</strong> to deep breathing. For starters, it is free. It can be done anywhere. And unlike a 30-minute <strong>meditation</strong> practice, most deep breathing exercises do not take much time.</p>
<p>Also, it gives you something to <strong>focus</strong> on – your breathing. Experts say that this can help to calm racing thoughts.</p>
<p>Focusing on breathing for one to five minutes can help you clear your mind and let you “get back to focusing on the one thing you want to <strong>accomplish</strong>,” said Glenn Levine. He is a heart and blood system doctor and professor at Baylor College of Medicine in Houston, Texas.</p>
<p>A good way to do deep breathing exercises is outside, Levine said. However, if that is not possible, doing them at a desk works.</p>
<p>“Instead of focusing on the screen or work, just focus on your breathing. If possible,” Levine said, “close your eyes.”</p>
<p>Even very busy people can find time for daily breathing exercises.</p>
<p>Lisa Marie Deleveaux is a marketing professional and mother of five. She lost her job several months ago and has struggled to find a new one. Deleveaux wakes early most mornings before her children, to do breathing exercises.</p>
<p>“If you set a <strong>priority</strong> for yourself ... you can make the time,” Deleveaux said.</p>
<p>With one breathing exercise, she breaths in through one nostril and then out through the other. She uses a thumb or forefinger to hold one nostril closed at a time.</p>
<p>“It relaxes my mind. It makes my mind so full of ease. It brings you back to the present moment,” she added.</p>
<p>To get ahead of anxiety before starting her workday, sales representative Lindsay Carlisle of Michigan does breathing exercises with her seven-year-old daughter during their drive to school. They breathe in for seven counts, hold their breath for five, and then breathe out for seven counts. They repeat this several times.</p>
<p>“Throughout that process, my shoulders start to drop on their own, and it really is calming,” Carlisle said.</p>
<p>Suze Yalof Schwartz was an overworked magazine editor when her mother-in-law taught her a three-minute meditation method.</p>
<p>Yalof Schwartz says it changed her life. She left her career and founded Unplug Meditation, a Santa Monica, California, company with a meditation studio, an app, and programs for corporate customers.</p>
<p>“When we slow down our breath, we send a signal to our brain that everything's OK, even when it's not,” she said.</p>
<p>Another 16-second breathing exercise is called box breathing. You breathe in for four counts, hold for four, breathe out for four counts and hold for another four. Yalof Schwartz has taught it to people in stressful jobs including firefighters, police and doctors.</p>
<p>“It is the best thing that you can do at work before you have a meeting, before you send out an email that you wish you didn't send, before you have a difficult conversation, because it just calms you down, gets rid of your <strong>negative </strong>energy,” she said.</p>
<p>Employers such as Coca-Cola, Mattel and Netflix have used Unplug Meditation to teach breathing or meditation.</p>
<p>It is not always easy for workers to find space for deep breathing exercises. For example, salespeople often work alongside their customers. Yalof Schwartz suggests doing breathing exercises when making a sale or organizing items.</p>
<p>Carlisle, the sales representative, sets a timer on her phone telling her to breathe deeply. She also keeps a note near her computer that simply says “Breathe.”</p>
<p>“The anxiety is always going to be there,” Carlisle said. “But at least I know I have one small tool. ... It sounds so simple and <strong>silly</strong>, but it works.”</p>
<p>And that's the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo. And I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Cathy Bussewitz</em><em> reported this story for the Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>relax </strong><em>–v. </em>to make less tense or rigid</p>
<p><strong>weird </strong><em>–adj. </em>of strange or extraordinary character</p>
<p><strong>shallow </strong><em>–adj. </em>having little depth</p>
<p><strong>anxiety </strong><em>–n. </em>fear or nervousness about what might happen</p>
<p><strong>benefit </strong><em>–n. </em>something that produces good or helpful results or effects or that promotes well-being</p>
<p><strong>meditate </strong><em>–v. </em>to spend time in quiet thinking and breathing : <strong>meditation </strong><em>–n. </em>the act of meditating</p>
<p><strong>focus </strong><em>–n. </em>a center of activity, attraction, or attention</p>
<p><strong>accomplish </strong><em>–v. </em>to succeed in reaching (a stage in a progression)</p>
<p><strong>priority</strong> <em>–n. </em>precedence in exercise of rights in the same subject matter</p>
<p><strong>negative </strong><em>–adj. </em>not positive or helpful</p>
<p><strong>silly </strong><em>–adj. </em>playfully lighthearted and amusing</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Handwriting Might Have Identified Famous Byzantine Artist (2024/12/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/handwriting-might-have-identified-famous-byzantine-artist.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Crime-solving methods might have provided an answer to an ancient mystery — the identity of a leading Byzantine painter.</p>
<p>The artist Giotto who lived in Italy about 700 years ago is often considered the father of Western painting. But at the same time that Giotto lived, Manuel Panselinos was equally important to a different tradition: the art of Byzantium.</p>
<p>The art of Byzantium can be found in Eastern Orthodox churches across Greece, Serbia and other Orthodox countries. Byzantium is an ancient name for the modern city of Istanbul.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Christina Sotirakoglou a handwriting expert, observes Byzantine paintings based on photographs prints, at her office, in Thessaloniki, northern Greece, Saturday, Nov. 30, 2024. (AP Photo/Giannis Papanikos)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/5f11a40f-724f-4bce-a3db-57ceaaba34e7_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Christina Sotirakoglou a handwriting expert, observes Byzantine paintings based on photographs prints, at her office, in Thessaloniki, northern Greece, Saturday, Nov. 30, 2024. (AP Photo/Giannis Papanikos)</span></div>
<p><strong>Who was Panselinos? </strong></p>
<p>Nothing is known of Panselinos' life. Historians now believe Panselinos was a <strong>nickname</strong>. They now suspect his real name was likely Ioannis Astrapas. He was from the northern Greek city of Thessaloniki.</p>
<p>Work said to be made by Panselinos, from the late 1200s and early 1300s, is considered the finest produced in the Byzantine empire. That ancient empire covered parts of Europe and Asia. It lasted from the fall of the Roman Empire until the capture of the capital Constantinople by the Ottoman Turks in 1453.</p>
<p>Art historians had long suspected that “Panselinos” could have been a nickname, or a pseudonym, for a member of the Macedonian School of painting in Thessaloniki. The name means “full moon” in Greek.</p>
<p>Recent research by a Greek <strong>monk </strong>and a language expert have linked Panselinos with Macedonian School painter Astrapas.</p>
<p>Now <strong>handwriting</strong> expert Christina Sotirakoglou has found new evidence. She matched lettering on a document thought to be by Astrapas with writing on a church painting at Mount Athos in northern Greece. The Protaton church painting has been considered Panselinos' best work.</p>
<p>Father Cosmas Simonopetritis is a former administrator at Mount Athos; the religious community is where the Protaton church stands. He said Sotirakoglou's and his own research “clearly prove” Panselinos' real identity.</p>
<p>“Panselinos was a real person, and (the name) was just the nickname by which Ioannis Astrapas became known,” Simonopetritis told the Associated Press (AP).</p>
<p>Constantinos Vafiadis is a professor of Byzantine art who was not involved in the research. Vafiadis said he found strong points in the nickname theory and naming Astrapas as the true artist. However, he added that it appeared more than one painter had created the art at the Protaton church.</p>
<p>“I agree with <strong>attributing</strong> part of the paintings to Ioannis Astrapas,” Vafiadis said. “But again there remains much ground for future research into that person, because other Mount Athos monuments from the same period have not yet been sufficiently published.”</p>
<p>“Panselinos” and his fellow artists at the time are linked with a rebirth in Eastern Orthodox art. Their work brought back forms and skills inherited from ancient times. Facial expressions got a deeper humanity, and greater attention was paid to proportion and depth of field in composition.</p>
<p>Simonopetritis said Astrapas was an “extremely gifted painter” with deep knowledge. He added that Astrapas mixed “the ancient, classical world with Orthodox Byzantine spirituality.”</p>
<p><strong>How they did it </strong></p>
<p>The trail started with linking Astrapas to the person who wrote a book called the Marcian Codex GR 516 from the early 1300s. The book contains artwork and is handwritten in Greek. Among the painted pictures, or illustrations, is a full moon.</p>
<p>“For me ... that was the main proof,” Simonopetritis said.</p>
<p>With a name found for the person who produced the manuscript, the next step was to compare it to the writing on the painting in the Protaton church that has been traditionally linked with “Panselinos.”</p>
<p>“Mrs. Sotirakoglou, who is a handwriting expert, filled in that blank,” Simonopetritis said.</p>
<p>But women have for more than 1,000 years been banned from entering the Mount Athos religious community.</p>
<p>“I was forced to study the Protato paintings based on photographs,” Sotirakoglou told the AP. Sotirakoglou works as a court expert who examines handwriting in criminal cases.</p>
<p>The first clue came from the Greek letter “Phi,” the English “F,” in the Marcian codex manuscript.</p>
<p>“It's a Phi that stands out, and is similar” in both the manuscript and the Protato painting, she said. “Matches also followed with other letters, T, with its proportions, which is bigger, covering the other letters and is topped with a curve, the proportions of the K.”</p>
<p>“But when the Phi was revealed, the code of the writing was broken and the job became much easier,” she added.</p>
<p>Father Cosmas said that during his duties on Mount Athos he attended services at the Protaton church every day.</p>
<p>“That's where my desire was born...to explore the mystery around the name and the identity of Panselinos,” he said, adding that he thinks the artist has now gotten “his true identity.”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Costas Kantouris and Nicholas Paphitis reported this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>nickname</strong><em> – n.</em> a usually descriptive or familiar name given instead of the one belonging to a person</p>
<p><strong>monk</strong> <em>–n.</em> a male member of a religious group in certain religions who lives in a community apart from the rest of society and does not marry or hold much property</p>
<p><strong>handwriting</strong> <em>– n.</em> writing done by hand</p>
<p><strong>attribute</strong> <em>– v.</em> to consider or reckon as made in an indicated fashion</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Report: Wealth Held by Billionaires Jumped in 2024 (2024/12/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/report-wealth-held-by-billionaires-jumped-in-2024.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The Union Bank of Switzerland (UBS) Billionaire Ambitions Report for 2024 said the total number of <strong>billionaires</strong> worldwide had risen to 2,682 from 2,544 a year earlier.</p>
<p>Their worth increased to $14 trillion from $12 trillion. In 2015, their total wealth stood at $6.3 trillion.</p>
<p>The World Bank says that the world's population was just over 8 billion, and its gross domestic product, or GDP, was about $105.4 trillion last year. GDP is a measure of all the goods and services produced in a year. This shows that a very small group of people holds about 13 percent of the world's GDP.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - SpaceX CEO Elon Musk (L) shakes hands with Japanese billionaire Yusaku Maezawa who was introduced as the first SpaceX private passenger to circle the moon, in Hawthorne, California September 17, 2018. (REUTERS/Gene Blevins)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/A8DDDFCD-BAB3-4F09-AEE9-1B1EB83017F6_cx3_cy8_cw96_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - SpaceX CEO Elon Musk (L) shakes hands with Japanese billionaire Yusaku Maezawa who was introduced as the first SpaceX private passenger to circle the moon, in Hawthorne, California September 17, 2018. (REUTERS/Gene Blevins)</span></div>
<p><strong>Self-made billionaires</strong></p>
<p>The UBS report for 2023 showed that new billionaires gained more wealth through <strong>inheritance</strong> than through <strong>entrepreneurship</strong>. But most of the year's new billionaires were self-made.</p>
<p>The 2024 report was based on a study of billionaires between June and September and wealth data on the super-rich. It showed the risk of international conflict and inflation were their main worries. The study also showed that most billionaires see North America as offering the best investment returns over the next year.</p>
<p>In the United States, the number of billionaires jumped to 835 from 751, led by industrial and tech entrepreneurs, with their total wealth climbing to $5.8 trillion from $4.6 trillion.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: 9pt;">India, the world's most populous country, saw its number of billionaires increase during the past year by over a fifth to 185. Their wealth rose by more than 40 percent to almost $906 billion, UBS said.</span></p>
<p>In Western Europe, Switzerland passed Britain to become the country with the second-highest number of billionaires after Germany, increasing its total by 10 to 85. The British total dropped by one to 82, UBS said.</p>
<p>Germany with 117 (or 8 more), France with 46 (or 12 more), Italy with 62 (or 6 more) and Spain with 27 (or 3 more), all gained billionaires. The combined wealth of France's billionaires was highest among Europeans.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Jill Robbins adapted this story for Learning English from a Reuters report. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>billionaire</strong> – <em>n</em>. a rich person who has at least a billion dollars, pounds, or other currency</p>
<p><strong>inheritance</strong> – <em>n.</em> money, property, etc., that is received from someone when that person dies</p>
<p><strong>entrepreneur</strong> – <em>n</em>. a person who starts a business and is willing to risk loss in order to make money</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Rare Birth Gives Hope to Endangered Deer (2024/12/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/rare-birth-gives-hope-to-endangered-deer.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Recently, a rare pudu was born in an Argentinian zoo. The birth has given scientists and <strong>conservationists</strong> a chance to study and collect data on the small deer.</p>
<p>Pudus are one of the smallest deer <strong>species</strong> in the world. They can grow up to 50 centimeters tall and weigh up to 12 kilograms. At birth, the white-spotted male pudu weighed just 1.21 kilograms.</p>
<p>Workers at the conservation organization Temaiken Foundation named it Lenga after a tree species in the Andean Patagonian Forest of Chile and Argentina.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A rare pudu fawn born earlier this month is seen next to its mother, at the Temaiken Foundation, in Buenos Aires, Argentina, Nov. 22, 2024. (REUTERS/Alessia Maccioni)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e83c31f7-075b-44c5-9de6-a8365eb7abb7_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A rare pudu fawn born earlier this month is seen next to its mother, at the Temaiken Foundation, in Buenos Aires, Argentina, Nov. 22, 2024. (REUTERS/Alessia Maccioni)</span></div>
<p>"It's a very <strong>enigmatic</strong> animal. It's not easy to see," said Maximiliano Krause. He is Lenga's caretaker at the nonprofit organization.</p>
<p>Krause says Lenga is spending his days exploring the park with his mother, Chalten, and father, Nicolino. Lenga is breastfeeding for the first two months until he can eat plants on his own.</p>
<p>After that, Lenga will lose his white spots and the spotty skin color that helps small deer hide from both daytime and nighttime <strong>predators</strong>. At about one year, pudus develop antlers and reach up to 10 centimeters.</p>
<p>Pudus are very elusive animals. In other words, they are hard to find and difficult to see in the wild. When chased by predators, they escape in a <strong>zig-zag</strong> manner. The small deer also face threats from wild dogs and species introduced into southern Argentina and Chile.</p>
<p>Only about 10,000 pudus remain in the wild. They are <strong>classified</strong> as near-threatened by the International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN).</p>
<p>"This pudu birth is obviously a joy for us," said Cristian Guillet. He is the director of zoological operations at the Temaiken Foundation.</p>
<p>Guillet said that Lenga will help them research and gather data that will help conservation efforts for pudus and other Patagonian deer, like the huemul.</p>
<p>"(This) offers hope of saving them from <strong>extinction</strong>," Guillet said.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Lucila Sigal and Alexander Villegas reported this story for Reuters. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>conservationist </strong><em>– n.</em><strong> </strong>a person who is in favor of conservation especially of natural resources (as forests)</p>
<p><strong>species </strong><em>– n. </em>a category of living things that ranks below a genus, is made up of related individuals able to produce fertile offspring, and is identified by a two-part scientific name</p>
<p><strong>enigmatic </strong><em>– adj. </em>of, relating to, or resembling a puzzle or enigma : mysterious</p>
<p><strong>predator </strong><em>– n.</em> an animal that obtains food mostly by killing and eating other animals</p>
<p><strong>zig-zag </strong><em>– adv. </em>one of a series of short sharp turns, angles, or alterations in a course</p>
<p><strong>classify </strong><em>– v. </em>to consider (someone or something) as belonging to a particular group : to arrange in classes that have systematic relations usually founded on common properties</p>
<p><strong>extinction </strong><em>– n. </em>the process of no longer existing : an act of extinguishing or an instance of being extinguished</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>New Study Examines Whether Venus Had Liquid Water (2024/12/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/new-study-examines-whether-venus-had-liquid-water.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A new study suggests that Venus likely never had water flowing on its surface. The research was based on data related to the chemical makeup of the planet's atmosphere.</p>
<p>Scientists have long considered whether Venus once held liquid water, even possibly large oceans. Such research was based on the fact that Venus is like our own planet in many ways. It is a rocky planet similar in structure and size to Earth and is also our closest planetary neighbor.</p>
<p>But the latest study provides evidence that Venus has likely always been the hot, extremely dry planet it remains today. Researchers from Britain's University of Cambridge led the study. It recently <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41550-024-02414-5">appeared</a> in the publication <em>Nature Astronomy</em>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This file photo, provided by NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory, shows a computer-generated 3D model of Venus' surface. (NASA/JPL/Handout via REUTERS)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/29dfc8bd-80f6-481a-a39e-d0065ce57aec_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This file photo, provided by NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory, shows a computer-generated 3D model of Venus' surface. (NASA/JPL/Handout via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>The researchers' data examinations led them to conclude that both the surface and interior of Venus remain dry. The team said the strongest evidence that Venus once had large amounts of water would be the discovery of some water inside the planet today. But the study provided no evidence of that.</p>
<p>Since water is considered an important element for supporting life, the researchers also suggest that Venus was likely never habitable, or able to support life.</p>
<p>The lead writer of the study was Tereza Constantinou, a doctoral student at the University of Cambridge's Institute of Astronomy. She told Reuters news agency, "We suggest that a habitable past would be associated with Venus' present interior being water-rich, and a dry past with Venus' present interior being dry.”</p>
<p>The researchers <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cam.ac.uk/research/news/researchers-deal-a-blow-to-theory-that-venus-once-had-liquid-water-on-its-surface">explained</a> they attempted to measure the current destruction rate of molecules in water, carbon dioxide and carbonyl sulfide in Venus' atmosphere. The state of the planet's atmosphere is linked to volcanic activity, the team said.</p>
<p>“Volcanism, through its supply of gases to the atmosphere, provides a window into the interior of rocky planets like Venus,” the researchers wrote <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cam.ac.uk/research/news/researchers-deal-a-blow-to-theory-that-venus-once-had-liquid-water-on-its-surface">in a statement</a>. “As <strong>magma</strong> rises from the <strong>mantle</strong> to the surface, it releases gases from the deeper portions of the planet.</p>
<p>Volcanic explosions, or eruptions, can provide information on the amount of water contained deep below a planet's surface, the scientists said.</p>
<p>On Earth, for example, volcanic eruptions mostly release steam, a <strong>vapor</strong> created when water gets heated. Measurements of volcanic gases on Earth have shown they release about 60 percent water vapor.</p>
<p>But the researchers said their examinations suggested volcanic gases released on Venus were less than 6 percent water vapor. This persuaded the team to conclude that the planet's interior – the source of the magma that releases volcanic gases – must be very dry.</p>
<p>The team noted that scientists have had two leading theories on the history of water on Venus. The first is that the planet had a moderate climate for billions of years, with liquid water flowing over areas of the surface. Over time, widespread volcanic activity likely led to extreme heat and dry conditions that made the water disappear.</p>
<p>The second theory imagined Venus as being very hot from the beginning, preventing liquid water from ever forming on the surface.</p>
<p>Constantinou said, “Both of those theories are based on climate models, but we wanted to take a different <strong>approach</strong> based on observations of Venus' current atmospheric chemistry.” She added that the team did not find evidence that any chemicals being removed from the atmosphere were later being restored.</p>
<p>This provides strong evidence that Venus has a very dry interior today, the scientists concluded. "The atmospheric chemistry suggests that volcanic eruptions on Venus release very little water, <strong>implying</strong> that the planet's interior...is equally dry,” Constantinou said.</p>
<p>She added that her team “would have loved to find that Venus was once a planet much closer to our own.” However, Constantinou noted the finding suggests that researchers should center their searches “on planets that are mostly likely to be able to support life – at least life as we know it.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from Reuters and the University of Cambridge. </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>magma</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> hot liquid rock found just below the surface of the Earth</p>
<p><strong>mantle </strong><em>– n.</em> a layer of something that covers a surface</p>
<p><strong>vapor</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> many small drops of liquid that form in the air</p>
<p><strong>approach </strong><em>– n. </em>the way something is done</p>
<p><strong>imply</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to communicate an idea or feeling without saying it directly</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>California Proposes Plan to Protect Its Famous Joshua Trees (2024/12/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/california-proposes-plan-to-protect-its-famous-joshua-trees.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The California Department of Fish and Wildlife has released a proposed plan to protect the state's famous Joshua trees. Environmentalists say the trees are threatened by wildfires, human development and climate change.</p>
<p>An early version of the plan calls for avoiding or reducing direct and indirect effects of <strong>overgrazing</strong>, insect-killing chemical use and <strong>off-roading</strong> activity. The plan advises moving trees when projects require their removal or could harm them. It also calls for identifying and protecting lands where the trees could survive if the climate in southern California becomes drier and hotter.</p>
<p>“In many ways, it's a good <strong>comprehensive</strong> plan of the things we need to do if the western Joshua tree is going to survive the very, very difficult <strong>decades</strong> ahead,” said Brendan Cummings. He is conservation director with the Center for Biological Diversity based in Tucson, Arizona. The nonprofit group asked the California government in 2019 to list the western Joshua tree as threatened under the state's Endangered Species Act.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A Joshua tree is silhouetted in front of the Bobcat Fire at sunset Saturday, Sept. 19, 2020, in Juniper Hills, California. (AP Photo/Marcio Jose Sanchez, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/0c078bdf-94cd-4a36-82c1-b900d89b9dec_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A Joshua tree is silhouetted in front of the Bobcat Fire at sunset Saturday, Sept. 19, 2020, in Juniper Hills, California. (AP Photo/Marcio Jose Sanchez, File)</span></div>
<p>The conservation plan is a requirement by the Western Joshua Tree Conservation Act. California lawmakers passed the act last year. It is the first law in the state to protect a species from the threats of climate change. The law also bars anyone from killing, damaging, or removing a tree without state permission.</p>
<p>The proposed plan lists ways to help identify land that should be recognized as most important for conservation. This includes large areas with Joshua trees or areas with a high density of healthy and adult trees. The plan suggests placing restrictions on areas where there is low risk of such threats as fires, invasive plants and animals, development and where <strong>pollinators</strong> and seed-spreading animals exist. It aims to identify these lands by December 2025 and place permanent restrictions on 70 percent of them by 2033.</p>
<p>The plan also calls on land <strong>managers</strong> and wildfire workers to create methods to reduce and fight wildfires that threaten the trees and lessen effects from <strong>rehabilitating</strong> burned areas. That includes protecting trees, replanting them, planting other native species, and controlling invasive ones.</p>
<p>The proposed plan says, its effectiveness and the survival of the trees will mainly depend on whether reductions can be made in the release of heat-trapping gases. Such emissions come mainly from burning coal, oil and gas.</p>
<p>Cummings said climate change could destroy most, if not all, of the areas where the trees live if the situation does not change.</p>
<p>If emissions are limited as planned, Cummings said, “we have a very good chance of saving the species if all the things outlined in this plan are carried out. And primarily that's doing what we can to protect as many of them as possible."</p>
<p>Approval from California's Fish and Game Commission is necessary for the proposed plan to go into effect.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted the story for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>over-grazing </strong><em>– n.</em> the act of permitting animals to graze (an area, such as a field) to the point of damaging vegetational cover</p>
<p><strong>off-roading</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n</em>. the activity of driving a vehicle in a place where there is no road</p>
<p><strong>comprehensive</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj</em>. covering completely or broadly</p>
<p><strong>decade</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a period of 10 years</p>
<p><strong>pollinator</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> an agent (such as an insect) that pollinates flowers</p>
<p><strong>rehabilitate </strong><em>– v. </em>to restore or bring to a condition of health or useful and constructive activity</p>
<p><strong>manager</strong> <em>– n.</em> a person who runs a business or organization</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>'Show Your Hand', other Card Idioms (2024/12/8)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/show-your-hand-other-card-idioms.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">07 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Playing cards is a popular <strong>pastime</strong> for people of all ages. Some games are easy, while others are complex. And people of <u>all walks of life</u> play cards. A set of playing cards is called a deck. A deck of cards is not costly and can be bought almost anywhere.</p>
<p>With one deck of 52 cards, you can play many different games. Some of the games include poker, blackjack, bridge, rummy, 500, snap, hearts, and crazy eights ... just to name a few.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Finance professionals learn how to play guandan, a poker-like card game, during a training session in Beijing, China, August 6, 2023. (REUTERS/Yew Lun Tian)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-ae30-08dbad65d3e9_cx17_cy17_cw82_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Finance professionals learn how to play guandan, a poker-like card game, during a training session in Beijing, China, August 6, 2023. (REUTERS/Yew Lun Tian)</span></div>
<p>The deck of cards also gives the English language many <strong>idioms</strong>. Today we will talk about a few of them.</p>
<p>To win at many card games, you must keep your cards hidden from the other players. In many games, the cards you are <strong>dealt </strong>and play with are called your “hand.” If your opponents know your hand, they can easily beat you. Some players keep their cards hidden by holding them to their chest.</p>
<p>In life, you might need to keep some parts of a plan hidden or secret for them to succeed. You might need to <u>keep your cards close to your chest</u>. This idiom means to keep your plans, <strong>intentions</strong> or methods secret.</p>
<p>However, with most card games, players must show their cards to the other players at some point, sometimes at the end of the game.</p>
<p>This gives us two similar idioms – <u>to show your hand</u> and <u>to lay your cards on the table</u>.</p>
<p>As an idiom, to <u>show your hand</u> or your cards means to tell people your plans or intentions that you had kept hidden.</p>
<p>The same is true of <u>laying your cards on the table</u>. In many card games, the players must show their cards by placing them face up on the table for everyone to see. When we put our cards on the table, we show something that we have kept hidden. These can be things like our reasons for doing something, our intentions or our opinions.</p>
<p>Now, in a game of cards, luck or chance plays an important part. You must play with the cards you are dealt. This is the case in life, too. Not everything is a choice. Sometimes we must deal with things that are out of our control. We must <u>play with the cards we are dealt</u>. We can also say <u>play the hand we are dealt</u>.</p>
<p>So, luck is part of the game. We cannot know or predict<strong> </strong>the cards we are dealt. But sometimes other players cheat. They can do this by <strong><u>stacking</u></strong><u> the deck</u>. When you <u>stack the deck</u>, you add cards to the deck that will help you win. This gives you an unfair <strong>advantage</strong>.</p>
<p>In life, we can sometimes feel that things are <u>stacked against us</u>. This means that no matter how hard we try, we still struggle. We feel as though life has <u>dealt us a bad hand,</u> and we must struggle and fight to gain anything at all.</p>
<p>For example, if the <u>deck is stacked</u> against you, the <strong><u>odds</u></strong><u> are not in your <strong>favor</strong></u>. You might have to struggle against all odds to succeed.</p>
<p>These are just a few of the idioms English gets from a deck of cards. There are many more.</p>
<p>But that's all the time we have today. Keep listening to <em>Words and Their Stories </em>to learn more!</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>_____________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>pastime </strong>–n. an activity done for enjoyment in one's free time</p>
<p><strong>idiom </strong>–n. an expression in language that has a meaning different from the words' literal meaning</p>
<p><strong>intention </strong>–n. what someone means to do but which might not be clear from what they say or do</p>
<p><strong>stack </strong>–v. to place on thing on top of another</p>
<p><strong>advantage </strong>–n. a positive or good result that is gained from an action</p>
<p><strong>odds </strong>–n. (pl.) the likelihood that something will or will not happen</p>
<p><strong>favor </strong>–n. something that happens to help or support a person</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Peruvian Women Heal Themselves with Song, Art (2024/12/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/peruvian-women-heal-themselves-with-song-art.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The 36-year-old Peruvian artist Sadith Silvano makes creations born of ancient songs.</p>
<p>Brush in hand, eyes on the cloth, the Peruvian woman paints as she sings. And through her voice, her ancestors speak.</p>
<p>“When we paint, we listen to the inspiration that comes from the music and connect to nature, to our elders,” said Silvano.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Sadith Silvano, from Paoyhan, a Shipibo-Konibo Indigenous community in the Amazon, puts on an earring at her home and workshop where she hand-paints textiles in Lima, Peru, Saturday, Oct. 19, 2024. (AP Photo/Guadalupe Pardo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/0c0d2e78-757b-4beb-8d0f-15b030e4ebda_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Sadith Silvano, from Paoyhan, a Shipibo-Konibo Indigenous community in the Amazon, puts on an earring at her home and workshop where she hand-paints textiles in Lima, Peru, Saturday, Oct. 19, 2024. (AP Photo/Guadalupe Pardo)</span></div>
<p>The artist now lives and works in Lima, Peru, where she moved 20 years ago from Paoyhan. It is a Shipibo-Konibo Indigenous community located in the Amazon.</p>
<p>“These pieces are sacred,” she added. “We bless our work with the energy of our songs.”</p>
<p>Official data says close to 33,000 Shipibo-Konibo people live in Peru. They are believed to come from the surroundings of the Uyacali river. Many moved to urban areas like Cantagallo, the Lima neighborhood where Silvano lives.</p>
<p>Hand-painted textiles like the ones she makes have slowly gained recognition. Known as “kené,” these works were declared part of the “Cultural Heritage of the Nation” by the Peruvian government in 2008.</p>
<p>Each kené is special, Shipibo craftswomen say. Every design speaks of a woman's community, her worldview and beliefs.</p>
<p>“Every design tells a story,” Silvano said while dressed in traditional clothing. “It is a way in which a Shipibo woman distinguishes herself.”</p>
<p>Paoyhan, where Silvano was born, is far from Lima. To get there requires an airplane flight and a 12-hour boat trip.</p>
<p>In her hometown, locals rarely speak languages other than Shipibo. Doors and windows there have no locks.</p>
<p>Adela Sampayo, a 48-year-old healer who was born not too far from Paoyhan, moved to Cantagallo in 2000.</p>
<p>But she says that all her skills come from the Amazon River area.</p>
<p>“Since I was a little girl, my mom treated me with traditional medicine,” said Sampayo. “She gave me plants to become stronger, to avoid getting sick, to be courageous,” she added. “That's how the energy of the plants started growing inside me.”</p>
<p>Sampayo, too, communicates her worldview through her textiles. Though she does not paint, she embroiders, and each thread tells a tale from home.</p>
<p>“Each plant has a spirit,” said the healer, pointing to the leaves embroidered in the cloth. “And medicinal plants come from God.”</p>
<p>The plants painted by Silvano also bear meaning. One of them represents pure love. Another represents a wise man. And another, a serpent.</p>
<p>“The anaconda is special for us,” Silvano said. “It's our protector, like a god that cares for us and provides food and water.”</p>
<p>In ancient times, she said, her people believed that the sun was their father, and the anacondas were their guardians. Colonization brought Catholicism and their worldview changed.</p>
<p>“Nowadays we have different religions...but we respect our other beliefs too,” Silvano said.</p>
<p>For many years, after her father took her to Lima hoping for a better future, she thought of her time in the jungle. Life in Paoyhan was not easy, but she learned to be strong at a young age.</p>
<p>“When we encounter difficult times, we overcome them with our therapy: designing, painting, singing,” Silvano said. “We have a song that is melodic and heals our soul, and another one that is inspiring and brings us joy.”</p>
<p>Few Shipibo girls are told to study or make a living of their own, Silvano said. Instead, they are taught to wait for a husband. And once married, they are taught to deal with problems, difficulties, or bad treatment.</p>
<p>“Even though we suffer, people tell us: Take it, he's the father of your children. Take it, he is your husband,” Silvano said. “But deep inside, we are wounded. So what do we do? We sing.”</p>
<p>The lesson is taught by mothers to daughters: If you are hurt at home, grab your cloth, your brush and leave. Go far away, alone, and sit. Connect with your kené and paint. And while you paint, sing.</p>
<p>“That's our healing,” Silvano said. “Through our songs, our kenés, we are free.”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Maria Teresa Hernandez reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>brush</strong> <em>– n</em>. a device with bristles typically set into a handle and used especially for painting</p>
<p><strong>inspiration </strong><em>– n.</em> a divine influence or action on a person believed to qualify him or her to receive and communicate sacred revelation</p>
<p><strong>sacred</strong> <em>– adj. </em>of or relating to religion, worthy of respect</p>
<p><strong>courageous</strong> <em>–adj.</em> showing the ability to do difficult things</p>
<p><strong>textile </strong><em>– n.</em> a woven or knit cloth</p>
<p><strong>craftswoman</strong> <em>–n.</em> a woman who is skilled in a craft</p>
<p><strong>distinguish </strong><em>– v. </em>to mark as separate or different</p>
<p><strong>embroider</strong> <em>– v.</em> to decorate with needlework</p>
<p><strong>anaconda<em> </em></strong><em>– n. </em>a large kind of constricting snake</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How the Animals Lost Their Tails by Carl Sandburg (2024/12/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/american-stories-how-the-animals-lost-their-tails-by-carl-sandburg.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p><strong>Introduction:</strong></p>
<p><em>Today's story is How the Animals Lost Their Tails and Got Them Back Traveling from Philadelphia to Medicine Hat. It appeared in the book Rootabaga Stories by Carl Sandburg, published in 1922.</em></p>
<p><em>Sandburg was a very famous American poet. He wrote Rootabaga Stories for his three daughters Margaret, Janet and Helga. The stories make liberal use of repetition and nonsense language, a fun form of word play.</em></p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e9b8d234-737f-4e19-8c46-ee5932263831_w100_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p><em>Listen closely to the language of this story about talking animals with a big problem.</em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<p>Far up in North America, near the Saskatchewan River in Winnipeg wheat country not far from the town of Moose Jaw, where nobody works unless they have to, and they nearly all have to, there is a place known as Medicine Hat.</p>
<p>There, on top of a high tower in a high chair, sits the Head Spotter of the Weather Makers.</p>
<p>When the animals lost their tails, it was because the Head Spotter got careless.</p>
<p><strong>How all the animals lost their tails</strong></p>
<p>You see, the tails of the animals were hard and dry because of a stretch of hot, dusty weather. Then, at last, came a rain. It poured down on the animals' tails and softened them.</p>
<p>But then a cold wind came and froze all the tails solid. A big wind followed and blew and blew and blew until all the animals' tails flew off their bodies.</p>
<p>It was easy for the hogs with their short tails. But it was not so easy for the blue fox, who uses his tail to run and to write secret letters in the snow.</p>
<p>It was easy for the rabbit and her little white tail. But it was hard for the yellow flongboo who lights up her home in the hollow tree with her bright tail.</p>
<p>The animals decided to choose a committee of representatives to represent them in parleyhoo to see what steps could be taken by talking to do something.</p>
<p>There were 66 representatives on the committee. They decided to call it the Committee of Sixty Six.</p>
<p>For a chairperson they picked the top flongboo. When there was a fight among the flongboo families, she was the one who would say who was right and who was wrong.</p>
<p>She was from Chappaquiddick and lived there in a horse chestnut tree between South Hadley and Northampton.</p>
<p>After her nomination and election, she brought the Committee of Sixty Six to order.</p>
<p>“It is <strong>no picnic</strong> to lose your tail and we are here for business,” she said banging the <strong>gavel</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>The blue fox's proposal</strong></p>
<p>Then a blue fox from Waco, Texas stood up and said, “Madam Chairwoman, do I have the floor?”</p>
<p>That is a way of saying, “May I speak?”</p>
<p>“I <strong>make a motion</strong>,” said the blue fox.</p>
<p>“I <strong>move</strong> that this committee get on a train at Philadelphia and ride on the train until it stops and then take another train until we get to Medicine Hat where the Head Spotter of the Weather Makers sits. There, we will ask if he will bring back our tails.”</p>
<p>The Chairwoman said, “All in favor of the motion will clean their right ears with their right paws.”</p>
<p>And all the blue foxes and yellow flongboos began cleaning their right ears with their right paws.</p>
<p>“All who oppose the motion will clean their left ears with their left paws,” said the chairwoman.</p>
<p>And all the blue foxes and yellow flongboos began cleaning their left ears with their left paws.</p>
<p>“The motion is carried both ways, it's a <strong>razzamatazz</strong>,” said the chairwoman.</p>
<p>“Once again, all in favor of the motion will stand up on their toes.”</p>
<p>And all the blue foxes and all the yellow flongboos stood up.</p>
<p>“And now,” said the chairwoman, “all who are against the motion will stand on the top of their heads, stick their hind legs up in the air, and make a noise like woof, woof.”</p>
<p>No one opposed the motion.</p>
<p>“The motion is carried,” said the chairwoman.</p>
<p>So the committee went to Philadelphia to get the train to Medicine Hat.</p>
<p>The Chairwoman asked a policeman there: “Would you be so kind as to tell us the way to the Union Depot.”</p>
<p>“It pays to be <strong>polite</strong>,” said the policeman.</p>
<p>“May I ask you again if you would kindly direct us to the Union Depot where the train is?” asked the flongboo again.</p>
<p>“Polite persons and angry persons are different kinds,” said the policeman.</p>
<p>The flongboo's eyes changed their light, and a slow fire burned from where her tail used to be.</p>
<p>She said, “Sir, I must inform you that we are The Committee of Sixty Six. We are <strong>distinguished</strong> representatives from places you do not know. This committee is going to ride to Medicine Hat with a special message and a secret <strong>errand</strong> for the Head Spotter of the Weather Makers.”</p>
<p>“I am a polite friend of all respectable people,” said the policeman touching the star on his chest.</p>
<p>“This is the first time ever in the history of the United States that a committee of sixty-six has ever visited a city in the United States,” said the flongboo.</p>
<p>“I beg to be mistaken,” finished the policeman. “The Union Depot is under that clock.” And he pointed to a big clock nearby.</p>
<p><strong>The train trip to Medicine Hat</strong></p>
<p>Over to Union Depot train station they went, all sixty-six, half foxes, half flongboos.</p>
<p>“They are speaking in some strange language from where they come from,” said one passenger.</p>
<p>“They have secrets to keep among each other, and never tell us,” said another passenger.</p>
<p>“We will find out all about it in the newspapers tomorrow,” said a third passenger.</p>
<p>Then the foxes and flongboos climbed into a special car.</p>
<p>The train left the station. It came to the Horseshoe Curve near Altoona where the tracks bend in a half circle. Then it went on toward Ohio.</p>
<p>Two baby blue foxes, the youngest on the committee, sat at the front of the car.</p>
<p>Crossing Ohio and Indiana at night the flongboos took off the top of the car. The conductor told them, “I must have an explanation.” “It is between us and the stars,” they told him.</p>
<p>The train ran on to Chicago. There were pictures in the newspapers that afternoon showing foxes and flongboos eating pink ice cream with iron <strong>axes</strong>.</p>
<p>Each blue fox and yellow flongboo got their own newspaper.</p>
<p>Crossing to the north the sky began to fill with the snow ghosts of Minnesota. Again the foxes and flongboos lifted the top off the car so they would not miss the show.</p>
<p>Some went to sleep but the two baby blue foxes stayed up watching the snow ghosts and telling snow ghost stories to each other.</p>
<p>Early in the night the first baby blue fox said to the second, “Who are the snow ghosts the ghosts of?” The second baby blue fox answered, “Snow men, snow foxes and snow fishes, everybody has a snow ghost.”</p>
<p>And that was only the beginning of their talk. They would talk until morning about where the snow ghosts go on Christmas morning and how the snow ghosts watch the New Year.</p>
<p>Somewhere between Winnipeg and Moose Jaw, they stopped the train and all ran out in the snow. The white moon was shining down a valley of birch trees.</p>
<p>At last they came to Medicine Hat, near the Saskatchewan River in Winnipeg wheat country not far from the town of Moose Jaw, where nobody works unless they have to, and they nearly all have to.</p>
<p>There they ran to the place where the Head Spotter of the Weather Makers sits in a high chair on a high tower watching the weather.</p>
<p>“Let loose another big wind to blow back our tails, let loose a big freeze to freeze our tails back on, and let us get back our lost tails,” they said to the Head Spotter.</p>
<p>Which was just what he did, giving them exactly what they wanted, so they all went back home satisfied.</p>
<p><em>Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted this public domain story by Carl Sandburg for VOA Learning English.</em></p><p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>no picnic </strong><em>– idiom </em>a difficult thing to do or an unpleasant experience</p>
<p><strong>gavel</strong> <em>– n.</em> a small hammer that is used for getting attention in a court or a formal meeting of officials or lawmakers</p>
<p><strong>have the floor </strong>– <em>idiom</em> have the right to speak at a public meeting</p>
<p><strong>make a motion </strong>– <em>idiom</em> to formally propose something in a debate or formal proceedings</p>
<p><strong>move </strong>– <em>v</em>. (formal) to propose that something be done</p>
<p><strong>razzamatazz </strong>– <em>n</em>. noisy and excited activity meant to attract attention</p>
<p><strong>hind legs </strong>– n<em>. (pl.)</em> the two back legs of a four-legged animal</p>
<p><strong>polite </strong>– <em>adj.</em> showing good manners and respect for others</p>
<p><strong>distinguished </strong>– <em>adj.</em> known by many people for some special quality or something done in the past</p>
<p><strong>errand </strong>– <em>n</em>. a short trip aimed at getting something done</p>
<p><strong>ax</strong> - <em>n.</em> a tool used for cutting wood</p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<p><em>We have a new comment system. Here is how it works: </em></p>
<ol>
<li><em>Write your comment in the box.</em></li>
<li><em>Under the box, you can see four images for social media accounts. They are for Disqus, Facebook, Twitter and Google.</em></li>
<li><em>Click on one image and a box appears. Enter the login for your social media account. Or you may create one on the Disqus system. It is the blue circle with “D” on it. It is free.</em></li></ol>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Notes about ‘Being’ (2024/12/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/notes-about-being.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Tayyab in Pakistan about a form of the verb “be” in English.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear Teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/499c6236-13c1-4ee9-90c9-d6b651dac57c_w268_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>I am always confused when it comes to the usage of “being.”</p>
<p>Thank you,</p>
<p>Tayyab</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Tayyab.</p>
<p>Let's start by considering a basic way we use the <strong>verb</strong> “be” in English. We commonly use this verb to link, or join, a subject with its description. The description will often be a noun or an <strong>adjective</strong>. The following two examples show this:</p>
<p><em>That man is a farmer.</em></p>
<p><em>That man is rich. </em></p>
<p>Expanding on this use of the verb “be,” we can call a description of how a person feels and experiences his or her life as a “state of being.” A state of being can last for a short or a long time. However, a state of being is longer than a momentary feeling. The following examples show this usage:</p>
<p><em>In retirement, her <u>state of being</u> became more relaxed.</em></p>
<p><em>His <u>state of being</u> has not been good in recent months. </em></p>
<p>We can also use the word “being” to begin a description. This can help us describe something or someone in one sentence instead of two. For example, we could use two sentences to describe a man who does not speak very much with other people:</p>
<p><em>Mr. Jones was someone who spoke very little. He sat quietly while others did the talking</em>.</p>
<p>But if we use the word “being,” we can express this idea in one sentence, as in the following example:</p>
<p><em><u>Being a man of few words</u></em><em>, Mr. Jones sat quietly while others did the talking. </em></p>
<p>Here is another example of changing a description from two sentences to one sentence:</p>
<p><em>Manut was very tall. That is why he decided to play basketball instead of football. </em></p>
<p><em><u>Being very tall</u></em><em>, Manut decided to play basketball instead of football. </em></p>
<p>We can also use the word “being,” combined with the noun or adjective that follows it, as the subject of a sentence. Consider the following examples:</p>
<p><em><u>Being a parent</u></em><em> has helped me better understand my own parents. </em></p>
<p><em><u>Being open to criticism</u></em><em> will help you improve your work. </em></p>
<p>In these examples, the phrases “being a parent” and “being open to criticism” are the subjects of the sentences.</p>
<p>Lastly, we can use the word “being” as a noun to describe a highly intelligent form of life. Humans are beings, and somewhere in the universe, other intelligent beings might exist.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? We'd like to hear from you. Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please include where you are from in your email, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>verb </strong><em>–n.</em> a word that describes action or existence</p>
<p><strong>adjective </strong><em>–n.</em> a word that gives additional information about or modifies a noun</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Vienna Sausage Stand Gets UNESCO Recognition (2024/12/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/vienna-sausage-stand-gets-unesco-recognition.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">05 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A popular kind of sausage stand in Vienna, Austria has been recognized by the United Nations for its cultural value.</p>
<p>The street stands – called “Würstelstands” in German – are a famous part of the Austrian capital's history. In addition to selling food, they are known for being a place where many different kinds of people can come together to eat and spend social time.</p>
<p>UNESCO is the United Nations' Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization. It seeks to recognize and help save cultural treasures and traditions around the world.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="Customers line up at a traditional sausage stand (Wuerstelstand), which are named as intangible cultural heritage by the Austrian UNESCO Commission, in Vienna, Austria, Thursday, Nov. 28, 2024. (AP Photo/Heinz-Peter Bader)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/7bf267af-b0e8-43c0-a48d-30d528a0b887_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">Customers line up at a traditional sausage stand (Wuerstelstand), which are named as intangible cultural heritage by the Austrian UNESCO Commission, in Vienna, Austria, Thursday, Nov. 28, 2024. (AP Photo/Heinz-Peter Bader)</span></div>
<p>Vienna's Würstelstands were recently added to a list of the country's “<strong>intangible</strong> cultural <strong>heritage</strong>.” The Austrian UNESCO Commission oversees the list.</p>
<p>Among other things on the list are Vienna's traditional wine establishments – called “Heurigen” – which were recognized in 2019. In addition, the city's famous coffee house culture was honored in 2011.</p>
<p>The Associated Press reports the history of Würstelstands goes back generations. And they are known for much more than the tasty sausages they serve. They have been bringing people of many different backgrounds together for many years. The stands have also developed some of their own terms.</p>
<p>These include the “Haasse,” a special kind of boiled sausage. Another unusual stand offering is known as the “Kasekrainer” – a smoked creation filled with cheese. And there is “Oaschpfeiferl,” a spicy peperoni version, as well as the <strong>pickled</strong> “Krokodü.”</p>
<p>Josef Bitzinger runs the Bitzinger Würstelstand. He told the AP that sausage stands have a long history in Vienna." His stand enjoys a favorable spot, next to the city's Albertina museum and just behind the Vienna State Opera.</p>
<p>“<strong>Originally</strong> it was just a bucket with hot water in which the sausages used to swim," Bitzinger said. He added that the stands began with small vehicles pulled by dogs or horses. Later, they were transported by cars or big trucks.</p>
<p>The tradition of Würstelstand goes back to the pre-World War I days of the Austro-Hungarian Empire. At that time, former soldiers set up movable cooking shops to make a living.</p>
<p>The city's longest-serving stand in a fixed spot is Würstelstand Leo. It has been serving up sausages since 1928. The stands started to develop quickly in 1969, when the government decided to begin approving fixed stands.</p>
<p>Vienna's mayor, Michael Ludwig, said he thinks the UNESCO recognition “honors the tradition, the <strong>hospitality</strong> and the <strong>diversity</strong> of our city.” He added that the stands remain a big part of the city's culture.</p>
<p>Bitzinger said he and other owners had long campaigned for the UNESCO recognition. “The special thing about it is that it's a form of <strong>gastronomy</strong> everybody can <strong>afford</strong>."</p>
<p>Bitzinger added, "Here the general director and, during the opera ball, a <strong>celebrity</strong> stands next to a worker and the street sweeper who just finished cleaning the street. That unites people.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>intangible</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj.</em> a quality that exists but is difficult to describe or prove</p>
<p><strong>pickled </strong><em>– adj.</em> a process by which food is put into vinegar or salt water and stored for a long time</p>
<p><strong>heritage</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> the buildings, paintings, customers, etc. that have existed for a long time and are important in a culture or society</p>
<p><strong>original </strong><em>– adj.</em> existing since the beginning</p>
<p><strong>hospitality </strong><em>– n.</em> the foods, drinks and entertainment provided by or organization or business</p>
<p><strong>diversity </strong><em>– n.</em> the fact that there are many different kinds of things or people included in something</p>
<p><strong>gastronomy</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> the art and knowledge used in preparing and eating good food</p>
<p><strong>afford </strong><em>– v.</em> able to pay for something</p>
<p><strong>celebrity</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a famous person</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>People on Island Near Singapore Face Uncertain Future (2024/12/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/people-on-island-near-singapore-face-uncertain-future.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A short boat ride from the wealthy city-state of Singapore is something rare – a small, quiet island.</p>
<p>People living on Pulau Ubin still talk about the arrival of solar power 11 years ago. They call it a “<strong>miracle</strong>.”</p>
<p>Although the electricity was expensive, Chu Yok Choon said he loved the <strong>convenience</strong>. He could just press a button, and a pump would send water to his home from the village well. Until 2013, Chu had to carry water from the well by hand and use <strong>generators</strong> to provide electricity.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A visitor leaves Changi ferry terminal on a boat to visit Singapore's Pulau Ubin island, November 1, 2024. (REUTERS/Edgar Su)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/bba78e9f-d4cf-4877-b560-5863da0765a0_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A visitor leaves Changi ferry terminal on a boat to visit Singapore's Pulau Ubin island, November 1, 2024. (REUTERS/Edgar Su)</span></div>
<p>Chu is one of 30 people living on Pulau Ubin. The island measures only 10 square kilometers. He spoke to Reuters recently and compared life on the island to life in Singapore, or as he calls it, the mainland.</p>
<p>"Life on the mainland doesn't feel natural," said the 79-year-old. "Life here is quieter."</p>
<p>Pulau Ubin includes forest areas and wetlands. The wetlands were once under threat from development until the plans were postponed.</p>
<p>The island offers visitors walks along thick greenery and lakes that were formed from rock <strong>quarries</strong>. They can ride bicycles on roads free of vehicles and eat seafood meals by the water's edge.</p>
<p>For those living in Singapore, the island is an escape. It can be reached in about 10 minutes by ferry. But for those who live on the island, those ferry rides can be inconvenient. Trips to the mainland to buy food and other necessities can be delayed.</p>
<p>Also, ferries can be costly. For visits to the city, Chu said he would have to wait until the ferry filled up with 12 passengers. Each person pays $3. This cost is similar to Singapore's public transportation. But if he is in a hurry, he would have to pay $36 for the whole boat.</p>
<p>Still, the residents stay. They say they are enjoying a life different from the busy, <strong>stressful </strong>conditions in the city.</p>
<p>"The energy is so <strong>fantastic</strong>," said 54-year-old Koh Bee Choo. She lives in a house on top of wooden supports that extends out over the water.</p>
<p>"I go for morning walks and I <strong>absorb</strong> the energy in the jungle," added Koh. She lived in Singapore for nearly five years but returned to the island to run a bicycle rental shop.</p>
<p>While the older generation enjoys island life, their children have moved to the city after going there to attend school.</p>
<p>This has left an aging population. The island's youngest residents are in their 50s. <strong>Conservation</strong> experts worry about the island's future. No one is permitted to move to the island from the city. In 2001, the government said the island was safe from changes until changes are required for development.</p>
<p>At the height of its popularity, almost 4,000 people lived on the island. They worked in granite quarries and on farms. But the largest quarry closed in 1970. Then, many people moved to the city where a policy to develop industry grew the economy and covered a once-struggling nation in new developments, roads and factories.</p>
<p><strong>A disappearing way of life</strong></p>
<p>Each June for the past nine years, Singaporean officials have celebrated "Ubin Day." The goal is to help people value and love the island's heritage and ecosystem, the National Parks Board says on its website.</p>
<p>Games and enrichment <strong>booths </strong>mark the celebration. So do plans for the island's future.</p>
<p>In 1991, the government stopped a plan to extend the subway to the island. Now there are talks about saving the island for future generations. But there will come a day when no one will live there anymore.</p>
<p>"The old people have died off, one by one...,” said Chu. He told Reuters that young people do not want to stay.</p>
<p>Koh said she hoped officials would let more people stay in <strong>guesthouses</strong>. "Not the high-end ones but the kampung-type," she added, using the Malay term for a village.</p>
<p>Lim Csye See is a 69-year-old who runs a bicycle rental shop. Lim said he did not want the island to become like Sentosa, Singapore's <strong>theme park</strong> island which is crowded with costly hotels and homes.</p>
<p>"If this place becomes like Sentosa, then that's the end," said Lim.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Xinghui Kok reported this story for Reuters. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>miracle </strong>–n. a wondrous or amazing event</p>
<p><strong>convenience </strong>–n. a quality or situation in which things are easy and do not involve hard work</p>
<p><strong>generator </strong>–n. a machine that produces electricity usually from burning fuel</p>
<p><strong>quarry </strong>–n. an open place where rock is cut to use for building purposes</p>
<p><strong>stressful </strong>–adj. something that causes tension and worry</p>
<p><strong>fantastic </strong>–adj. wonderful or especially good</p>
<p><strong>absorb </strong>–v. to take in</p>
<p><strong>conservation </strong>–n. marked by a desire to save maintain and save something for the future</p>
<p><strong>guesthouse </strong>–n. a place where visitors can stay, usually for a modest price and with modest rooms and accommodations</p>
<p><strong>theme park</strong> –n. a place with many mechanical rides and exciting events that are meant to entertain people</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>As Space Traffic Grows, UN Calls for More International Cooperation (2024/12/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/as-space-traffic-grows-un-calls-for-more-international-cooperation.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>As the amount of space traffic continues to grow, the United Nations is calling for increased international cooperation to improve safety.</p>
<p>Continued deployment of satellites and sharp increases in space <strong>debris</strong> over the years have resulted in the crowding of low Earth orbit. Space experts and industry leaders say this has created safety risks that will worsen if the problem is not dealt with.</p>
<p>A U.N. gathering of experts in October called for more sharing of information about orbital space objects, as well as creation of an international process to follow and <strong>manage</strong> them. The meeting was organized by the U.N.'s Office for Outer Space Affairs.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This illustration provided by NASA depicts the non-operating RHESSI (Reuven Ramaty High Energy Solar Spectroscopic Imager) solar observation satellite.(NASA via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/da396372-a847-4c24-b021-e2060a754541_cx0_cy12_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This illustration provided by NASA depicts the non-operating RHESSI (Reuven Ramaty High Energy Solar Spectroscopic Imager) solar observation satellite.(NASA via AP)</span></div>
<p>Data from the American-based company Slingshot Aerospace suggests there are more than 14,000 satellites around the world in low Earth orbit. That number includes about 3,500 satellites that are currently inactive, Reuters news agency reports.</p>
<p>In addition, there are about 120 million pieces of orbital debris left over from spacecraft launches, crashes or other causes. Only a few thousand of those are large enough to follow, or track.</p>
<p>"There's no time to lose on space traffic <strong>coordination</strong>,” the director of the U.N.'s Office for Outer Space Affairs, Aarti Holla-Maini, told Reuters. She added, “With so many objects being launched into space, we have to do everything we can to ensure space safety, and that means <strong>facilitating </strong>the sharing of information between operators.”</p>
<p>Holla-Maini explained that such coordination should involve both public and private organizations. The goal is to take steps to avoid crashes between space objects orbiting in low Earth orbit. She added that this area of space must remain safe to prevent costly difficulties to technologies that drive worldwide communication, <strong>navigation</strong> and scientific exploration.</p>
<p>Currently, there is no centralized system to help prevent such problems. It has also been difficult for organizations to agree on a set of guidelines aimed at improving safety in low Earth orbit. While some countries are willing to share data, others object because of security or privacy concerns.</p>
<p>There have been several examples of these issues over the past year. A Chinese launcher rocket exploded in August, creating thousands of pieces of debris in low Earth orbit. In June, an unused Russian satellite exploded, releasing thousands of metal pieces. That incident forced astronauts on the International Space Station to briefly take shelter.</p>
<p>Low Earth orbit is the most crowded area of space. This is because it offers a balance between cost and <strong>proximity</strong>, making it a popular target for the quickly growing private space industry.</p>
<p>It is estimated that many more satellites – tens of thousands more – will enter low-Earth orbit in the coming years. One prediction by Canada-based space tracking company NorthStar Earth &amp; Space suggests the possible financial risk of space object collisions is likely to reach $556 million over five years.</p>
<p>NorthStar's chief executive, Stewart Bain, told Reuters the situation had reached "a critical point” for establishing rules to cover space objects in low Earth orbit. Bain noted that SpaceX's Starlink is launching thousands of satellites per year and China and others are preparing to follow. Such expansion could threaten the load <strong>capacity </strong>of objects in low Earth orbit, he said.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Reuters reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>debris</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> broken pieces of something</p>
<p><strong>manage </strong><em>– v.</em> to deal with something</p>
<p><strong>coordinate</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to organize all the different parts of something</p>
<p><strong>facilitate </strong><em>– v.</em> to make something possible or easier</p>
<p><strong>navigate</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to find directions by using maps or other equipment</p>
<p><strong>proximity </strong><em>– n.</em> how near one thing is to another, or the fact of being near something</p>
<p><strong>capacity</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> the largest amount or number something can hol</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Five Things to Know about Notre Dame Cathedral (2024/12/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/five-things-to-know-about-notre-dame-cathedral.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Notre Dame Cathedral in the French capital of Paris is set to reopen to the public Sunday after a five-year-long rebuilding project. The Cathedral had been badly damaged in a fire in 2019.</p>
<p>The Roman Catholic religious center is considered a jewel of Gothic building design, a <strong>symbol</strong> of Paris and is a popular site to visit.</p>
<p>The cathedral took 182 years to build between the 12th and 14th centuries. It holds some surprising stories. Here are five special things to know about this famous Parisian site:</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="French President Emmanuel Macron, center left, and his wife Brigitte Macron, third right, visit the restored interiors of Notre-Dame Cathedral, Friday, Nov.29, 2024 in Paris. (Christophe Petit Tesson, Pool via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/47d79232-3e69-4e7f-a599-2bcc234ad808_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">French President Emmanuel Macron, center left, and his wife Brigitte Macron, third right, visit the restored interiors of Notre-Dame Cathedral, Friday, Nov.29, 2024 in Paris. (Christophe Petit Tesson, Pool via AP)</span></div>
<p><strong>The cathedral is considered France's geographic center. </strong></p>
<p>In front of the cathedral, a metal and stone marker in the road describes the place as the "starting point of the roads of France.'' This sign marks the starting point for measuring distances between Paris and other cities across the country.</p>
<p>The marker was placed in 1924, but the idea of the cathedral as the center of the nation dates to 1769. King Louis XV thought there should be a central site for France's growing system of roads. That idea tied the nation's <strong>geography</strong> to its heart in Paris.</p>
<p><strong>Its famous statues were added in the 19th century</strong></p>
<p>Those frightening stone statues on Notre Dame might seem ancient, but not all of them are what they appear. The <strong>gargoyles</strong> are <strong>monster</strong>-shaped elements used to direct rainwater away from the building. They have been around since the time of the cathedral's <strong>construction</strong>. But the monster-like creatures often seen in <strong>photos</strong> and movies are <strong>chimera</strong>, and they are much newer.</p>
<p>In 1841, the French government asked the architects Eugène Viollet-le-Duc and Jean-Baptiste Lassus to repair the then-collapsing building. Viollet-le-Duc added these frightening-looking statues to make the cathedral seem more mysterious. He drew ideas for the chimera from Victor Hugo's famous book <em>The Hunchback of Notre Dame.</em></p>
<p>How to tell them apart? Gargoyles <strong>resemble horizontal spikes</strong> coming out of the<strong> facade</strong> and have <strong>spouts </strong>to permit rainwater to flow out.</p>
<p><strong>During the French Revolution, protesters changed Notre Dame.</strong></p>
<p>During the French Revolution, there were protests of religious centers.</p>
<p>In 1793, revolutionaries took away the cathedral's religious symbols and renamed it "Notre-Dame de la Raison," or, in English, “Our Lady of Reason.”</p>
<p>During that time, the cathedral held events celebrating science and new ideas and, for a short time, it was even used to store the alcoholic drink called wine.</p>
<p>Religious services started again in 1795 under the rule of Napoleon I.</p>
<p><strong>Statues without heads were found and repaired.</strong></p>
<p>In 1792, revolutionaries also cut the heads off 28 statues from the front of Notre Dame, thinking the statues were of French <strong>royalty</strong>. They were really representations of ancient kings of Judah, from stories in the Bible, the Christian holy book.</p>
<p>The heads were thought lost forever.</p>
<p>But in 1977, workers working in a <strong>courtyard</strong> in Paris uncovered hundreds of pieces of stone sculptures. Experts confirmed they were the missing heads of Notre Dame's kings of Judah statues.</p>
<p>Today, 22 of the heads have been repaired and are shown at the Cluny Museum in Paris.</p>
<p><strong>The 2019 fire exposed a worldwide lack of outdoor lead pollution guidelines.</strong></p>
<p>The 2019 fire that almost destroyed Notre Dame caused a serious health risk. When the<strong> flames</strong> melted the top of the building, large amounts of harmful lead dust were released into the air and came down across Paris.</p>
<p>Officials found there were no rules to measure the danger of outdoor lead dust. This was not just a Paris issue — major cities like London and Rome, and even the World Health Organization — do not have guidelines for outdoor lead pollution.</p>
<p>The Notre Dame fire forced officials to take a closer look at their safety standards. It took four months for the city to complete an extensive cleaning of the city's streets even as visitors and the citizens of Paris walked around the cathedral every day.</p>
<p>Now that you know these five things, you can enjoy seeing the photos of the new Notre Dame when it opens to the public.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p>Tom Nouvian<em> reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>symbol</strong> –<em> n</em>. an action, object, event, etc., that expresses or represents a particular idea or quality</p>
<p><strong>gargoyle </strong>– <em>n</em>. a strange or ugly human or animal figure that sticks out from the roof of a building (such as a church) and is used to cause rainwater to flow away from the sides of a building.</p>
<p><strong>chimera</strong> – <em>n</em>. a monster from Greek mythology that breathes fire and has a lion's head, a goat's body, and a snake's tail</p>
<p><strong>resemble </strong>– <em>v</em>. to look or be like</p>
<p><strong>horizontal </strong>– <em>adj</em>. positioned from side to side rather than up and down; parallel to the ground</p>
<p><strong>spike</strong> – <em>n</em>. a long, thin rod that ends in a point and is often made of metal</p>
<p><strong>fa<i></i>231;ade</strong> – <em>n.</em> the front of a building</p>
<p><strong>spout</strong> –<em> n</em>. a tube, pipe, or hole out of which a liquid flows</p>
<p><strong>royalty </strong>–<em> n.</em> members of a royal family</p>
<p><strong>courtyard</strong> –<em> n</em>. an open space that is surrounded completely or partly by a building or group of buildings</p>
<p><strong>flame</strong> – <em>n</em>. the hot, glowing gas that can be seen when a fire is burning</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What to Know about South Korea’s Short Period of Martial Law (2024/12/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/what-to-know-about-south-korea-s-short-period-of-martial-law.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>South Korea's parliament moved to <strong>impeach</strong> President Yoon Suk Yeol after he declared <strong>martial law</strong> and sent troops into the streets on Tuesday night.</p>
<p>For several hours, armed forces with helicopters and <strong>armored</strong> vehicles surrounded the parliament. Lawmakers had to climb walls to get into the building and used <strong>fire extinguishers</strong> to hold off the troops.</p>
<p>The lawmakers who were able to reenter the building rejected Yoon's martial law declaration with a 190-0 vote. Eighteen lawmakers from Yoon's party also voted against the declaration. The vote forced Yoon to lift martial law about six hours after it began.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Members of main opposition Democratic Party stage a rally against South Korean President Yoon Suk Yeol at the National Assembly in Seoul, South Korea, Wednesday, Dec. 4, 2024. (AP Photo/Ahn Young-joon)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/9d8822a1-59c8-4cd9-a66c-e56ccadcf44a_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Members of main opposition Democratic Party stage a rally against South Korean President Yoon Suk Yeol at the National Assembly in Seoul, South Korea, Wednesday, Dec. 4, 2024. (AP Photo/Ahn Young-joon)</span></div>
<p>Opposition parties then began the process of impeachment.</p>
<p>Impeachment is a way for lawmakers to charge a public official with a crime while they are in office. Impeaching Yoon requires the support of two-thirds of the National Assembly and at least six of the nine Constitutional Court justices. The liberal opposition Democratic Party holds a majority in the 300-seat parliament and has called for Yoon's resignation.</p>
<p>A vote on the impeachment motion could be held as early as Friday, Democratic Party lawmaker Kim Yong-min said.</p>
<p><strong>Yoon said there was a plan to rebel </strong></p>
<p>Yoon ordered martial law without warning in a speech late Tuesday. He promised to remove "anti-state" forces he said were planning to rebel. He accused the main opposition parties of supporting North Korea.</p>
<p>Yoon gave no direct evidence when he pointed to North Korea as a threatening force. Yoon has long held that a hard line is the only way to stop the North from following through on its nuclear threats against the South.</p>
<p>In the late 1980s, several South Korean strongmen spoke of the threat from the North when struggling to control protesters and political opponents in the South.</p>
<p>As president, Yoon has struggled to get his proposals through the opposition-controlled parliament. At the same time, Yoon and his wife have faced charges of corruption.</p>
<p><strong>What is martial law?</strong></p>
<p>South Korea's constitution gives the president power to use the military to keep order in "wartime, war-like situations or other comparable national emergency states.” That can include suspending civil rights and temporarily limiting the powers of the courts and government agencies.</p>
<p>But it also gives the National Assembly power to lift the declaration with a majority vote.</p>
<p>Some experts say the way Yoon declared martial law went far beyond his lawful powers. The constitution does not permit a president to use the military to suspend parliament. And many question whether the country really faces a situation comparable to war.</p>
<p>The opposition said Yoon's actions were “illegal and unconstitutional.” The sudden declaration was also opposed by the leader of Yoon's own conservative party. Han Dong-hoon called the decision wrong and promised to "stop it with the people."</p>
<p>South Korea became a democracy only in the late 1980s, and military intervention in civilian affairs is still a sensitive subject. South Koreans were in shock with the actions. And many expressed surprise and worry on social media over Yoon's announcement.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Foster Klug reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>impeach</strong> – <em>v</em>. to charge (a public official) with a crime done while in office</p>
<p><strong>martial law </strong>– <em>n</em>. control of an area by military forces rather than by the police</p>
<p><strong>armored</strong> – <em>adj</em>. covered in flat pieces of metal to protect against attack</p>
<p><strong>fire extinguisher</strong> – <em>n</em>. a metal container filled with chemicals that is used to put out a fire</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Tips for Better Writing (2024/12/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/tips-for-better-writing.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By VOA</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the Education Report.</p>
<p>Today we continue our series of expert suggestions for academic writing. Our guest is Jennifer Ahern-Dodson, assistant professor of the Practice in Writing Studies at Duke University in North Carolina.</p>
<p>Ms. Ahern-Dodson starts a <strong>conversation </strong>with both students and professors planning to write a paper or essay. She asks about their earlier writing <strong>experiences.</strong> Were they <strong>negative or positive</strong>?</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Students at the University of Texas-Southmost College work on a writing assignment in an English as a Second Language class in 2006. (AP Photo/Brad Doherty)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/ffa53382-773c-42f8-be66-ab08da38659e_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Students at the University of Texas-Southmost College work on a writing assignment in an English as a Second Language class in 2006. (AP Photo/Brad Doherty)</span></div>
<p>She advises that you are not alone if you have had problems with your writing. She says everyone struggles with writing.</p>
<p>“Writing is hard. All writers struggle at some point. And even if writing has come easily for you, at some point in your work as a student, that eventually you're going to <strong>hit a roadblock</strong>. And so part of what I like to get folks thinking about is -- besides writing's hard for everybody – is to really take a moment to think about their past writing experiences. And when the writing is going well, what was happening? When the writing wasn't going well, what was happening?”</p>
<p>She says most people's negative writing experiences happened because a very specific <strong>formula </strong>is required for a paper including an exact length.</p>
<p>“And so they primarily focus on, and worry about, what the final product has to look like, like how many pages for a research essay? Or if it is in the second or third language, you know, punctuation and grammar, like whether it gets communicated in the right language.</p>
<p>“And so focusing on the end makes it really hard to get started.”</p>
<p>Another problem can arise when the need to do well on a paper is extremely important.</p>
<p>“...like a timed essay exam, or a college application essay, or a research paper that is at the end of the semester, and it's tied to the entire grade for the class. So worrying about what will happen if they don't do well – get bad grades, don't get into college -- creates, of course, significant anxiety<strong>.</strong> And that can make it harder to get the writing done.”</p>
<p>Then she and the people she's helping move to more <strong>positive</strong> projects. She says usually when writing comes easily, the writers feel they have something important to say.</p>
<p>The teacher advises asking yourself questions. What personal understanding of the subject can you bring to your paper? Why is this subject important? For whom is it meaningful? Who will be reading it?</p>
<p>“...Think about who your<strong> audience</strong> is, and what it is that you really want to say to them. And what that can do is help you switch from the final product and what it can look like (to) really more on what you have to offer, your particular <strong>perspective.” </strong></p>
<p>She says that is an important change for all writers.</p>
<p>And that's the VOA Learning English Education Report. Coming soon: Jennifer Ahern-Dodson talks about doing research, sitting down to write and sharing your writing with others.</p>
<p>I'm Jeri Watson.</p>
<p>__________________________________________________<strong> </strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in this Story</h2>
<p><strong>conversation - </strong><em>n.</em> an informal talk involving two people or a group of people</p>
<p><strong>experiences - </strong><em>n.</em> the processes of doing and seeing things and having things happen to you</p>
<p><strong>negative - </strong><em>adj. </em> unpleasant, unproductive</p>
<p><strong>positive</strong><em> - n. </em>pleasant, productive</p>
<p><strong>hit a roadblock</strong><em> - idiom, </em>encountering a situation that blocks one's progress</p>
<p><strong>audience - </strong><em>n.</em> the people who watch, read, or listen to something</p>
<p><strong>perspective </strong>- <em>n.</em> the way you view something; point of view</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>South Korean Man Guilty of Gaining Weight to Avoid Military Service (2024/12/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/south-korean-man-guilty-of-gaining-weight-to-avoid-military-service.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A South Korean court has found a man guilty of purposefully gaining weight to avoid completing required service in the country's military.</p>
<p>Seoul's Eastern District Court sentenced the 26-year-old man to one year in prison for violating the country's military service act. The Associated Press reports that the court suspended the sentence for two years. The court said the man did not appeal the November 13 ruling against him.</p>
<p>The court said the man had gained more than 20 kilograms in an effort to get released from a government requirement to serve in the military.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file photo, South Korean army soldiers carry out an anti-terror drill as part of the Ulchi Taeguk exercise at a park in Seoul, South Korea, May 27, 2019. (AP Photo/Ahn Young-joon, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/c8a2881a-9139-4638-a725-50ad478100fb_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this file photo, South Korean army soldiers carry out an anti-terror drill as part of the Ulchi Taeguk exercise at a park in Seoul, South Korea, May 27, 2019. (AP Photo/Ahn Young-joon, File)</span></div>
<p>South Korea requires all able-bodied men to serve in the military for 18-21 months. However, some individuals with health issues can instead perform service in non-military positions. Such service can be carried out at welfare centers or at other approved places within communities.</p>
<p>People with serious health problems are not required to serve in the military at all.</p>
<p>A health examination in 2017 found the man was physically able to become an active-duty soldier while weighing 83 kilograms. But the court said the man received advice that he could get permission to serve a non-military, social service position if he was overweight. This led him to start gaining weight.</p>
<p>The court said that in three physical exams carried out in 2022 and 2023, the man weighed 102-105 kilograms, a weight that made him fit for social service.</p>
<p>The AP reported it was not clear how the crime was discovered nor if the man began his military duty before he was tried. The court said only that he had promised to meet his military service requirement.</p>
<p>South Korea operates a <strong>compulsory</strong> military service system to deal with<strong> </strong>possible military threats from North Korea. But the policy is widely debated in the country. Some critics of the system point to the fact that requiring military service forces young men to suspend their studies or professional careers.</p>
<p>South Korea's Military Manpower Administration is responsible for operating the country's compulsory military service system. It says that each year, about 50-60 cases of <strong>dodging</strong> military duties have been reported.</p>
<p>The organization notes the most common ways to avoid military duties are to gain or lose large amounts of weight or to not complete necessary medical treatments before physical exams.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>compulsory</strong><strong> </strong><em>– adj.</em> an official requirement to do something</p>
<p><strong>dodge </strong><em>– v.</em> to avoid something, often in a dishonest way</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Microsoft’s AI ‘Agents’ Aim to Take over Many Human Duties (2024/12/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/microsoft-s-ai-agents-aim-to-take-over-many-human-duties.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Microsoft is expanding its artificial intelligence (AI) tool offerings to include “personal <strong>agents</strong>” which are designed to take over different human processes.</p>
<p>The American software company said the new offerings are designed to help users complete certain business activities with little or no human involvement. The agents are expected to be offered to some users starting in the coming weeks. A full release is expected sometime next year.</p>
<p>Microsoft has said its agents are designed to expand on so-called chatbots. A chatbot is an AI tool that can work by itself to produce human-level writing or discussion. Such systems – also known as generative AI – can also produce images and videos based on short text descriptions.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Microsoft CEO Satya Nadella introduces the Azure Boost DPU at the company's Ignite conference Tuesday, Nov. 19, 2024, in Chicago. (AP Photo/Charles Rex Arbogast)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/7e2f7f13-2575-43ff-b39d-83e1ff5bd902_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Microsoft CEO Satya Nadella introduces the Azure Boost DPU at the company's Ignite conference Tuesday, Nov. 19, 2024, in Chicago. (AP Photo/Charles Rex Arbogast)</span></div>
<p>While chatbots perform some functions on their own, they also depend heavily on humans to operate and guide them. The idea behind AI agents is to give them the ability to take over whole business processes with little or no guidance from people.</p>
<p>In a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2024/10/21/new-autonomous-agents-scale-your-team-like-never-before/">statement</a> last month, Microsoft said it was preparing for a world where every organization would have a collection of AI agents to perform different business activities.</p>
<p>In <a class="wsw__a" href="https://news.microsoft.com/source/features/ai/ai-agents-what-they-are-and-how-theyll-change-the-way-we-work/">another statement</a> issued last week, the company said the agents being developed are designed to “operate around the clock” to ease the workload of human workers. Examples of agent duties include processing <strong>customer</strong> orders or returns and examining shipping records to prevent errors.</p>
<p>Microsoft has moved quickly to offer AI technologies to everyday users of its business software products. The methods are largely based on models built by AI developer OpenAI, creator of the ChatGPT chatbot. Microsoft has invested about $13 billion in OpenAI.</p>
<p>Microsoft's Chief Marketing Officer, Jared Spataro, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2024/10/21/new-autonomous-agents-scale-your-team-like-never-before/">said</a> the public should “think of agents as the new apps for an AI-powered world.”</p>
<p>The company added that its customers will be able to use its Copilot Studio service to create their own AI agents to meet specific needs. Copilot is Microsoft's existing AI chatbot tool. In addition, the company said it has introduced 10 ready-to-use agents to carry out <strong>routine</strong> business activities.</p>
<p>Charles Lamanna is the corporate vice president of business and industry for Copilot. He told Reuters news agency, "The idea is that Copilot is the user <strong>interface</strong> for AI." He added, "Every employee will have a Copilot, their personalized AI agent. And then they will use that Copilot to interface and interact with the sea of AI agents that will be out there."</p>
<p>In an online explanation of the AI tools, Microsoft said “instead of just assisting you, agents can work alongside you or even <strong>on your behalf</strong>.” This could include “a range of things, from responding to customer questions to more (complex) or multistep assignments,” the company added.</p>
<p>The abilities of AI agents remain limited for now. But ongoing development of the tools has raised concerns about certain risks linked to the technology. Microsoft officials have said the company had developed responsible AI guidelines to protect users from possible security or privacy problems.</p>
<p>Other big technology companies also aim to develop such agents. These include Salesforce, Nvidia, Google and Oracle. Industry experts have said the tools could provide companies with an easier path to earn money from the billions of dollars they are investing in AI systems.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press, Reuters and Agence France-Presse and Microsoft reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>agent </strong><em>– n.</em> a person or system whose job it is to deal with business for someone else</p>
<p><strong>customer </strong><em>– n.</em> a person or organization that buys goods or services from a shop or business</p>
<p><strong>routine </strong><em>– adj</em>. a regular task that gets repeated over and over again</p>
<p><strong>interface </strong><em>– n. </em>a connection between a person and a computer system</p>
<p><strong>on behalf (of someone) </strong><em>– phrase</em> acting for someone else</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Ancient Footprints Suggest 2 Human Species Were Neighbors in Kenya 1.5 Million Years Ago (2024/12/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/ancient-footprints-suggest-2-human-species-were-neighbors-in-kenya-1-5-million-years-ago.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists say ancient footprints left in wet dirt on a Kenyan lakeside suggest that two early human ancestors were neighbors about 1.5 million years ago.</p>
<p>Two separate <strong>species</strong> made the sets of footprints “within a matter of hours, or at most days,” said paleontologist Louise Leakey, a writer of the research published recently in the journal <em>Science</em>. Paleontologists study <strong>fossils</strong> to learn about the history of life on Earth.</p>
<p>Scientists already knew from earlier fossil finds that these two <strong>extinct </strong>lines of human development – called Homo erectus and Paranthropus boisei – lived about the same time in the Turkana Basin.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="An aerial view shows a research team standing alongside the fossil footprint trackway at the excavation site on the eastern side of Lake Turkana in northern Kenya, 2022. (Louise Leakey via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/08ad1e64-92bb-4ece-affc-d0bc2dd71073_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">An aerial view shows a research team standing alongside the fossil footprint trackway at the excavation site on the eastern side of Lake Turkana in northern Kenya, 2022. (Louise Leakey via AP)</span></div>
<p>But dating fossils is not exact. “It's plus or minus a few thousand years,” said paleontologist William Harcourt-Smith of Lehman College and the American Museum of Natural History in New York. He was not involved in the study</p>
<p>Yet with fossil footprints, “there's an actual moment in time <strong>preserved</strong>,” he said. “It's an amazing discovery.”</p>
<p>Researchers found the fossil footprints in 2021 in what is today Koobi Fora, Kenya, said Leaky, who is based at Stony Brook University in New York.</p>
<p>Study co-writer Kevin Hatala is a paleoanthropologist at Chatham University in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. He said the two species likely knew of each other's existence whether they left the prints at the same time or a day or two apart.</p>
<p>“They probably saw each other, probably knew each other was there and probably influenced each other in some way,” Hatala said.</p>
<p>Scientists were able to tell the difference between the two species because of the shape of the footprints. The shape of each informed researchers about the structure of the foot and how it was being used at the time.</p>
<p>Homo erectus appeared to be walking similarly to how modern humans walk – striking the ground heel first, then moving weight over the ball of the foot and toes and pushing off again.</p>
<p>The other species, which was also walking upright, was moving “in a different way from anything else we've seen before, anywhere else,” said co-writer Erin Marie Williams-Hatala, a human development <strong>anatomist</strong> at Chatham.</p>
<p>Among other details, the footprints suggest greater ability of movement in their big toe, compared to Homo erectus or modern humans, said Hatala.</p>
<p>Our common <strong>primate</strong> ancestors probably had hands and feet fit for grasping branches. But, over time, the feet of human ancestors developed to permit walking upright, researchers say.</p>
<p>The new study adds to a growing amount of research that suggests the change to walking on two feet did not happen at a single moment, in a single way.</p>
<p>Instead, there may have been a number of ways that early humans learned to walk, run and slide on prehistoric muddy hills.</p>
<p>“It turns out, there are different gait mechanics – different ways of being <strong>bipedal</strong>,” said Harcourt-Smith.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted the story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>species </strong><em>– n.</em> <strong> </strong>a class of things of the same kind and with the same name</p>
<p><strong>fossil </strong><em>– n.</em> a trace or print or the remains of a plant or animal of a past age preserved in earth or rock</p>
<p><strong>extinct </strong><em>– adj</em>. no longer existing</p>
<p><strong>preserve </strong><em>– v</em>. <strong> </strong>to keep or save from decomposition</p>
<p><strong>anatomist </strong><em>– n.</em> a scientist who studies the structural makeup of a living organism or any of its parts</p>
<p><strong>bipedal </strong><em>– adj.</em> of, or relating to, walking on two feet</p>
<p><strong>primate</strong> <em>– n.</em> any of an order of mammals that are characterized by hands and feet that grasp, a relatively large complex brain, and vision in which objects are seen in three dimensions and that includes human beings, apes, m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s, and related forms (such as lemurs and tarsiers)</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: More Than 800 Million Have Diabetes Worldwide, Many Untreated (2024/12/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/study-more-than-800-million-have-diabetes-worldwide-many-untreated.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A new study reports that more than 800 million adults have diabetes worldwide. And more than half of those aged over 30 who have the condition are not receiving treatment.</p>
<p>Diabetes is a disease in which your blood sugar level is too high. If untreated, it can damage the heart, blood vessels, nerves and other organs.</p>
<p>The study, recently published in the publication <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(24)02317-1/fulltext"><em>Lancet</em></a>, found that around 828 million people aged 18 and older had diabetes worldwide in 2022. Among those 30 and older, the study said 445 million, or 59 percent, were not receiving treatment.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A person receives a blood sugar test for diabetes in Dhaka, Bangladesh on November 14, 2024. (REUTERS/Mohammad Ponir Hossain)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a853c27d-6ac4-4712-ae84-e8a44a59a070_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A person receives a blood sugar test for diabetes in Dhaka, Bangladesh on November 14, 2024. (REUTERS/Mohammad Ponir Hossain)</span></div>
<p>The study was done by the NCD Risk Factor Collaboration and the World Health Organization (WHO). It is the first worldwide <strong>evaluation</strong> based on more than 1,000 studies involving more than 140 million people.</p>
<p><strong>Shocking increase</strong></p>
<p>The WHO <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/diabetes">estimated</a> that the number of people living with diabetes worldwide rose from 200 million in 1990 to about 830 million in 2022. The study's researchers say the increase has been caused largely by rising cases in low- and middle-<strong>income</strong> countries. Treatments in those countries have not kept up with the rise, while the situation has improved in some higher-income countries.</p>
<p>WHO Director-General Dr. Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus said in a statement that the increase shown in the study was shocking. “To bring the <strong>global</strong> diabetes epidemic under control, countries must urgently take action," he said. Those actions should include policies supporting healthy diets and physical activity, as well as health systems that can prevent, identify and treat the condition.</p>
<p><strong>Treating the disease is costly</strong></p>
<p>Jean Claude Mbanya is a professor at the University of Yaounde I in Cameroon. He said that in parts of sub-Saharan Africa, only 5-10 percent of those estimated to have diabetes were getting treatment. He added that treating diabetes, either with <strong>insulin</strong> or drugs, can be costly. "A huge number (are) at risk of serious health complications," he said.</p>
<p>Some of the largest improvements, 25 to 37 percentage points, happened in countries in Latin America, central and western Europe, Canada, South Korea, Russia, Seychelles, and Jordan.</p>
<p>The WHO says the number of deaths caused by diabetes has been increasing since 2000. In 2021, the disease was the direct cause of 1.6 million deaths.</p>
<p><strong>Symptoms and prevention</strong></p>
<p>The health agency says <strong>symptoms</strong> of diabetes may happen suddenly or take many years to be noticed. They include:</p>
<ul>
<li>feeling very thirsty</li>
<li>needing to urinate more often than usual</li>
<li>blurred vision</li>
<li>feeling tired</li>
<li>losing weight</li>
</ul>
<p>The best way to prevent or delay the illness, the WHO says, is to make lifestyle changes. For example:</p>
<ul>
<li>keeping a healthy body weight</li>
<li>staying active with at least 150 minutes of exercise each week</li>
<li>eating a healthy diet and avoiding sugar and saturated fat</li>
<li>not smoking tobacco.</li>
</ul>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jennifer Rigby reported this story for Reuters.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted the story for Learning English with additional information from The Lancet and the WHO.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>evaluate</strong> – <em>v</em>. to judge the value or condition of (someone or something) in a careful and thoughtful way</p>
<p><strong>income</strong> – <em>n</em>. money that is earned from work, investments, business, etc.</p>
<p><strong>global</strong> – <em>adj</em>. involving the entire world</p>
<p><strong>insulin</strong> – <em>n.</em> a substance that your body makes and uses to turn sugar into energy</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Research of Galaxies Supports Einstein’s General Theory of Relativity (2024/12/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/research-of-galaxies-supports-einstein-s-general-theory-of-relativity.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>An international group of scientists has been studying how the structure of the universe has grown over the past 11 billion years.</p>
<p>These researchers recently announced findings about how gravity behaves at a very large scale. What they found supports a prediction physicist Albert Einstein made in his 1915 theory of general relativity.</p>
<p><strong>Dark energy and gravity </strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - The Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument at Kitt Peak National Observatory in Arizona is operated imaging the night sky in 2022, in Kitt Peak, Arizona, U.S. (Kitt Peak National Observatory/NOIRLab/U.S. National Science Foundation/AURA/T. Slovinsky/Handout via REUTERS)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/c5a9df68-7c1f-4dc7-a5ac-eb7d15b066fc_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - The Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument at Kitt Peak National Observatory in Arizona is operated imaging the night sky in 2022, in Kitt Peak, Arizona, U.S. (Kitt Peak National Observatory/NOIRLab/U.S. National Science Foundation/AURA/T. Slovinsky/Handout via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>The findings are part of a years-long study of the history of the universe that has <strong>focused</strong> on dark energy. Dark energy is an invisible and mysterious force that is accelerating, or speeding up, the ongoing expansion of the universe.</p>
<p>The study's researchers used a year of observations by the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) at Kitt Peak National Observatory in Arizona.</p>
<p>Gravity is one of the universe's <strong>fundamental</strong> forces. Einstein's theory linked space, time and gravity. The theory holds that large amounts of mass and energy <strong>curve</strong> the structure of space-time, influencing the motion of whatever passes nearby.</p>
<p>Dragan Huterer of the University of Michigan was co-leader of the working group that examined the data from DESI.</p>
<p>Huterer said: "Einstein's theory of general relativity describes the motion of <strong>massive </strong>objects in a gravitational field that they create. It is one of the most successful physical theories that we have.”</p>
<p>But the announcement in 1998 that the universe's expansion was speeding up raised doubts about Einstein's model.</p>
<p>“The discovery of the accelerating universe...led to suggestions that maybe general relativity needs to be modified,” Huterer said.</p>
<p>The new DESI findings revealed gravity is behaving as Einstein predicted that it would.</p>
<p>Scientists say the Big Bang event 13.8 billion years ago began the universe, which has been expanding ever since. They say experiments show the expansion was actually accelerating and dark energy is a possible cause.</p>
<p>The new DESI findings focused on the growth of what is called the cosmic structure. It dates to when the universe was about 20 percent of its current age.</p>
<p>This cosmic structure has a direct connection to the large-scale organization of matter. Galaxies, galaxy clusters and even larger galaxy superclusters form a cosmic web or connected networks with large areas of space existing in between.</p>
<p>This structure results from the gravitational pull of matter throughout the universe.</p>
<p>The new study was based on DESI observations of almost 6 million galaxies and their centers, dating back 11 billion years.</p>
<p>The DESI scientists in April released the largest three-dimensional map of the cosmos. They announced findings suggesting that dark energy may not be an unchangeable force. Instead, it might change over time. Those findings focused on a specific behavior of galaxy clusters. The new research expanded what is known about that behavior.</p>
<p>Mustapha Ishak-Boushaki of the University of Texas at Dallas was a co-leader of the working group. He said, "Our DESI data shows that it is in agreement with Einstein's theory of gravity but still favors a <strong>dynamical</strong> dark energy - and finding these <strong>simultaneously </strong>is new."</p>
<p>The universe includes ordinary matter: stars, planets, gas, dust. It also contains dark matter. Dark matter is invisible material that might make up about 27 percent of the cosmos. In addition to that, scientists also believe there is dark energy which might make up 68 percent of the cosmos.</p>
<p>"Dark energy is responsible for the accelerated expansion of the universe. The physical nature of dark energy is at present unknown," Huterer said.</p>
<p>The new findings appear to support the current “standard model” of cosmology that includes the theory of general relativity.</p>
<p>The DESI working group involves more than 900 researchers from more than 70 organizations worldwide. It is overseen by the U.S. Department of Energy's Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory. The new research was published in the arXiv online database before undergoing the process of<strong> peer review</strong>.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Will Dunham reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>focus</strong> <em>– v.</em> to concentrate attention or effort</p>
<p><strong>fundamental </strong><em>–adj.</em> ideas that form the basis of other ideas or theories</p>
<p><strong>curve </strong><em>–n.</em> a shape that is similar to a circle or a rounded line</p>
<p><strong>massive</strong> <em>– adj.</em> forming or consisting of a large mass; very large</p>
<p><strong>dynamical </strong><em>– adj. </em>of or relating to physical force or energy</p>
<p><strong>simultaneously </strong><em>– adv.</em> existing or happening at the same time</p>
<p><strong>peer review<em> </em></strong><em>– n.</em> a process for publishing scholarly research in which academic people with similar positions and jobs as the writers' offer criticism of a research paper before it is officially published in a scholarly journal</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Publish Version of a Map of Human Body Cells (2024/12/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/scientists-publish-version-of-a-map-of-human-body-cells.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Researchers have created an early version of a map of some of the human body's cells.</p>
<p>The human body has an estimated 37.2 trillion cells. Each <strong>type</strong> of cell has a <strong>unique</strong> job. Knowing each cell's job can help scientists better understand health and diseases such as cancer.</p>
<p>The work is part of the Human Cell Atlas<strong> </strong>project. The effort began in 2016. It involves researchers around the world. The group, called a consortium, plans to release a more complete <strong>atlas</strong> in 2026 by mapping cells from 18 organs and body systems. These include the skin, heart, and breasts.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image provided by Ana-Maria Cujba shows blood vessels in a portion of the human small intestine, March 21, 2024. (Ana-Maria Cujba/Wellcome Sanger Institute via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/5f5045b6-c127-4964-8d33-63b8056263c8_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image provided by Ana-Maria Cujba shows blood vessels in a portion of the human small intestine, March 21, 2024. (Ana-Maria Cujba/Wellcome Sanger Institute via AP)</span></div>
<p>Some of the researchers published their findings on bone development in embryos. The study appeared in <em>Nature </em>on November 20.</p>
<p>Aviv Regev is a founding co-chair of the project. Regev is currently executive vice president and head of research and early development at U.S. biotech company Genentech. She said the work is important in two ways.</p>
<p>First, the project relates to <strong>curiosity</strong>. Humans have long wanted to know what they are made of. “And, in fact, <strong>biologists</strong> have been mapping cells since the 1600s for that reason," Regev added.</p>
<p>Second, Regev said knowing how cells work is critical for understanding how to treat disease.</p>
<p>"Cells are the basic unit of life, and when things go wrong, they go wrong with our cells, first and foremost," she added.</p>
<p>"<strong>Fundamentally</strong>, these studies tell us how tissues, organs and humans are built," said Muzlifah Haniffa of Wellcome Sanger Institute and Newcastle University in Britain. Haniffa was a member of the project's organizing committee.</p>
<p><strong>What is the Human Cell Atlas?</strong></p>
<p>Scientists are<strong> focusing</strong> on certain organs. They are mapping the jobs of cells in the mouth, stomach and intestines. They are researching cells that guide how bones and joints develop. They also are exploring which cells group into tissue, where they are found in the body and how they change over time.</p>
<p>The <strong>high-resolution,</strong> <strong>open-access</strong> atlas is considered a first version. The scientists say they hope it will help researchers fight diseases that damage human cells.</p>
<p>The current cell map not only shows many types of human cells. It also shows the relationships between cells, said Dr. Timothy Chan. Chan is a cancer expert at the Cleveland Clinic who was not involved in the project. Chan said the atlas project is a “<strong>deep dive </strong>into human biology” that is sure to help identify and treat cancer cells.</p>
<p>Scientists are also creating other atlases that could show more about the foundations of health and disease in specific parts of the body.</p>
<p>For example, researchers working on a brain atlas are seeking to understand the structure, <strong>location</strong> and function of the many types of brain cells. A new gut microbiome atlas is meant to show the collection of microorganisms in the intestines. Those organs play important parts in digestion and immune system health.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Adithi Ramakrishnan and Laura Ungar reported this story for The Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English with additional information from Reuters and other sources. </em></p>
<p><em>______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>type </strong><em>–n.</em> a particular kind of thing that is like others in the same group</p>
<p><strong>unique </strong><em>–adj.</em> something that is unlike anything else</p>
<p><strong>atlas </strong><em>–n.</em> a detailed map of a place or a thing that include picture or images</p>
<p><strong>curiosity </strong><em>–n.</em> the condition of being interested in something and wanting to learn more about it</p>
<p><strong>biologist </strong><em>–n.</em> a scientist who studies the processes of life and the living structures involved in it</p>
<p><strong>focus </strong><em>–v.</em> to place special attention on something or someone</p>
<p><strong>high-resolution </strong><em>–adj.</em> usually related to a kind of image that is very rich or high in detail showing very small or complex things clearly</p>
<p><strong>open-access </strong><em>–adj.</em> available to anyone and not requiring payment</p>
<p><strong>deep dive </strong><em>–n.</em> a complete investigation into something</p>
<p><strong>location </strong><em>–n.</em> the place where something is</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Mysterious Creature from Argentina Has Made Its Home in Dubai (2024/12/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202412/mysterious-creature-from-argentina-has-made-its-home-in-dubai.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 December, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Dubai in the United Arab Emirates is known for its tall, modern buildings rising high above the desert. But an unusual animal from Argentina, the Patagonian mara, can be found there, too.</p>
<p>The animal, like a rabbit, has long legs and ears and a body larger than most other rodents. They have been found near the Al Qudra Lakes, which are usually home to gazelle and other desert creatures found in the Emirates, or UAE.</p>
<p>How they got there remains a mystery. But in the UAE, <strong>exotic</strong> animals have ended up in the private homes and farms of the wealthy.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A Patagonia mara is seen at Al Qudra Lakes in Dubai, United Arab Emirates, Thursday, Nov. 21, 2024. (AP Photo/Jon Gambrell)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/57b429f6-d892-4742-b7f6-01e618b337ab_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A Patagonia mara is seen at Al Qudra Lakes in Dubai, United Arab Emirates, Thursday, Nov. 21, 2024. (AP Photo/Jon Gambrell)</span></div>
<p>The UAE's Climate Change and Environment Ministry and officials in Dubai did not answer questions from the Associated Press (AP) about the Patagonian maras. But one estimate suggests that as many as 200 could be <strong>thriving</strong> in the area of the Al Marmoom Desert Conservation Reserve nearby. Few dead maras have been found.</p>
<p>An AP reporter found at least five maras on a recent visit to the Al Qudra Lakes, a wide desert area 40 kilometers south of Dubai. On another visit, the reporter saw several <strong>packs</strong> of the animals, including one mother still <strong>nursing</strong> a baby.</p>
<p>Al Qudra is at the end of a long bicycle path. It is popular in the winter months. Campers and others come to enjoy the outdoors in the cooler weather among the area's lakes. Some of the lakes have been engineered into shapes like a moon, two hearts or as an advertisement for Dubai's Expo 2020.</p>
<p>The Patagonian maras first appeared publicly in 2020 during the height of the coronavirus pandemic. A request for information on their sightings was first published in an issue of the Dubai Natural History Group's monthly newsletter. Volunteers described seeing them in Al Qudra and on Saadiyat Island near the UAE's capital of Abu Dhabi.</p>
<p>“This large rodent is a common <strong>species</strong> in zoological collections and undoubtedly found its way out from captivity,” wrote Jacky Judas, who has long studied mammals in the UAE.</p>
<p>“They can regularly be seen sleeping or eating grass in the middle of <strong>roundabouts</strong> at Al Qudra...it can possibly survive in highly modified <strong>habitats</strong> with tree plantations, lawns and ponds,” Judas wrote.</p>
<p>Those words describe the environment found at Al Qudra and are probably the reason for the maras' continued survival. But temperatures in the UAE regularly reach 45 degrees Celsius in the summer, making it a difficult environment.</p>
<p>The number of maras at Al Qudra suggests that they are breeding. Patagonian maras mate for life, and females can get pregnant only a few times a year. They can give birth to one to three babies at a time. In Argentina, the animals can be hunted and eaten, their fur used for rugs and blankets.</p>
<p>The Patagonian maras eat plants and are no threat to humans. There are few animals that might hunt them at Al Qudra. Arabian red fox do live and hunt in the area.</p>
<p>Patagonian maras normally live in central and southern Argentina. But they have been trafficked into areas as <strong>exotic</strong> pets in the past. In the United States, the appearance of one was covered by the local news in Denver, Colorado. In August, a Patagonian mara was found in a car about to enter Turkey from Greece. Officials discovered other animals in the suspected trafficking attempt.</p>
<p>It is illegal to keep endangered or threatened wildlife in the Emirates. But there have been many reports and social media videos of Emirati men in <strong>luxury</strong> cars with pet lions along for the ride.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Jon Gambrell reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>thrive</strong> <em>–v.</em> to not only survive but to live well and to reproduce</p>
<p><strong>pack</strong> <em>–n. </em>a group of certain kinds of animals like dogs, hyenas, and some rodents</p>
<p><strong>nurse</strong> <em>–v.</em> when mother mammals provide milk to their young</p>
<p><strong>species</strong><strong> </strong><em>–n.</em> a kind of animal or plant that is like others of its kind and can reproduce with them</p>
<p><strong>roundabout</strong><strong> </strong><em>–n</em>. a circular roadway where two or more roads meet</p>
<p><strong>habitat </strong><em>–n.</em> an environment in which a plant or animal lives</p>
<p><strong>luxury </strong><em>–adj.</em> market by being very costly or excessive</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What Does ‘Like Gangbusters’ Mean? (2024/12/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/what-does-like-gangbusters-mean.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">30 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>With a new project, you may want to start with energy and excitement. If that is the case, you could say you want to start <u>like gangbusters.</u></p>
<p>To start <u>like gangbusters</u> means you start a project <u>on the right foot</u> – an exciting one! You begin with energy, speed, and sometimes, attention-getting success.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - John Dillinger (C), a well-known gangster, is handcuffed and guarded in court awaiting his trial on Feb. 9, 1934. (AP PHOTO)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/14F4B16C-9315-45BE-A9FD-96C3EF88CB4D_cx1_cy16_cw96_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">FILE - John Dillinger (C), a well-known gangster, is handcuffed and guarded in court awaiting his trial on Feb. 9, 1934. (AP PHOTO)</span></div>
<p>Let's hear some examples:</p>
<p><em>She works <u>like gangbusters</u> and gets the job done quickly. </em></p>
<p><em>The wildflowers are spreading <u>like gangbusters</u>.</em></p>
<p>We can use this expression to describe something that starts with a lot of <strong>enthusiasm</strong>. It can also mean someone or something is having great effect -- usually in a good way. Whatever the attempt is, it is successful.</p>
<p>To start something <u>like gangbusters</u> can also mean it involves great force or <strong>aggressiveness</strong>. For example, the partners worked <u>like gangbusters</u> to open their business before their <strong>rivals</strong> in the city.</p>
<p><u>Like gangbusters</u> can simply mean something is growing very fast. For example, if the economy is growing <u>like gangbusters,</u> it is growing very fast.</p>
<p>Sometimes we add the phrasal verb “come on,” making the expression <u>to come on like gangbusters.</u> The expression <u>to come on like gangbusters</u> can also mean to work hard and in an energetic, forceful manner to get something done.</p>
<p>Here are some examples:</p>
<p><em>When I gave the lesson to my students, they <u>came on like gangbusters</u> to try to solve the mystery.</em></p>
<p><em>The new employee <u>came on like gangbusters</u> during her first few months on the job. </em></p>
<p>But why <u>gangbusters</u>?</p>
<p>As a noun, <u>gangbuster</u> is a term for a law-enforcement officer who breaks up organized crime. <u>Gangbusters</u> often use forceful or aggressive means.</p>
<p>Word experts say the expression <u>like gangbusters</u> comes from a popular radio show called <em>Gang Busters</em> broadcast in the United States from 1935 to 1957. This crime-fighting radio drama started with a lot of noise and excitement – police sirens, screams, gun fire and exciting music.</p>
<p><u>Gangbuster</u> is also an adjective. It can describe something that is excellent or successful. For example, experts are reporting of a <u>gangbusters</u> housing market in rural areas.</p>
<p>It can also describe someone who is energetic or <strong>eager</strong> to do something. For example, if someone asks you to volunteer during the weekend you can say, “I'm not really <u>gangbusters</u> over that idea." However, this usage is not as common as <u>to come on like gangbusters.</u></p>
<p>And if you do not want to use <u>gangbusters</u>, you could say you <u>started something with a bang</u>. To <u>start or begin something with a bang </u>means you start in an exciting and noticeable way. You can also say to <u>be back with a bang.</u></p>
<p>Here's an example using that expression:</p>
<p><em>The singer took a year off. But with her new <strong>album</strong>, she's <u>back with a bang.</u></em></p>
<p>And that's end of this Words and Their Stories. Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>enthusiasm </strong><em>–n.</em><strong> </strong>strong excitement of feeling</p>
<p><strong>aggressiveness </strong><em>–n. </em>being forceful in getting things done</p>
<p><strong>rival </strong><em>–n. </em>one of two or more trying to get what only one can have</p>
<p><strong>eager </strong><em>–adj.</em><strong> </strong>marked by enthusiastic or impatient desire or interest</p>
<p><strong>album </strong><em>–n. </em>a collection of one or more audio recordings that is presented as a single unit and is typically longer than a single</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What Is GivingTuesday? (2024/11/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/what-is-givingtuesday.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Since its start in 2012, GivingTuesday, the Tuesday after Thanksgiving, has become one of the biggest money-raising days of the year for nonprofits in the United States.</p>
<p>In 2022 and 2023, GivingTuesday raised $3.1 billion for charity, or aid, organizations, as estimated by GivingTuesday.</p>
<p>This year, GivingTuesday is on December 3.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - N.C. State defensive end Davin Vann works among the donations collected to help Hurricane Helene victims in western North Carolina, Wednesday, Oct. 2, 2024 in Raleigh, N.C. (AP Photo/Aaron Beard)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/92e09aab-cba2-4a35-9147-5a51d5ee79b5_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - N.C. State defensive end Davin Vann works among the donations collected to help Hurricane Helene victims in western North Carolina, Wednesday, Oct. 2, 2024 in Raleigh, N.C. (AP Photo/Aaron Beard)</span></div>
<p><strong>How did GivingTuesday start?</strong></p>
<p>The #GivingTuesday <strong>hashtag</strong> started as a project of the 92nd Street Y in New York City in 2012. It became an independent organization in 2020. It has grown into a worldwide organization of local groups that support giving in their communities, often on different dates that have local importance, like holidays.</p>
<p>Now, GivingTuesday, the nonprofit, also gathers researchers studying everyday giving. It also collects data from wide sources like payment processors, <strong>crowdfunding</strong> sites, employee giving software and organizations that offer charitable giving.</p>
<p><strong>What is the purpose of GivingTuesday?</strong></p>
<p>For nonprofits, the point of GivingTuesday is to raise money and engage their supporters. Many nonprofits will organize fundraising campaigns with email and mail appeals that arrive on the Tuesday after Thanksgiving.</p>
<p>Nonprofits do not have to be linked in any way with GivingTuesday, the organization, to run a fundraising campaign. GivingTuesday will still provide them with <strong>graphics </strong>and advice. In that way, it remains a grassroots effort with groups and donors taking part as they like.</p>
<p><strong>Has GivingTuesday been successful?</strong></p>
<p>GivingTuesday has grown far beyond its early days when it mainly pushed for giving on social media. The day has become a well-known event that seeks to center charitable giving and volunteering in the U.S. and around the world.</p>
<p>For years, GivingTuesday has been a major <strong>focus</strong> of fundraising for nonprofits, with many seeking to organize <strong>matching</strong> donations from major donors. It is the beginning of the end-of-year fundraising race as nonprofits seek to reach their budget targets for the following year.</p>
<p>Donations on GivingTuesday in 2022 and 2023 reached $3.1 billion, an increase from $2.7 billion in 2021. While that is a lot to raise in a single day, the <strong>trend</strong> last year was flat and fewer donors were giving. The organization says that is a worrying sign.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted the story for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>hashtag </strong><em>– n.</em> a word or phrase preceded by the symbol # that classifies or categorizes the accompanying text (such as a tweet)</p>
<p><strong>crowdfunding </strong><em>– n</em>. the practice of obtaining needed funding (as for a new business) by soliciting contributions from a large number of people especially from the online community</p>
<p><strong>graphics </strong><em>– n</em>. <strong> </strong>graphic media such as images, maps, charts, etc.</p>
<p><strong>focus </strong><em>– n.</em> special attention you give something</p>
<p><strong>matching </strong><em>– adj.</em> equal in amount</p>
<p><strong>trend </strong><em>– n. </em>a general movement</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>The Cask of Amontillado (2024/11/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/cask-of-amontillado-edgar-allan-poe-american-stories.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By VOA</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>
Our story today is called "The Cask of Amontillado." It was written by Edgar Allan Poe. Here is Larry West with the story.</p>
<p>Storyteller: Fortunato and I both were members of very old and important Italian families. We used to play together when we were children.</p>
<p>Fortunato was bigger, richer and more handsome than I was. And he enjoyed making me look like a fool. He hurt my feelings a thousand times during the years of my childhood. I never showed my anger, however. So, he thought we were good friends. But I promised myself that one day I would punish Fortunato for his <strong>insults</strong> to me.</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/98805174-4c71-42c0-abb6-b0d1f03e19d1_w100_r1.png"/></div>
<p>Many years passed. Fortunato married a rich and beautiful woman who gave him sons. Deep in my heart I hated him, but I never said or did anything that showed him how I really felt. When I smiled at him, he thought it was because we were friends.</p>
<p>He did not know it was the thought of his death that made me smile.</p>
<p>Everyone in our town respected Fortunato. Some men were afraid of him because he was so rich and powerful. He had a weak spot, however. He thought he was an excellent judge of wine. I also was an expert on wine. I spent a lot of money buying rare and costly wines. I stored the wines in the dark rooms under my family's <strong>palace</strong>.</p>
<p>Our palace was one of the oldest buildings in the town. The Montresor family had lived in it for hundreds of years. We had buried our dead in the rooms under the palace. These tombs were quiet, dark places that no one but myself ever visited.</p>
<p>Late one evening during carnival season, I happened to meet Fortunato on the street. He was going home alone from a party. Fortunato was beautiful in his silk suit made of many colors: yellow, green, purple and red. On his head he wore an orange cap, covered with little silver bells. I could see he had been drinking too much wine. He threw his arms around me. He said he was glad to see me.</p>
<p>I said I was glad to see him, too because I had a little problem.<br/>
<br/>
"What is it?" he asked, putting his large hand on my shoulder.</p>
<p>"My dear Fortunato," I said, "I'm afraid I have been very stupid. The man who sells me wine said he had a rare barrel of Amontillado wine. I believed him and I bought it from him. But now, I am not so sure that the wine is really Amontillado."<br/>
<br/>
"What!" he said, "A <strong>cask</strong> of Amontillado at this time of year. An entire barrel? Impossible!"</p>
<p>"Yes, I was very stupid. I paid the wine man the full price he wanted without asking you to taste the wine first. But I couldn't find you and I was afraid he would sell the cask of Amontillado to someone else. So I bought it."</p>
<p>"A cask of Amontillado!" Fortunato repeated. "Where is it?"</p>
<p>I pretended I didn't hear his question. Instead I told him I was going to visit our friend Lucresi. "He will be able to tell me if the wine is really Amontillado," I said.</p>
<p>Fortunato laughed in my face. "Lucresi cannot tell Amontillado from vinegar."<br/>
<br/>
I smiled to myself and said "But some people say that he is as good a judge of wine as you are."<br/>
<br/>
Fortunato grabbed my arm. "Take me to it," he said. "I'll taste the Amontillado for you."<br/>
<br/>
"But my friend," I protested, "it is late. The wine is in my wine <strong>cellar</strong>, underneath the palace. Those rooms are very damp and cold and the walls drip with water."<br/>
<br/>
"I don't care," he said. "I am the only person who can tell you if your wine man has cheated you. Lucresi cannot!"</p>
<p>Fortunato turned, and still holding me by the arm, pulled me down the street to my home. The building was empty. My servants were enjoying <strong>carnival</strong>. I knew they would be gone all night.</p>
<p>I took two large candles, lit them and gave one to Fortunato. I started down the dark, twisting stairway with Fortunato close behind me. At the bottom of the stairs, the damp air wrapped itself around our bodies.<br/>
<br/>
"Where are we?" Fortunato asked. "I thought you said the cask of Amontillado was in your wine cellar."</p>
<p>"It is," I said. "The wine cellar is just beyond these tombs where the dead of my family are kept. Surely, you are not afraid of walking through the tombs.</p>
<p>He turned and looked into my eyes. "Tombs?" he said. He began to cough. The silver bells on his cap jingled.</p>
<p>"My poor friend," I said, "how long have you had that cough?"<br/>
<br/>
"It's nothing," he said, but he couldn't stop coughing.<br/>
<br/>
"Come," I said firmly, "we will go back upstairs. Your health is important.You are rich, respected, admired, and loved. You have a wife and children. Many people would miss you if you died. We will go back before you get seriously ill. I can go to Lucresi for help with the wine."</p>
<p>"No!" he cried. "This cough is nothing. It will not kill me. I won't die from a cough."<br/>
<br/>
"That is true," I said, "but you must be careful." He took my arm and we began to walk through the cold, dark rooms. We went deeper and deeper into the cellar.<br/>
<br/>
Finally, we arrived in a small room. Bones were pushed high against one wall. A doorway in another wall opened to an even smaller room, about one meter wide and two meters high. Its walls were solid rock.</p>
<p>"Here we are," I said. "I hid the cask of Amontillado in there." I pointed to the smaller room. Fortunato lifted his candle and stepped into the tiny room. I immediately followed him. He stood stupidly staring at two iron handcuffs chained to a wall of the tiny room. I grabbed his arms and locked them into the metal handcuffs. It took only a moment. He was too surprised to fight me.</p>
<p>I stepped outside the small room.</p>
<p>"Where is the Amontillado?" he cried.</p>
<p>"Ah yes," I said, "the cask of Amontillado." I leaned over and began pushing aside the pile of bones against the wall. Under the bones was a basket of stone blocks, some cement and a small shovel. I had hidden the materials there earlier. I began to fill the doorway of the tiny room with stones and cement.</p>
<p>By the time I laid the first row of stones Fortunato was no longer drunk. I heard him moaning inside the tiny room for ten minutes. Then there was a long silence.<br/>
<br/>
I finished the second and third rows of stone blocks. As I began the fourth row, I heard Fortunato begin to shake the chains that held him to the wall. He was trying to pull them out of the granite wall.</p>
<p>I smiled to myself and stopped working so that I could better enjoy listening to the noise. After a few minutes, he stopped. I finished the fifth, the sixth and the seventh rows of stones. The wall I was building in the doorway was now almost up to my shoulders.<br/>
<br/>
Suddenly, loud screams burst from the throat of the chained man. For a moment I worried. What if someone heard him? Then I placed my hand on the solid rock of the walls and felt safe. I looked into the tiny room, where he was still screaming. And I began to scream, too. My screams grew louder than his and he stopped.</p>
<p>It was now almost midnight. I finished the eighth, the ninth and the tenth rows. All that was left was a stone for the last hole in the wall. I was about to push it in when I heard a low laugh from behind the stones.<br/>
<br/>
The laugh made the hair on my head stand up. Then Fortunato spoke, in a sad voice that no longer sounded like him.</p>
<p>He said, "Well, you have played a good joke on me. We will laugh about it soon over a glass of that Amontillado. But isn't it getting late. My wife and my friends will be waiting for us. Let us go."</p>
<p>"Yes," I replied, "let us go."</p>
<p>I waited for him to say something else. I heard only my own breathing. "Fortunato!" I called. No answer. I called again. "Fortunato!" Still no answer.</p>
<p>I hurried to put the last stone into the wall and put the cement around it. Then I pushed the pile of bones in front of the new wall I had built.</p>
<p>That was fifty years ago. For half a century now, no one has touched those bones. "May he rest in peace!"</p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="p3">Words in this Story</h2>
<p><strong>carnival</strong> - <em>n</em>. a festival held before Lent that includes music and dancing</p>
<p><strong>cask</strong> - <em>n</em>. a container that is shaped like a barrel and is used for holding liquids (“an oak cask for wine”)</p>
<p><strong>palace</strong> - <em>n</em>. a very large and impressive house</p>
<p><strong>cellar</strong> - <em>n</em>. the part of a building that is entirely or partly below the ground</p>
<p><strong>insult</strong> - <em>v</em>. to do or say something that is o<i></i>64256;ensive to (someone) : to do or say something that shows a lack of respect for (someone) (“She felt they had insulted her by repeatedly ignoring her</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>It and That (2024/11/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/it-and-that.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Masa in Japan about the usage of the words “it” and “that” in English conversation.</p>
<p><strong>Question`</strong></p>
<p>Dear teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/dc0486e7-42af-4c21-88f3-fc823a8869f0_w268_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>I'd like to ask about [the choice of] pronouns, either "it" or "that,” in my English conversation. Sometimes, I'm confused about [choosing] these words.<br/>
Thank you,</p>
<p>Masa</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Masa.</p>
<p>We usually use the word “it” to describe a general state of our environment or a situation. And we often use the word “that” to answer something specific that someone said.</p>
<p>Let's consider the word “it” first. To describe a state means to describe what the environment or situation is like. The word “it” gives us a quick way of doing this. And we typically contract the word “it” with the verb “is” and say “It's”. So instead of saying:</p>
<p><em>The weather is very cold in Siberia in the winter. </em></p>
<p>We can simply say:</p>
<p><em><u>It's</u></em><em> very cold in Siberia in the winter. </em></p>
<p>Similarly, we can say:</p>
<p><em><u>It's</u> noisy here.</em></p>
<p><em><u>It's</u> crowded right now on the train.</em></p>
<p>We can also use the word “it” to describe what it is like to do something in general. Consider these examples:</p>
<p><em><u>It's</u> difficult to find a good hotel in that city. </em></p>
<p><em><u>It's</u> normal to feel nervous before giving a speech.</em></p>
<p>Now, let's consider the word “that.” Instead of describing the state of an environment, each of the following examples shows a person responding to a specific statement.</p>
<p>A: <em>I'm surprised you disagree with her.</em></p>
<p>B: <em>No, no,</em> <em><u>that</u> is not what I mean. I agree with what she said. </em></p>
<p> </p>
<p><em>A: Is <u>that</u> your explanation?</em></p>
<p><em>B: <u>That</u> is the best answer I can give you.</em></p>
<p> </p>
<p><em>A: Did Diane say she was leaving her job? </em></p>
<p><em>B: <u>That</u> is what I heard. </em></p>
<p>So, in general, when you answer to someone in conversation, you can use the word “that.”</p>
<p>However, there are times when we use the word “it” to answer something specific. For example, if someone asks you if you enjoy an activity, you can reply:</p>
<p><em>Yes, <u>it's</u> great. I love <u>it</u>. </em></p>
<p>There are many more uses of the word “that.” You can read and listen to a previous <em>Ask a Teacher </em>program: <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/this-and-that/7328363.html"><em>This and That</em></a><em>.</em></p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? We'd like to hear from you. Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please include where you are from in your email, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Astronomers Study Newly Discovered Fast-forming Exoplanet (2024/11/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/astronomers-study-newly-discovered-fast-forming-exoplanet.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Astronomers have observed a newborn planet that formed in three million years, a relatively brief time. They say the discovery<strong> </strong>leads to questions about the current understanding of the speed of planetary formation.</p>
<p>Space scientists estimate the planet to be around 10 to 20 times the mass of Earth. It is an exoplanet, meaning a planet outside our solar system. It is one of the youngest exoplanets ever discovered. It exists among dense gas and dust orbiting a young star. The orbiting matter is called a protoplanetary disk. It provides the materials necessary for planet formation.</p>
<p>The star it orbits is not as hot and is about half as bright as our sun. The star's mass is about 70 percent that of the sun. It is in our Milky Way galaxy, about 520 light-years from Earth. A light-year is the distance light travels in a year, 9.5 trillion kilometers.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Artist's concept of a young, newly discovered planet, exposed to observation by a warped debris disk. Photo by NASA/JPL-Caltech/R. Hurt, K. Miller (Caltech/IPAC)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/535a22b8-ad2a-4c90-a66f-51a06576c157_cx0_cy54_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Artist's concept of a young, newly discovered planet, exposed to observation by a warped debris disk. Photo by NASA/JPL-Caltech/R. Hurt, K. Miller (Caltech/IPAC)
</span></div>
<p>"This discovery confirms that planets can be in a <strong>cohesive</strong> form within 3 million years, which was <strong>previously</strong> unclear as Earth took 10 to 20 million years to form," said Madyson Barber, a research student at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill (UNC). Barber is the lead writer of the study published recently in <em>Nature </em>magazine.</p>
<p>"We don't really know how long it takes for planets to form," UNC professor and study co-writer Andrew Mann added. "We know that <strong>giant</strong> planets must form faster than their disk<strong> dissipates</strong> because they need a lot of gas from the disk. But disks take 5 to 10 million years to dissipate. So do planets form in one million years? Five? Ten?"</p>
<p>The planet orbits its star every 8.8 days. Its mass is in between that of Earth, the largest of our solar system's rocky planets, and Neptune, the smallest of the gas planets. It is less dense than Earth and has a <strong>diameter</strong> about 11 times greater. Its chemical makeup is not known.</p>
<p>The researchers suspect that the planet formed further away from its star and then moved closer.</p>
<p>"Forming large planets close to the star is difficult because the protoplanetary disk dissipates away from closest to the star the fastest, meaning there's not enough material to form a large planet that close that quickly," Barber said.</p>
<p>The researchers found the planet using the so-called "transit" method: observation of a drop in the star's brightness, from the <strong>perspective</strong> of an observer on Earth, when the planet passes in front of it. NASA's Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite, or TESS, space telescope discovered the exoplanet.</p>
<p>"This is the youngest-known transiting planet. It is on par with the youngest planets known," Barber said.</p>
<p>Stars and planets form from clouds of interstellar gas and dust.</p>
<p>"To form a star-planet system, the cloud of gas and dust will collapse and<strong> spin </strong>into a flat environment, with the star at the center and the disk surrounding it. Planets will form in that disk. The disk will then dissipate” starting from the star side, Barber said.</p>
<p>"It was previously thought that we wouldn't be able to find a transiting planet this young because the disk would be in the way. But for some reason that we aren't sure of, the outer disk is <strong>warped</strong>, leaving a perfect window to the star," Barber added.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Reuters news agency reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>cohesive </strong><em>– n.</em> exhibiting or producing the act or state of sticking together tightly</p>
<p><strong>previously </strong><em>– adv</em>. before; in the past</p>
<p><strong>giant </strong><em>– n</em>.<strong> </strong>huge</p>
<p><strong>dissipate </strong><em>– n. </em>to break up and scatter or vanish</p>
<p><strong>diameter </strong><em>– adj.</em> the length of a straight line through the center of an object or space</p>
<p><strong>spin </strong><em>– v. </em>to turn in a circular motion</p>
<p><strong>warp </strong>- to be turned or twisted out of, or as if out of, shape</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>‘Mini Moon’ Object Moves Away from Earth’s Orbit (2024/11/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/mini-moon-object-moves-away-from-earth-s-orbit.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">28 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>An <strong>asteroid</strong> that moved closer to Earth's orbit in recent months is now moving away from our planet as gravity pulls it back toward the sun.</p>
<p>The asteroid is small – about 10 meters long – and never presented any threat to Earth. But the object, known as 2024 PT5, was recently pulled closer to our planet by Earth's gravitational forces.</p>
<p>Scientists sometimes call such objects “mini-moons.” This is because they behave similarly to the permanent moon orbiting Earth when they are captured by gravity. But they are much smaller and stay only temporarily in Earth's orbit.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A supermoon with a partial lunar eclipse rises over Lake Michigan in Chicago, Sept. 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Kiichiro Sato, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/cc2e8c42-9edf-4bbd-bcf3-79dfd7cf9d2e_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A supermoon with a partial lunar eclipse rises over Lake Michigan in Chicago, Sept. 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Kiichiro Sato, File)</span></div>
<p>The American space agency NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://blogs.nasa.gov/planetarydefense/2024/10/02/nasa-to-track-asteroid-2024-pt5-on-next-close-pass-january-2025/">said</a> it does not consider 2024 PT5 a mini-moon because it was never expected to be fully captured by Earth's gravity. But NASA has described the small asteroid as “an interesting object” that is worthy of study. Such asteroids are considered near-Earth objects.</p>
<p>The space agency <a class="wsw__a" href="https://blogs.nasa.gov/planetarydefense/2024/10/02/nasa-to-track-asteroid-2024-pt5-on-next-close-pass-january-2025/">noted</a> that similarities between the asteroid's motion and that of Earth suggest the object could be a large piece of rock that broke off from the moon's surface after an asteroid strike in the distant past.</p>
<p>The object was first observed on August 7 by two astronomer brothers from Spain's Complutense University of Madrid – Carlos de la Fuente Marcos and Raúl de la Fuente Marcos. They identified the asteroid through observations made by a telescope in South Africa.</p>
<p>The Spanish astronomers said it appeared 2024 PT5 is part of a group of near-Earth objects within the Arjuna asteroid belt. They wrote that asteroids in this belt are believed to be “surrounding the path followed by the Earth-moon system.”</p>
<p>The Associated Press reported the astronomers had used telescopes in the Spanish Canary Islands, off the coast of northwestern Africa, to make hundreds of observations. The object is currently more than 3.5 million kilometers from Earth. Only powerful telescopes can see the asteroid because of its small size and low brightness.</p>
<p>The astronomers say 2024 PT5 should head back to Earth in the coming weeks. It is expected to pass as close as 1.8 million kilometers from Earth in January. The moon stays at a distance of about 384,000 kilometers from our planet, NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/moon/facts/">explains</a>.</p>
<p>The asteroid will then move farther into the solar system while orbiting the sun. Scientists say the next time the object is expected to make another close move toward Earth is in 2055.</p>
<p>Raul de la Fuente Marcos told the AP that 2024 PT5 was first identified in August and began its move toward Earth in late September. He said the object's path was similar to the shape of a horseshoe.</p>
<p>De la Fuente Marcos noted that by the time the asteroid returns in January, it will be moving at more than double the speed from September. Current data suggests that during its 2055 visit, it will again make a temporary and partial circle around Earth.</p>
<p>NASA said teams at its Center for Near Earth Object Studies had continually followed the movements of 2024 PT5. It is normal for NASA and its international partners to continuously search the skies for near-Earth objects. Such objects include asteroids and <strong>comets</strong> that come within 50 million kilometers of Earth's orbit.</p>
<p>The search system, called ATLAS, involves four different telescopes. Two of them are based in Hawaii. Another operates in Chile and the other sits in South Africa. NASA explains that ATLAS is designed to search the whole sky several times each night looking for moving objects.</p>
<p>The space agency <a class="wsw__a" href="https://blogs.nasa.gov/planetarydefense/2024/10/02/nasa-to-track-asteroid-2024-pt5-on-next-close-pass-january-2025/">says</a> it will use its large Goldstone Solar System Radar observer – which sits in Barstow, California – to follow 2024 PT5 when it again is pulled toward Earth's orbit in 2025.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>asteroid </strong><em>– n.</em> a rocky object that goes around the sun like a planet</p>
<p><strong>comet </strong><em>– n.</em> an object in space that leaves a bright line behind it in the sky</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Proposes Measures to Limit Google after Monopoly Ruling (2024/11/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/us-proposes-measures-to-limit-google-after-monopoly-ruling.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">27 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The United States government has proposed a series of measures to limit Google from anti-competition business activities. The move comes after a federal judge ruled in August Google had violated trade laws by operating its search engine as an illegal <strong>monopoly</strong>.</p>
<p>The <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/judge-rules-google-has-illegal-monopoly-over-search/7733698.html">ruling</a> accused Google of paying smartphone makers to ensure that its search engine was set as the <strong>default</strong> system on new devices. The U.S. Justice Department brought the antitrust case against Google's parent company, Alphabet.</p>
<p>Last week, the Justice Department issued a set of corrective guidelines for Google. Here is a look at the proposed measures as well as the government's case against the American tech giant.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Sundar Pichai, current head of Google, speaks at Google I/O 2013 in San Francisco, Wednesday, May 15, 2013. (AP Photo/Jeff Chiu)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-c0a8-0242-64ef-08db838b1ac9_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Sundar Pichai, current head of Google, speaks at Google I/O 2013 in San Francisco, Wednesday, May 15, 2013. (AP Photo/Jeff Chiu)</span></div>
<p><strong>What is the Justice Department's goal?</strong></p>
<p>Justice Department officials say the main goal of the proposals is to get Google to stop using its highly popular search engine to illegally block competition and restrict <strong>innovation</strong>.</p>
<p>The Department said Google's violations of U.S. trade law had given the company an unfair <strong>advantage</strong> in the online search business. It accuses Google of illegally gaining that advantage.</p>
<p>Google has criticized the court's decision. The company's chief legal officer, Kent Walker, also condemned the Justice Department's corrective proposals. He called the guidelines “wildly overbroad” in an online statement. He added his opinion that the measures seek to go way beyond the court's ruling.</p>
<p>Walker said the proposals “would break a<strong> range</strong> of Google products – even beyond search – that people love and find helpful in their everyday lives.”</p>
<p><strong>What are some of the Justice Department's proposals?</strong></p>
<p>The Justice Department proposed a series of measures to limit Google from blocking competition from other search engine providers.</p>
<p>The main proposal is a ban on Google from signing deals – worth billions of dollars – to lock its search engine as the default system on Apple's iPhone and other popular devices. This measure could result in reduced profits for companies that sign such deals.</p>
<p>Other proposed measures include a ban on Google from using search results to favor its own services, such as YouTube or its artificial intelligence (AI) tool, Gemini. Another would force Google to<strong> license</strong> its search data to competitors.</p>
<p>In addition, the Justice Department is seeking to require Google to be more open about how it sets the prices advertisers must pay to be listed near the top of some targeted search results.</p>
<p>Another proposal would give publishers, websites and content creators the right to request that their data not be included in Google's search results or be used to train the company's AI models.</p>
<p><strong>What comes next in the case?</strong></p>
<p>Google will also have the chance to propose its own list of fixes to the court. After that, federal <strong>regulators</strong> will create a new version of the proposals in early March. Court hearings on the proposed measures are set to begin in April and the judge is expected to issue a final decision before September 2025.</p>
<p>The trial to rule on the final proposals will take place after President-elect Donald Trump takes office. Trump has made comments suggesting a breakup of Google is not in the U.S. national interest.</p>
<p>However, some recent nominations put forward by Trump's <strong>transition</strong> team have favored those who have been critical of big technology companies. And since the case was brought during Trump's first term, it is likely to move forward.</p>
<p>But before the final trial begins, Google is expected to appeal the case. Experts say this may mean the case could stretch out for years in the courts.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>monopoly </strong><em>– n.</em> complete control of the entire supply of goods or of a service in a certain area or market</p>
<p><strong>default </strong><em>– n.</em> what exists or usually happens if no changes are made</p>
<p><strong>innovation </strong><em>– n</em>. the act or process of introducing new ideas, devices or methods</p>
<p><strong>advantage </strong><em>– n</em>. a condition that provides a greater chance of success</p>
<p><strong>range</strong> <em>– n.</em></p>
<p><strong>license</strong> <em>– v.</em></p>
<p><strong>regulate </strong><em>– v.</em> to bring something under government control</p>
<p><strong>transition </strong><em>– n.</em> a change from one system or administration to another</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Thanksgiving: An American Tradition (2024/11/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/thanksgiving-american-tradition-2017.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Ashley Thompson</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">27 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The American holiday of Thanksgiving is celebrated every year on the fourth Thursday in November. The holiday is during autumn -- the main season for harvesting crops. Thanksgiving is an autumn harvest <strong>festival</strong> like those found in many cultures around the world.</p>
<p>On this day, most Americans gather with friends and family. Many take time to think about what they are thankful for, cook <strong>up a storm</strong>, and eat.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/871699e4-0f5b-48b3-83f9-34d2801e6ed9_cx0_cy10_cw0_w100_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>A lot.</p>
<p>The star of most Thanksgiving dinners is a <strong>roasted </strong>turkey. Turkeys are large birds native to North America.</p>
<p>The turkey is cooked in an oven for many hours, often with a mix of celery, bread, onions and spices inside the bird. This mix becomes <strong>stuffing </strong>-- another star of the Thanksgiving dinner table.</p>
<p>Anna Matteo here at Learning English says the smell of turkey and stuffing roasting together is the quintessential smell of Thanksgiving. “Quintessential” means the perfect example of something.</p>
<p>After the bird is cooked, the stuffing is taken out and served as a side dish.</p>
<p>One of <em>many </em>side dishes. Families often make other foods like mashed potatoes, sweet potatoes, cranberry sauce and vegetable casseroles. A casserole is a dish that cooks slowly in an oven.</p>
<p>And do not forget about the gravy. This rich sauce is made from the fatty liquid that comes off the turkey as it cooks. People cover their turkey meat, stuffing and mashed potatoes with gravy.</p>
<p>The meal does not end with the turkey, stuffing, and side dishes, though. For some people, the best part of the meal is dessert.</p>
<p>The quintessential Thanksgiving dessert is pie. Pumpkin, cherry, apple or pecan pie are all great ways to finish off a Thanksgiving meal...if you are not too full of food by that point!</p>
<p><strong>Thanksgiving travel </strong></p>
<p>Some Americans must travel long distances to be with their families. In fact, the Sunday after Thanksgiving is the busiest travel day of the entire year. This is usually when people return home from family gatherings.</p>
<p>Not everyone can make the return home each Thanksgiving. So, young people living in cities away from their hometowns sometimes celebrate “Friendsgiving” -- a Thanksgiving meal with their friends instead of their family. They gather at someone's apartment or house and have a “<strong>potluck</strong>.” This is a meal where everyone who is invited brings food to share with others.</p>
<p><strong>Beyond the table</strong></p>
<p>Thanksgiving is a big day for television, games and other entertainment.</p>
<p>One tradition is the television broadcast of Macy's Thanksgiving Day Parade. It takes place each year in New York City. Workers of the Macy's store on Herald Square organized the first parade in 1924. Many of the workers were immigrants and wanted to hold a big parade like the ones in Europe. So, they dressed in costumes and borrowed some animals from the zoo. They also carried small balloons that floated just overhead.</p>
<p>Many professional American football games are also played on Thanksgiving. Fans of the sport enjoy relaxing and watching a game or two after eating a big Thanksgiving meal.</p>
<p>Some start Thanksgiving Day early - and in a healthy way. So-called “Turkey <strong>Trot</strong>” races take place in many towns and cities. These events involve runners dressing up in a Thanksgiving-related costume and running a short distance -- usually five kilometers.</p>
<p>Many Turkey Trots urge runners to bring canned food to donate to local food banks -- non-profit organizations that give food to poor people in a community.</p>
<p><strong>Serving those less fortunate</strong></p>
<p>Certainly, not everyone in America has an easy Thanksgiving. The United States is home to many poor and homeless people. Some cannot afford a Thanksgiving dinner. Others are without friends or families. Many religious and service organizations around the country try to fill these needs. Some provide community dinners at churches and other centers. Some groups also deliver Thanksgiving meals to people too sick or old to leave their homes.</p>
<p>The writer O. Henry called Thanksgiving the one holiday that is purely American. It is not linked to a religion or a certain group. Anyone in the United States on the fourth Thursday of November is welcome to celebrate Thanksgiving.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p>And I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>Ashley Thompson wrote this story for Learning English. It was first published in 2017.</em></p>
<p>___________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"> </h2>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>festival</strong> - <em>n</em>. a special time or event when people gather to celebrate something</p>
<p><strong>up a storm</strong> - <em>idiom</em>. used to say that something is being done with a lot of energy or enthusiasm</p>
<p><strong>roasted </strong>- <em>adj</em>. cooked with dry heat in an oven or over a fire</p>
<p><strong>stuffing</strong> - <em>n</em>. a seasoned mixture of food that is put inside another food and cooked</p>
<p><strong>potluck</strong> - <em>n</em>. a meal to which everyone who is invited brings food to share</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Mysterious Shoe Thief Identified (2024/11/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/mysterious-shoe-thief-identified.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">27 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Police suspected someone was stealing shoes from a children's school in southwestern Japan. But a security camera caught the thief in action. It was a weasel!</p>
<p>The small animal with a long body and short legs usually hunts for rats and rabbits. But this one was hunting for children's shoes.</p>
<p>After the children's shoes began disappearing, police put in place three security cameras in the school in Fukuoka in southern Japan. Soon after, recorded video showed a weasel with a small shoe in its mouth.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image made from security camera video released by Kasuya Police shows a weasel with a shoe at a kindergarten in Koga, Fukuoka prefecture, southwestern Japan, on Nov. 11, 2024. (Kasuya Police via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/362b0edd-d99c-43e9-b19b-6bde2764535b_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image made from security camera video released by Kasuya Police shows a weasel with a shoe at a kindergarten in Koga, Fukuoka prefecture, southwestern Japan, on Nov. 11, 2024. (Kasuya Police via AP)</span></div>
<p>“It's great it turned out not to be a human being,” Deputy Police Chief Hiroaki Inada told The Associated Press recently. Teachers and parents had feared the thief could be a person with mental health problems.</p>
<p>Japanese often take their shoes off before entering homes. The shoes that disappeared were all <strong>slip-ons</strong> the children wore indoors, stored in special spaces near the door.</p>
<p>Weasels are known to hide items. People who keep weasels as <strong>pets</strong> give them toys so they can hide them.</p>
<p>The weasel moved shoes around and took 15 of them before police were called. Six more were taken the following day. The weasel returned to steal one more shoe. The video of that theft was seen the next day.</p>
<p>The shoe-loving weasel only took the white indoor shoes made of canvas, likely because they are light to carry.</p>
<p>“We were so <strong>relieved</strong>,” the school's <strong>kindergarten</strong> director Yoshihide Saito told Japanese broadcaster RKB Mainichi Broadcasting.</p>
<p>The children got a good laugh when they saw the weasel in the video.</p>
<p>Although the stolen shoes were never found, the remaining shoes are now safely behind <strong>netting</strong> that covers the storage spaces.</p>
<p>The weasel, which is believed to be wild, is still on the loose.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Yuri Kageyama reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>slip-on </strong><em>– n.</em> a shoe without fastenings</p>
<p><strong>pet </strong><em>-- n. </em>a domesticated animal kept for pleasure</p>
<p><strong>relieved </strong><em>– adj. </em>experiencing or showing relief especially from anxiety or emotions that have built up</p>
<p><strong>kindergarten </strong><em>– n. </em>a school or class for children who are usually five to six years old</p>
<p><strong>netting </strong><em>-- n. </em>material consisting of pieces of string or rope that are woven together</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Nations Agree to $300 Billion Deal at Climate Talks (2024/11/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/nations-agree-to-300-billion-deal-at-climate-talks.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Countries from around the world recently agreed to provide $300 billion to support poor nations in the face of climate change.</p>
<p>The agreement reached on November 24 at the United Nations climate talks in Azerbaijan left many unsatisfied. But some were hopeful that it would be a step in the right direction.</p>
<p>The final deal says that rich countries have agreed to collectively provide at least $300 billion a year by 2035. The amount is much smaller than the $1.3 trillion that developing nations were asking for and that experts said was needed.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Activists participate in a demonstration for climate finance at the COP29 U.N. Climate Summit, Friday, Nov. 22, 2024, in Baku, Azerbaijan. (AP Photo/Sergei Grits)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/5c5bc254-ba86-4ae4-99e5-7f6d58325c6f_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Activists participate in a demonstration for climate finance at the COP29 U.N. Climate Summit, Friday, Nov. 22, 2024, in Baku, Azerbaijan. (AP Photo/Sergei Grits)
</span></div>
<p>Chandni Raina is India's negotiator at the climate talks. She told The Associated Press that the amount of money in the deal was very small. She said, “I'm sorry to say we cannot accept it.”</p>
<p>Nigeria's Nkiruka Maduekwe, head of the National Council on Climate Change, called the deal an insult and a joke.</p>
<p>Ani Dasgupta is head of the environmental organization World Resources Institute. Dasgupta called it "an important down payment toward a safer, more <strong>equitable</strong> future." However, he added that the poorest countries are "rightfully disappointed” that wealthy nations did not offer more money with billions of lives at risk.</p>
<p>The meeting went on longer than expected because of serious divisions and strong disagreements among countries. But delegations who feel more hopeful about the agreement said this deal is headed in the right direction, with hopes that more money will come in the future.</p>
<p>Eamon Ryan, Ireland's environment minister, called the agreement “a huge <strong>relief</strong>.” He said in a time of division and war, “the fact that we could get it through in these difficult <strong>circumstances</strong> is really important.”</p>
<p><strong>Final agreement at climate talks</strong></p>
<p>The final agreement includes a call for parties to work together using "all public and private sources" to get closer to the $1.3 trillion per year goal by 2035. That means also pushing for large international banks to help pay the bill. And it means, hopefully, that companies and private investors will follow by spending their money toward climate action.</p>
<p>The agreement also calls for developing countries that receive money to limit or cut the release of heat-trapping gases. Those targets are to be set early next year. They are part of the plan to keep cutting pollution with new targets every five years, which the world agreed to at the U.N. talks in Paris in 2015.</p>
<p>The money will pay for the move away from <strong>fossil fuels</strong> toward clean energy. It will go to countries hard hit by extreme weather to prepare for floods, storms and fires. It will also go toward improving a farming process to help them survive weather extremes. In areas hit regularly by severe storms, the money can help build stronger homes or help people move to safer places.</p>
<p>The Philippines, for example, has been hit by six major storms in less than a month. Millions of people faced strong winds, rising waters and serious damage to homes, roads and bridges and farmland.</p>
<p>Esther Penunia works with the Asian Farmers Association. She said many farmers had to deal with storm damage such as trees that will not produce fruit for months or years, or animals that died.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Melina Walling </em><em>reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>equitable </strong>- <em>adj</em>. dealing fairly and equally with everyone</p>
<p><strong>relief</strong> – <em>n</em>. a pleasant and relaxed feeling that someone has when something unpleasant stops or does not happen</p>
<p><strong>circumstances</strong> – <em>n</em>.(usually plural) a condition or fact that affects a situation</p>
<p><strong>fossil fuel</strong> – n. a fuel (such as coal, oil, or natural gas) that is formed in the earth from dead plants or animals</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Group Helps People Exercise Outdoors (2024/11/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/group-helps-people-exercise-outdoors.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the Health &amp; Lifestyle report.</p>
<p>In Edmonton, Alberta, the sun had yet to come up. The temperature was more than 20 degrees below zero. In the dark and cold, Tanis Smith was ready to run up and down hundreds of stairs among the trees in the Saskatchewan River Valley.</p>
<p>And Smith was not alone. Ten people joined her for the activity. All were wearing several <strong>layers</strong> of clothing to keep warm.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this May 25, 2016 photo, members of the running group " and="" andrew="" down="" friendship="" fun="" group="" harnik="" in="" keep="" lincoln="" memorial="" moving.="" november="" of="" people="" photo="" project="" run="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/6822190d-518b-4cd8-9775-efd50b696af8_w268_r1.jpg" stairs="" the="" to="" up="" uses="" washington.=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this May 25, 2016 photo, members of the running group "November Project" run up and down the stairs of the Lincoln Memorial, in Washington. The group uses fun and friendship to keep people moving. (AP Photo/Andrew Harnik)</span></div>
<p>“You're pretty much just putting everything you own on,” said Smith, an accountant. “If you look at the pictures, you don't know who you are unless you remember what you were wearing.”</p>
<p>Since that winter back in 2013, Smith has rarely missed a workout with a group called November Project.</p>
<p>November Project is a network of free outdoor group exercise classes that started in Boston, Massachusetts. No matter the weather, members get out of bed before sunrise at least once a week and go outdoors for group exercise.</p>
<p>November Project is part exercise, part fun, and part community. It is a model for exercising outdoors, especially in the winter.</p>
<p>It started in 2011, when two friends agreed to exercise every morning for the month of November. They were looking for accountability and <strong>motivation</strong> to help them stick to an exercise <strong>routine</strong>.</p>
<p>By the end of that first month, they had invited others to join them. Soon, their meetings were bringing in almost forty people. And it became a year-round project.</p>
<p>“A party is better when there's more people around. We would talk to anybody who would listen,” said Bojan Mandaric. He created the project with friend, Brogan Graham.</p>
<p>Then, as people moved to other cities, they took the idea with them. So, the November Project grew. Now, there are 52 groups in eight countries, including 44 in the United States and Canada.</p>
<p><strong>What do the workouts look like?</strong></p>
<p>People of all ages and fitness levels join the workouts. Some groups begin with something called “The Bounce.” They <strong>chant</strong> and jump at the same time to bring the group together. Those who feel <strong>inhibited</strong>, do not have to do this.</p>
<p>Most classes include running and body weight exercises like <strong>squats</strong>. The project also uses the surroundings of the location. So, for example, some places include running up steps in an outdoor sports <strong>stadium</strong>. Currently in D.C., members meet on Wednesdays to run up the steps of the Lincoln Memorial.</p>
<p>To keep the workouts fun, they also might include fun games and activities from childhood. In Edmonton, they play snow games in winter and water games in summer. The games help to lower inhibitions. This helps people make connections, said Jason Shaw. He is co-leader of the Indianapolis, Indiana group.</p>
<p>“Nobody (is) cool at November Project,” he said.</p>
<p>Shaw said groups recognize members' <strong>milestones</strong>. People can earn prizes for reaching different goals.</p>
<p>To find out if a November Project group is near you, go to their website at <a class="wsw__a" href="https://november-project.com/np-experience/">November-Project.com</a>. Building community and making friends is another big part of the project. So, each group is active on social media.</p>
<p>If you do not have a November Project nearby, you can find another type of outdoor exercise group. Or start your own.</p>
<p>The November Project organizers offer a few suggestions on how to work out during colder months.</p>
<p><strong>Find workout friends</strong></p>
<p>Find workout friends. At the center of the project, is accountability. Members promise to show up. There is a sense of letting down your teammates if you do not show up, said Mandaric, who moved to Boston from Serbia to row <strong>crew</strong> for Northeastern University. (Rowing crew is a type of boat racing.)</p>
<p><strong>Invest in some cold-weather clothing</strong></p>
<p>There is no such thing as bad weather, just bad clothing, said Shaw, the leader from Indianapolis. He suggests wearing clothing next to your skin that removes <strong>sweat</strong>. This will help keep you warm and dry. Avoid cotton, he warned. It keeps sweat in contact with your body and will make you colder.</p>
<p>Also, add a top layer that protects against bad weather. On its webpage, the November Project leaders for Washington, DC say workouts are not cancelled for weather.</p>
<p><strong>Make it a usual activity</strong></p>
<p>Promise yourself to exercise on the same days and times for a month. Create a routine. This will make it easier to stick to an exercise routine, says Mandaric.</p>
<p><strong>Make it fun</strong></p>
<p>And make sure to have fun. Exercise does not have to be hard or serious.</p>
<p>Smith, the member from Edmonton, Alberta, says she enjoys the social part of the November Project the most. She calls it “a chosen family.” They came together because they had fun exercising. She said. “You can have fun and get fit.”</p>
<p>And that's the Health &amp; Lifestyle report. I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Albert Stumm reported this story for the Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it into a lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>layer </strong><em>-n.</em><strong> </strong>one thickness or fold over or under another</p>
<p><strong>call-and-response </strong><em>-n.</em><strong> </strong>statement quickly followed by an answering statement</p>
<p><strong>chant </strong><em>-n. </em>a rhythmic, one-tone statement or song said out loud</p>
<p><strong>squat </strong><em>-n. </em>an exercise in which a standing person lowers to a position in which the torso is erect and the knees are deeply bent and then rises to an upright position</p>
<p><strong>burpee </strong><em>-n. </em>conditioning exercise in which a person squats, places the palms of the hands on the floor in front of the feet, jumps back into a push-up position, in some cases completes one push-up, returns to the squat position, and then jumps up into the air while extending the arms overhead</p>
<p><strong>inhibition </strong><em>-n. </em>a restraint or check upon the free or spontaneous instincts or impulses of an individual guided or directed by the social and cultural forces of the environment</p>
<p><strong>milestone </strong><em>-n. </em>a significant point in development</p>
<p><strong>crew </strong><em>-n. </em>the sport of rowing a boat, causing it to move through water using poles with flat ends called oars</p>
<p><strong>sweat </strong><em>-n. </em>the fluid excreted from the sweat glands of the skin</p>
<p><strong>routine</strong> <em>-n. </em>a standard or regular way of doing something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Fossil from Germany Provides New Details about Ancient Flying Reptiles (2024/11/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/fossil-from-germany-provides-new-details-about-ancient-flying-reptiles.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists say a <strong>fossil</strong> found in Germany is providing new details about flying reptiles that lived on Earth about 147 million years ago.</p>
<p>The fossil was discovered in 2015 in the southeastern German state of Bavaria. It contains the remains of a newly identified <strong>species</strong> called Skiphosoura bavarica.</p>
<p>Skiphosoura is considered a pterosaur, an ancient flying reptile. It lived toward the end of the Jurassic Period. Researchers say the creature played an important part in the development of <strong>ecosystems</strong> during the age of the dinosaurs.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A life restoration of two individuals of the newly identified Jurassic Period pterosaur species Skiphosoura bavarica are pictured in flight, in this illustration released on November 18, 2024. (Gabriel Ugueto/Handout via REUTERS)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4a2b77e1-d0d9-40d5-834d-f12dec72f9f8_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A life restoration of two individuals of the newly identified Jurassic Period pterosaur species Skiphosoura bavarica are pictured in flight, in this illustration released on November 18, 2024. (Gabriel Ugueto/Handout via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>The reptile had a wing reach of about 2 meters for traveling and a set of sharp teeth to help capture and eat other animals. Skiphosoura would have been one of the largest fliers in its ecosystem. Researchers say the discovered fossil was in good shape, with nearly every bone remaining in the skeleton. This has permitted the team to learn new details about this pterosaur.</p>
<p>One of the leaders of the fossil examinations is David Hone of Queen Mary University of London. He told Reuters news agency he thinks the fossil find was "of huge importance."</p>
<p>Hone was the lead writer of a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cell.com/current-biology/fulltext/S0960-9822(24)01377-0">study</a> describing the team's work in the publication <em>Current Biology</em>. He added that Skiphosoura has provided new information about the evolution of pterosaurs. "It also brings other pterosaur finds we had already made into <strong>focus</strong>,” Hone said.</p>
<p>He added that the discovery also helps better explain “where they go in the family tree of pterosaurs” and permits scientists to show this development from early to later forms.</p>
<p>"The teeth are quite long and sharp. They are for <strong>puncturing</strong> and holding," Hone said. He noted these were likely used to catch smaller animals such as lizards, small mammals, insects and possibly fish.</p>
<p>Pterosaurs are considered ancestors of the dinosaurs. They were the first of three groups of vertebrates – animals with a backbone – to enjoy powered flight. Pterosaurs disappeared about 66 million years ago in the mass <strong>extinction</strong> that also took out most of the dinosaurs after an <strong>asteroid</strong> struck Earth.</p>
<p>Scientists divide pterosaurs into two major groups - the early non-pterodactyloids and the later pterodactyloids. The early group's members had a short head, short neck, long tail and a long fifth toe on the foot. The later ones had a large head, long neck, short tail, long wrist and short fifth toe.</p>
<p>The team says the discovery of Skiphosoura – along with another species that lived 170 million years ago in Scotland – have helped shape important events in pterosaur development.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Reuters reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>fossil </strong><em>– n.</em> something (such as a leaf, skeleton, or footprint) from a plant or animal that lived in ancient times and that you can see in old rocks</p>
<p><strong>species </strong><em>– n</em>. a group of animals or plants that are similar and can produce young animals or plants</p>
<p><strong>ecosystem </strong><em>– n</em>. all the living things in a particular area, as well as the ways the things affect each other and the environment</p>
<p><strong>focus </strong><em>– n.</em> special attention you give something</p>
<p><strong>puncture </strong><em>– v.</em> to make a hole in something</p>
<p><strong>extinct </strong><em>– adj. </em>not existing anymore</p>
<p><strong>asteroid </strong><em>– n. </em>a rocky object that goes around the sun like a planet</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Doctors Give New Guidelines for Preventing Stroke (2024/11/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/doctors-give-new-guidelines-for-preventing-stroke.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>New guidelines have been issued in the United States for preventing stroke – the nation's 4<sup>th</sup> biggest killer.</p>
<p>The U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) says that in 2023, stroke was the fourth leading cause of death in the United States. An estimated half a million people suffer strokes in the U.S. each year. But the CDC notes that up to 80 percent of strokes could be prevented with better nutrition and exercise, along with improved risk identification.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A beach goer exercises as the sun rises above the Atlantic Ocean, Feb. 1, 2023, in Surfside, Fla. (AP Photo/Wilfredo Lee, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/adfb512d-035a-4eae-9bb2-3ad6e53e2eed_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A beach goer exercises as the sun rises above the Atlantic Ocean, Feb. 1, 2023, in Surfside, Fla. (AP Photo/Wilfredo Lee, File)</span></div>
<p><strong>What is a stroke?</strong></p>
<p>A stroke happens when blood flow to part of the brain is blocked or if a blood vessel in the brain breaks open, or bursts. The event keeps oxygen from getting to the brain. This can result in the person having difficulty thinking, talking and walking. In some cases, a stroke can even cause death.</p>
<p>Stroke is a major health problem across the world. On its website, the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.world-stroke.org/world-stroke-day-campaign/about-stroke/impact-of-stroke">World Stroke Organization</a> says the condition is a leading cause of death and disability worldwide. Over 100 million people worldwide have suffered a stroke. It is estimated that 25 percent of adults over 25 will have a stroke during their lifetime.</p>
<p>The new guidelines on stroke prevention came from the American Stroke Association. They are the first to be issued in 10 years. The advice includes suggestions for people and doctors and are based on improved information about who has strokes and why. The guidelines also include new drugs that can help reduce risk.</p>
<p>Health researchers say the best way to reduce the risk of stroke is the same as reducing risks for many other conditions. These include eating a healthy diet, moving the body often and not smoking.</p>
<p>Here is what to know about stroke and the newly issued guidelines:</p>
<p><strong>Eating healthy can reduce stroke risk</strong></p>
<p>Experts say eating healthy can help control possible stroke risks. The goal is to prevent or reduce high cholesterol, high blood sugar and obesity, the condition of being extremely overweight.</p>
<p>The advice urges people to choose foods in the so-called Mediterranean diet. These include fruits, vegetables, whole grains and olive oil. Eating these foods can help keep cholesterol levels down.</p>
<p>Red meat should be limited, along with <strong>saturated fats</strong>. Additional protein can come from beans, nuts, poultry and seafood. Highly processed foods and drinks with a lot of added sugar should also be avoided.</p>
<p><strong>Moving your body can help prevent strokes</strong></p>
<p>Getting up and walking around for at least 10 minutes a day can greatly reduce a person's stroke risk, said Dr. Cheryl Bushnell. She is a neurologist at Wake Forest University School of Medicine in North Carolina.</p>
<p>Bushnell was part of the group that came up with the new guidelines. She said regular exercise can help reduce blood pressure, a major risk <strong>factor</strong> for stroke.</p>
<p>However, health experts say more movement is better. The stroke association suggests at least 150 minutes of moderate <strong>aerobic</strong> or 75 minutes of <strong>vigorous</strong> exercise activity every week. Such exercise could include going to the gym, taking a walk or running. People can also use exercise machines at home, dance or play a sport.</p>
<p><strong>New tools to reduce obesity, a risk factor for stroke</strong></p>
<p>The guidelines include a new group of drugs that have been proven to help people lose weight.</p>
<p>The drugs – designed for people with obesity or diabetes – had not been approved when past guidelines were issued. But the advice now suggests doctors consider these drugs for patients at risk for stroke. These include versions sold under the names Ozempic, Wegovy, Mounjaro, and Zepbound,.</p>
<p>The new guidelines also help doctors identify people who might be at higher risk for stroke. For the first time, the advice suggests doctors <strong>screen</strong> patients for other risk factors. They could include gender or non-medical factors such as economic issues or the availability of quality health care.</p>
<p>The new guidelines also suggest that doctors screen for conditions that may increase a woman's risk for stroke. These could include high blood pressure during pregnancy or early <strong>menopause</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>How do I know if I'm having a stroke and what do I do?</strong></p>
<p>Three of the most common stroke signs include face weakness, arm weakness and difficulty speaking. Also, time is important when a person suffers a stroke. Brain damage can happen quickly, but it can be limited if a stroke is treated quickly.</p>
<p>Stroke experts have created an <strong>acronym</strong> to help people remember: FAST -- F for face, A for arm, S for speech, and T for time.</p>
<p>If you think you or a loved one may be having a stroke, call the emergency response number in your area immediately.</p>
<p>And that's the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p>And I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Kenya Hunter </em><em>reported this story for the Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>factor </strong><em>–n.</em><strong> </strong>something that contributes to the production of a result</p>
<p><strong>saturated fat </strong><em>–n. </em>a fat that contains a fatty acid molecule which has no double bonds and only single bonds in its hydrocarbon chain, that is solid at room temperature, and that is found especially in animal products (such as meat and dairy), coconut, and palm products</p>
<p><strong>calorie </strong><em>–n.<strong> </strong></em>an amount of food having an energy-producing value of one large calorie</p>
<p><strong>moderate</strong> <em>–adj. </em>neither very much nor very little :<strong> </strong>average in size or amount</p>
<p><strong>aerobic </strong><em>–adj. </em>involving or increasing oxygen use</p>
<p><strong>vigorous </strong><em>–adj. </em>possessing vigor <strong>: </strong>full of physical or mental strength or active force</p>
<p><strong>screen </strong><em>–v. </em>to examine usually methodically in order to make a separation into different groups : to test or examine for the presence of something (such as a disease)</p>
<p><strong>menopause </strong><em>–n. </em>the natural cessation of menstruation that usually occurs between the ages of 45 and 55</p>
<p><strong>acronym</strong> <em>–n. </em>a word (such as NATO, radar, or laser) formed from the initial letter or letters of each of the successive parts or major parts of a compound term</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Would You Pay $344 for a Coffee? (2024/11/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/would-you-pay-344-for-a-coffee.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A Scottish dairy, or milk cow farm, is offering what it calls Britain's costliest coffee: one cup for $344.</p>
<p>It is a huge price for a little cup of coffee, but the man selling it offers a deal sweetener: a share of a dairy farm.</p>
<p>For that price, they also receive 34 shares in Mossgiel Organic Dairy. The company offers the deal in a <strong>crowdfunding</strong> campaign it opened. It hopes to raise enough money to enlarge its <strong>sustainable</strong> operation and produce more milk.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This undated handout photo shows farmer and owner of Mossgiel Organic Farm Bryce Cunningham, right, giving a bottle of milk to barista Jacob Smith, as they pose outside The Good Coffee Cartel in Glasgow, Scotland. (Mossgiel Organic Dairy via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/794ef179-2795-4803-8e2f-d393072ebf9e_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This undated handout photo shows farmer and owner of Mossgiel Organic Farm Bryce Cunningham, right, giving a bottle of milk to barista Jacob Smith, as they pose outside The Good Coffee Cartel in Glasgow, Scotland. (Mossgiel Organic Dairy via AP)</span></div>
<p>Investors who buy 34 shares get a <strong>certificate</strong> for a special coffee drink called a flat white. Holders can present their certificate and get their flat white at one of 13 coffee shops in Scotland that use the dairy's milk.</p>
<p>The dairy's owner, Bryce Cunningham, notes his coffee costs 80 times the usual price. "We know it sounds crazy, but when you break it down, it's a pretty good deal. How much is the future of farming worth,” he asked.</p>
<p>The price tops the $320 for a flat white at Shot London, a coffee bar in the wealthy Mayfair and Marylebone neighborhoods. That flat white was made with rare coffee beans from Okinawa, Japan. <em>The Telegraph</em> newspaper reported in April that it was the most costly coffee in Britain.</p>
<p>Cunningham is seeking about $375,000 from small investors in order to secure a much larger bank loan. He had already raised more than a third of his goal when he offered the flat white farm shares deal.</p>
<p>The loan he is seeking is worth more than $1.1 million. He says that financing will help him double operations and expand out of Scotland all the way to London.</p>
<p>Shareholders receive other rewards, too, such as farm visits, milk transport deals and invitations to special events. But investors are also given a <strong>standard</strong> warning that they could lose some or all of the money they invest.</p>
<p>The dairy farm in Mauchline, about 40 kilometers south of Glasgow, is historic. The famous 18th-century Scottish poet Robert Burns once worked at the farm. Burns, considered the national poet of Scotland, wrote while working in the fields there for two years. An image of his face is on each glass container of Mossgiel milk.</p>
<p>Todd Whiteford is an owner of The Good Coffee Cartel in Glasgow, that is serving the costly cups. He said the store has been using Mossgiel's milk for several years. He said other milk producers cannot meet the quality of Mossgiel's milk. He said it makes “rounder, smoother and sweeter” drinks.</p>
<p>“Theirs is the best. I'll argue with anyone about that,” Whiteford said.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter Jr.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>cohesive </strong><em>– n.</em> exhibiting or producing the act or state of sticking together tightly</p>
<p><strong>previously </strong><em>– adv</em>. before; in the past</p>
<p><strong>giant </strong><em>– n</em>.<strong> </strong>huge</p>
<p><strong>dissipate </strong><em>– n. </em>to break up and scatter or vanish</p>
<p><strong>diameter </strong><em>– adj.</em> the length of a straight line through the center of an object or space</p>
<p><strong>spin </strong><em>– v. </em>to turn in a circular motion</p>
<p><strong>warp </strong>- to be turned or twisted out of, or as if out of, shape</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>American Companies Develop Unmanned Aircraft for Crops (2024/11/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/american-companies-develop-unmanned-aircraft-for-crops.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">24 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>American companies are developing unmanned aircraft systems that are larger than <strong>drones</strong>. The goal is for the aircraft to help agricultural producers and reduce risks to human safety.</p>
<p><strong>Rotor technologies </strong></p>
<p>When Hector Xu was learning to pilot a <strong>helicopter</strong> in college, he remembered having a few bad experiences while flying at night.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A Rotor Technologies unmanned semi-autonomous helicopter sprays a payload of water during a test flight over Intervale Airport, Monday, Nov. 11, 2024, in Henniker, N.H. (AP Photo/Charles Krupa)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a7f9bcb1-c664-4a2b-8cd7-0f144a5722a3_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A Rotor Technologies unmanned semi-autonomous helicopter sprays a payload of water during a test flight over Intervale Airport, Monday, Nov. 11, 2024, in Henniker, N.H. (AP Photo/Charles Krupa)</span></div>
<p>The experiences led him to research unmanned aircraft systems while getting his doctorate at Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Then, Xu formed Rotor Technologies in 2021 to develop unmanned helicopters.</p>
<p>Rotor has built two <strong>autonomous</strong> helicopters that the company calls Sprayhawks. Rotor aims to have as many as 20 Sprayhawks ready for market next year. The company also is developing helicopters that would fly shipments into disaster areas and to oil rigs in oceans. The helicopters could also be used to fight wildfires.</p>
<p>For now, Rotor is paying attention to agriculture. The industry has accepted automation with drones but sees unmanned helicopters as a better way to spray larger areas with <strong>pesticides </strong>and fertilizers.</p>
<p><strong>Safety </strong></p>
<p>A major appeal of automation in agriculture flights is safety.</p>
<p>Because special airplanes called <strong>crop dusters </strong>fly at around 240 kph and only about 3 meters off the ground, there are tens of accidents each year. The small planes hit power lines, cell towers and other planes. Older planes in disrepair and pilot tiredness play a part in accidents.</p>
<p>A 2014 report from the National Transportation Safety Board found there were more than 800 agriculture flight accidents between 2001 and 2010, including 81 that were deadly. A separate report from the National Agriculture Aviation Association found nearly 640 accidents from 2014 until this month with 109 deaths.</p>
<p>“It is a very, very dangerous, profession,” said Dan Martin, a research engineer with the U.S. Department of Agriculture's Agriculture Research Service. Martin said about the pilots, “They make all their money in those short few months so sometimes it may mean that they fly 10 to 12 hours a day or more.”</p>
<p>Job risks also include possible contact with farming chemicals.</p>
<p>In recent years, safety and cost concerns have led to a number of drones flying above farmers' fields, Martin said.</p>
<p>He added that some 10,000 drones will likely be sold this year alone. “It's growing <strong>exponentially</strong> as a market, super fast,” Martin said.</p>
<p>But the size of the drones means they only can cover a small amount of the area that a plane or helicopter can. The limitation is providing an opening for companies building bigger unmanned aircraft like Rotor and another company, Pyka.</p>
<p>California-based Pyka announced in August that it had sold its first autonomous electric aircraft for crop protection to a buyer in the United States. Pyka's Pelican Spray, a fixed-wing aircraft, received official approval last year to fly for crop protection. The company also sold its Pelican Spray to Dole for use in Honduras and to the Brazilian company, SLC Agrícola.</p>
<p>Lukas Koch is chief technology officer at Heinen Brothers Agra Services, the company which bought the Pelican Spray in August. Koch has called unmanned aircraft part of a coming “revolution,” that will save farmers money and increase safety.</p>
<p>The Kansas-based company operates out of airports from Texas to Illinois. Koch does not see the unmanned aircraft replacing all the company's pilots but rather taking over the riskiest jobs.</p>
<p>“The biggest draw is taking the pilot out of the aircraft inside of those most dangerous situations,” Koch said.</p>
<p>But Koch also says that autonomous aviation systems could bring new dangers to an already busy airspace. Still, the risk is less of a concern in rural areas with plenty of open space and fewer people.</p>
<p><strong>The future </strong></p>
<p>Companies like Rotor have developed their systems to work if bad events come up.</p>
<p>Rotor's helicopter, for example, has a half-dozen communications systems and, for now, a remote pilot in control.</p>
<p>If the ground team loses contact with the helicopter, Rotor has a system to deal with the problem. The system makes sure the engine can be turned off and the helicopter can perform a controlled landing.</p>
<p>The safety measures will go a long way to helping the company receive what it expects will be official government approval to fly its helicopters for business purposes. Once the company has approval, the difficulty, as Xu sees it, will be building more devices to meet the demand in the United States and Brazil.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Michael Casey reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>drone </strong><em>– n.</em> a small uncrewed aircraft guided by remote control or onboard computers</p>
<p><strong>helicopter</strong><em>—n.</em> an aircraft whose lift comes from one or more powered rotors turning about vertically</p>
<p><strong>autonomous</strong><em> – adj.</em> undertaken or carried on without outside control</p>
<p><strong>pesticide</strong> <em>– n.</em> a chemical or agent used to destroy pests</p>
<p><strong>crop duster</strong> – <em>n.</em> the airplane used to spray crops especially with pesticides</p>
<p><strong>exponentially</strong> <em>– adv.</em> characterized by an extremely fast increase</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>NASA Reconnects with Voyager, Longest Serving Mission in History (2024/11/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/nasa-reconnects-with-voyager-longest-serving-mission-in-history.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">24 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>NASA has once again reconnected with its Voyager spacecraft, marking a continuation of the American space agency's longest mission in history.</p>
<p>The two spacecraft – Voyager 1 and Voyager 2 – launched within weeks of each other in 1977. So they have been operating for more than 47 years.</p>
<p>NASA officials have reported several difficulties with the spacecraft in recent years, mainly communication issues. The most recent problems involved the Voyager 1 spacecraft. NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.jpl.nasa.gov/news/nasas-voyager-1-resumes-sending-engineering-updates-to-earth/">said</a> in a statement in April it had remained out of touch with the spacecraft for the previous five months.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This artist's concept shows NASA's Voyager 1 spacecraft traveling through interstellar space, or the space between stars, which it entered in 2012. (Image Credit: NASA/JPL-Caltech)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-521b-08dbfbd5ea87_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This artist's concept shows NASA's Voyager 1 spacecraft traveling through interstellar space, or the space between stars, which it entered in 2012. (Image Credit: NASA/JPL-Caltech)</span></div>
<p>Agency officials said they later learned the problem was linked to a <strong>chip</strong> inside one of Voyager 1's onboard computers. The issue made data being sent by the spacecraft unreadable. NASA said its engineers were able to fix that problem by making changes to how the spacecraft stores and reads data.</p>
<p>Then, in October, NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://blogs.nasa.gov/voyager/2024/10/28/after-pause-nasas-voyager-1-communicating-with-mission-team/">reported</a> another communication issue that resulted in a brief delay in receiving data from Voyager 1. That problem turned out to be linked to the spacecraft's radio transmitter system.</p>
<p>The agency said that, for some reason, Voyager 1's <strong>fault</strong> protection system was activated when NASA sent a command for the spacecraft to turn on one of its heaters. This activation – meant to save power – led Voyager 1 to start sending signals to a different radio <strong>transmitter</strong> system than it normally uses.</p>
<p>This meant NASA had to listen for the signals on the S-band instead of the usual X-band. Once they did this, they were able to start receiving data again. NASA has said the S-band is much weaker than the X-band, so engineers were seeking to get the X-band radio communication system back online for long-term use.</p>
<p>NASA said the agency had not used the S-band since 1981.</p>
<p>Voyager 1 and Voyager 2 are NASA's most distant operating spacecraft. The agency has reported Voyager 1 is exploring space from about 24 billion kilometers from Earth, while Voyager 2 is operating from about 20.5 billion kilometers away.</p>
<p>Because of this great distance, NASA says its communication with the two Voyagers takes about one day to receive data, and another day to send information back from Earth.</p>
<p>The two Voyagers were first designed to explore Jupiter and Saturn. Both spacecraft successfully carried out studies of those planets. Later, Voyager 2 made the first-ever close observations of Uranus and Neptune in 1989.</p>
<p>The two spacecraft then began a new mission to explore distant areas of space. In 2013, NASA announced Voyager 1 had crossed over the border dividing our solar system from interstellar space. The term “interstellar” means “between stars.” Scientists say interstellar space begins where the sun's continuous flow of particles and its magnetic field stop.</p>
<p>Voyager 2 first entered interstellar space in 2018. NASA said the spacecraft was more than 17.7 billion kilometers from the sun at the time. Both Voyagers are the only spacecraft so far to explore interstellar space.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p>The space agency says the Voyagers are studying how the interstellar medium interacts with the solar wind. Solar wind is the continuous flow of charged particles released by the sun. The spacecraft have also provided data on the heliosphere, a kind of protective <strong>bubble</strong> around our solar system.</p>
<p>Suzanne Dodd is the current project manager for the Voyager mission at NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory in California. She recently <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/missions/voyager-program/still-kickin-since-the-70s-nasas-voyager-mission-keeps-exploring/">said</a> in a statement the agency has no plans to retire the two Voyagers as long as they are communicating with mission members back on Earth. Dodd said the spacecraft are currently centered on observing how interstellar space and the heliosphere interact with each other.</p>
<p>"We wouldn't be doing Voyager if it wasn't taking science data," she added. Dodd noted one reason the Voyagers have been operating for so long is that the engineers who built them provided multiple backup systems to avoid future problems.</p>
<p>She said some who worked on Voyager in its earliest days have even come back from retirement to pass on knowledge to the next generation of scientists and engineers.</p>
<p>"From where I sit as a project manager, it's really very exciting to see young engineers be excited to work on Voyager,” Dodd said. “To take on the <strong>challenges</strong> of an old mission and to work side by side with some of the <strong>masters</strong>, the people that built the spacecraft – they want to learn from each other."</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from NASA.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>chip </strong><em>– n.</em> a small part of a computer that stores and helps process information</p>
<p><strong>fault </strong><em>– n.</em> something that goes wrong with a particular system</p>
<p><strong>transmitter </strong><em>– n</em>. a piece of equipment used to send and receive radio signals through the air</p>
<p><strong>bubble </strong><em>– n</em>. a ball of gas enclosed by another material</p>
<p><strong>challenge </strong><em>– n.</em> something difficult that tests one's ability or determination</p>
<p><strong>master </strong><em>– n.</em> someone who has demonstrated they can do something very well</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Fossil Found in Brazil Shows Birds’ Brain Development (2024/11/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/fossil-found-in-brazil-shows-birds-brain-development.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">24 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The brains of today's birds show a level of intelligence and behavioral complexity <strong>rivaled</strong> only by<strong> mammals</strong>. But scientists do not fully understand how bird brains have changed over millions of years from the form they had as dinosaurs. That understanding is now growing thanks to a <strong>fossil</strong> discovery in Brazil.</p>
<p>Researchers unearthed the remains, or fossil, of a head bone, or skull, of a bird <strong>species</strong> not known before. It has been named Navaornis hestiae. The fossil was in such good condition that scientists were able to create a computer image of its brain and inner ear structures. It lived in a dry area about 80 million years ago during the Cretaceous Period, near the end of the age of dinosaurs.</p>
<p><strong>One of a kind</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Photo of Navaornis hestiae fossil from report by Luis M. Chiappe, Guillermo Naval&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;243;n, Agust&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;237;n G. Martinelli, Ismar de Souza Carvalho, Rodrigo Miloni Santucci, Yun-Hsin Wu &amp; Daniel J. Field, November 13, 2024. (https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-08114-4#rightslink)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/6d6b9299-e754-47c0-a5d1-34e3a56ac629_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Photo of Navaornis hestiae fossil from report by Luis M. Chiappe, Guillermo Naval<i>&amp;#</i>243;n, Agust<i>&amp;#</i>237;n G. Martinelli, Ismar de Souza Carvalho, Rodrigo Miloni Santucci, Yun-Hsin Wu &amp; Daniel J. Field, November 13, 2024. (https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-08114-4#rightslink)</span></div>
<p>"This finding is one-of-a-kind," said University of Cambridge fossil expert Guillermo Navalón, a lead researcher of the study. It appeared this month in the publication <a class="wsw__a" href="https://rdcu.be/d0IAO"><em>Nature</em></a><em>.</em></p>
<p>Birds developed from small, feathered dinosaurs during the Jurassic Period. The Navaornis discovery filled in a 70-million-year <strong>gap </strong>in the understanding of the development of the bird, dating back to the earliest-known bird Archaeopteryx. It lived about 150 million years ago in what is now Europe.</p>
<p>The researchers said the Navaornis skull has a bill and eye shape like modern birds. Its brain shows both modern and ancient elements, and some that are in between.</p>
<p><strong>Well-preserved example</strong></p>
<p>Luis Chiappe is a fossil scientist at the Natural History Museum of Los Angeles County in California and a co-writer of the study.</p>
<p>He said scientists rarely find such skulls of early birds, “and this one is the best <strong>preserved</strong> ever."</p>
<p>Daniel Field is a fossil scientist at the University of Cambridge and the study's lead writer. He said scientists have long struggled to understand how and when the brains and intelligence of birds developed. “The field has been awaiting the discovery of a fossil exactly like this one," he said.</p>
<p>The Navaornis brain - measuring about 10 millimeters across - is smaller, relative to skull size, than that of modern birds. But the skull is larger and more complex than that of Archaeopteryx.</p>
<p>Its cerebellum, a brain structure that in living birds helps with motor control during flight, was smaller than in today's bird species and more like Archaeopteryx's. But its brain was connected to the spinal cord in a way similar to modern birds, as well as humans. It was unlike Archaeopteryx and the dinosaurs from which birds evolved.</p>
<p>Navaornis also had something special – its inner ear organ for balance is larger than in any other known bird.</p>
<p>The fossil included 80 percent of the bird's bone structure, or skeleton. The scientists say they believe the bird could fly well based on their examination of the remains.</p>
<p>Its name means "Nava's bird," named for William Nava, the scientist who discovered the fossil in 2016 in the southeastern Brazilian state of Sao Paulo.</p>
<p><strong>No direct line to today's birds</strong></p>
<p>Navaornis lived during the Cretaceous period, but none of these birds survived the <strong>asteroid</strong> strike that took place 66 million years ago. That means there is no direct line from Navaornis to today's birds, and its modern-looking abilities and appearance developed separately from theirs.</p>
<p>The researchers said the bird ate insects and seeds it could take in whole. It lived side-by-side with huge, long-necked plant-eating dinosaurs and large meat-eating dinosaurs.</p>
<p>Field said if you gave it a quick look you might think it was like a living bird. But a closer look would show you some important differences – like <strong>claws</strong> coming out of its wings.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Will Dunham </em><em>reported this story for Reuters. The images are licensed under Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License </em>(https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-08114-4#rightslink<em>). Jill Robbins adapted the report for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>rival</strong> – <em>v</em>. to be as good or almost as good as (someone or something)</p>
<p><strong>mammal </strong>– <em>n. </em>a type of animal that feeds milk to its young and that usually has hair or fur covering most of its skin</p>
<p><strong>fossil </strong>- <em>n</em>. something (such as a leaf, skeleton, or footprint) that is from a plant or animal which lived in ancient times and that you can see in some rocks</p>
<p><strong>species</strong> – <em>n</em>. biology. a group of animals or plants that are similar and can produce young animals or plants</p>
<p><strong>gap</strong> –<em> n</em>. a difference between two people, groups, or things — often + between</p>
<p><strong>skull </strong>- <em>n</em>. the structure of bones that form the head and face of a person or animal</p>
<p><strong>evolve</strong> –<em> v.</em> to change or develop slowly often into a better, more complex, or more advanced state; to develop by a process of evolution</p>
<p><strong>paleontologist</strong> <em>– n. </em>the science that deals with the fossils of animals and plants that lived very long ago especially in the time of dinosaurs</p>
<p><strong>preserved</strong> –<em> adj</em>. kept in good condition over a long period of time</p>
<p><strong>asteroid</strong> –<em> n</em>. any of the small rocky celestial bodies found especially between the orbits of Mars and Jupiter</p>
<p><strong>claw</strong> – <em>n</em>. a sharp usually slender and curved nail on the toe of an animal</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Learn 'Rub Elbows,' Other 'Rub' Expressions (2024/11/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/learn-to-rub-elbows-other-rub-expressions.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">23 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Today we are talking about the term “rub.” While this three-letter word is small, it should not be seen as unimportant. In fact, "rub" carries a lot of meaning and can be used in many different situations.</p>
<p>For starters, "rub" is a noun.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Boston Red Sox third baseman Rafael Devers gets an elbow bump from the batboy (right) after hitting a two-run home run at Tropicana Field, Sept. 10, 2020, St. Petersburg, Florida. (Reinhold Matay-USA TODAY Sports)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/054e991e-0780-41c9-9bc7-ec67c96d5132_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Boston Red Sox third baseman Rafael Devers gets an elbow bump from the batboy (right) after hitting a two-run home run at Tropicana Field, Sept. 10, 2020, St. Petersburg, Florida. (Reinhold Matay-USA TODAY Sports)</span></div>
<p>One way it is used this way is in cooking. A rub is a collection of dry seasonings that can be added to meat, tofu or vegetables before cooking.</p>
<p>"Rub" can also mean something problematic. If I ask, "<u>What's the rub</u>?" I am asking “What's the problem?” (This expression is very <strong>informal</strong>.)</p>
<p>“Rub” is also a verb.</p>
<p>For example, I might rub my head if I have a headache. Or I may rub my shoulder if it hurts. And if something really hurts, I might rub in some medicine to help reduce the pain.</p>
<p>But <u>to rub something in</u> also has another meaning – an <strong>idiomatic </strong>one. If you <u>rub something in</u>, you keep reminding someone of something unpleasant. This is a very common expression. So, let's hear it used in a conversation.</p>
<p><em>A: Hey, I had fun playing basketball yesterday. Your team almost won. Almost. </em></p>
<p><em>B: It was fun. I got a great workout. </em></p>
<p><em>A: What was the score again?</em></p>
<p><em>B: Okay, okay. Stop <u>rubbing it in!</u> Your team beat mine by ... a lot!</em></p>
<p><u>Rubbing something in</u> is similar to <u>rubbing someone's nose in something</u>. In the example we just heard, one man rubs his friend's nose in a loss at a basketball game. When we rub someone's nose in something, we remind them that they have failed or got something wrong.</p>
<p>As a verb, “rub” is used in many other expressions.</p>
<p>If you <u>rub someone the wrong way</u>, you cause that person to be angry or annoyed. It means you have <strong>irritated</strong> them, usually for something in your <strong>personality</strong> or behavior. You do not have to do anything specific to <u>rub someone the wrong way</u>. For example, the president of the company <u>rubbed some of his employees the wrong way</u> with his direct way of speaking.</p>
<p>Another expression is <u>to rub elbows with someone.</u> We use this expression to describe being at the same event as someone or simply being around them. But we don't generally use it for interactions with our close friends. Often, the people we <u>rub elbows</u> with are famous, important, or influential. For example, I <u>rubbed elbows</u> with some famous people at the mayor's birthday celebration.</p>
<p>Another way to use the verb “rub” is in the expression <u>to rub salt in the wound</u>. This means you make a bad situation worse for someone else. Let's say you know someone who loses their job. When they tell you that news, you remind them that they still owe you money. You have just <u>rubbed salt in the wound</u>. Ouch! This is similar to <u>kicking someone when they are down</u>.</p>
<p>Another use of the word “rub” is in the phrasal verb <u>rub together</u>. We use this with other words to say that we lack something. For example, if I <u>don't have two brain cells to rub together</u>, I can't think straight. I'm <strong>confused</strong>. Or, if you <u>don't have two dimes to rub together</u>, you have no money. You are <strong>broke</strong>! (You could also say pennies or quarters -- as long as they are coins.)</p>
<p>Our last expression is <u>to rub something out</u>. That means you get rid of it. And sometimes we use it in a rather violent situation. If a bad person <u>rubs someone out</u>, they do away with them. In other words, they actually kill them!</p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>!</p>
<p>Until next time ... I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>informal </strong><em>-adj.</em><strong> </strong>characteristic of or appropriate to ordinary, casual, or familiar use</p>
<p><strong>idiom </strong><em>-n. </em>an expression that cannot be understood from the meanings of its separate words but must be learned as a whole</p>
<p><strong>idiomatic </strong><em>-adj.</em> of, relating to, or conforming to idiom<em> </em></p>
<p><strong>irritated </strong><em>-adj. </em>to be impatient, angry, or displeased</p>
<p><strong>personality </strong><em>-n. </em>the whole collection of individual emotions and behavior that make one person different from others</p>
<p><strong>confused </strong><em>-adj. </em>being disordered or mixed up</p>
<p><strong>broke </strong><em>-adj. </em>having no money</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Baby Hippo in Thailand Gets Official Song for Worldwide Fans (2024/11/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/baby-hippo-in-thailand-gets-official-song-for-worldwide-fans.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A baby hippopotamus in Thailand became famous earlier this year when zoo workers published images and videos of her online. Now the pygmy hippo, named Moo Deng, has an official song and video released in several languages for her fans worldwide.</p>
<p>Moo Deng lives at Khao Kheow Open Zoo, southeast of the Thai capital, Bangkok. Zoo worker Atthapon Nundee has been posting sweet moments of the animal's life for the past few months.</p>
<p>During that time, the hippo has received widespread attention on social media. Fans of the animal have expressed how they enjoy watching the pink-cheeked baby actively interact with her mother and other zoo workers.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Two-month-old baby hippo Moo Deng walks at the Khao Kheow Open Zoo in Chonburi province, Thailand, Sept. 19, 2024. (AP Photo/Sakchai Lalit, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f3e16e95-3879-43b1-92f5-c9065e5496b6_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Two-month-old baby hippo Moo Deng walks at the Khao Kheow Open Zoo in Chonburi province, Thailand, Sept. 19, 2024. (AP Photo/Sakchai Lalit, File)</span></div>
<p>Moo Deng – which means “<strong>bouncy</strong> pork” in Thai – is a kind of meatball. The name, chosen by fans on social media, is similar to those of her two <strong>siblings</strong>: Moo Toon (stewed pork) and Moo Waan (sweet pork). In addition, the zoo has a common hippo named Kha Moo (stewed pork leg).</p>
<p>Moo Deng's popularity has spread internationally and she has gained the attention of some professional sports teams. Fans say her name fits her lively <strong>personality</strong>. Moo Deng likes to “deng,” or bounce, and her bouncing behavior has led to countless internet <strong>memes</strong>.</p>
<p>For example, the German soccer team FC Bayern, American basketball team Phoenix Suns and the American football team Washington Commanders have all created Moo Deng memes. The images give her interesting things to wear and put her in different human-like situations.</p>
<p>Atthapon, the zoo worker, told The Associated Press he was surprised the newborn pygmy hippo quickly became such a huge internet star. “I wanted people to know her,” he explained. “I wanted a lot of people to visit her, or watch her online, or leave fun comments. I never would've thought (of this),” he added.</p>
<p>The widespread publicity led a well-known Thai composer to write and produce a special song for Moo Deng. The lively, 50-second song is called, naturally, <em>Moodeng</em>. One of Thailand's biggest recording companies, GMM Music, released the song.</p>
<p>A music video that goes along with the song shows the baby hippo bouncing around, playing with her keeper or spending time with her mother, Jona.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p>Moo Deng is now four months old. She has also been drawing big crowds at the zoo. Officials estimated the baby hippo has brought in about 3,000 to 5,000 visitors a day on average during the past few months. The zoo has been selling clothes, bedding and other products based on Moo Deng.</p>
<p>The zoo's director is Narongwit Chodchoi. He told the AP that the additional earnings from Moo Deng will help the zoo's <strong>breeding</strong> programs for many endangered animals, like the pygmy hippopotamus. Illegal hunting and loss of <strong>habitat</strong> threatens the animal's existence. Pygmy hippos are native to West Africa. But experts say there are only 2,000-3,000 of them left in the wild.</p>
<p>All four versions of the Moo Deng song are available on YouTube and on streaming services including Spotify and Apple Music.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>bounce </strong><em>– v.</em> to move up or away after hitting a surface</p>
<p><strong>sibling </strong><em>– n.</em> a brother or sister</p>
<p><strong>personality </strong><em>– n.</em> a set of emotional qualities that makes a person different from other people</p>
<p><strong>meme </strong><em>– n. </em>an idea, image, video, etc. that spreads very quickly on the internet</p>
<p><strong>breed </strong><em>– v. reproduce</em></p>
<p><strong>habitat </strong><em>– n. </em>the natural environment an animal or plant usually lives in</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Learning Prepositions (2024/11/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/learning-prepositions.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Kelvin in Ghana about the usage of prepositions in English.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/47edc4e2-745b-439f-a1c9-24dda264089d_w268_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>Please, I would like to know more about prepositions.</p>
<p>Thank you,</p>
<p>Kelvin</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Kelvin.</p>
<p>Prepositions are those small words that give additional information about nouns, such as direction, time, location, and possession.</p>
<p>We can put prepositions into two large groups. In the first group, prepositions tell us about direction, location, time, and relations between people or things. These details are what people first learn when they study prepositions in English. Just a few examples of location and time include:</p>
<p><em><u>on</u> the table.</em></p>
<p><em><u>under</u></em><em> the table.</em></p>
<p><em><u>by</u> nine <u>in the</u> morning.</em></p>
<p><em><u>at</u></em><em> night.</em></p>
<p>Some examples that show relations between people include:</p>
<p><em>A friend <u>of</u> mine.</em></p>
<p><em>I worked <u>with</u> him. </em></p>
<p><em>I did it <u>for</u> you.</em></p>
<p><strong>Prepositions in common expressions</strong></p>
<p>The second large group includes common expressions where the preposition sometimes has a less exact meaning. That is why knowing which preposition to use with these expressions becomes more difficult.</p>
<p>Consider the following two examples. The first is used in British English, the second in American English:</p>
<p><em>This house is <u>different to</u> the one I used to live in.</em></p>
<p><em>This house is <u>different from</u> the one I used to live in. </em></p>
<p>The two examples mean the same thing. And there is no clear reason why we should use one preposition instead of the other.</p>
<p>Here is another expression where we use one preposition instead of another. We often say:</p>
<p><em>The news took me <u>by</u> surprise.</em></p>
<p>But we never say:</p>
<p><em>The news took me <u>with</u> surprise.</em></p>
<p>However, notice that changing the preposition “by” to the preposition “with” does not appear to change the meaning of this expression.</p>
<p>To someone learning English, one preposition might seem as good a choice as any other for this expression. That is why it is easy to make mistakes and sometimes difficult to remember the correct preposition to use.</p>
<p>So, how can you remember what preposition to use with such expressions?</p>
<ul>
<li>Do not try to learn the expression separately from the preposition, and then go back and put the preposition in your memory.</li>
<li>Instead, try to hear and remember the entire expression as one phrase instead of several words.</li>
<li>Just as we put numbers into groups of three or four to remember phone numbers, try to think of an expression and its preposition together as one group.</li>
</ul>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? We'd like to hear from you. Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please include where you are from in your email, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>‘A Great Situation:’ Canadian Town Lives with Polar Bears (2024/11/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/a-great-situation-canadian-town-lives-with-polar-bears.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Churchill, Manitoba is a small, rural Canadian town that lives with neighboring <strong>predators </strong>and loves it. That is because the predators — a polar bear population — attract the visitors who saved the town's economy after a military base there closed. <strong>Tourists</strong> wanting to see the bears bring millions of dollars into the local economy.</p>
<p class="summary">However, the bears are entering the town more often in search of food. Researchers say the sea ice where the bears normally hunt is shrinking.</p>
<p>Geoff York is with Polar Bears International, a nonprofit environmental group based in Manitoba. York said: “You're seeing more bears because there are more bears on the land for longer periods of time to be seen” and they are willing to take more risks, getting closer to people.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A polar bear stands near rocks, Tuesday, Aug. 6, 2024, in Churchill, Manitoba. (AP Photo/Joshua A. Bickel)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/6f419059-a387-44fe-8237-101fdde25f0f_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A polar bear stands near rocks, Tuesday, Aug. 6, 2024, in Churchill, Manitoba. (AP Photo/Joshua A. Bickel)</span></div>
<p>There are about 600 polar bears in this Western Hudson Bay population. Environmentalists say that is about half what it was 40 years ago. Humans in Churchill outnumber the bears although not by very many.</p>
<p class="summary">It has been more than 10 years since a polar bear attacked anyone in Churchill. But townspeople look out for each other and tourists with a warning system and guards. There is even a polar bear jail.</p>
<p class="summary"><strong>Controlling Churchill's bears</strong></p>
<p>Sergeant Ian Van Nest is a Manitoba province conservation officer. He recently guarded the streets of Churchill in his truck. It was the beginning of polar bear season in Churchill.</p>
<p class="summary">The vehicle is equipped with a rifle and a <strong>barred</strong> back seat to hold anyone he might have to arrest.</p>
<p class="summary">Van Nest saw a crowd of people who were watching a bear. He looked around for trouble in the area and then quietly spoke to the group's leader.</p>
<p>“How are you today?” Van Nest asked. The group leader answered that they were all right and then asked if their gathering place is acceptable to Van Nest.</p>
<p>“You're good,” the officer answered. “You [have] got a lot of distance there,” he added. So, the tour group continued to watch a polar bear on some nearby rocks.</p>
<p><strong>The importance of visitors</strong></p>
<p>Visitors interested in seeing the polar bears saved Churchill from shrinking out of existence when a military base there closed in the 1970s. The closure led to a drop in Churchill's population, from a few thousand <strong>residents</strong> to about 870.</p>
<p>A 2011 government study found that the average polar bear tourist spent about $5,000 per visit. The tourism adds more than $7 million yearly to the economy of the little town. Churchill has a few nice restaurants and more than 25 places where visitors can stay.</p>
<p>“We're...used to bears so (when you see one) you don't start to <strong>tremble</strong>,” Mayor Mike Spence said. “It's their area too. It's important how the community coexists with bears and wildlife in general to really get along. We're all connected.”</p>
<p>Churchill residents show polar bear <strong>pride</strong> in a way that mixes terror and fun.</p>
<p>“You know we're the polar bear capital of the world, right? We have the product, it's just about getting out there to see the bears safely,” said Dave Daley, who owns a gift shop, runs <strong>dog sleds</strong> and <strong>promotes</strong> the city. He also is a former president of the Chamber of Commerce, an office that supports business activity.</p>
<p>The former military base had a rocket launch area. It seemed to keep bears away. When it closed, the bears started entering the town more often, longtime residents said. So, Churchill and province officials “put together a polar bear alert program to make sure the community members were looked after, [and] protected,” said Spence who has been Churchill's mayor since 1995.</p>
<p>The town's old curfew <strong>siren</strong> sounds nightly, warning people that it is time to go inside to be safe from bears.</p>
<p>Georgina Berg recalls growing up in the 1970s near Churchill, where many First Nations people lived. “First Nations” is used in Canada to identify native people.</p>
<p>She remembers how differently her father and mother would react to seeing a bear in the past. She said her father would not pay attention to them.</p>
<p>“He said, ‘If you don't <strong>bother</strong> them, then they won't bother you,'" she recalled.</p>
<p>When a bear came near in later years, after her father had died, her mom was frightened.</p>
<p>“Everybody was yelling, and all the kids had to come in and everybody had to go home. And then we stayed silent in the house for a long time until we knew for sure that bear was gone,” Berg recalled.</p>
<p>For Van Nest, the provincial officer, the recent meeting with a group of bear watchers was different. The group was about 100 meters away from the bear. He said the bear was “putting on a bit of a show” for the tourists.</p>
<p>“This is a great situation to be in," he said. “The tourists are a safe distance away and the bear's doing his natural thing and not being <strong>harassed</strong> by anybody.”</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins. And I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Seth Borenstein reported this story for the Associated Press. Caty Weaver adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>predator </strong><em>–n.</em> an animal that eats other animals to live</p>
<p><strong>tourist </strong><em>–n.</em> a person who visits places for enjoyment</p>
<p><strong>barred </strong><em>–adj.</em> equipped with bars to detain people</p>
<p><strong>resident </strong><em>–n.</em> a person who lives in a town, city, state or country</p>
<p><strong>tremble </strong><em>–v.</em> to shake uncontrollably</p>
<p><strong>pride </strong><em>–n.</em> a feeling of importance or happiness about something you have done</p>
<p><strong>dog sled </strong><em>–n.</em> a vehicle for the snow that is pulled by dogs and usually has runners</p>
<p><strong>promote </strong><em>–v. </em>to bring attention to something and to support its activities</p>
<p><strong>siren </strong><em>–n.</em> a loud device that is used to warn people over a large area</p>
<p><strong>bother </strong><em>–v.</em> to cause a person to feel worried, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_kXc9E9gC">concerned</a> or annoyed</p>
<p><strong>harass </strong><em>–v.</em> to repeatedly bother someone by creating a situation that causes them problems</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What Are the Good Effects of Walking? (2024/11/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/what-are-the-good-effects-of-walking.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Many medical experts say that walking is an easy way to improve physical and mental health, support fitness and prevent disease. They advise that walking is a great first step toward a healthy life although other forms of exercise are also important.</p>
<p><strong>Good effects of walking</strong></p>
<p>Dr. Sarah Eby is a sports medicine physician with Mass General Brigham in the state of Massachusetts. Eby said walking has many good effects and people do not need extra things. “You don't need equipment and you don't need a <strong>gym</strong> membership,” Eby noted “And the benefits are so <strong>vast</strong>.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A member of the Get Healthy Walking Club walks past the rhinoceros exhibit in the morning at the Louisville Zoo in Louisville, Ky., Friday, Oct. 18, 2024. (AP Photo/Timothy D. Easley)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a42eb562-f66a-4635-b30b-7190377cb151_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A member of the Get Healthy Walking Club walks past the rhinoceros exhibit in the morning at the Louisville Zoo in Louisville, Ky., Friday, Oct. 18, 2024. (AP Photo/Timothy D. Easley)</span></div>
<p>The U.S. surgeon general, a federal health officer, recommends that adults get at least two and a half hours of moderate-intensity physical activity every week.</p>
<p>Walking helps meet that goal. Exercise lowers the risk of heart disease, high blood pressure, dementia, depression and many kinds of cancer.</p>
<p>Walking also helps blood sugar levels, is good for bone health, and can help people lose weight and sleep better. That is what Julie Schmied said. She is a health care worker with Norton Healthcare in Kentucky, which runs the free Get Healthy Walking Club.</p>
<p>Walking is also a relatively low-<strong>impact</strong> exercise that puts less pressure on joints than other exercises while strengthening the heart and lungs.</p>
<p>James Blankenship is 68 years old. He said joining a walking club at the Louisville Zoo last year helped him recover after a heart attack and a complex triple-bypass heart operation in 2022.</p>
<p>“My cardiologist says I'm doing great,” he said.</p>
<p>Some say walking is not enough. Anita Gust teaches exercise science at the University of Minnesota Crookston. Gust said walking “is not enough for overall health and well-being” because it does not provide resistance training that builds muscle strength and <strong>endurance</strong>.</p>
<p>Some health experts say that is especially important for healthy bone development in women as they age.</p>
<p>Experts recommend adding other activities at least twice weekly. These could include using weights, gym equipment or one's own body for resistance exercises. Training that improves <strong>flexibility,</strong> like yoga or stretching, can also be helpful.</p>
<p><strong>How much should you walk?</strong></p>
<p>Many people have heard about the walking goal of 10,000 steps a day. This advice dates back to a 1960s marketing campaign in Japan. But, experts note that this is only a guideline.</p>
<p>Shmied said the average American walks about 3,000 to 4,000 steps a day, and it is fine to increase that number to 10,000.</p>
<p>Setting a time goal can also be useful. Shmied suggests dividing the recommended 150 minutes per week into 30 minutes a day, or 10 minutes three times a day, for five days. During rainy or snowy weather, people can walk in malls or on <strong>treadmills</strong>.</p>
<p>As they become seasoned walkers, they can speed up or walk up hills while still keeping the activity level moderate.</p>
<p>“If you can talk but not sing,” Eby said, “that's what we consider moderate-intensity exercise.”</p>
<p><strong>Staying with your walking program</strong></p>
<p>Walking with friends, including dogs, is one way to keep walking.</p>
<p>Walking clubs have appeared across the nation. In 2022, 31-year-old personal trainer Brianna Joye Kohn started City Girls Who Walk with a TikTok post inviting others to walk with her in New York.</p>
<p>“We had 250 girls show up,” she said.</p>
<p>Since then, the group has walked every Sunday for around 40 minutes, with some meeting afterward for a meal or coffee.</p>
<p>The Louisville Zoo launched its walking club in 1987. It joined with Norton Healthcare in 2004 to expand it and now has more than 15,000 registered members. Every day from March 1 through October 31, people walk around and around the zoo before it officially opens.</p>
<p>Recently, Janet Rapp walked down a path through the city zoo, waving at friends and stopping briefly to greet big flightless birds called emus that she knows by name.</p>
<p>The 71-year-old retiree starts each morning this way with a walking club.</p>
<p>“I'm obsessed,” she said. Not only does it ease her joint pain, “it just gives me energy...And then it calms me, too.”</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Laura Ungar reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>gym (gymnasium) </strong><em>–n</em>. a building or room that has equipment and space for exercise</p>
<p><strong>vast</strong> <em>–adj. </em>extremely great or large</p>
<p><strong>impact</strong> <em>–n.</em> involving force against or on something</p>
<p><strong>endurance </strong><em>–n.</em> the ability to be physically active for a long time</p>
<p><strong>flexibility</strong> <em>–adj.</em> the ability to bend and move one's body freely without pain or injury</p>
<p><strong>treadmill</strong><em> –n. </em>a machine with a moving surface that lets the user walk in place</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Italian Artist’s Banana Artwork Sells for $6.2 Million (2024/11/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/italian-artist-s-banana-artwork-sells-for-6-2-million.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A much-publicized art piece made up of a single banana taped to a wall has sold for $6.2 million.</p>
<p>The sale happened Wednesday night during an <strong>auction</strong> in New York City at famous art seller Sotheby's. The work, called <strong><em>Comedian</em></strong>, was sold to cryptocurrency businessman Justin Sun. He is a Chinese collector and founder of the cryptocurrency company Tron. Sun placed the winning bid over the phone and the sale was completed in cryptocurrency.</p>
<p>Before the auction, Sotheby's said the unusual art piece was expected to bring in at least $1.5 million. But the price quickly started rising after the auction began, with people <strong>bidding</strong> inside the auction room, as well as on the phone and online.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file photo, a woman looks at artist Maurizio Cattelan's piece of art " alvarez="" an="" at="" auction="" comedian="" during="" eduardo="" file="" in="" monday="" munoz="" new="" nov.="" photo="" preview="" sotheby="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/773557b8-b82e-4d13-9293-23d2e3492663_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg" york=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this file photo, a woman looks at artist Maurizio Cattelan's piece of art "Comedian" during an auction preview at Sotheby's in New York, Monday, Nov. 11, 2024. (AP Photo/Eduardo Munoz Alvarez, File)</span></div>
<p>The art piece had already sold three times for prices between $120,000 and $150,000, The Associated Press reported.</p>
<p>Sun said in a statement after the auction that <em>Comedian</em> "is not just an artwork." He added that the piece "bridges the worlds of art, <strong>memes</strong>, and the cryptocurrency community.”</p>
<p>Sun said he planned to eat the banana, as at least two onlookers did when the artwork was presented at places around the world. Sotheby's says the fruit was always meant to be replaced repeatedly, along with the <strong>duct tape</strong>.</p>
<p>The work was created by Italian artist Maurizio Cattelan. It was first presented in 2019 at the Art Basel Miami Beach show in Miami, Florida. The piece quickly led to much public discussion about what should be considered art.</p>
<p><em>Comedian</em> belongs to a kind of art known as conceptual artwork. A conceptual piece is one in which the idea or meaning behind the work is more important than the finished object itself.</p>
<p>The head of contemporary art at Sotheby's is David Galperin. He told the AP he understands the piece's popularity because it is highly provocative. Provocative describes something likely to produce a strong reaction and much public debate.</p>
<p>“What Cattelan is really doing is turning a <strong>mirror</strong> to the contemporary art world,” Galperin said. He added that he thinks <em>Comedian</em> can cause people to question what values should be attached to artworks and what can be defined as artwork.</p>
<p>“What you buy when you buy Cattelan's <em>Comedian</em> is not the banana itself, but a <strong>certificate of authenticity</strong>,”<strong> </strong>Galperin said. That document, he added, gives the owner permission to reproduce the banana and duct tape on their own wall as an <strong>original </strong>artwork by the artist.</p>
<p>The sale of <em>Comedian</em> came shortly after Sotheby's auctioned off a famed artwork in the <em>Water Lilies</em> series by French painter Claude Monet. That piece sold on Monday for $65.5 million.</p>
<p>When asked to compare Cattelan's simple wall art to major works like Monet's, Galperin said that form of art, called impressionism, was not taken seriously when that movement first began.</p>
<p>“No important, <strong>profound</strong>, meaningful artwork of the past 100 years or 200 years, or our history for that matter, did not provoke some kind of discomfort when it was first unveiled,” Galperin said.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>auction</strong> - <em>n</em>. a public sale at which things are sold to the people who offer to pay the most</p>
<p><strong>comedian </strong><em>– n.</em> a person who performs in front of an audience and makes people laugh by telling jokes or funny stories or by acting in a way that is funny</p>
<p><strong>bid </strong><em>– v.</em> to offer to pay a particular amount of money for something</p>
<p><strong>meme </strong><em>– n</em>. an idea, image, video, etc. that spreads very quickly on the internet</p>
<p><strong>duct tape </strong><em>– n.</em> a very strong tape that is often used to cover holes and other repair jobs</p>
<p><strong>mirror </strong><em>– n.</em> a piece of glass with a shiny, metal-covered back that reflects light and produces an image of whatever is in front of it</p>
<p><strong>certificate of authenticity </strong><em>– n. </em>document that prove an artwork, or something, is real</p>
<p><strong>original </strong><em>– adj. </em>an original piece of work, such as a painting, etc. is produced by the artist and not a copy</p>
<p><strong>profound </strong><em>– adj. </em>felt or experienced very strongly or in an extreme way</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Thanksgiving and English Grammar (2024/11/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/thanksgiving-and-english-grammar.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Every year around the Thanksgiving holiday, a strange ceremony happens in Washington, DC. The president stands outside the White House, gives a brief speech and then officially pardons a turkey.</p>
<p>A pardon is a declaration that someone will not be punished.</p>
<p>You might be asking yourself, "What is the connection between turkeys, Thanksgiving and grammar?"</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="everyday grammar - thanksgiving and stative verbs " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/13C7BB45-AAD5-4C6C-B105-CF27EF766749_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">everyday grammar - thanksgiving and stative verbs </span></div>
<p>In today's report, we explore what turkeys can teach you about English verbs.</p>
<p>In particular, we will show you how Thanksgiving can teach you to use<strong> stative</strong> verbs. We will also show you the difference between stative and <strong>progressive</strong> verbs.</p>
<p><strong>What is a stative verb?</strong></p>
<p>The term stative verb refers to a verb that has a stative meaning. In other words, these verbs show or describe conditions or situations that do not do anything but exist.</p>
<p>Verbs that commonly have a stative meaning include:</p>
<p>-verbs that show emotional states, such as love and <strong>dislike</strong>;</p>
<p>-verbs that describe sense perceptions, such as smell or taste;</p>
<p>-verbs that show existence, such as seem or look.</p>
<p>In the present tense, a verb with a stative meaning is generally used in its simple form. "I love turkey," or "Americans like turkey" are two examples.</p>
<p>Verbs that have stative meanings are generally not used in the progressive tense. So, you will probably not hear a native speaker say, "I am loving turkey," or "Americans are liking turkey."</p>
<p><strong>Thanksgiving and stative verbs</strong></p>
<p>Do not fear: we can use our Thanksgiving example to make the point clearer.</p>
<p>Imagine you are at an American store. You hear a conversation between a customer and a store employee. The customer wants to buy a turkey that weighs 10 pounds, or 4.5 kilograms.</p>
<p>Unlike the turkey from the pardoning ceremony, this turkey will have a sad fate: the dinner table.</p>
<p>The conversation you hear might go like this:</p>
<p><em>Customer: How much does that turkey weigh?</em></p>
<p><em>Butcher: It weighs 10 pounds.</em></p>
<p><em>Customer: How much does it cost?</em></p>
<p><em>Butcher: It costs 20 dollars.</em></p>
<p>In the dialogue, you can hear two examples of stative verbs: weigh and cost.</p>
<p>The butcher said, "The turkey weighs 10 pounds,” and "The turkey costs 20 dollars." In both cases, the verbs have a stative meaning: The butcher is describing a condition or situation that simply exists – the weight and cost of the turkey.</p>
<p>Now imagine you are eating Thanksgiving dinner with an American family. You might hear any one of the following sentences:</p>
<p><em>"I love turkey!"</em></p>
<p><em>"I dislike turkey."</em></p>
<p><em>"The turkey smells wonderful!"</em></p>
<p><em>"The food tastes great!"</em></p>
<p><em>"The turkey seems undercooked."</em></p>
<p><em>"The turkey looks awful."</em></p>
<p>All these sentences include stative verbs. You might notice that the verbs are also in the simple present form.</p>
<p><strong>Why not use a progressive verb?</strong></p>
<p>So, why would an English speaker not say, "The turkey is seeming undercooked," or, "I am disliking turkey?"</p>
<p>Susan Conrad and Douglas Biber are two English grammar experts. They say that, in general, English speakers use the progressive tense only when the subject of the verb actively controls the state or action.</p>
<p>In addition, English speakers generally use the progressive only when the verb describes an action or state that happens over an extended period of time.</p>
<p>So, you would not hear an English speaker say, "The turkey is seeming undercooked" because the subject of the verb, the turkey, does not control its state – being undercooked.</p>
<p>For the same reason, you would not hear an English speaker say, "I am disliking turkey," because the verb's subject, <em>I</em>, probably does not have control over the action of disliking turkey.</p>
<p>Now, some verbs can have stative and progressive meanings.</p>
<p>Consider these examples:</p>
<p><em>"The food tastes good."</em></p>
<p><em>"The president is tasting the food."</em></p>
<p>In the first sentence, the food does not control whether it is good or bad. As a result, the verb <em>taste </em>has a stative meaning because it simply describes the condition of the food.</p>
<p>In the second sentence, "The president is tasting the food," the subject of the verb, <em>the president</em>, has control over his action.</p>
<p>In addition, the action takes place over an extended period of time: the president must think about tasting food, then raise the food to his mouth, then consider its quality. So, you could say that the verb taste in this example has a progressive meaning.</p>
<p><strong>What can you do?</strong></p>
<p>The next time you are reading or listening to the news, pay special attention to the verbs.</p>
<p>Notice when the progressive form is used, and when the simple form is used. Then ask yourself why. Does the verb's subject control the action? Does the action occur over an extended period of time? Or does the verb simply describe a condition that exists?</p>
<p>If you are still confused about whether you should use a simple or progressive verb in your own conversations, Conrad and Biber have one tip that might help you.</p>
<p>They say that in conversations, English speakers use simple verbs around 120 times in every 1,000 words.</p>
<p>Progressive verbs are much less common: they appear fewer than 20 times in every 1,000 words.*</p>
<p>I'm Alice Bryant.</p>
<p>And I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>John Russell wrote this lesson for Learning English.</em></p>
<p><em>* See Conrad, Susan and Biber, Douglas. Real Grammar: A Corpus-Based Approach to English. Pearson-Longman. 2009. Pgs. 4-6</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>stative </strong><em>– adj.</em> expressing a state, condition, or relation</p>
<p><strong>progressive</strong> <em>– adj.</em> of or relating to the progressive tense of a verb</p>
<p><strong>dislike</strong> <em>– v.</em> to not like (something or someone)</p>
<p><strong>undercooked </strong><em>– adj.</em> not cooked enough</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Social Media Service Bluesky Adds Millions of Users Since US Election (2024/11/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/social-media-service-bluesky-adds-millions-of-users-since-us-election.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">20 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The social media service Bluesky says it has been gaining millions of users since the U.S. presidential election. Usage data shows Bluesky reached 20 million users this week. That was up from about 12 million users just one month ago.</p>
<p>Bluesky is seen as a major competitor to social networking service X, formerly Twitter. American businessman Elon Musk bought Twitter in October 2022 and changed the name to X.</p>
<p>Musk made a series of changes to X shortly after taking over. These included greatly reducing the number of employees, as well as removing some existing restrictions on user content. Many of the released workers were responsible for <strong>monitoring</strong> the service to identify banned material or account violations.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file photo, the app for Bluesky is shown on a mobile phone, left, and on a laptop screen on June 2, 2023, in New York. (AP Photo/Richard Drew, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/3eee3676-9e80-4845-af2d-984d492bc198_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this file photo, the app for Bluesky is shown on a mobile phone, left, and on a laptop screen on June 2, 2023, in New York. (AP Photo/Richard Drew, File)</span></div>
<p>Musk has described the changes as an effort to protect the free speech of users. But his critics have noted that removing content restrictions had resulted in more harmful content and hate speech appearing on X.</p>
<p>Some industry experts also see the recent rise in Bluesky users as a possible reaction to the changes under Musk's leadership at X.</p>
<p><strong>What is Bluesky?</strong></p>
<p>Bluesky was started by the former head of Twitter, Jack Dorsey. He created it in 2019 as an internal project at Twitter. It started as an invitation only service, or platform. But after further development efforts, it was opened up to all users last February.</p>
<p>Bluesky operates similarly to X and Twitter. It offers a feed of accounts that users follow. Users can send direct messages and lock certain posts at the top of a user's feed. Bluesky also offers pre-chosen “starter packs” to help new users decide which individuals and organizations to follow.</p>
<p><strong>Why is Bluesky growing?</strong></p>
<p>Bluesky announced in mid-November that its total users had reached 15 million from 13 million at the end of October. The rate of new users has continued to grow during the past few weeks.</p>
<p>But the latest post-election increase was not the first time Bluesky has gained from people leaving X. In the week after X was banned in Brazil in August, Bluesky said it added about 2.6 million users – 85 percent of them from Brazil. And during one day in October, about 500,000 new users signed up for Bluesky after X warned that blocked accounts would be able to see a user's public messages.</p>
<p>Many new users – including reporters, left-leaning politicians and <strong>celebrities</strong> – have shared messages or created <strong>memes</strong> to explain their decisions for leaving X for Bluesky. Some expressed that they saw Bluesky as similar to an early version of Twitter.</p>
<p>Several well-known organizations and individuals recently announced they were leaving X because of concerns about changes to that service. These included the nonprofit Center for Countering Digital Hate, British news publisher <em>The Guardian</em> and former CNN news presenter Don Lemon.</p>
<p>Even with Bluesky's growth, X issued a statement after the U.S. presidential election saying it had “<strong>dominated</strong> the global <strong>conversation</strong> on the U.S. election”<strong> </strong>and had set new records.</p>
<p><strong>Beyond social networking</strong></p>
<p>Even though Bluesky currently operates much like X, company leaders have said they plan to expand in new directions, The Associated Press reports. For example, Bluesky says it is seeking to build a new technical foundation it describes as “a <strong>protocol </strong>for public conversation.”</p>
<p>That system is designed to make social networks work across different platforms such as email, internet blogs or phone numbers. Currently, users cannot cross between social platforms to leave a comment on someone's account. X users must stay on X, TikTok users must stay on TikTok, etc.</p>
<p>Industry experts say this design is what big technology companies wanted – to build out multiple product offerings around their online properties. Such systems support the advertising-driven business models of tech companies.</p>
<p>Bluesky has said it is trying to reimagine this kind of system on its path toward “<strong>interoperability</strong>” with other platforms.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters and Bluesky.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>monitor </strong><em>– v.</em> to watch something very carefully</p>
<p><strong>celebrity </strong><em>– n.</em> a famous person</p>
<p><strong>dominate </strong><em>– v. </em>to have control over a place or person</p>
<p><strong>conversation </strong><em>– n.</em> a talk between two or more people that is generally informal</p>
<p><strong>meme </strong><em>– n. </em>an idea, image, video, etc. that spreads very quickly on the internet</p>
<p><strong>protocol </strong><em>– n. </em>a set of rules covering something, often involving a very formal event</p>
<p><strong>interoperable </strong><em>– adj. </em>the ability of something to work well with other things around it</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
