<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>VOA Special English</title>
        <link>https://www.21voa.com/special_english/</link>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <itunes:category>ESL</itunes:category>
        <itunes:author>VOA</itunes:author>
        <description>美国之音（以下称VOA）的英语节目，按播音速度可分为两种：Standard English （标准英语）和 Special English（特别英语）。

Special English 又叫“慢速英语”，是VOA 专为全世界非英语国家初学英语的听众安排的一种简易、规范的英语广播节目。该节目创始于50年代末期，是VOA 的专家们研究如何与世界各地的英语学习者进行交际的产物。它正式开播于1959年10月。当时只面向欧洲和中东，但由于这个节目适合许多国家英语学习者的需要，所以它的广播对象不久就扩大到世界其他地区，并很快在全世界范围内产生了广泛的影响。现在这个节目对欧洲、非洲和拉丁美洲每晚广播一次，对加勒比地区每晚广播一次（星期天除外），对东南亚广播次数最多，每天上午两次，晚上三次。

30多年来，VOA 为了办好Special English节目，进行了大量的调查研究工作，对播音速度、内容及用词范围都作了具体规定，基本上达到了既能为英语学习者提供信息，又不损害英语本身风格的目的，使之成为VOA 独具特色，拥有最大量听众的节目。

美国著名词汇学家S. B. Flexmer 指明了Special English的三条标准，也就是它所“特别”的地方：

1、它是一种由美国人最常用的1500个基本单词为主体构成的美国英语；

2、它用简短、明晰的句子写作和广播；

3、它以每分钟90个单词的速度，即2/3的Standard English（标准英语）速度进行广播。

Special English的节目可分为两大类：一类是新闻节目；一类是专题节目。

1．新闻节目

VOA Special English 的新闻广播向听众提供世界范围内的政治、经济、军事、外交、国际关系、宗教、天气以及各种重大事件和珍闻奇事等各个方面的信息，每天向东南亚地区广播五次，早上两次，晚上三次，每逢半点播出。

Special English新闻节目每次长约十分钟，大都播出十条左右新闻，近一千个单词，每条新闻多为一分钟，但偶尔也有长达两分钟的要闻。除头条新闻外，每条新闻都由一个电头引导，这样显得结构分明，条理清晰，适宜初学英语的人收听。在节目结束之前，播音员常常用三四句话重播其中三条新闻的提要以加深听众对要闻的印象。

Special English新闻中70%左右的内容与同时整点播出的Standard English新闻相同，但相同新闻的先后次序有所变动。每次节目的开头和结尾大同小异，格式比较固定。

2．专题节目（一）

Special English的专题节目（Feature Programs）,从时间上看，可分为两大类：一是每五分钟一次的专题，二是每十五分钟一次的专题。本节先介绍每项五分钟一次的专题材节目。

Special English五分钟一次的专题材节目安排在Special English新闻节目之后和（或）每十五分钟一次的专题材节目之前播出，每星期播七次。根据内容，可分为三个小类，即：Science Report（科学报道），逢星期一、三、五播出，每天播六遍；Agriculture Report（农业报道），逢星期二、四播出，每天播六遍；Words And Their Stories（词语掌故），逢星期六和星期天播出，每天播五遍。这三个专题材各具特色，具有相对的独立性，听众每听完一个节目，都会获得一个完整的印象。

Science Report（科学报道）这一专题材节目每周向听众介绍三篇有关现代科学技术最新发展情况的报道，涉及物理、化学、天文至高无上理、生物、环卫、心理、教育、医学和计算机等方面。适宜理工科大学生和科技工作者收集信息，积累资料，学习科技英语。

Agriculture Report（农业报道） Agriculture Report是为农业科技工作者和生产者安排的一个专题。它专门报道世界各国，特别是美国现代农业生产的最新成文汇报总务科 学家对农业生产某一方面的研究进展，以及他们对影响农业生产的某一自然现象进行分析和研究的近况。此外，它还经常向听众介绍发展中国家家业生产的一些有益经验等内容。

Words And Their Stories（词语掌故）这一专题节目，旨在向学习英语的听众介绍美国英语中生动有趣的词语和惯用法，并从科学研究和通俗词源学的角度来解释它们的含意、产生的背景及其在使用过程中的演变情况等。它通过讲故事的形式讲解每一个词语。这是VOA Special English中的优秀节目之一，是学习美国英语的极好材料。通过收听这一节目，听众不仅能学到娓娓动听的掌故和地道的美国英语，而且能增加美国的社会文化背景知识，历史传统与现状的了解。

VOA 为了更好地办好这个节目，便于听众收听学习，于1978年编辑出版了一本名为Words And Their Stories的书，共收集一百篇故事，作者是Herbert Sutcliffe, Harold Bermen 及VOA 该节目的部分编辑人员。在每次的实际广播中，播音员都以此书为蓝本，再根据需要对原稿进行适当增删。按每周两个故事计算，此书的一百个故事还不能满足一年的播音需要。于是编辑们就是重播部分词语掌故的同时，不断增加许多新的词语掌故，及时将词源学家的最新研究成果和不断增加的新词汇介绍给听众。收听实践证明，初学者在收听过程中必然会遇到许多人名、地名和一些较难的句子，有时甚至在听完之后还很难理解所播词语的确切含义及其汉语意思，为此，听众可参看1983年由中国对外翻译出版公司出版的该书英汉对照本中的有关部分。

3．专题节目（二）

VOA Special English的专题节目，除上节谈的五分钟一次的以外，还有本节要介绍的每十五分钟一次的节目。这类节目共有七个不同的小专题，以星期为单位循环，每天分四次复播出一个专题，但星期日和星期六的两个专题材每晚只播三遍，每次节目约十分钟，继每次五分钟的专题节目之后播出。

这类专题节目的基本结构是，在特定的伴声中先报告当次节目的名称，并扼要介绍其主要内容，然后播送节目正文。最后，在伴乐声中报告节目主持人和撰稿人的姓名，以邀请听众在下周的这个时间继续收听该节目而结束。

People in America（美国人物志） 这是有关美国历史名人的一个专题节目，每逢星期天晚上播出。它向听众介绍在美国历史上产生过重大影响、起过重要作用、作出了突出贡献的科学、文学、政治、或其他各方面的历史人物。节目一般都对他们的生平事迹进行简要的叙述，对其贡献作出评介，类似人物小传。有的重要人物事迹很多，必须用两次或几次的节目时间进行联播。对这样的节目要坚持收听，才会获得完整的印象。

TThis is America（今日美国） This Is America向听众介绍美国人民的生活、学习、工作和娱乐情况，是英语学习者解美国社会的一条渠道。该专题大都一个节目一个整体，每逢星期一晚播出。

Science in the News（科学新闻） 这一专题材主要对新近的科学技术新闻进行综述或摘要广播。向听众介绍世界各国在自然、医学、疾病、原子能、航天等方面的科研动态、成果、突破性进展及存在的困难。涉及当今世界人们普遍关心的重大问题，如核事故、航天飞机爆炸、自然灾害、环境污染和爱滋病等等。每逢星期二播出，每次播一到五条新闻摘要。

Explorations（自然探索） 每逢星期三晚上，听众可以收听到Explorations这一专题节目。该专题既涉及人类遨游太空、探索原子、研究自身、改造自然的现代技术，也报道发展中国家开发新资源，利用新工艺改善人民生活等方面的成就，其侧重点在各种科技实验和简易实用技术方面。该节目一般安排一段时间播一个系列，每次播出一个主题，以便能将某项新技术的研究和应用的全过程介绍给听众，电台还乐意为感兴趣的听众提供所需的文字材料。

The Making of a Nation（建国史话） 这一专题节目向听众介绍美利坚合众国从十三个殖民地区域到现代工业国的孕育、诞生以及形成超级大国的历史过程，并以历史为线索，特定的历史时期为单位，以重大的历史事件为主题材来叙述各个党派、各届总统和政府的历史作用与贡献。这是每个英语学习者都应了解的基本知识。The Making of a Nation每逢星期四播出。这是个系列节目，坚持收听，则有助于系统了解美国的历史概况。

American Mosaic（美国万花筒） American Mosaic是一个radio magazine（广播杂志）节目。该节目题材广泛、内容丰，展示着美国社会文化生活中比较轻松愉快的生活画面；听众收听该节目就如同在阅读一本图文并茂的杂志。它每次有三到五个小节目，涉及音乐、图书、技术和教育等方面的内容。我们既可以从中欣赏到著名歌唱的优秀歌曲，对美国音乐有所了解，又可以获取一些生动有趣的现代美国社会生活知识，随着播音员那亲切悦耳的声音步入美国风景如画的大好河山；同时还能听到世界各地的听众提出的有关英语语方文学等方面的问题和电台的解答。

American Stories（美国故事） 这一专题材节目安排在每星期六晚上播出。这样能使听众在学习和工作之余，得以轻松一下头脑。我们可以通过这一美国文学的“窗口”，接触各种流派、各类名家的文学作品。了解美国英语的时代特色，欣赏、学习美国人民运用语方的技巧，并从那些佳作名篇中获得艺术享受。该节目对短篇故事采取一次播一篇的方式，对中、长篇小说则先进行简写加工，再分几次播出全文。在播出故事正文之前，播音员常常先介绍故事的主要情节。对需要分几次节目时间播出的中长篇，在播第二或以后各部分之前，主持人还先重述已播部分的故事梗概，以唤起听众的回忆，使故事听起来更加连贯。</description>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          <item>
            <title>Social Media Service Bluesky Adds Millions of Users Since US Election (2024/11/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/social-media-service-bluesky-adds-millions-of-users-since-us-election.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">20 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The social media service Bluesky says it has been gaining millions of users since the U.S. presidential election. Usage data shows Bluesky reached 20 million users this week. That was up from about 12 million users just one month ago.</p>
<p>Bluesky is seen as a major competitor to social networking service X, formerly Twitter. American businessman Elon Musk bought Twitter in October 2022 and changed the name to X.</p>
<p>Musk made a series of changes to X shortly after taking over. These included greatly reducing the number of employees, as well as removing some existing restrictions on user content. Many of the released workers were responsible for <strong>monitoring</strong> the service to identify banned material or account violations.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file photo, the app for Bluesky is shown on a mobile phone, left, and on a laptop screen on June 2, 2023, in New York. (AP Photo/Richard Drew, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/3eee3676-9e80-4845-af2d-984d492bc198_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this file photo, the app for Bluesky is shown on a mobile phone, left, and on a laptop screen on June 2, 2023, in New York. (AP Photo/Richard Drew, File)</span></div>
<p>Musk has described the changes as an effort to protect the free speech of users. But his critics have noted that removing content restrictions had resulted in more harmful content and hate speech appearing on X.</p>
<p>Some industry experts also see the recent rise in Bluesky users as a possible reaction to the changes under Musk's leadership at X.</p>
<p><strong>What is Bluesky?</strong></p>
<p>Bluesky was started by the former head of Twitter, Jack Dorsey. He created it in 2019 as an internal project at Twitter. It started as an invitation only service, or platform. But after further development efforts, it was opened up to all users last February.</p>
<p>Bluesky operates similarly to X and Twitter. It offers a feed of accounts that users follow. Users can send direct messages and lock certain posts at the top of a user's feed. Bluesky also offers pre-chosen “starter packs” to help new users decide which individuals and organizations to follow.</p>
<p><strong>Why is Bluesky growing?</strong></p>
<p>Bluesky announced in mid-November that its total users had reached 15 million from 13 million at the end of October. The rate of new users has continued to grow during the past few weeks.</p>
<p>But the latest post-election increase was not the first time Bluesky has gained from people leaving X. In the week after X was banned in Brazil in August, Bluesky said it added about 2.6 million users – 85 percent of them from Brazil. And during one day in October, about 500,000 new users signed up for Bluesky after X warned that blocked accounts would be able to see a user's public messages.</p>
<p>Many new users – including reporters, left-leaning politicians and <strong>celebrities</strong> – have shared messages or created <strong>memes</strong> to explain their decisions for leaving X for Bluesky. Some expressed that they saw Bluesky as similar to an early version of Twitter.</p>
<p>Several well-known organizations and individuals recently announced they were leaving X because of concerns about changes to that service. These included the nonprofit Center for Countering Digital Hate, British news publisher <em>The Guardian</em> and former CNN news presenter Don Lemon.</p>
<p>Even with Bluesky's growth, X issued a statement after the U.S. presidential election saying it had “<strong>dominated</strong> the global <strong>conversation</strong> on the U.S. election”<strong> </strong>and had set new records.</p>
<p><strong>Beyond social networking</strong></p>
<p>Even though Bluesky currently operates much like X, company leaders have said they plan to expand in new directions, The Associated Press reports. For example, Bluesky says it is seeking to build a new technical foundation it describes as “a <strong>protocol </strong>for public conversation.”</p>
<p>That system is designed to make social networks work across different platforms such as email, internet blogs or phone numbers. Currently, users cannot cross between social platforms to leave a comment on someone's account. X users must stay on X, TikTok users must stay on TikTok, etc.</p>
<p>Industry experts say this design is what big technology companies wanted – to build out multiple product offerings around their online properties. Such systems support the advertising-driven business models of tech companies.</p>
<p>Bluesky has said it is trying to reimagine this kind of system on its path toward “<strong>interoperability</strong>” with other platforms.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters and Bluesky.</em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>monitor </strong><em>– v.</em> to watch something very carefully</p>
<p><strong>celebrity </strong><em>– n.</em> a famous person</p>
<p><strong>dominate </strong><em>– v. </em>to have control over a place or person</p>
<p><strong>conversation </strong><em>– n.</em> a talk between two or more people that is generally informal</p>
<p><strong>meme </strong><em>– n. </em>an idea, image, video, etc. that spreads very quickly on the internet</p>
<p><strong>protocol </strong><em>– n. </em>a set of rules covering something, often involving a very formal event</p>
<p><strong>interoperable </strong><em>– adj. </em>the ability of something to work well with other things around it</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Sake Makers Hope for UNESCO Listing (2024/11/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/sake-makers-hope-for-unesco-listing.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">20 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The Japanese rice wine called sake is made using ancient <strong>brewing</strong> methods. They date back more than a thousand years.</p>
<p>Junichiro Ozawa, the 18th-generation leader of Ozawa Brewery, founded in 1702, hopes sake-brewing will win recognition as a UNESCO Intangible Cultural Heritage. Officials of the UN agency are expected to decide on the nomination next month.</p>
<p>“We always think about the people who're enjoying our sake when we make it. I'm now so excited, imagining the faces of all the people around the world,” he told reporters during a visit to the brewery on the edge of Tokyo.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Traditional containers to keep Japanese sake are placed for decorations at a room shown during a media tour at the Ozawa Sake Brewery in Ome, on the western outskirts of Tokyo, Japan, Wednesday, Nov. 13, 2024. (AP Photo/Hiro Komae)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a0a7f12c-6787-4a13-9dc7-275e8dfa52d0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Traditional containers to keep Japanese sake are placed for decorations at a room shown during a media tour at the Ozawa Sake Brewery in Ome, on the western outskirts of Tokyo, Japan, Wednesday, Nov. 13, 2024. (AP Photo/Hiro Komae)</span></div>
<p>Sake was the drink of choice of the nobility represented in Japan's most celebrated work of writing, The Tale of Genji. Sake has been growing in popularity in recent years, helped by an increasing international interest in Japanese cooking and food.</p>
<p>Sake exports from Japan total more than $265 million a year, with the U.S. and China as the two biggest buyers. That information comes from the Japan Sake and Shochu Makers Association.</p>
<p>Sake exports have almost doubled in value since 2018. But exports still make up a very small amount of overall sake production in Japan. Brazil, Mexico and Southeast Asia, as well as France and the rest of Europe, all places where Japanese restaurants are gaining popularity, are starting to take a liking to sake.</p>
<p>The main elements in sake are rice and water. The production process takes about two months and includes <strong>fermentation</strong> and pressing.</p>
<p>For a product to be named Japanese sake, the rice must be Japanese. The relatively soft quality of freshwater in Japan, like that provided by the two wells at Ozawa Brewery, is also important.</p>
<p>Among Ozawa's sake choices is the Junmai Daiginjo, one of the top offerings, with 15 percent alcohol content and costing about $23 for 720 milliliters.</p>
<p>Another, Karakuti Nigorizake, is unrefined sake. The liquid is not as clear as usual sake. It has 17 percent alcohol content and sells for $16 for 1,800 milliliters.</p>
<p>In Japan, sake is used to purify and to celebrate. Small tastes of sake from a cup show the confirmation of a marriage, for example.</p>
<p>“Sake is not just an alcoholic<strong> beverage</strong>. It is Japanese culture itself,” said Hitoshi Utsunomiya of the Japan Sake and Shochu Makers Association.</p>
<p>The UNESCO Intangible Cultural Heritage<strong> designation</strong> can be awarded to <strong>practices</strong> passed down for generations. These practices include spoken traditions, performing arts, and food making.</p>
<p>The UNESCO designation is not meant to be used for commercial purposes. But industry officials are open about their hope that such recognition will increase international sales. They believe the designation could help the tradition stay alive amid competition from beer, grape-based wine and other drinks.</p>
<p>One reason for sake's growing popularity around the world is that its smooth flavor goes well with a number of foods. These foods include sushi, spicy Asian and Western dishes, says Max Del Vita, a sake wine expert and co-founder of The Sake Company, an import and distribution business in Singapore.</p>
<p>Del Vita told The Associated Press. “Sake is more than a drink. It is a living embodiment of Japan's seasonal rhythms, community values and artistic heritage.”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Yuri Kageyama reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>brew</strong> <em>– v. </em><strong> </strong>to prepare (sake, beer, etc.) by boiling and fermentation</p>
<p><strong>fermentation</strong> <em>– n.</em> the breakdown of an energy-rich compound (such as a carbohydrate to carbon dioxide and alcohol) by the action of microorganisms (such as bacteria or yeast)</p>
<p><strong>beverage</strong> <em>– n. </em>a drinkable liquid</p>
<p><strong>designation</strong> <em>– n.</em> a distinguishing name or title</p>
<p><strong>practice</strong> <em>– n. </em>a custom; a repeated or customary action</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Thai City Fixing up Monkey Problem (2024/11/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/thai-city-fixing-up-monkey-problem.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">20 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>People will no longer have to fight with m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s in the historic Thai city of Lopburi.</p>
<p>That is because of new efforts to keep the animals from reproducing and to limit their movements.</p>
<p><strong>M<i><i>onkey</i></i> City</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A long-tailed macaque takes food from a local student near Phra Prang Sam Yot temple, in Lopburi, Thailand, June 7, 2024. ( REUTERS/Chalinee Thirasupa)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a4c617d0-33e4-4cb4-b8b0-8edf2c1d4c9c_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A long-tailed macaque takes food from a local student near Phra Prang Sam Yot temple, in Lopburi, Thailand, June 7, 2024. ( REUTERS/Chalinee Thirasupa)</span></div>
<p>Before public health measures to control COVID-19 closed businesses in Lopburi, about 3,000 long-tailed macaques lived there. The people of the city fed them and even had a yearly party for them. Tourists came to the city north of Bangkok to see the macaques in what was known as "M<i><i>onkey</i></i> City."</p>
<p>The macaques are believed to bring good luck. They live in the nearby forests and have long been a part of the city's history. But after Lopburi came out of the pandemic lockdown in the middle of 2022, people found that the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s had become unruly without people feeding them.</p>
<p>Groups of macaques had taken over buildings. They stole food and caused accidents by walking in the streets. Groups of the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s also fought each other, shocking local people. Some of the townspeople put up <strong>cages</strong> around their homes to keep the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s out.</p>
<p><strong>Stealing food</strong></p>
<p>Wisarut Somngam is a local researcher with the non-governmental organization, Ecoexist Society. He said the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s would steal from people by taking any container they thought might contain food. People began to carry slingshots, a small weapon that shoots stones, to protect against the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, officials began their efforts to catch the macaques. By May, they were increasing the effort to prevent the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s from reproducing that began during the pandemic.</p>
<p>"Our goal is to <strong>neuter</strong> all the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s, 100 percent of them," said local veterinarian Patarapol Maneeorn from the government wildlife department in September. The m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s would then be put into an area where they will be looked after, he said.</p>
<p><strong>Capture of m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s</strong></p>
<p>Now, the situation in the city seems to be under control, as the officials have captured 1,600 of the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s. Some animal rights groups agree the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s should be neutered, but they do not want them to be kept in captivity.</p>
<p>Edwin Wiek is founder of Wildlife Friends Foundation Thailand. He said, “The m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s are suffering because currently they're in a cage that is not designed for them.” Wiek pressed the government to increase funding for the government wildlife department to train people in animal care and treatment.</p>
<p>The people of Lopburi are happy that the streets are safe again. Clock maker Chalit Nithiwkram said, "Things have become a little easier because most of the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s were captured. Life is easier." He said his business is improving because people are no longer afraid to park near his shop.</p>
<p>For others, the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s are important to Lopburi. Supaporn Reanprayoorn operates a store near a temple where m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s often gathered. "M<i><i>onkey</i></i>s are part of Lopburi's identity," she said. She sometimes gave them a little food. "Let tourists take pictures with them - just a hundred or two," she joked.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Artorn Pookasook reported this story for Reuters. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>cage </strong>– <em>n.</em> a box made of wire or metal bars in which people keep animals or birds</p>
<p><strong>neuter</strong> –<em> v</em>. to remove the sex organs from (an animal)</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Can Bees, Dogs Identify Cancer Earlier Than Machines? (2024/11/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/can-bees-dogs-identify-cancer-earlier-than-machines.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Researchers at Michigan State University recently found that bees' sense of “smell” is sensitive enough to identify chemical smells of cancer.</p>
<p>Bees sense chemicals in their environment using antennae, structures on their heads, which serve as “noses” to sense smells.</p>
<p>The researchers wrote in a study published last month that honeybees can <strong>sniff out</strong> lung cancer on a patient's breath.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A honeybee in the harness, with blue wax holding the bee in place, as an odor line is placed in front of the bees' antennae. (Courtesy Saha Lab)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/3f939f41-1fb8-4afc-839e-1407f10e9915_cx0_cy13_cw0_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A honeybee in the harness, with blue wax holding the bee in place, as an odor line is placed in front of the bees' antennae. (Courtesy Saha Lab)
</span></div>
<p>Debajit Saha is an assistant professor of biomedical engineering at Michigan State University. He was part of a team that published the research.</p>
<p>“Our world is <strong>visual</strong>. [The] insects' world is all based on smell, so their sense of smell is very, very good,” Saha said.</p>
<p>“There is quite a bit of research that shows that when some cancer grows inside our body, our breath actually changes. Our research does show that honeybees can <strong>detect</strong> lung cancer and possibly other diseases based on the smell of those cells.”</p>
<p>Saha and his team placed bees in small <strong>harnesses</strong> and attached small wires to their brains. The insects were then placed near chemicals that are like the breath of a person with lung cancer.</p>
<p>The scientists said that the bees could tell the difference between the cancer breath and the laboratory copy of the healthy human breath 93 percent of the time. The scientists added that the bees could also tell the difference between different kinds of lung cancer.</p>
<p>The discovery could help doctors detect many cancers, including lung, breast, head and neck, and colorectal cancers, earlier than other methods. Saha says detecting cancers this way would be an improvement. “The reason is, many times we detect the cancer late,” when a growth has become too big to control easily. But, he added, when cancer starts growing the breath starts changing much earlier.</p>
<p>He hopes to develop a system that a patient will be able to breathe into and which can be carried around easily. This would deliver test results immediately.</p>
<p>“Hopefully, within the next five years, we'll have something to show that humans can be <strong>diagnosed</strong> using these insect brain disc sensors,” Saha said.</p>
<p><strong>Dogs can also help find cancer</strong></p>
<p>Using animals to detect cancer is not a new idea. At the Penn Vet Working Dog Center at the University of Pennsylvania, researchers are training dogs to smell some kinds of cancer.</p>
<p>Cindy Otto is executive director of the Penn Vet Working Dog Center in Philadelphia. She said many other animals also have very good senses of smell. “But part of what makes dogs so good is that they cooperate with humans, and so, they communicate that information,” she added.</p>
<p>The dogs are in a program where they live with families and are brought to “work” each day. Not all dogs can do this work. Otto said,</p>
<p>“They need to love it to be <strong>engaged</strong>. And so, it's a really fun game for them.”</p>
<p>Some researchers say that dogs detect cancer better than machines. They note that a dog's sense of smell is 10,000 to 100,000 times sharper than that of humans.</p>
<p>Amritha Mallikarjun is another postdoctoral researcher at the center. She said dogs are more sensitive to smells than any machines sold today. But the scientists hope to create a machine that will identify disease just as well as dogs.</p>
<p>Otto said doctors in ancient Greece and Rome used odor as a tool to identify disease. She hopes the researchers can build on that “and <strong>advance</strong> the health of not only humans, but dogs and other species as well.”</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Dora Mekouar reported this story for VOA News. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>sniff out</strong> –<em> phrasal verb.</em> detect by smell</p>
<p><strong>visual </strong><em>– adj.</em> related to the sense of sight</p>
<p><strong>detect</strong> – <em>v.</em> to discover or notice the presence of (something that is hidden or hard to see, hear, taste, or sense)</p>
<p><strong>harness</strong> –<em> n.</em> a set of straps that are placed on an animal</p>
<p><strong>diagnose</strong> <em>– v. </em>to recognize (a disease, illness, or the like) by examining someone</p>
<p><strong>engage </strong><em>– v.</em> to be involved in something</p>
<p><strong>advance </strong><em>– v.</em> to move forward or to make progress</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>College Degree Remains Big Prize for Many Student-athletes (2024/11/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/college-degree-remains-big-prize-for-many-student-athletes.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Name, image, and likeness, or NIL, deals have enabled student-athletes to make money while going to college in the United States. But outside of some big-name athletes, many say that a degree remains the biggest, most important prize for going to school.</p>
<p>For years, college athletes could only receive free education and living costs while competing for school teams. But that changed in 2021 when the U.S. Supreme Court ruled that athletes could earn money by selling their name, image and likeness.</p>
<p>Well-known athletes like Jayden Daniels, now with the Washington Commanders, and Caitlin Clark, who currently plays for the Indiana Fever, made large amounts of money while in college.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Northern Arizona University's Jonny Bottorff poses for a photo on campus on Monday, Oct. 28, 2024, in Flagstaff, Ariz. (AP Photo/Josh Biggs)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/8008216e-fe19-4bbf-9ab6-66fab0487a32_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Northern Arizona University's Jonny Bottorff poses for a photo on campus on Monday, Oct. 28, 2024, in Flagstaff, Ariz. (AP Photo/Josh Biggs)</span></div>
<p>But several athletes told The Associated Press that the money available to them through NIL remains a small consideration compared with earning a degree and competing in the sports they love.</p>
<p>NIL deals were not on Jonny Bottorff's mind when he <strong>transferred </strong>to Northern Arizona University on a football <strong>scholarship</strong> from a small college in Missouri.</p>
<p>Bottorff said, “I think the reality for most college athletes is things haven't really changed that much. We just got an extra little bit of <strong>cash</strong> in our pockets...”</p>
<p>For some athletes, NIL money is a reason to stay longer in college. But Anthony Leal said he is staying at Indiana University for a different reason.</p>
<p>Leal plays for Indiana's basketball team. Under college athletic rules, he can play four seasons for the team within five years. Leal already received his undergraduate degree<strong> </strong>last year. But he is coming back as a fifth-year student to get a master's in business administration.</p>
<p>“I'm about 70 percent through the program in the Kelley School of Business,” he said. “I wanted to get that degree.”</p>
<p><strong>Another rule change </strong></p>
<p>Another change in college rules also makes it easy for athletes to transfer and play the next season. Under previous rules, athletes had to sit out a year before competing.</p>
<p>Now, the top athletes can enter what is called a transfer portal to get more NIL money at another school and compete right away. University of Nevada, Las Vegas football player Matthew Sluka, for one, recently left the team in a dispute over an NIL payment. His representative said he was promised payment but never received it.</p>
<p>But Ray Harrison said NIL money was not the reason why he left Presbyterian College and joined the basketball team at Grand Canyon University in Phoenix, Arizona.</p>
<p>Harrison said, “I just came out here because this is where God led my heart. Of course, we win two (conference) championships and that changes things.”</p>
<p>A college education remains a dream for many younger athletes.</p>
<p>Tavarius Covington from Chicago wants to continue to play football in college. He hopes that football will help him become the first in his family to go to college and earn a business degree. He also wants to be an example for his younger brother.</p>
<p>“I want him to know there is more to look forward to coming out of high school,” Covington said.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Cheyanna Mumphrey, Michael Marot, and David Brandt reported on this story for the Associated Press. Hai Do adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>undergraduate degree</strong><em>-- n.</em><strong> </strong>a kind of credential you get after high school;<strong> </strong>a program of study that leads to a qualification such as a bachelor's degree or associate's degree</p>
<p><strong>transfer</strong> <em>– v.</em> to withdraw from one educational institution to enroll at another</p>
<p><strong>scholarship </strong><em>-- n. </em><strong> </strong>a grant-in-aid to a student</p>
<p><strong>cash </strong><em>-- n.</em> money</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Artists in Lebanon Keep Creating During Conflict (2024/11/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/artists-in-lebanon-keep-creating-during-conflict.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Charbel Samuel Aoun is a working artist in the Middle Eastern nation of Lebanon. As the Israeli military launches a deadly attack against the militant group Hezbollah in his home country, Aoun asks, "Does art still have a place in such a crisis?"</p>
<p>Lebanon has long played an important part in the Arab world's artistic community. It has been a center for arts, music and theater, combining traditional and modern influences.</p>
<p>Now, Lebanese artists are using their work as a way to express the anger and loss they feel after a year-long Israeli offensive that has killed more than 3,200 people, most of them since September.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Displaced and refugee children attend an event where Lebanese singer Joy Fayad and musician Oliver Maalouf perform, amid the ongoing hostilities between Hezbollah and Israeli forces, in Dbayeh, Lebanon November 9, 2024. (REUTERS/Emilie Madi)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/d925dcf6-f7da-4827-b44f-3a6759bf569e_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Displaced and refugee children attend an event where Lebanese singer Joy Fayad and musician Oliver Maalouf perform, amid the ongoing hostilities between Hezbollah and Israeli forces, in Dbayeh, Lebanon November 9, 2024. (REUTERS/Emilie Madi)</span></div>
<p>Aoun's works of art are directly connected to the conflicts Lebanon has seen. In 2013, he began gathering dust from Syrian refugee camps in Lebanon to create a series of paintings before moving on to explore other materials.</p>
<p>Now, he says the darkness and hopelessness of the war and the waste left behind by Israel's intense bombing campaign have renewed his desire to create art from dust.</p>
<p>"You either stop everything or keep going with the little that still has meaning," he said.</p>
<p>Two of his <strong>exhibitions</strong> have been canceled due to the war. While he once made money from selling art, he now also relies on selling honey from his <strong>beehives</strong>, which he first set up as a project to create art from <strong>beeswax</strong>.</p>
<p>"I can no longer rely on the art market," he said.</p>
<p><strong>No demand for art</strong></p>
<p>Exhibition spaces across Beirut have closed in recent months. Their owners told Reuters there is no demand to buy art at this time. Even Lebanon's famous Sursock Museum has stored its collections underground.</p>
<p>Lebanese singer and musician Joy Fayad has also struggled with the emotional cost of the conflict. It has made it difficult for her to perform for months.</p>
<p>"It limited my creativity; it was like I <strong>shut down</strong>. I couldn't give to others, nor to myself," Fayad, 36, said.</p>
<p>Instead, she threw her energy into songwriting. One line in a new song reads: "You are from the <strong>downtrodden</strong> people, whose word has been silenced, and by their weapons, you are paying the price with your blood."</p>
<p>She recently began performing again, singing for displaced and refugee children in Lebanon at an event north of Beirut.</p>
<p>"They're changing the atmosphere, having fun after such a difficult period," she said, especially for those who became used to the sound of bombs instead of music.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Emilie Madi and Riham Alkousaa </em><em>reported this story for Reuters.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>exhibition</strong> –<em> n</em>. an event at which objects (such as works of art) are put out in a public space for people to look at : a public show of something</p>
<p><strong>beehive</strong> – <em>n</em>. a nest for bees</p>
<p><strong>beeswax </strong>– <em>n</em>. wax made by bees that is used for making candles and other products</p>
<p><strong>shut down </strong>– <em>phrasal verb (informal.)</em> to cause (an opponent) to be unsuccessful, unable to score, or function</p>
<p><strong>downtrodden – </strong><em>adj.</em> without hope because of being treated badly by powerful people, governments, or the like</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>South Korean Team Develops Wheels That Climb over Barriers (2024/11/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/south-korean-team-develops-wheels-that-climb-over-barriers.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Imagine a wheelchair equipped with wheels <strong>flexible</strong> enough to move over all kinds of barriers: including the raised edges of streets.</p>
<p>A robotic delivery vehicle could use the same wheels to go up <strong>stairs</strong> to deliver food or other purchases.</p>
<p>This is what researchers from the Korea Institute of Machinery and Materials (KIMM) see as the future for their <strong>'morphing'</strong> wheel. The wheels can change their shape and can roll over barriers up to 1.3 times their radius. The radius of a wheel is half its height.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A Korea Institute of Machinery and Materials researcher controls a wheelchair with stiffness-variable morphing wheels as it goes over an obstacle in Daejeon, South Korea November 5, 2024. (Reuters TV/via REUTERS)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/06bb1a2a-2f14-4c11-845b-18fab7669b75_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A Korea Institute of Machinery and Materials researcher controls a wheelchair with stiffness-variable morphing wheels as it goes over an obstacle in Daejeon, South Korea November 5, 2024. (Reuters TV/via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>Other possible applications for the morphing wheel include robots that gather information about an enemy in the battlefield.</p>
<p>The KIMM team also hopes that morphing wheels will one day be used with two and four-legged robots. Now, the movement of those machines is limited. Too much <strong>shaking</strong> is also a problem. With the morphing wheels, the robots could carry objects that need smooth movement for industrial use.</p>
<p><strong>Aim to increase speed</strong></p>
<p>Song Sung-hyuk is the lead researcher at South Korea's KIMM and a member of the AI robotics research team. He said the goal is to make the wheels work at the average speed of a car. That is about 100 kilometers per hour.</p>
<p>Wheels developed for a similar purpose, such as airless wheels, have flexibility but are limited in their ability to overcome barriers, said Song. The difference between airless wheels and the morphing wheel is that airless wheels are always soft, but the morphing wheels can change from hard to soft when they meet a barrier. They can then return to being hard to permit faster travel where there are no barriers.</p>
<p>The morphing wheel is made of an outer circle of <strong>chain</strong> and a series of wires running through its central hub. A sensor controls the <strong>stiffness</strong> of the wires in reaction to the barriers in its path.</p>
<p>Song's team demonstrated to Reuters a model of a wheelchair riding on morphing wheels as it climbed stairs with 18-cm steps. The team has also tested a device using the wheel at speeds of up to 30 kilometers an hour.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Hyun Young Yi, Daewoung Kim and Jack Kim reported this story for Reuters. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>flexible</strong> – <em>adj</em>. capable of bending or being bent</p>
<p><strong>stairs</strong> – <em>n</em>. a series of steps that go from one level or floor to another</p>
<p><strong>morph</strong> – <em>v</em>. to change gradually and completely from one thing into another thing usually in a way that is surprising or that seems magical</p>
<p><strong>shake </strong><em>–v.</em> to move back and forth quickly and even violently</p>
<p><strong>chain </strong><em>–n.</em> a series of metal links that look like a rope or similar line</p>
<p><strong>stiff</strong> – <em>adj</em>. difficult to bend or move</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Hawaiian Volcano Showed Signs Two Months before Exploding (2024/11/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/study-hawaiian-volcano-showed-signs-two-months-before-exploding.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists say they were able to identify signs that Hawaii's Mauna Loa volcano might <strong>erupt</strong> about two months before it exploded.</p>
<p>A new study explains the signs they discovered and how their method might be used to predict future eruptions.</p>
<p>Mauna Loa is the world's largest active volcano. The volcano's most recent eruption began in November 2022. In the weeks before the eruption, scientists identified, or detected, small earthquakes nearby. They also recognized other signs of volcanic activity and were able to warn people on the island of Hawaii.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file photo, onlookers watch the lava flow down the mountain from the Mauna Loa eruption, Tuesday, Nov. 29, 2022, near Hilo, Hawaii. (AP Photo/Marco Garcia, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/b4539f6a-c3a9-4e85-a076-3179d66cd507_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this file photo, onlookers watch the lava flow down the mountain from the Mauna Loa eruption, Tuesday, Nov. 29, 2022, near Hilo, Hawaii. (AP Photo/Marco Garcia, File)</span></div>
<p>Now, examinations of lava from the volcano have confirmed when melted rock underground started to move.</p>
<p>Kendra Lynn is a research geologist at the Hawaiian Volcano Observatory who helped lead the research. She also co-wrote the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-024-52881-7">study</a>, which recently appeared in the publication <em>Nature Communications</em>.</p>
<p>Lynn told the Associated Press that ground expansion and increased earthquake activity near the volcano resulted from melted <strong>magma</strong> rising from lower levels of Earth's <strong>crust</strong>. This movement of liquefied rock filled openings beneath the volcano.</p>
<p>When the underground pressure got high enough, the magma broke through hard surface rock and became lava. Later, the researchers collected pieces of the volcanic rock.</p>
<p>The team studied the chemistry of certain <strong>crystals</strong> within the lava to estimate when major movements began. It found that around 70 days before Mauna Loa's eruption, large amounts of melted rock had moved from three to five kilometers underground to just two kilometers beneath the surface. The researchers said this movement matched the timeline the geologists had observed with other signs.</p>
<p>Before 2022, the last time Mauna Loa erupted was in 1984. Most of the U.S. volcanoes scientists consider to be active are found in Hawaii, Alaska and near the West Coast. Worldwide, about 585 volcanoes are considered active.</p>
<p>“Volcanoes are <strong>tricky </strong>because we don't get to watch directly what's happening inside – we have to look for other signs," said Erik Klemetti Gonzalez. He is a volcano expert at Denison University in Ohio who was not involved in the study.</p>
<p>Ben Andrews heads a volcano program for the U. S. government's Smithsonian Institution. He also was not involved in the study. Andrews told the AP that scientists are still not able to fully predict volcanic eruptions. But he said they can issue a “<strong>forecast</strong>” based on observations and data.</p>
<p>Andrews compared volcano forecasts to weather forecasts, which are based on the probability that an event might happen. Experts say better data about past volcanic behavior can help researchers produce more detailed forecasts of future activity.</p>
<p>Klemetti Gonzalez added, “We can look for similar <strong>patterns</strong> in the future and expect that there's a higher probability of conditions for an eruption happening.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>erupt </strong>–v. to have a sudden and violent explosion</p>
<p><strong>magma </strong>–n. melted rock underneath the Earth's surface</p>
<p><strong>crust </strong><em>– n</em>. a hard, dry layer of the surface of something</p>
<p><strong>crystal </strong><em>– n.</em> a kind of see-through rock</p>
<p><strong>tricky </strong><em>– adj.</em> difficult to deal with or do</p>
<p><strong>forecast </strong><em>– n. </em>a report saying what is likely to happen in the future</p>
<p><strong>pattern </strong><em>– n. </em>a particular way that something is often done or repeated</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How to Keep Tropical Plants Through the Winter (2024/11/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/how-to-keep-tropical-plants-through-the-winter.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Are you dreaming of a vacation to a warm place next to the sea?</p>
<p>You may be thinking of sitting under a palm tree, or next to a banana plant. Or you may dream of walking on a faraway island in the <strong>tropics</strong> surrounded by colorful flowers such as birds of paradise and cannas.</p>
<p>Tropical plants make us feel like we are in warm places with a pleasing climate. In cold climates, these plants can grow outside during the summer. But they suffer in cold weather.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This 2006 image provided by Chris Petersen shows an orange canna plant in bloom at Landcraft Environmentals in Mattituck, N.Y. (Chris Petersen via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/10886dcf-65f9-49ce-8041-a11e0a1fa2c0_cx0_cy12_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This 2006 image provided by Chris Petersen shows an orange canna plant in bloom at Landcraft Environmentals in Mattituck, N.Y. (Chris Petersen via AP)</span></div>
<p>The gardening expert for the Associated Press, Jessica Damiano, says most people in the United States have to treat tropical plants like annuals because they do not survive cold winters. An annual plant is one that dies after one growing season.</p>
<p>Following her guidelines you will find out how to save both tropical plants and money. You also can make future summers at home feel like an <strong>exotic</strong> getaway.</p>
<p><strong>Colocasia</strong></p>
<p>If you bought <strong>potted</strong> elephant ear plants, also called Colocasia, cannas or caladiums, bring the pots inside instead of putting them into the waste collection. Place them near a sunny window, water often and fertilize as directed with ordinary houseplant fertilizer at half strength.</p>
<p>If the plants are too big for the house or have been planted in the garden, leave them outdoors until the first <strong>frost</strong> turns their leaves brown. Then cut the plants down to 15 centimeters tall and dig them up.</p>
<p>Rinse and separate their roots, which might have small, rounded parts, and let them dry completely. Then prepare a box with some air holes and peat moss to store the roots. Place the box or container in a cool, dark place.</p>
<p>Examine them once a month, adding water if they seem to be drying out, and throw out any rotten pieces. Plant outdoors and fertilize when the soil has warmed up to 16 degrees Celsius in spring. You also can start them indoors in potting mix one month earlier. Set them by your sunniest window or under grow lights, keeping the soil a little wet.</p>
<p><strong>Potted hibiscus and angel trumpets</strong></p>
<p>Gardeners should also bring potted hibiscus and angel trumpets, also known as Brugmansia, indoors before the first frost. Treat them as houseplants by placing them next to a sunny window during winter. These plants may lose their leaves, but they will come back in the spring.</p>
<p>If there is no room for the plants in your living space, you can help them get through winter by storing pots at six to seven degrees Celsius. Examine them twice a month and water them very lightly when the soil feels dry at finger depth.</p>
<p>Before moving them outdoors, place the plants in a warm, sunny spot. Lightly <strong>prune </strong>them, water and fertilize the plants about one month before it is safe to move them back outdoors.</p>
<p><strong>Banana plants</strong></p>
<p>Potted banana plants should be cut down to soil level when the first frost browns their leaves. Store the containers in a dark place at roughly six to seven degrees Celsius. Look at the soil monthly, watering very lightly only when completely dry. Growth will begin again in spring but keep the plants indoors until the danger of frost has passed. Fertilize and resume regular watering.</p>
<p>Do not cut back bananas that are growing in the ground in the fall. Just dig them up and contain their roots in a plastic waste bag. Store them as you would a potted banana plant. Cut them down to 15 centimeters in spring and plant them in the garden after the danger of frost has passed.</p>
<p>Then, put the money you would have spent on new plants toward a water container, a firepit or tropical fruit juice. You can then sit back and enjoy your tropical backyard <strong>oasis</strong>.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jessica Damiano reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>tropics</strong> <em>– n.</em> the part of the world that is near the equator where the weather is very warm</p>
<p><strong>exotic</strong> – <em>adj.</em> of a plant or animal - not living or growing naturally in a particular area: from another part of the world</p>
<p><strong>potted </strong><em>– adj. </em>grown in a pot, a round container usually made out of clay, ceramic or plastic</p>
<p><strong>frost</strong> – <em>n. </em>a thin layer of ice that forms on the ground, on grass, etc., when the air becomes cold</p>
<p><strong>prune</strong> – <em>v. </em>to cut off some of the branches of (a tree or bush) so that it will grow better or look better</p>
<p><strong>oasis</strong> – <em>n</em>. an area in a desert where there is water and plants</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Chinese Rover Finds Evidence of Ancient Ocean on Mars (2024/11/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/study-chinese-rover-finds-evidence-of-ancient-ocean-on-mars.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists say newly examined data from a Chinese explorer on Mars adds to existing evidence that the planet once had a very large ocean.</p>
<p>The exploring vehicle, or rover, is called Zhurong. It landed on the Martian surface in 2021. The rover has been operating in an area known as Utopia Planitia. This area is a large <strong>plain</strong> in Mars' northern hemisphere, the American space agency NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.jpl.nasa.gov/images/pia03796-utopia-planitia/">explains</a>.</p>
<p>The researchers combined data from Zhurong's instruments with observations from satellites and spacecraft orbiting Mars. The team said the examinations appeared to show that Utopia Planitia had geological elements suggesting an ancient ocean coastline.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file photo, a screen broadcasts a CCTV state media news update, showing an image of Mars taken by Chinese Mars rover Zhurong as part of the Tianwen-1 mission, in Beijing, China, May 19, 2021. (REUTERS/Thomas Peter/File Photo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/00f7a5aa-8732-455e-a1be-d0988b6772f1_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this file photo, a screen broadcasts a CCTV state media news update, showing an image of Mars taken by Chinese Mars rover Zhurong as part of the Tianwen-1 mission, in Beijing, China, May 19, 2021. (REUTERS/Thomas Peter/File Photo)</span></div>
<p>The scientists said multiple elements, or features, pointed to evidence that a large ocean existed on Mars billions of years ago. The discovered surface features included <strong>troughs</strong> and <strong>channels</strong> that may have been formed by flowing water on Mars.</p>
<p>Earlier research that examined data of similar surface features suggested they might have been created by mud volcanoes, which likely formed in areas where there had been water or ice.</p>
<p>The researchers said the evidence suggests the area likely contained deep ocean environments as well as <strong>shallow</strong> ones. The research findings were recently reported <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-024-75507-w">in a study</a> in the publication <em>Scientific Reports</em>.</p>
<p>Bo Wu was the lead writer of the study. He is a planetary scientist at Hong Kong Polytechnic University. Wu told Reuters news agency, "We estimate the flooding of the Utopia Planitia on Mars was approximately 3.68 billion years ago. The ocean surface was likely frozen in a geologically short period."</p>
<p>The search for water on Mars is closely linked to the search for signs of possible life. Evidence of a past ocean raises the possibility that the planet may have once supported microbial life.</p>
<p>There have been past studies suggesting Mars once had a large northern ocean. <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/new-evidence-for-large-ancient-ocean-on-mars/6818883.html">One such study</a> was released in 2022. That research was based on satellite images of the Martian surface. The images were combined to produce detailed maps of the planet's northern hemisphere. Examination of the maps led to evidence of coastlines that once sat at the edge of a large ocean.</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/new-study-suggests-mars-has-large-underground-ocean/7744218.html">Another study</a>, released in August, presented evidence suggesting Mars may contain a large ocean deep beneath its surface. That evidence was based on NASA's InSight Lander.</p>
<p>China's Zhurong rover began its data collection mission in May 2021. It stopped operating about one year later, with mission planners saying the power system was likely affected by sand and dust. But the rover still outlasted its planned mission of three months.</p>
<p>The researchers said the data shows that the ocean seems to have disappeared by about 3.42 billion years ago.</p>
<p>The study suggests the water that likely filled the Martian ocean was “heavily silted,” study co-writer Sergey Krasilnikov said. He is a planetary scientist at Hong Kong Polytechnic University. Silt is a mix of sand and clay that has been carried by water, but later settles on land.</p>
<p>Krasilnikov added that during the period when the Martian ocean would have been active, the planet “...probably had a thick, warm atmosphere.” At that time, “microbial life was much more likely," he said.</p>
<p>Hong Kong Polytechnic's Wu said the new findings do “provide further evidence to support the theory of a Martian ocean.”</p>
<p>However, he told the French news agency AFP the study does "not claim that our findings <strong>definitively</strong> prove” there was an ocean on Mars. Such proof, he said, would likely require a future mission to bring Mars materials back to Earth for closer study.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from Reuters, Agence France-Presse, Hong Kong Polytechnic University and Scientific Reports.</em></p>
<p><strong>________________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>plain </strong><em>– n. </em>a large area of flat land</p>
<p><strong>trough </strong><em>– n.</em> a low point in a series of high and low points</p>
<p><strong>channel </strong><em>– n.</em> a long, narrow passageway for water or other liquids to flow along</p>
<p><strong>shallow </strong><em>– adj. </em>not deep</p>
<p><strong>definitive </strong><em>– adj. </em>certain, clear and not likely to change</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Ethiopia Finds Limited Success in Moving to Electric Vehicles (2024/11/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/ethiopia-finds-limited-success-in-moving-to-electric-vehicles.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>As the price of fuel increased greatly in Ethiopia earlier this year, Awgachew Seleshi decided to buy an electric vehicle, or EV. The decision follows government efforts to slowly remove gas-powered vehicles from the roads.</p>
<p>Months later, Seleshi is not sure whether it was the right decision. He now faces an uneven supply of electricity and a lack of parts for repair. He told the Associated Press that imported parts from China are costly and, “few <strong>mechanics</strong> are able to fix such cars and the <strong>resale</strong> value of such cars is poor."</p>
<p>Seleshi's problems are like those of many in Ethiopia.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A driver charges his electric car at a charging station in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia Thursday, Oct. 3, 2024. (AP Photo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/354c49eb-6b91-4ed2-9eb9-735419b0c137_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A driver charges his electric car at a charging station in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia Thursday, Oct. 3, 2024. (AP Photo)</span></div>
<p><strong>Ban on non-electric private vehicles</strong></p>
<p>In January, the East African country became the first in the world to ban imports of non-electric private vehicles. The decision eased pressure on the government's use of limited foreign <strong>currency</strong> to lower the cost of fuel.</p>
<p>In early October, Ethiopia's government raised the price of fuel by up to 8 percent as part of a plan to slowly end fuel <strong>subsidies</strong> in Africa's second-most populous country.</p>
<p>Officials say more than 100,000 electric cars are imported into the country each month. And the government hopes to increase that number by 2030. By that time, the country's new dam on the Nile River is expected to produce electricity at full power.</p>
<p>Ethiopian Prime Minister Abiy Ahmed said earlier this year that the Grand Renaissance Dam will start producing more than 5,000 megawatts of electric power within a year. Officials say such a production level would support the move to electric vehicles.</p>
<p><strong>Repair services </strong></p>
<p>For now, many in Addis Ababa, a city of more than 5 million people, think the country is not ready to provide enough charging stations and repair services.</p>
<p>The few service station owners who can fix broken electric vehicles say they have too much work. And the EV owners say they are overcharged by repair shops because of a lack of competition. Many EVs are now parked, waiting for parts to come from China.</p>
<p>Bareo Hassen Bareo is the transport minister. Bareo believes Ethiopia can be a model nation with a green economy, especially with the move toward electric vehicles. He said that the government will invest in public charging stations and has plans to manufacture EV batteries to reduce imports. Private efforts to manufacture EVs with South Korean carmaker Hyundai in Ethiopia, however, have collapsed over sourcing of materials.</p>
<p><strong>Charging stations </strong></p>
<p>Samson Berhane, an economist based in Addis Ababa, said the sudden flood of EVs into the country makes it difficult for owners to find charging stations. But, he believes Ethiopia can provide enough electricity for EVs within the next 10 years while meeting its industrial goals.</p>
<p>Some Ethiopians are already <strong>giving up</strong> on electric vehicles.</p>
<p>Yared Alemayehu sold his Chinese-made EV at a loss and bought a used Toyota Corolla. He said the EV “frequently broke,” and the repair shop “was overcharging.”</p>
<p>Taxi driver Dereje Hailu said he had high hopes for his Chinese-made EV earlier this year. But now, he says, "With such a car, I fear I might be <strong>stuck</strong> if I go far from Addis Ababa, where there are no charging stations,"</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Samuel Getachew </em><em>reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>mechanic</strong> – <em>n</em>. a person who repairs machines (such as car engines) and keeps them running properly</p>
<p><strong>currency</strong> – <em>n</em>. the money that a country uses; a specific kind of money</p>
<p><strong>subsidy </strong>– <em>n</em>. money that is paid usually by a government to keep the price of a product or service low or to help a business or organization to continue to function</p>
<p><strong>resale </strong>– <em>n</em>. the act of selling something that you have bought</p>
<p><strong>give up </strong>– <em>phrasal verb</em>. to stop having, doing, or using (something)</p>
<p><strong>stuck </strong>– <em>adj</em>. difficult or impossible to move from a position</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Too Many Deer Live in England's Forests (2024/11/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/too-many-deer-live-in-england-s-forests.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Martin Edwards studies the shadows of the ancient forest from a high seat and waits. Sitting still, he watches with his special camera.</p>
<p>Then, Edwards aims and fires his rifle.</p>
<p>He has killed a male deer, or buck. It was one of many wild deer found in this forest in Hampshire, southern England.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A Stag in rut bellows in early morning mist Bushy Park southwest London, Saturday, Sept. 28, 2024. (AP Photo/Alastair Grant)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f7e7fb7f-eb7b-4aa5-99b6-cebdce1b8b61_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A Stag in rut bellows in early morning mist Bushy Park southwest London, Saturday, Sept. 28, 2024. (AP Photo/Alastair Grant)</span></div>
<p>Edwards supports controlling the deer population with a method called humane deer management.</p>
<p>The idea is to make sure the animals do not become too numerous for the forests and farmland in a country where deer no longer have natural predators. A predator is an animal that catches and kills other animals for food.</p>
<p><strong>Population </strong></p>
<p>There are now more deer in England than at any other time in the last 1,000 years, says the Forestry Commission, the government department looking after England's public forests.</p>
<p>An estimated 2 million deer now live in the country.</p>
<p>The high deer numbers have had a big effect on the environment, officials say. Deer have damaged large areas of woodland, including young trees, as well as the living areas of some birds like robins. Some landowners have lost large amounts of crops to deer. And overpopulation means that the animals are more likely to suffer from starvation and disease.</p>
<p>Forestry experts and businesses argue that killing the deer — and supplying the meat to <strong>consumers </strong>— is a good idea.</p>
<p>The reduced deer population can bring back balance to the environment and provide a low-fat, <strong>sustainable</strong> protein.</p>
<p><strong>Venison </strong></p>
<p>Deer meat is called venison. It is a red meat similar to lean beef but with a stronger flavor.</p>
<p>Although many in Britain see venison as a high-end food, one support group sees it as a good protein for those who do not have enough money to buy other meats.</p>
<p>“Why not utilize that<strong> fantastic</strong> meat to feed people in need?” said SJ Hunt of The Country Food Trust. The group gives meals made with wild venison to food banks.</p>
<p>The government says native wild deer play a role in healthy forest environments. Still, the government admits that the deer population needs controlling.</p>
<p>But experts like Edwards, a spokesman for the British Association for Shooting and Conservation, believe killing them for meat is the only effective choice.</p>
<p>The deer population increased greatly during the COVID-19 pandemic. Hunters, like everyone else, stayed home and the restaurant market — the main source for venison sales in Britain — disappeared overnight.</p>
<p>“There were no sales of venison and the price was absolutely on the floor,” said Ben Rigby, a leading venison and game meats seller. “The deer had a chance to breed <strong>massively</strong>.”</p>
<p>Rigby's company now processes hundreds of deer a week. The business sends venison or steaks to restaurants and food markets. One difficulty, Rigby said, is growing people's taste for venison. This is especially important after Brexit put new barriers up for exporting the meat.</p>
<p><strong>From the forest to the table </strong></p>
<p>In England, shooting deer is legal under some restrictions. Hunters must have a permit, use certain kinds of firearms and observe open seasons. They also need an acceptable or valid reason, such as when a landowner permits them to kill the deer when their land is damaged. Hunting deer with groups of dogs is illegal.</p>
<p>Making wild venison more widely available in food stores and beyond will bring out more hunters and ensure the meat does not go to waste, Edwards said.</p>
<p>Forestry England, which controls public forests, is part of the effort to increase venison use. In recent years, it supplied some hospitals with 1,000 kg of wild venison to use for food.</p>
<p>The approach appears to have been well received. However, it has gotten some criticism from animal welfare group PETA. PETA supports veganism – the practice of not eating or using animal products.</p>
<p>SJ Hunt of The Country Food Trust said it is possible to do much more with the meat. Her organization provided hundreds of thousands of venison meals to food banks last year — and people are hungry for more, she said.</p>
<p>She described the meat as nutritious and “free-range to the purest form of that definition.”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Sylvia Hui reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>consumer </strong><em>– n.</em> one that uses or buys goods</p>
<p><strong>sustainable</strong> <em>– adj.</em> used in a way that does not overly deplete natural resources</p>
<p><strong>fantastic </strong><em>– adj. </em>excellent, very good</p>
<p><strong>massively</strong> <em>-- adv.</em> large in scope or degree</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What Does It Mean to ‘Hit Pay Dirt'? (2024/11/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/what-does-it-mean-to-hit-pay-dirt.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>On this program we explore words and expressions in the English language. We give examples and notes on usage.</p>
<p>Many valuable materials are buried deep inside the ground, such as gold, oil and diamonds. But finding these riches and bringing them to the surface takes much time and effort.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - " and="" at="" black="" c.="" congress="" dillon="" dirt="" for="" gold="" grabill="" h.="" hills="" in="" lamb="" library="" of="" old="" panning="" rockervill="" s.d.="" spriggs="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/03370000-0aff-0242-c00c-08daf30a700c_cx4_cy12_cw90_w268_r1.jpeg" the="" timers="" work=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - "Old timers, Spriggs, Lamb and Dillon at work" panning for gold (pay dirt) at Rockervill, S.D., in the Black Hills, 1889. (John C. H. Grabill/Library of Congress)</span></div>
<p>In the past, the term <u>pay dirt </u>was used to describe something found in the dirt that could bring you money. Gold is a common example of pay dirt. In fact, word experts say the term dates back to when North America's famous gold rush was happening.</p>
<p>By the mid-1800s, thousands of people had come to parts of the United States and Canada to search for gold. The work was hard and dangerous. The weather and <strong>terrain</strong> presented many difficulties.</p>
<p>Here is an example of how to use <u>pay dirt</u> from <a class="wsw__a" href="https://dictionary.cambridge.org/us/dictionary/english/pay-dirt">Cambridge's</a> online dictionary:</p>
<p><em>Gold rushes continued into the 19th century as lucky <strong>prospectors</strong> struck <u>pay dirt</u>.</em></p>
<p>However, <u>pay dirt</u> does not have to be a valuable material found in the ground. These days, it can also describe something that produces money or profit. Or it can even be the money or profit itself.</p>
<p>Here are some additional examples:</p>
<p><em>Email addresses are the new <u>pay dirt</u> in social media marketing. You can reach a possible buyer in their inbox.</em></p>
<p><em>The musical group <u>hit pay dirt</u> with their song after it went viral on TikTok. </em></p>
<p>And that gives us the expression <u>to hit pay dirt.</u></p>
<p><u>To hit pay dirt</u> means to do or find something that results in money or success. And like digging gold, it usually doesn't come easily. It requires work. When you <u>hit pay dirt,</u> you work hard to make money or profit from an idea or activity.</p>
<p>We often use the verb “hit” when using the term <u>pay dirt</u>. But sometimes we also say “strike” pay dirt. This is similar to the expression <u>to strike it rich</u>. Many people have dreams of <u>striking it rich</u> one day.</p>
<p>In her book <em>Gold Rush</em>, author and illustrator Flora Delargy describes the process of <u>hitting pay dirt</u>. She writes that in order to get large amounts of <u>pay dirt</u> out of the ground, “<strong>miners</strong> would have to break through layers of <strong>permafrost</strong> to reach the <strong>gravel</strong> <strong>bedrock</strong> beneath.”</p>
<p>This description demonstrates the difficulties faced by miners seeking to <u>strike pay dirt.</u></p>
<p>And that's the end of this <em>Words and Their Stories. </em>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>terrain </strong><em>-n.</em> the surface features of an area of land</p>
<p><strong>prospector </strong><em>-n. </em>someone who explores for mineral deposits</p>
<p><strong>miner </strong><em>-n. </em>one who digs or forms a pit or tunnel from which minerals (as coal, gold, or diamonds) are taken</p>
<p><strong>permafrost </strong><em>-n. </em>a permanently frozen layer at variable depth below the surface in frigid regions of a planet (such as earth)</p>
<p><strong>gravel </strong><em>-n. </em>loose rounded fragments of rock</p>
<p><strong>bedrock </strong><em>-n. </em>the solid rock lying under surface materials (as soil) that are not in layers</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Microsoft Helps Vatican Recreate St. Peter’s Basilica Digitally (2024/11/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/microsoft-helps-vatican-recreate-st-peter-s-basilica-digitally.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Technology company Microsoft is working with the Roman Catholic Church to create a detailed, digital version of St. Peter's Basilica in Vatican City.</p>
<p>The project aims to give people a new way to experience the famous building, which sits in the Catholic Church's spiritual and administrative center in Rome.</p>
<p>Roman Catholic leaders recently joined Microsoft's President Brad Smith to present the new digital creation to the public. The official launch of the system has been set for December 1. It will permit individuals to explore St. Peter's Basilica online and provide interactive experiences for all visitors to the Vatican.</p><div class="contentImage"><img ai-enhanced="" alt="A view of St. Peter's basilica during the preview to the press of the exhibition 'Petros eni', which is part of the project " at="" basilica:="" borgia="" experience="" gregorio="" nov.="" peter="" photo="" saturday="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/629ce677-eb1d-493b-841c-4de7dd60cd85_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg" st.="" the="" vatican=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A view of St. Peter's basilica during the preview to the press of the exhibition 'Petros eni', which is part of the project "St. Peter's Basilica: AI-Enhanced Experience" at the Vatican, Saturday, Nov. 9, 2024. (AP Photo/Gregorio Borgia)</span></div>
<p>The effort involved <strong>drones </strong>flying around the empty basilica for four weeks to capture images of all parts of the building. The drones – equipped with many cameras and lasers – took more than 400,000 high-quality pictures.</p>
<p>The process used artificial intelligence (AI) methods to create a complete 3D copy of the basilica. One goal of the project was to provide a way for anyone in the world to have the chance to “visit” the church and learn about its history.</p>
<p>Microsoft chief Smith told a press conference at Vatican City the project represented “one of the most technologically <strong>advanced</strong> and <strong>sophisticated</strong> projects of its kind” ever carried out.</p>
<p>Cardinal Mauro Gambetti is the Archpriest of St. Peter's Basilica. He <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.vaticannews.va/en/vatican-city/news/2024-11/ai-technology-st-peters-basilica-digital-experience-microsoft.html">praised</a> the new technology at the press conference. Gambetti compared the highly detailed digital experience to looking up at a “starry sky on a summer night.” He added, “The new tools act like a telescope or spaceship for better viewing.”</p>
<p>The project was launched ahead of the Vatican's 2025 Jubilee celebration. This marks a holy year at the Vatican when more than 30 million <strong>worshippers</strong> are expected to visit the basilica. This will be in addition to the 50,000 people who visit on a normal day. The basilica will celebrate its 400th anniversary in 2026.</p>
<p>The Associated Press reported Pope Francis visited Smith and the project's development teams at the Vatican. He said the effort should help everyone “feel welcome in this great house.”</p>
<p>The pope added that the project was a way to recognize and continue to celebrate the Vatican's rich spiritual history. “...It is a gift and a <strong>task</strong> to care for it, in both a spiritual and material sense, even through the latest technologies,” he said.</p>
<p>Pope Francis has warned that AI should only be used in <strong>ethical </strong>ways.<strong> </strong>In his World Message of Peace this year, he proposed an international treaty to control, or regulate, the technology. He argued that AI systems lack human values and could cause great harm.</p>
<p>The digital system permits visitors to request entry times to the basilica. This could be a welcome change for visitors used to waiting in lines for hours to get into the basilica, which is one of the world's most visited buildings.</p>
<p>The collected images have already identified structural damage and signs of <strong>deterioration</strong>.<strong> </strong>Experts said the technology can find such problems much faster and more effectively than human workers. Vatican officials plan to use the images to continually identify areas needing repairs.</p>
<p>Smith did not say how much Microsoft had invested in the project. But he said the idea came after Pope Francis urged technology companies in 2018 to come together to use AI for cultural purposes.</p>
<p>Smith noted his company had also completed similar AI projects at Mont Saint-Michel in France and for Ancient Olympia in Greece.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press, Reuters, Agence France-Presse and Vatican News reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>drone </strong><em>– n. </em>a pilotless aircraft</p>
<p><strong>advanced </strong><em>– adj.</em> having developed or progressed to a late stage</p>
<p><strong>sophisticated </strong><em>– adj.</em> developed to a high level of complexity</p>
<p><strong>worshipper </strong><em>– n. </em>to honor or show respect for a divine being</p>
<p><strong>task </strong><em>– n.</em> a piece of work to be done</p>
<p><strong>ethical </strong><em>– adj. </em>conforming to accepted standards of behavior</p>
<p><strong>deteriorate </strong><em>– v. </em>to make or become worse or of less value</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Most and Almost (2024/11/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/most-and-almost.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Paola in Bolivia about the usage of the words “most” and “almost."</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/65b023c9-e43f-4975-9b87-f1256728ff9a_w268_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>I am having some confusion about the words “most” and “almost.” Sometimes they seem like the same to me, and I wish to know how they can be different.</p>
<p>Thank you,</p>
<p>Paola</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Paola.</p>
<p>The word “almost” is an adverb. The word “most” can be an adjective, adverb, or quantifier. A quantifier is a word that describes how much of something there is. The words “more,” “some,” and “all” are other examples of quantifiers.</p>
<p>As a quantifier, “most” simply means a majority of a group or the largest part of something. However, the phrase “almost all of” means nearly all of something, such as 90 percent or more.</p>
<p><strong>When to use the preposition “of”</strong></p>
<p>Some English learners have difficulty knowing when to use the preposition “of” with the words “most” or “almost.”</p>
<p>We cannot put the <strong>preposition</strong> “of” directly after the adverb “almost”. Instead, we must use the two words “all of” after “almost” to describe a noun, as in this example:</p>
<p><em><u>Almost all of the</u></em><em> children who got sick felt better within 48 hours. </em></p>
<p>When we use the word “most” as an adjective, we can simply put a noun directly after it when we are describing something in general, as in this example:</p>
<p><em><u>Most</u> children enjoy playing games.</em></p>
<p>However, we use the preposition “of” after the adjective “most” when we describe something specific. The following two examples show this:</p>
<p><em><u>Most of the</u> children in his class enjoy playing this game. </em></p>
<p><em><u>Most of his</u> friends live in the city. </em></p>
<p><strong>More uses of most and almost</strong></p>
<p>The adverb “almost” means “very nearly or very close.” For example, if you have a job to do that takes an hour to finish and you have already worked 55 minutes, you can say:</p>
<p><em>I am <u>almost</u> finished.</em></p>
<p>As an adverb, the word “most” can describe another adjective, as in this example:</p>
<p><em>That was <u>the most beautiful</u> sunset I have seen in a long time. </em></p>
<p>We sometimes use “most” -- without the word “the” -- as an adverb after any form of the verb “be.”</p>
<p><em>The thing <u>I'm most worried about</u> is her health.</em></p>
<p>Note, however, that we also often use the word “the” before “most.”</p>
<p><em>The thing I'm <u>the most worried about</u> is her health. </em></p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? We'd like to hear from you. Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please include where you are from in your email, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>preposition </strong>–n. a small word that provides additional information about a noun, such as direction, degree or location</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Identify Misunderstanding about Uranus (2024/11/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/scientists-identify-misunderstanding-about-uranus.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">14 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In 1781, German-born British astronomer William Herschel made Uranus the first planet discovered with a telescope. But, 243 years later, we still do not know much about this cold planet, the third largest in our solar system. And some of what we thought we knew about it turns out to be untrue.</p>
<p>Much of the knowledge about Uranus was collected when NASA's robotic spacecraft Voyager 2 flew past it in 1986. But scientists have since learned that the craft visited at a time of unusual conditions. An intense solar wind event at the time led to misleading observations about Uranus, and especially its magnetic field.</p>
<p><strong>Observations in a solar wind event</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - An image of the planet Uranus taken by the NASA spacecraft Voyager 2 in 1986. (NASA/JPL/Handout via REUTERS )" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/b866f7af-b6b1-4a5b-a65b-ec143da00494_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - An image of the planet Uranus taken by the NASA spacecraft Voyager 2 in 1986. (NASA/JPL/Handout via REUTERS )</span></div>
<p>The solar wind is a high-speed flow of charged particles coming from the sun. The researchers took a second look at eight months of data from around the time of Voyager 2's visit and found that it flew near Uranus just a few days after the solar wind had reduced the planet's magnetosphere to about 20 percent of its usual size.</p>
<p>A <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/heliophysics/focus-areas/magnetosphere-ionosphere/">magnetosphere</a> is an area of space surrounding a planet that is controlled by the planet's magnetic field. The magnetosphere protects the planet from solar and cosmic particle radiation.</p>
<p>The Voyager 2 observations led scientists to think Uranus' magnetosphere lacked in plasma and had very intense belts of highly energetic electrons.</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.psfc.mit.edu/vision/what_is_plasma">Plasma</a> is often called the fourth state of matter after solids, liquids and gases. In the night sky, plasma gives out light in the form of stars, <strong>nebulas</strong>, and even the <strong>auroras</strong> above the north and south poles. Plasma is a common feature in the magnetosphere of other planets, so scientists did not understand why there would not be much of it observed around Uranus.</p>
<p>Jamie Jasinski studies space plasma at NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory. He is the lead writer of the study published recently in the publication <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41550-024-02389-3"><em>Nature Astronomy</em></a>.</p>
<p>"We found that the solar wind conditions present during the flyby only <strong>occur</strong> 4 percent of the time. The flyby occurred during the maximum <strong>peak</strong> solar wind intensity in that entire eight-month period," Jasinski said. "We would have observed a much bigger magnetosphere if Voyager 2 had arrived a week earlier.”</p>
<p>Such a visit would likely have shown that the Uranus magnetosphere is like those of Jupiter, Saturn and Neptune, the solar system's other large planets, the researchers said.</p>
<p><strong>Future exploration</strong></p>
<p>Uranus looks blue green because of the methane contained in its atmosphere. The planet is big enough to fit 63 Earths inside it. Among the solar system's eight planets, only Jupiter and Saturn are larger.</p>
<p>Uranus orbits almost 20 times further from the sun than Earth does. And it has 28 known moons and two sets of rings.</p>
<p>Data collected by Voyager 2 had suggested that its two largest moons - Titania and Oberon - often orbit outside the magnetosphere. But the new study shows that they usually stay inside the protective space, making it easier for scientists to magnetically <strong>detect</strong> possible subsurface oceans.</p>
<p>"Both are thought to be <strong>prime</strong> candidates for hosting liquid water oceans in the Uranian system...," Jet Propulsion Laboratory planetary scientist and study co-writer Corey Cochrane said.</p>
<p>Scientists want to learn whether subsurface oceans on moons in the outer solar system have conditions that could support life. So, on October 14, NASA launched a spacecraft on a mission to Jupiter's moon Europa to try to answer that question.</p>
<p>"A future mission to Uranus is <strong>crucial</strong> to understanding not only the planet and magnetosphere, but also its atmosphere, rings and moons," Jasinski said.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Will Dunham </em><em>reported this story for Reuters.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>nebula</strong><em> – n.</em> a cloud of gas or dust in space that can sometimes be seen at night</p>
<p><strong>aurora</strong><em> </em>(_ borealis, or Northern Lights) <em>– n. </em>large areas of green, red, blue, or yellow light that sometimes appear in the night sky in far northern regions</p>
<p><strong>occur</strong> – v. to happen</p>
<p><strong>peak</strong><em> – adj.</em> at the highest point or level</p>
<p><strong>detect</strong><em> – v. </em>to discover or notice the presence of (something that is hidden or hard to see, hear, taste, etc.)</p>
<p><strong>prime</strong><em> – adj.</em> most important</p>
<p><strong>crucial</strong> – <em>adj.</em> very important</p>
<p><em>What do you think of this story? Write to us in the Comments Section. </em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>An Introduction to Verb Tenses (2024/11/15)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/an-introduction-to-verb-tenses.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Adam Brock</span><br/><span class="datetime">14 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>For VOA Learning English, this is Everyday Grammar.</p>
<p>Today we are going to give you a basic overview of the verb tense system in English.</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/c1b55610-3750-4060-934d-8a5ed2cdcc08_w268_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>Verb tenses tell us how an action relates to the flow of time.</p>
<p>There are three main verb tenses in English: <em>present, past </em>and <em>future</em>. The present, past and future tenses are divided into four <strong>aspects</strong>: the <em>simple, progressive, perfect </em>and<em> perfect progressive</em>.</p>
<p>There are 12 major verb tenses that English learners should know.</p>
<p>English has only two ways of forming a tense from the verb alone: the past and the present. For example,</p>
<p><em>We drove</em> and <em>we drive</em>.</p>
<p>To form other verb tenses, you have to add a form of <em>have, be </em>or <em>will</em> in front of the verb. These are called helping, or <strong>auxiliary verbs</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Time, culture, and grammar</strong></p>
<p>Verb tenses can be difficult to learn in a foreign language. Different cultures think different ways about time. Chinese, for example, has no grammatical verb tenses. Other languages, like Indonesian, express time only through adverbs — there are no changes to the verb form.</p>
<p>English verb tenses give many details about time and action such as:</p>
<p><em>Is the action finished? How long did the action happen? Was the action repeated? Did the action happen at a known or unknown time? Is the action a habit? Is the action planned or <strong>spontaneous</strong>?</em></p>
<p>It is difficult to think about time <strong>distinctions</strong> that do not exist in your own language. So, it can take many years for English learners to master verb tenses.</p>
<p>Let's get started. We are going to give examples of all 12 verb tenses using the verb <em>drive</em>.</p>
<p><strong>Simple tenses</strong></p>
<p>We'll start with the simple tenses. These are probably the first tenses you learned in English. Simple tenses usually refer to a single action. In general, simple tenses express facts and situations that existed in the past, exist in the present, or will exist in the future.</p>
<p>Simple present: <em>I drive home every day.</em></p>
<p>Simple past: <em>I drove home yesterday.</em></p>
<p>Simple future: <em>I will drive home later.</em></p>
<p><strong>Progressive (continuous) tenses</strong></p>
<p>Let's go on to the progressive tenses. We use progressive tenses to talk about unfinished events. Progressive tenses are also called <em>continuous</em> tenses.</p>
<p>Past progressive: <em>I was driving when you called.</em></p>
<p>Present progressive: <em>I am driving now. </em></p>
<p>Future progressive: <em>I will be driving when you call.</em></p>
<p><strong>Perfect tenses</strong></p>
<p>Now let's look at the perfect tenses. Perfect tenses cause the most confusion. To put it simply, they express the idea that one event happens before another event.</p>
<p>There are many tricky exceptions with the perfect tenses, which we will discuss in a future episode. The adverbs <em>never, yet </em>and<em> already </em>are common in perfect tenses.</p>
<p>Present perfect: <em>I have driven that road.</em></p>
<p>Past perfect:<em> I had already driven that road in the past. </em></p>
<p>Future perfect:<em> I will have driven 200 miles by tomorrow.</em></p>
<p><strong>Perfect progressive tenses</strong></p>
<p>Finally, let's look at the perfect progressive tenses. Generally, perfect progressive tenses express duration, or <em>how long</em>? Perfect progressive tenses usually include the adverbs <em>for </em>or<em> since</em>.</p>
<p>Present perfect progressive: <em>I have been driving since this morning.</em></p>
<p>Past perfect progressive: <em>I had been driving for three hours before I stopped to get gas.</em></p>
<p>Future perfect progressive:<em> I will have been driving for five hours by the time I arrive.</em></p>
<p>Don't worry if you don't understand everything yet. Here are some recommendations we have for learning verb tenses.</p>
<p><strong>Adverbs are your friends</strong></p>
<p>First, think of adverbs as your friends. Adverbs of time offer valuable clues about the correct verb tense.</p>
<p>Let's use the adverb <em>ago</em>. <em>Ago </em>is only used in the simple past as in, “I left home three years ago.” The adverb<em> ago</em> is never used in the present perfect. Certain adverbs occur with certain verb tenses.</p>
<p><strong>Keep it simple</strong></p>
<p>English learners sometimes try to impress people by using complex verb tenses. You often have a choice of several verb tenses. When you do, always choose the simplest one. It will be clearer for your listener, and there is less chance of making a mistake.</p>
<p><strong>Practice with questions</strong></p>
<p>Native speakers don't think <strong>consciously</strong> about verb tenses. With enough practice, English learners can internalize the verb tense system, too. Instead of worrying about deep time relationships, try using adverbs and your ear to choose the right verb tense.</p>
<p>Often when someone asks a question, you can respond in the same verb tense. We'll ask a question in each verb tense. Give an answer in the same tense, then listen to our answer.</p>
<p>Ready?</p>
<p>1. Did you get enough sleep last night? (simple past)</p>
<p><em>Yes, I slept well.</em></p>
<p>2. Do you shower every day? (simple present)</p>
<p><em>Yes, I shower every day.</em></p>
<p>3. Are you going to study tonight? (simple future)</p>
<p><em>Yes, I'm going to study tonight.</em></p>
<p>4. What were you doing when I called you last night? (past progressive)</p>
<p><em>I was eating dinner when you called me last night.</em></p>
<p>5. What are you doing right now? (present progressive)</p>
<p><em>I am practicing verb tenses right now.</em></p>
<p>6. What will you be doing at midnight on New Year's Eve? (future progressive)</p>
<p><em>I will be celebrating the New Year with my friends.</em></p>
<p>7. Had you ever tried skiing before today? (past perfect)</p>
<p><em>Yes, I had already done it several times before.</em></p>
<p>8. Have you ever broken the law? (present perfect)</p>
<p><em>No, I have never broken the law.</em></p>
<p>9. Will you have gotten married by the time you turn 30? (future perfect)</p>
<p><em>No, I will not have gotten married by the time I turn 30.</em></p>
<p>10. How long had you been smoking before you quit? (past perfect progressive)</p>
<p><em>I had been smoking for two years before I quit.</em></p>
<p>11. How long have you been waiting for the bus? (present perfect progressive)</p>
<p><em>I have been waiting for the bus for 20 minutes.</em></p>
<p>12. How long will you have been working before you retire? (future perfect progressive)</p>
<p><em>I will have been working for 30 years before I retire.</em></p>
<p>This is just a basic introduction to verb tenses. In the following weeks, we will cover the more difficult verb tenses in more detail.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins. And I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Adam Brock wrote this lesson for Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p>
<strong>aspect</strong> – <em>n</em>. the verb form that indicates completion, duration, or repetition of an action.</p>
<p><strong>distinction</strong> – <em>n</em>. a difference that you can see, hear, smell, feel, etc: a noticeable difference between things or people</p>
<p><strong>spontaneous</strong> – <em>adj</em>. done or said in a natural and often sudden way and without a lot of thought or planning</p>
<p><strong>consciously </strong>– <em>adv</em>. done after thinking about facts and reasons carefully</p>
<h3 class="wsw__h3">Reference</h3>
<table cellpadding="5" class="wsw__table"><tbody><tr><td style="width:156px">
<p>VERB TENSES</p>
</td><td style="width:156px">
<p>past</p>
</td><td style="width:156px">
<p>present</p>
</td><td style="width:156px">
<p>future</p>
</td></tr><tr><td style="width:156px">
<p>Simple</p>
</td><td style="width:156px">
<p>It snowed yesterday.</p>
<p><strong>Simple past verb</strong></p>
</td><td style="width:156px">
<p>It snows every winter.</p>
<p><strong>Simple present verb</strong></p>
</td><td style="width:156px">
<p>It is going to snow tonight.</p>
<p>It will snow this winter.</p>
<p><strong>Will / be going to + simple present</strong></p>
</td></tr><tr><td style="width:156px">
<p>Progressive</p>
</td><td style="width:156px">
<p>It was snowing when I drove to work.</p>
<p><strong>Was/were + -ing verb</strong></p>
</td><td style="width:156px">
<p>It is snowing.</p>
<p><strong>Am/is/are+-ing verb</strong></p>
</td><td style="width:156px">
<p>It will be snowing by the time I get home.</p>
<p><strong>Will be + -ing verb</strong></p>
</td></tr><tr><td style="width:156px">
<p>Perfect</p>
</td><td style="width:156px">
<p>It had already snowed before I left.</p>
<p><strong>Had + past participle verb</strong></p>
</td><td style="width:156px">
<p>I have driven in snow many times.</p>
<p><strong>Have/has + past participle verb</strong></p>
</td><td style="width:156px">
<p>It will have snowed 6 inches by the end of the day.</p>
<p><strong>Will have + past participle verb</strong></p>
</td></tr><tr><td style="width:156px">
<p>Perfect progressive</p>
</td><td style="width:156px">
<p>It had been snowing for two days before it stopped.</p>
<p><strong>Had been + -ing verb + for/since</strong></p>
</td><td style="width:156px">
<p>It has been snowing all month long.</p>
<p><strong>Has/have + -ing verb + for/since</strong></p>
</td><td style="width:156px">
<p>It will have been snowing for three days by the time it stops.</p>
<p><strong>Will have been + -ing verb + for/since</strong></p>
</td></tr></tbody></table>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Australia Plans Social Media Ban for Children under 16 (2024/11/14)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/australia-plans-social-media-ban-for-children-under-16.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">13 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The Australian government recently announced plans to ban the use of social media by children under the age of 16.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Anthony Albanese said, “Social media is doing harm to our kids.” He added that now is the time for the government to intervene.</p>
<p>The country's Parliament will introduce a new bill during the final two weeks of its meeting starting on November 18. The bill will set an age limit of 16 for children to use social media and make the services responsible for enforcement.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - In this Sept. 28, 2020 file photo, The TikTok app logo appears in Tokyo. (AP Photo/Kiichiro Sato, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/B0E5B92F-5EA1-4085-9748-D2BF2AEB1CE7_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - In this Sept. 28, 2020 file photo, The TikTok app logo appears in Tokyo. (AP Photo/Kiichiro Sato, File)</span></div>
<p>Albanese told reporters that the age limit would take effect 12 months after the bill is passed. And social media services, including X, TikTok, Instagram and Facebook, would need to use the year to work out how to put age controls in place.</p>
<p>“I've spoken to thousands of parents, grandparents, aunties and uncles. They, like me, are worried sick about the safety of our kids online,” Albanese said.</p>
<p>The proposal comes at a time when governments around the world are considering ways to control how young people use smartphones and social media.</p>
<p>Under the Australian proposal, social media companies would face <strong>penalties</strong> for violating the age limit. However, under-age children and their parents would not face penalties.</p>
<p>Antigone Davis is the head of safety at Meta, which owns Facebook and Instagram. Davis said the company would respect any age limits the government wants to put in place. She added that officials need to discuss the ways social media can make the age limit happen. She suggested that stronger tools in app stores and computer systems for parents could be a “simple and effective solution.”</p>
<p>X did not immediately answer a request from The Associated Press (AP) for comment. TikTok said it would not offer a comment to the AP.</p>
<p><strong>Some groups oppose the age limit</strong></p>
<p>More than 140 experts in fields related to technology and children signed an open letter to Albanese last month opposing a social media age limit. The letter said a ban would not be an effective way to deal with the risks of social media use.</p>
<p>Sunita Bose is a director at the Digital Industry Group in Australia. Bose said in a statement, “Rather than blocking <strong>access</strong> through bans, we need to take a balanced approach to create age-<strong>appropriate</strong> spaces, build digital <strong>literacy</strong> and protect young people from online harm.”</p>
<p>Jackie Hallan is a director at the youth mental health service ReachOut. She also opposed the ban. She noted that 73 percent of young people across Australia seeking mental health support get it through social media. She added that young people are likely to find ways to use social media even with a ban in place.</p>
<p>Child psychologist Philip Tam said it would have been easier to enforce the ban for children under the age of 12 or 13. Tam said, “My real fear honestly is that the problem of social media will simply be driven underground.”</p>
<p>Prime Minister Albanese said there would be rules to permit social media use in some situations, such as a need to connect with educational services.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, the government began testing age-restriction technologies among a group of users. Officials will use the test results to guide what reasonable steps social media services can take.</p>
<p>Lawmaker Paul Fletcher said the services already have the technology to enforce such an age ban. He added that if the law for controlling social media use is well written, Australia can get the results it wants.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins. And I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Rod McGuirk wrote this story for The Associated Press. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>penalty </strong><em>–n. </em>a punishment for a violation of a rule or law</p>
<p><strong>access </strong><em>–n. </em>the ability to get to persons, places, or things you want</p>
<p><strong>appropriate </strong><em>–n.</em> correct or suitable in relation to a person or situation.</p>
<p><strong>literacy </strong><em>–n. </em>the ability to read and write; having knowledge of a particular subject</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers: Huge Drop in African Elephants (2024/11/14)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/researchers-huge-drop-in-african-elephants.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/><span class="datetime">13 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>African elephants are Earth's largest land animals. They are very intelligent and highly social. A recent study also says that numbers of African elephants sharply decreased over about fifty years.</p>
<p>The researchers described their work as the most <strong>comprehensive</strong> study of the two African elephant <strong>species</strong> - the savanna elephant and forest elephant. The study used data gathered at 475 areas in 37 countries from 1964 through 2016.</p>
<p>It found that savanna elephant populations fell by about 70 percent on average and forest elephant populations dropped by about 90 percent on average. The researchers mainly blame the <strong>decline</strong> on illegal hunting and the loss of the animals' natural environment.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Elephants walk at the Amboseli National Park in Kajiado County, Kenya, April 4, 2024. (REUTERS/Monicah Mwangi/File Photo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/c1e04c39-fe8b-463d-b99d-2c219e20f812_cx7_cy7_cw88_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Elephants walk at the Amboseli National Park in Kajiado County, Kenya, April 4, 2024. (REUTERS/Monicah Mwangi/File Photo)</span></div>
<p>However, the report also says populations of each species increased in other places because of wildlife protection programs.</p>
<p>"A lot of the lost populations won't come back, and many low-density populations face continued pressures. We likely will lose more populations going forward,” said George Wittemyer. He is a Colorado State University professor who works with the conservation group Save the Elephants. Wittemyer helped lead the study, published in the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.2403816121" target="_blank"><em>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</em></a><em>.</em></p>
<p>Illegal hunting of animals is also called poaching. Elephant poachers usually kill the animals in order to remove their tusks. These prized objects are then sold on illegal markets, driven mostly by demand in China and other parts of Asia.</p>
<p>The research says agricultural expansion is mainly responsible for the loss of elephant habitat, meaning the natural areas where the animal lives.</p>
<p>Poaching has mostly affected forest elephants. Its population is estimated to be about one-third that of savanna elephants. Poaching has been especially damaged populations in northern and eastern Africa, such as Mali, Chad and Nigeria. But, in southern Africa, elephant populations rose at 42 percent of the studied areas.</p>
<p>"We have seen real success in a number of places across Africa, but particularly in southern Africa, with strong growth in populations in Botswana, Zimbabwe and Namibia,” Wittemyer said. He credited conservation efforts by governments and independent organizations for the growth.</p>
<p>The study did not provide a continent-wide population count. It says the different methods used for counting over different periods made it impossible to keep a unified count of the African elephants. Instead, it estimates population<strong> trends</strong> in each of the studied areas.</p>
<p>A separate report from conservationists places the population of African elephants at between 415,000 and 540,000 as of 2016, the last year of the study period. It remains the most recent comprehensive continent-wide estimate.</p>
<p>Colorado State's Wittemyer said, "While the trends are not good, it is important to recognize the successes we have had and continue to have. Learning how and where we can be successful in conserving elephants is as important as recognizing the severity of the decline they have experienced."</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Will Dunham reported this story for Reuters. Hai Do adapted the story for Learning English.</em></p>
<p>____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>comprehensive </strong>- adj. including many, most or all</p>
<p><strong>species </strong>- n. a group of animals or plants that are similar</p>
<p><strong>decline</strong> - n. the change to a lower number</p>
<p><strong>trend</strong> - n. the general direction of change</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Pistachios Becoming Major Crop in California (2024/11/14)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/pistachios-becoming-major-crop-in-california.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">13 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In a large plant in the heart of California's farmland, millions of pistachios are inspected, prepared and shipped off around the world.</p>
<p>Pistachios, a kind of nut, have been around for over 3,000 years. First planted in central Asia, pistachios arrived in California in the 1850s along with thousands of people during the Gold Rush.</p>
<p>Since pistachios require little water, farmers have been using more land for the crops in California. Pistachios brought in nearly $3 billion last year in the state. And, in the past ten years, the United States has gone beyond Iran to become the world's top exporter of the nut.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Pistachios are hand sorted at the Wonderful Pistachios &amp; Almonds processing plant in Lost Hills, Calif., on Friday, Oct. 25, 2024. (AP Photo/Damian Dovarganes)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/35d5bacc-dd8c-4558-a129-1c4b46209d72_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Pistachios are hand sorted at the Wonderful Pistachios &amp; Almonds processing plant in Lost Hills, Calif., on Friday, Oct. 25, 2024. (AP Photo/Damian Dovarganes)</span></div>
<p>“There has been an explosion over the last 10 or 15 years of plantings, and those trees are coming online,” said Zachary Fraser. He is president and chief executive of American Pistachio Growers, an organization that represents more than 800 farmers in the southwestern U.S. “You are starting to see the fruit of people's vision from 40 years ago.”</p>
<p>California agricultural data shows that the state grows more than a third of vegetables and three-fourths of fruits and nuts in the U.S.</p>
<p>Pistachios have increased over the past ten years to become California's sixth-biggest agricultural product. The nuts have increased in value ahead of longtime crops such as strawberries and tomatoes, the data shows.</p>
<p>Much of the pistachio crop is headed to China, where it is a popular treat during Lunar New Year. But industry experts said Americans are also eating more pistachios.</p>
<p>The nuts were rarely seen in food stores a generation ago and today are found almost everywhere.</p>
<p>Pistachios are sold with or without shells. Their flavors range from salt and pepper to honey-roasted.</p>
<p>The Wonderful Co., a $6 billion agricultural company, is the biggest name in pistachios. The company has grown pistachios since the 1980s. But it increased production in 2015 after developing a <strong>rootstock </strong>that produces as much as 40 percent more nuts with the same soil and water, said Rob Yraceburu, president of Wonderful Orchards.</p>
<p>Now, Wonderful grows between 15 percent and 20 percent of the U.S. pistachio crop, he said.</p>
<p>“There is an increasingly growing demand in pistachios,” Yraceburu said. “The world wants more.”</p>
<p><strong>Pistachios weather dry times better </strong></p>
<p>Pistachios are set to weather California's dry times better than the state's even bigger nut crop, almonds.</p>
<p>Almonds produced nearly $4 billion in the state last year, industry experts said.</p>
<p>Pistachio orchards can survive with minimal water during<strong> drought</strong>, unlike almonds and other more sensitive crops. The trees also use wind instead of bees for <strong>pollination</strong> and can produce nuts for many years longer, Yraceburu said.</p>
<p>Many California farmers who grow pistachios and almonds are using lessons learned from almond farming. Almond production, which is much bigger than pistachio, also increased quickly in California. But prices fell amid a large amount of post-pandemic supply. At the same time, farmers faced a time of too little water and rising input costs.</p>
<p>As a result, some farmers did not replant aging orchards when it came time to take them out.</p>
<p>Pistachio growers say they hope to avoid a similar outcome and are working to keep demand for the nut ahead of supply. For example, American Pistachio Growers recently signed a deal with a top <strong>cricket</strong> player in India hoping to help promote pistachios there, Fraser said.</p>
<p>The rise of pistachios is part of California farmers' move into perennial crops, commanding higher returns than products such as cotton. Perennial crops, which are not replanted every year, cannot just be changed out during dry years. As a result, they can be difficult during long periods with too little water, said Brad Franklin of the Public Policy Institute of California.</p>
<p>But pistachios have <strong>benefits</strong> that other perennial crops do not have. They can go longer without water and grow in salty soils. That may make them appealing to California farmers who are facing limits on how much groundwater they can use under a new state law, he said.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Amy Taxin reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>drought</strong><em> – n.</em> a period of dryness (especially one that causes extensive damage to crops)</p>
<p><strong>pollination</strong> <em>– n.</em> the act of giving (a plant) pollen from another plant of the same kind so that seeds will be produced</p>
<p><strong>rootstock</strong> <em>– n.</em> an underground part of a plant</p>
<p><strong>cricket </strong><em>– n.</em> a game played on a large field by two teams of 11 players. The players try to score runs by hitting a small ball and then running between sets of wooden sticks</p>
<p><strong>benefit</strong> <em>– n.</em> a good or helpful result or effect</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Webb Telescope Shows a Black Hole Breaking a Theoretical Limit (2024/11/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/webb-telescope-shows-a-black-hole-breaking-a-theoretical-limit.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Researchers have observed a large black hole that gained mass at a rate much faster than scientists had thought possible.</p>
<p>New observations from the Webb telescope involve the largest kind of black hole, a <strong>supermassive </strong>black hole. It is called LID-568. Scientists say it existed when the universe was about 11 percent of its current age.</p>
<p><strong>Background of a black hole </strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="An artist's illustration shows a rapidly feeding black hole that is emitting powerful gas outflows. (NOIRLab/NSF/AURA/J. da Silva/M. Zamani/Handout via REUTERS)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/74d24335-d04e-469f-b310-1771860d797a_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">An artist's illustration shows a rapidly feeding black hole that is emitting powerful gas outflows. (NOIRLab/NSF/AURA/J. da Silva/M. Zamani/Handout via REUTERS)</span></div>
<p>Black holes are extremely dense objects with gravity so strong that not even light can escape. With their powerful gravitational pull, they grow in mass by taking in material such as gas, dust and stars that are nearby.</p>
<p>A supermassive black hole about four million times the mass of the sun, called Sagittarius A*, is at the center of our Milky Way galaxy. Supermassive black holes are believed to be at the center of most galaxies.</p>
<p>Since NASA's James Webb Space Telescope started operating in 2022, researchers have been surprised to find supermassive black holes in the early universe. Researchers had believed that it takes a longer amount of time to gather such huge amounts of mass.</p>
<p>New observations of one early black hole give information about how this growth took place.</p>
<p>"The existence of supermassive black holes in the early universe <strong>challenges</strong> our current models of black hole formation and growth," said Hyewon Suh of the International Gemini Observatory in Hawaii and the U.S. National Science Foundation's NOIRLab. Suh was the lead writer of the study detailing the findings in the scientific publication Nature Astronomy.</p>
<p>The supermassive black hole LID-568 existed about 1.5 billion years after the Big Bang. The Big Bang, the event that started the universe, took place around 13.8 billion years ago.</p>
<p>LID-568 has a mass 10 million times greater than the sun, or two- and one-half times the mass of Sagittarius A*. The researchers do not yet know the mass of its home galaxy.</p>
<p>The Webb telescope showed LID-568 gaining mass at a rate faster than scientists had thought possible. LID-568 appeared to be <strong>consuming</strong> <strong>infalling </strong>material - known as<strong> accretion</strong> - at more than 40 times the previously believed maximum for such activity.</p>
<p>This maximum is known as the Eddington limit.</p>
<p><strong>Exceeding the Eddington Limit </strong></p>
<p>Early black holes are thought to have started in one of two ways. They could have begun after the explosive death of the universe's first generation of stars or through the collapse of large clouds of gas present in the early universe.</p>
<p>The discovery of LID-568 suggests that a lot of mass growth can take place during one time, or episode, of rapid accretion, Suh suggested.</p>
<p>A good sign of a growing supermassive black hole is <strong>emission</strong> of X-rays, high-energy electromagnetic radiation with very short wavelengths. Material moving around a supermassive black hole is superheated and glows strongly in X-ray wavelengths before disappearing in the black hole.</p>
<p>The researchers first spotted LID-568 using NASA's Chandra X-ray Observatory. They then studied it more closely with the Webb space telescope.</p>
<p>The Webb observations suggest the existence of a faster way for black holes to take in material.</p>
<p>Suh described LID-568 as “remarkable.” She added, "We don't know yet how LID-568 is able to exceed the Eddington limit. To investigate further, we need more data, so we are planning to <strong>conduct</strong> follow-up observations with Webb."</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Will Dunham reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>supermassive</strong><em> – adj</em> (describes black hole) the largest kind of black hole</p>
<p><strong>challenge</strong><em> – v.</em> to dispute or question something</p>
<p><strong>consume</strong><em> –v.</em> to take in, use up or eat</p>
<p><strong>infalling </strong><em>– adj.</em> moving under the influence of gravity toward an object (such as a black hole)</p>
<p><strong>accretion </strong><em>– n.</em> the process of growth or enlargement by a gradual buildup</p>
<p><strong>emission</strong> <em>–n.</em> the process of releasing or sending out radiation</p>
<p><strong>conduct</strong><em> –v.</em> to carry out</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Europe Scientists Predict Another World Heat Record (2024/11/13)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/europe-scientists-predict-another-world-heat-record.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">12 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Europe's climate agency says this year is likely to break 2023's record for the hottest year ever.</p>
<p>Researchers at the Copernicus agency also predicted 2024 will be the first year to be more than 1.5 degrees Celsius hotter than what is called the pre-industrial period. That period, from 1850 to 1900, is when humans began the widespread burning of <strong>fossil fuels</strong>.</p>
<p>The new data was released ahead of the United Nations COP29 climate meeting taking place this week in Azerbaijan. At that meeting, international representatives are expected to agree to call for more spending to fight the worldwide effects of climate change.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Tourists with an umbrella walk in front of the Parthenon at the ancient Acropolis in central Athens, June 12, 2024. (AP Photo/Petros Giannakouris, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4d01faee-a971-4f15-b0e8-2515bb9d3425_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Tourists with an umbrella walk in front of the Parthenon at the ancient Acropolis in central Athens, June 12, 2024. (AP Photo/Petros Giannakouris, File)</span></div>
<p>The European climate agency said that from January to October, the average world temperature rose so much that 2024 would almost surely be the world's hottest year on record.</p>
<p>Copernicus said its records date back to 1940 and are compared with world temperature records going back to 1850.</p>
<p>The director of Copernicus, Carlo Buontempo, told Reuters news agency the main cause of this year's record is climate change. "The climate is warming, generally. It's warming in all <strong>continents</strong>, in all ocean <strong>basins</strong>. So we are bound to see those records being broken," Buontempo said.</p>
<p>Buontempo also said the data clearly show such warming would not be happening without the continued release of carbon <strong>emissions</strong> into the atmosphere. Scientists say carbon dioxide is released by the burning of coal, oil and gas.</p>
<p>Buontempo noted the importance of worldwide observations and data collection to support the group's findings and predictions. Copernicus gathers data from billions of measurements from satellites, ships, aircraft and weather stations around the world.</p>
<p>Sonia Seneviratne is a climate scientist at public research university ETH Zurich in Switzerland. She told Reuters she was not surprised by the new prediction.</p>
<p>Seneviratne urged delegates at COP29 to agree to stronger action to limit the use of carbon-producing fossil fuels. "The limits that were set in the Paris agreement are starting to <strong>crumble</strong> given the too-slow pace of climate action across the world," she said.</p>
<p>Many countries agreed to try to prevent the average temperature of the atmosphere from increasing by more than 1.5 degrees Celsius over a period of years by signing the 2015 Paris Agreement. Officials from Copernicus have said that the 1.5-degree Celsius limit could be passed around 2030. "It's basically <strong>around the corner</strong> now," Buontempo said.</p>
<p>Climate scientists say each increase in temperature can fuel extreme weather. Recent examples of weather-related events include flooding that killed hundreds of people in Spain and wildfires in Peru. In Bangladesh, flooding destroyed more than 1 million tons of rice, driving food prices higher.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press and Reuters reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>fossil fuels </strong><em>– n. </em>fuels such as coal, oil, or natural gas that are formed in the Earth from dead plants or animals</p>
<p><strong>continent </strong><em>–n.</em> one of a few very large landmasses on the Earth, such as Eurasia and Africa</p>
<p><strong>basin </strong><em>– n.</em> a low area of land from which water flows into a river</p>
<p><strong>emission </strong><em>– n. </em>the act of sending something out such as a gas, heat, or light</p>
<p><strong>crumble </strong><em>– v.</em> to collapse or break down</p>
<p><strong>around the corner </strong><em>– phr. </em>about to happen soon</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Japan Launches World’s First Wooden Satellite (2024/11/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/japan-launches-world-s-first-wooden-satellite.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>An experimental satellite made out of wood has been launched into space. Japanese developers of the device say it is the first time a wooden satellite has ever been sent to space.</p>
<p>The small satellite, called LignoSat, launched aboard an uncrewed Cargo Dragon spacecraft to the International Space Station (ISS). The satellite will later be released into orbit about 400 kilometers above Earth.</p>
<p>The satellite was built in the form of a box, with each side measuring about 10 centimeters. It was developed jointly by researchers at Kyoto University and Japanese homebuilder Sumitomo Forestry.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Takao Doi, a former Japanese astronaut and professor at Kyoto University, holds an engineering model of LignoSat during an interview with Reuters at his laboratory at Kyoto University in Kyoto, Japan, October 25, 2024. (REUTERS/Irene Wang)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/cbe6ecbd-f0c6-42b5-8e94-365c8c030199_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Takao Doi, a former Japanese astronaut and professor at Kyoto University, holds an engineering model of LignoSat during an interview with Reuters at his laboratory at Kyoto University in Kyoto, Japan, October 25, 2024. (REUTERS/Irene Wang)</span></div>
<p>A spokeswoman for Sumitomo Forestry told the French news agency AFP that the launch of the satellite was “successful.” She said the plan calls for the device to be released into orbit in about a month, when its strength and effectiveness will be tested.</p>
<p>While made mostly of wood, LignoSat contains electronic elements that will control its movements and collect data on its operation. Once deployed, the satellite is expected to remain in orbit for about six months.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p>The main goal of the experimental satellite is to see whether wood material can be used to build additional satellites or other space equipment. Wood is considered more environmental friendly. This is because it can just burn up when reentering Earth's atmosphere. Satellites and other materials made of metal can release polluting particles into the air and oceans upon reentry.</p>
<p>International officials have already identified space<strong> junk</strong> as a growing problem. This includes things like dead satellites, lost pieces of equipment or small pieces of paint. Such objects can present threats to spacecraft and satellites operating in space.</p>
<p>Takao Doi is an astronaut who has flown on past space missions and studies human space activities at Kyoto University. He told Reuters he thinks wood can greatly improve future stays for long-term space travelers. "With <strong>timber</strong>, a material we can produce by ourselves, we will be able to build houses, live and work in space forever," Doi said.</p>
<p>He added that the experiment is designed to demonstrate the abilities of wood to serve as a suitable material for developing future space equipment.</p>
<p>"Early 1900s airplanes were made of wood," said Kyoto University forest science professor Koji Murata. "A wooden satellite should be <strong>feasible</strong>, too." Murata noted that wood can last longer in space than on Earth because water or oxygen cannot burn or destroy it.</p>
<p>Doi said it is possible metal satellites could be banned in the future. "If we can prove our first wooden satellite works, we want to <strong>pitch</strong> it to Elon Musk's SpaceX."</p>
<p>The team said a 10-month experiment aboard the ISS found that honoki – a native tree in Japan and traditionally used to make <strong>sword</strong> covers – is well-suited for spacecraft. LignoSat is made of honoki as part of a traditional Japanese <strong>crafting </strong>method that does not use screws or glue.</p>
<p>Kenji Kariya is a leader at Sumitomo Forestry Tsukuba Research Institute. He told Reuters the wooden satellite will also test the ability of the material to reduce the effects of space radiation on <strong>semiconductors</strong>.</p>
<p>"It may seem <strong>outdated</strong>, but wood is actually <strong>cutting-edge</strong> technology as civilization heads to the moon and Mars." Kariya noted that expanding into space technologies could support the timber industry.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Reuters and Agence France-Press reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>junk </strong><em>– n. </em>material that is no longer of use or working</p>
<p><strong>timber </strong><em>– n.</em> wood used to construct buildings</p>
<p><strong>feasible </strong><em>– adj. </em>possible to do</p>
<p><strong>pitch </strong><em>– v.</em> try to persuade someone to do something</p>
<p><strong>sword </strong><em>– adj. </em>a weapon with a long, metal blade and a handle, that was especially used in the past</p>
<p><strong>crafting </strong><em>– n.</em> an activity in which you make something using a log of skill, especially with your hands</p>
<p><strong>semiconductor </strong><em>– n. a material, such as silicon, that permits electricity to move through it more easily when its temperature increases</em></p>
<p><strong>outdated </strong><em>– adj.</em> not modern enough</p>
<p><strong>cutting-edge </strong><em>– adj. </em>very modern, with all the newest developments</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How to Keep from Feeling Down in the Winter (2024/11/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/how-to-keep-from-feeling-down-in-the-winter.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>As fall and winter come to some parts of the world, daylight hours grow shorter. This lack of light can cause seasonal depression.</p>
<p>“It (is) a feeling of <strong>panic</strong>, fear, <strong>anxiety</strong> and <strong>dread</strong> all in one,” said Germaine Pataki. The 63-year-old woman living in Saskatoon, Saskatchewan, Canada, is among the millions of people estimated to have seasonal affective disorder, or SAD.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A lone walker moves around Washington Park as a winter storm packing wet, heavy snow moves through the area on Feb. 3, 2024, in Denver. (AP Photo/David Zalubowski)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4f86da14-3c48-4005-946e-9969621ddab1_cx0_cy4_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A lone walker moves around Washington Park as a winter storm packing wet, heavy snow moves through the area on Feb. 3, 2024, in Denver. (AP Photo/David Zalubowski)</span></div>
<p>To deal with her condition, Pataki uses yoga, walking, and an antidepressant medication. She is also part of a Facebook group for people with SAD and helps others deal with the condition. Pataki said, “This gives me purpose.”</p>
<p>People with SAD usually have depression that begins in the fall and eases in the spring or summer. Changing the clocks back to standard time, which happens in autumn in the United States, can also cause SAD to start.</p>
<p>Medical experts say there is a milder form, called subsyndromal SAD. There is also summer seasonal depression but less is known about that.</p>
<p>In 1984, a team led by Dr. Norman Rosenthal, then a researcher at the National Institutes of Health, first described SAD. He invented the term.</p>
<p><strong>What causes seasonal affective disorder?</strong></p>
<p>Scientists are still learning the causes of seasonal affective disorder. They have found that specialized cells in our eyes turn the blue wavelength of the light into neural, or brain signals. These signals affect <strong>mood</strong> and wakefulness, or <strong>alertness</strong>.</p>
<p>Sunlight has a lot of blue light. So, when the cells sense this blue light, the alertness centers of our brains turn on. We feel more alert and possibly even happier.</p>
<p>Kathryn Roecklein is a researcher at the University of Pittsburgh. She tested people with and without SAD to see how their eyes reacted to blue light. As a group, people with SAD were less sensitive to blue light than others, especially during winter months. That suggests a cause for wintertime depression.</p>
<p>“In the winter, when the light levels drop, that, combined with a lower sensitivity, might be too low for healthy <strong>functioning</strong>, leading to depression,” Roecklein said.</p>
<p>Miriam Cherry is 50 years old and lives in New York state. She spent the summer planning how she would deal with her winter depression. “It's like clockwork,” Cherry said. “The sunlight is low. The day ends at 4:45, and suddenly my mood is <strong>horrible</strong>.”</p>
<p><strong>Light therapy can help</strong></p>
<p>Many people with SAD respond to light <strong>therapy</strong>, said Dr. Paul Desan of Yale University's Winter Depression Research Clinic. The therapy devices give off light about 20 times brighter than regular indoor light.</p>
<p>“The first thing to try is light,” Desan said. “When we get patients on <strong>exposure </strong>to bright light for a half an hour or so every morning, the majority of patients get <strong>dramatically</strong> better. We don't even need medications.”</p>
<p>There is research that supports the idea that using a light that has a brightness of about 10,000 lux can be helpful. Lux is a measurement of brightness.</p>
<p>The research suggests that a person use it for 30 minutes every morning. Desan said this can help not only people with SAD but also those with less-severe, low moods in winter.</p>
<p><strong>What else might work?</strong></p>
<p>Experts suggest other forms of treatment. Doctors often suggest antidepressant medications as a first-line treatment for SAD. They also suggest going to bed and waking up at about the same time each day. Also, exercise such as walking outside, even on cloudy days, can help.</p>
<p>Kelly Rohan is a researcher at the University of Vermont. Rohan said another treatment is talk therapy. Also called cognitive behavioral therapy, or CBT, Rohan said it has been shown in studies to have more long-lasting effects. CBT involves working with a therapist to identify and change unhelpful thoughts.</p>
<p>“A very common thought that people have is ‘I hate winter,'” Rohan said. She suggests that people instead say, “I <strong>prefer</strong> summer to winter.”</p>
<p>Working with a therapist can help people take small steps toward having fun again, Rohan said. Try planning undemanding but enjoyable activities to break out of a bad mood. Rohan said simply meeting a friend for coffee can help.</p>
<p>People with SAD have half the year to create helpful methods. Some have found things that work for them -- although they might not be the subject of scientific research.</p>
<p>For example, in Folsom, California, Elizabeth Wescott says she believes a kind of water therapy helps her. The 69-year-old uses water therapy used in sports medicine. When she showers, she changes between hot and cold water. She also uses a light box and takes an antidepressant. “I'm always looking for new tools,” Wescott said.</p>
<p>In New York, Miriam Cherry grows the earliest <strong>blooming</strong> flowers. They bloom as early as February.</p>
<p>“That's going to be a sign to me that this isn't going to last forever,” Cherry said. “It will get better, and spring is on the way.”</p>
<p>And that's the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p>And I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Carla Johnson reported this story for the Associated Press. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>__________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>panic </strong><em>–n. </em>a sudden overpowering fright</p>
<p><strong>anxiety </strong><em>–n.</em> a state of extreme nervousness and worry</p>
<p><strong>dread </strong><em>–n.</em> fear of something that might happen</p>
<p><strong>mood </strong><em>–n.</em> the way a person feels; a person's emotional state</p>
<p><strong>alertness </strong><em>–n.</em> the ability to sense things happening around you</p>
<p><strong>horrible </strong><em>–adj.</em> terrible or causing fear</p>
<p><strong>therapy </strong><em>–n. </em>treatment of an abnormal state of the mind or body</p>
<p><strong>exposure </strong><em>–n.</em> the condition of sensing something or coming into contact with somethings</p>
<p><strong>dramatically </strong><em>–adv.</em> a lot or to a notable degree</p>
<p><strong>prefer </strong><em>–v. </em>to like better or best</p>
<p><strong>bloom </strong><em>–v. </em>to produce flowers</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Farmers Aim to Save Mexico City’s Island Gardens (2024/11/12)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/farmers-aim-to-save-mexico-city-s-island-gardens.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">11 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Several large lakes once surrounded Mexico City. Those lakes have disappeared over the years. But what is left of one of them is still important to local people who grow food.</p>
<p>Cassandra Gardu<i></i>241;o works in her family's chinampa. In Mexico, a chinampa is an island that was built up by the native Aztec people with fertile mud from the bottom of lakes that surrounded their capital.</p>
<p>One of the areas is called Xochimilco. The islands there are held together by a kind of willow tree planted around their edges. Narrow waterways connect them.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Small ancestral floating gardens are visible next to new soccer fields on the Xochimilco Lake, Mexico City, on Sunday, Oct. 20, 2024. (AP Photo/Felix Marquez)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e98ee2ee-4329-4be7-a4ae-caa857cbca6c_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Small ancestral floating gardens are visible next to new soccer fields on the Xochimilco Lake, Mexico City, on Sunday, Oct. 20, 2024. (AP Photo/Felix Marquez)
</span></div>
<p>Xochimilco has more than 1000 hectares of protected land owned by generations of local Chinamperos, as those who farm on the islands are known. Food grown on these islands has fed people for hundreds of years, but the chinampas are under threat from modern ways of life.</p>
<p>Growing food on the chinampas does not make much money. Many families are giving up the old ways to <strong>rent out</strong> or sell their land. They have found it easier and more profitable to use the land for soccer fields and <strong>tourism</strong>.</p>
<p>"People don't want to farm anymore, and people don't want to buy the products." said Gardu<i></i>241;o.</p>
<p>Some of those who stay, like Gardu<i></i>241;o, are working together to save and support the traditional use of the chinampas.</p>
<p>Gardu<i></i>241;o remembers seeing her grandparents' chinampas as a child. Even then, she saw how the chinampas were suffering under pressure from modern life. Some farmers had already given up.</p>
<p>Gardu<i></i>241;o bought land for her own chinampa in 2020. She grows several crops, including sunflowers, eggplant, and the Mexican marigold. She is a member of the growing collective called Chinampa Refuge. The National Autonomous University of Mexico started the collective.</p>
<p>With other farmers in the group, she has asked other Chinamperos to preserve their land. They follow old ways of growing. But they also are trying new <strong>commercial</strong> methods to compete with low-cost goods grown on big farms in Mexico.</p>
<p>Their products include a special <strong>tag</strong> — Etiqueta Chinampera — that tells buyers the produce came from a chinampa. The tag also might bring attention to the area's water quality or the chinampa's <strong>status</strong> as a biodiversity refuge.</p>
<p>"Change comes with educating the new generations," said Gardu<i></i>241;o. "Talking about the <strong>origins</strong> and efforts to <strong>conserve</strong> and why it's important to do it."</p>
<p>Luis Zambrano is a scientist at the National Autonomous University of Mexico who has worked in Xochimilco for many years. He said the fields can mostly support themselves. Fed and watered by the lake, they can produce three to five crops of vegetables a year without the need of chemicals or <strong>irrigation</strong>, he said.</p>
<p>Xochimilco's natural resources help the city in several ways. Many kinds of birds and fish live there. The system of waterways helps reduce the city's overall temperature, Zambrano said.</p>
<p>But now, on weekends, it is common to see more soccer players boating to islands than farmers <strong>tending</strong> their crops. Over the past two or three years, Zambrano said, there has been a “massive increase” in the number of soccer fields on the islands. There are also food stands and boat trips for visitors.</p>
<p>"If you do well (farming) you could earn $5,000 to $10,000 a year," Gardu<i></i>241;o said. "In the tourist area you could have that within a couple of weekends."</p>
<p>Zambrano said the soccer fields damage the environment “because the amount of chemicals that are used, the amount of pollution that is generated is very, very large."</p>
<p>Carlos Vasquez, director of the Natural Protected Areas under Mexico City's Environmental Department, said his group is working on ways to limit the damage by the soccer fields.</p>
<p>Sixty-three-year-old Juan <i></i>193;valos and his brother Salvador Gonzalez <i></i>193;valos, who is 55, have been working on chinampas all their lives. Salvador said they want to pass their farming methods on to their grandchildren.</p>
<p>"That's something we need to work on as grandparents," he said. "That they <strong>integrate</strong> themselves with a taste for this earth."</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Mariana Martínez Barba and Julián Trejo Bax reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>rent out </strong>–v. (phrasal) to offer property for others to use in exchange for regular payments</p>
<p><strong>tourism </strong>–n. the industry of providing goods and services for visitors from another place</p>
<p><strong>commercial </strong>–adj. related to business or activities aimed at making a profit</p>
<p><strong>tag </strong>–n. a small sign that has information about the product that it is attached to on it</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Saturn’s Moon Titan Has Huge Layer of Methane-filled Ice (2024/11/11)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/study-saturn-s-moon-titan-has-huge-layer-of-methane-filled-ice.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">10 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>New research suggests Saturn's moon Titan has a thick ice cover that could be warming lower areas and supporting molecular growth.</p>
<p>Scientists at the University of Hawaii carried out the new <a class="wsw__a" href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/PSJ/ad7018" target="_blank">study</a>. It appears in <em>The Planetary Science Journal</em>. The findings add to existing evidence that Titan may hold the right mix of materials to support possible life.</p>
<p>No life forms have been confirmed on Titan, a cold, icy world. But past studies suggest the moon now has a large <strong>layer</strong> of ice that once supported widely flowing water on the surface. Titan is also thought to contain a dense atmosphere rich in nitrogen and methane, both of which are found in Earth's own atmosphere.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Titan, Saturn's largest moon appears before the planet as it undergoes seasonal changes in this natural color view from NASA's Cassini spacecraft in this handout released by NASA August 29, 2012. (REUTERS/ NASA/JPL-Caltech/SSI)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1fa044d7-2390-4162-986d-1e2c2d539605_cx0_cy25_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Titan, Saturn's largest moon appears before the planet as it undergoes seasonal changes in this natural color view from NASA's Cassini spacecraft in this handout released by NASA August 29, 2012. (REUTERS/ NASA/JPL-Caltech/SSI)</span></div>
<p>NASA reports Saturn has a total of 146 moons orbiting it, more than any other planet. Titan, an ice giant, is the largest of them.</p>
<p>For more than 10 years, NASA's Cassini spacecraft studied Saturn “and its complex system of rings and moons,” the space agency <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/cassini/">said</a>. The new study used NASA data to closely examine surface details of Titan.</p>
<p>The researchers used computer modeling to examine different elements of Titan's surface. One of the main discoveries was that many <strong>craters</strong> examined on Titan's surface were not as deep as some other moons. The team reported that in some cases, craters were hundreds of meters shallower, or less deep, than scientists expected. In addition, only 90 craters were identified on the whole moon.</p>
<p>“This was very surprising because, based on other moons, we expect to see many more <strong>impact</strong> craters on the surface,” said University of Hawaii's Lauren Schurmeier, who led the study.</p>
<p>She said the research team had also expected to see much deeper craters. “We realized something <strong>unique</strong> to Titan must be making them become shallower and disappear relatively quickly,” she said.</p>
<p>Computer modeling carried out by the researchers showed how the surface might have changed to remove signs of major impact craters. The researchers said one of the most likely causes of such change was that the moon's icy surface is covered with a thick layer of solid water ice, with methane gas trapped inside.</p>
<p>The team said the data examinations suggest Titan has a methane-filled icy <strong>crust</strong> that is from five to 10 kilometers thick. The modeling operations run by the scientists produced images that looked similar to crater formations on Titan's surface.</p>
<p>Schurmeier said the methane crust, “warms Titan's interior” and can cause surprisingly fast changes to the surface structure. Schurmeier noted, for example, that crater shallowing on Titan is believed to be happening at a rate “that is close to that of fast-moving warm <strong>glaciers</strong> on Earth.”</p>
<p>The surface of Titan is estimated to be about minus 179 degrees Celsius. Because of this extreme cold, liquids on the moon's surface take the form of ice, with methane gas locked inside, the researchers said. This gas could help warm surface levels beneath, possibly permitting molecules to rise toward the surface.</p>
<p>Schurmeier said studying the thickness of Titan's icy crust is important because it might help explain how the moon's atmosphere began to develop. The measurements could also provide additional information on Titan's changing climate.</p>
<p>“Titan is a natural laboratory to study how the greenhouse gas methane warms and cycles through the atmosphere,” she said. The resulting information, she added, can provide important insights about such processes happening on Earth.</p>
<p>NASA's <a class="wsw__a" href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/cassini/about-the-mission/">Cassini</a> spacecraft ended it mission in 2017, when it crashed into Saturn's atmosphere. But the U.S. space agency has plans to send another explorer to Titan in 2028. That mission calls for a spacecraft called Dragonfly to travel to Titan to observe many different areas. The planned explorer, called a rotorcraft, operates similar to a helicopter.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from the University of Hawaii at Manoa, the University of Lisbon and NASA. </em></p>
<p><strong>_________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>layer </strong><em>– n. </em>an amount of something covering a surface</p>
<p><strong>crater </strong><em>– n.</em> a hole left in the ground by an object that hits it with a huge force</p>
<p><strong>impact </strong><em>– n. </em>the force or action of one object hitting another</p>
<p><strong>unique </strong><em>– adj.</em> different from everyone and everything else</p>
<p><strong>crust </strong><em>– n. </em>a hard, dry layer of the surface of something</p>
<p><strong>glacier </strong><em>– n.</em> a large mass of ice that moves very slowly, usually down a hill or valley</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What Is Veterans Day in the US? (2024/11/11)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/what-is-veterans-day-in-the-us.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By VOA</span><br/><span class="datetime">10 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>World War I officially ended with the signing of the Treaty of Versailles in France on June 28, 1919.</p>
<p>However, fighting had stopped seven months earlier with an armistice, or an agreement to stop fighting, between the Allied nations and Germany on the eleventh hour of the eleventh day of the eleventh month.</p>
<p>The date, November 11, is now remembered as Veterans Day, a holiday to thank and honor all who served in the United States military.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - U.S. Army veteran 2nd Lt. Allen Brandstater salutes during a Veterans Day observance in Los Angeles on Nov. 11, 2022. (AP Photo/Damian Dovarganes)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1f0d23e0-7a95-4d9b-90b4-0f1839da4858_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - U.S. Army veteran 2nd Lt. Allen Brandstater salutes during a Veterans Day observance in Los Angeles on Nov. 11, 2022. (AP Photo/Damian Dovarganes)</span></div>
<p>The celebration first started on November 11, 1919, as Armistice Day. At the time, U.S. President Woodrow Wilson said the day “will be filled with <strong>solemn</strong> pride in the heroism of those who died in the country's service and with <strong>gratitude</strong> for the victory...” The U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs <a class="wsw__a" href="https://department.va.gov/veterans-day/history-of-veterans-day/">says</a> there were plans to observe the day with parades, public meetings, and a brief suspension of business beginning at 11:00 a.m.</p>
<p>In 1926, the U.S. Congress officially recognized November 11, 1918, as the end of World War I. And in 1938, the body passed legislation to make the 11th of November in each year a legal holiday. Known as “Armistice Day,” it was a day set aside to honor veterans of World War I.</p>
<p>After American involvement in World War II and the Korean War, at the urging of veterans' organizations, Congress changed the law in 1954 to call it Veterans Day to honor American veterans of all wars.</p>
<p>The date for Veterans Day was changed in 1968 with the signing of the Uniform Holiday Act. With the law, Congress intended to create a three-day weekend for Americans by moving the holiday to a Monday in November. Many states and veterans' organizations did not agree with this decision. They continued to celebrate the holiday on November 11, leading to confusion. So, Congress returned the holiday to its <strong>original </strong>date.</p>
<p>Many Americans are confused about Veterans Day and Memorial Day, the other holiday honoring military service, which is observed on the last Monday in May.</p>
<p>The U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs says that both holidays “were established to recognize and honor the men and women who have worn the uniform of the United States Armed Forces.”</p>
<p>Memorial Day is set aside as a day for remembering and honoring those who died in the service of their country. For most Americans, it also marks the unofficial start of summer and a popular weekend for vacationing.</p>
<p>Veterans Day is largely <strong>intended</strong> to thank and honor all those who served honorably in the military, living or dead, and in wartime or peace.</p>
<p>To ensure that people remember Veterans Day, the U.S. Congress passed, and President Barack Obama signed the Veterans Day Moment of Silence Act in 2016. The law called on the people of the United States to observe a two-minute national moment of silence on Veterans Day at 2:11 p.m. Eastern Standard Time across all states and territories of the United States.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Hai Do wrote this report for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>solemn </strong><em>–adj.</em> done in a serious and respectful way</p>
<p><strong>gratitude</strong> <em>–n. </em>a feeling of thankfulness</p>
<p><strong>original <em>–</em></strong><em>adj.</em> what existed first before a following event</p>
<p><strong>intend</strong> <em>–v. </em>to mean to do something; to do something with the idea of having an identifiable effect</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Late Snow on Japan’s Mount Fuji Sets a Record (2024/11/11)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/late-snow-on-japan-s-mount-fuji-sets-a-record.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">10 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>A national <strong>symbol</strong> of Japan, the respected Mount Fuji usually has a <strong>cap</strong> of snow by early October. This year, weather experts said snowfall on the top of the mountain took place later than it has since records have been kept.</p>
<p>Last year, snow covered the top of the mountain on October 5. But this year, the first snowfall was on November 6, making this year's snowcap the latest to form since 1894 when records started.</p>
<p>The Kofu weather station declares the news every year. Officials at the Kofu observatory confirmed snow near the 3,776-meter top of the country's tallest volcano.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Peak of Mount Fuji showing snow as seen from Fujikawaguchiko, Yamanashi Prefecture, Japan. November 7, 2024. (Tom Bateman/REUTERS)
" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/bddb6ffd-9135-43a7-bdfa-5d1ccb228251_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Peak of Mount Fuji showing snow as seen from Fujikawaguchiko, Yamanashi Prefecture, Japan. November 7, 2024. (Tom Bateman/REUTERS)
</span></div>
<p>The office explained that the "first snowfall" on Mount Fuji is the point when the observatory <strong>staff</strong> can see that all or part of the mountain is covered with snow for the first time after summer.</p>
<p>Mamoru Matsumoto is an official of the Kofu observatory office. He said that Mount Fuji's first snowfall has been delayed in recent years although the reasons are still unclear.</p>
<p>"I feel <strong>relieved</strong> to finally see the snow," he added.</p>
<p>"The temperature at the Fuji summit has been high since October, so I could foresee quite a big delay in the snowfall, which was giving me an uneasy feeling."</p>
<p>Unusually warm weather prevented rainfall from turning to snow this October. The average temperature on the mountain's <strong>peak</strong> reached a record of 1.6 degrees Celsius compared to the October average of -2 degrees Celsius, official data showed.</p>
<p>Maria Gabriel, a visitor from Texas, came to Japan with plans to see the sacred mountain. She told Reuters, "It's beautiful with the snow, and that was kind of what our expectations were coming (to Japan)," she said, adding that the mountain's snowcapped image was famous worldwide.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Tom Bateman and Mariko Katsumura reported this story for Reuters. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>symbol </strong>– n. an action, object, event, or the like, that expresses or represents a particular idea or quality</p>
<p><strong>cap </strong>– <em>n</em>. a covering placed on the top of something</p>
<p><strong>staff </strong>– <em>n</em>. regular workers in an office</p>
<p><strong>relieved</strong> – <em>adj</em>. feeling relaxed and happy because something difficult or unpleasant has been stopped, avoided, or made easier</p>
<p><strong>peak </strong>– <em>n</em>. the high point of something tall, especially a mountain</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Britain Reports Four New Mpox Cases (2024/11/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/britain-reports-four-new-mpox-cases.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>British health officials say they have identified four cases of the new, highly infectious version of mpox that first appeared in the Democratic Republic of the Congo.</p>
<p>The announcement marks the first time the <strong>variant</strong> has caused a group of illnesses outside of Africa. Scientists said the risk to the public remains low.</p>
<p>Officials announced the first case of the new form of mpox in Britain last week. Officials said the person who was being treated at a London hospital had recently travelled to countries in Africa with ongoing outbreaks.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This colorized electron microscope image provided by the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases in 2024 shows Mpox virus particles, green, found within infected cultured cells, blue. (NIAID via AP, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/17f3e9f4-73a1-4444-a078-41b8bd8e53af_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This colorized electron microscope image provided by the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases in 2024 shows Mpox virus particles, green, found within infected cultured cells, blue. (NIAID via AP, File)</span></div>
<p>This week, the British Health Security Agency said it had now identified three additional cases. All of them lived in the same household as the first patient. The new cases are also being treated at a hospital in London.</p>
<p>Susan Hopkins is chief medical advisor of the British Health Security Agency. She said, “Mpox is very infectious in households with close contact and so it is not unexpected to see further cases within the same household."</p>
<p>The new variant of mpox was first reported earlier this year in the eastern part of the Democratic Republic of the Congo, or the DRC. Scientists believe it causes milder <strong>symptoms</strong> that are harder to notice. As a result, it might be easier to spread because people may not know they are infected. Its spread in the DRC and in other parts of Africa caused the World Health Organization to declare the outbreak a public health emergency of international concern in August.</p>
<p>Britain recorded more than 3,000 cases of another version of mpox during a 2022 outbreak that affected more than 100 countries.</p>
<p>The new variant of mpox has also caused outbreaks in Burundi, Kenya, Rwanda and Uganda. Single cases in travelers have also been reported in Sweden, India, Germany and Thailand.</p>
<p>To date, there have been about 43,000 suspect cases of mpox in Africa, including more than 1,000 deaths, mostly in the DRC.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, the WHO said it had given about 900,000 vaccine <strong>doses </strong>to nine African countries struggling with mpox epidemics.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>John Russell adapted this story from an Associated Press report. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>variant </strong><em>– n.</em> something that is different in some way from others of the same kind</p>
<p><strong>symptom</strong> <em>–n.</em> a sign that disease might be present</p>
<p><strong>dose<em> </em></strong><em>–n. </em>the amount of a medicine that is needed to cure or treat a health problem</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Have You Ever Felt the ‘Long Arm of the Law?’ (2024/11/10)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/have-you-ever-felt-the-long-arm-of-the-law.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">09 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Laws help to keep society running smoothly. They help to keep things in order.</p>
<p>So, when we talk about <u>law and order</u>, we are talking about how crime should be kept under control and how society should run.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A police car sits outside Ohio City Hall which received a bomb threat on Thursday morning, in Springfield, Ohio, U.S., September 12, 2024. (REUTERS/Julio-Cesar Chavez) " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/7ac41c48-13ee-4cc2-a2c6-746562c68856_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A police car sits outside Ohio City Hall which received a bomb threat on Thursday morning, in Springfield, Ohio, U.S., September 12, 2024. (REUTERS/Julio-Cesar Chavez) </span></div>
<p>The term <u>law and order</u> includes how police enforce laws and how the judicial system deals with criminals.</p>
<p><u>Law and order</u> also describes a situation where most people respect and obey laws. They want to feel safe and to have a sense of public order.</p>
<p>Sometimes people use the term to describe a political candidate. For example:</p>
<p><em>If a city has problems with crime, candidates for public office might run a <u>law and order</u> campaign. They promise to put policies in place that reduce crime.</em></p>
<p>Now, when we talk about catching criminals, we can use another expression: <u>the long arm of the law.</u> This describes the ability of police to find and catch people who commit crimes. It further describes the power of law enforcement and the legal system to punish criminals and carry out justice.</p>
<p>So, the <u>long arm of the law</u> is the far-reaching power of police and the legal system. For example:</p>
<p><em>Criminals who are <u>on the run</u> are unlikely to escape the long arm of the law forever. If they make one mistake, they might get caught.</em></p>
<p>Now, let's talk about non-criminals. Sometimes people might do things that they do not know are illegal. For example<strong>,</strong></p>
<p><em>A<strong> prank</strong> or <strong>practical joke</strong> played on a friend might seem harmless. But <u>in the eyes of the law,</u> it might actually be illegal.</em></p>
<p>When we say <u>in the eyes of the law</u>, we mean what a law actually says and how people who enforce the law understand it.</p>
<p>That leads us to another expression: <strong><u>ignorance</u></strong><u> of the law is no excuse</u>. If we are ignorant of something, we don't know about it. However, simply not knowing if an action is illegal doesn't matter in the eyes of the law.</p>
<p>The <u>long arm of the law</u> will still reach out and <strong>uphold</strong> the law. Then we might find ourselves <u>on the wrong side of the law</u>. And that's a bad place to be. Being <u>on the wrong side of the law</u> means we have broken a law, or worse, laws.</p>
<p>So, if we want to be <strong>upstanding</strong>, law-<strong>abiding </strong>citizens and avoid the <u>long arm of the law,</u> we should stay on the <u>right side of the law!</u></p>
<p>And that's the end of this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>.</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>___________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>prank </strong><em>–n.</em> a trick or joke that is played on a person</p>
<p><strong>practical joke </strong><em>–n.</em> a trick or joke meant to cause the subject embarrassment or public discomfort</p>
<p><strong>ignorance </strong><em>–n. </em>lack of knowledge, education, or awareness</p>
<p><strong>uphold </strong><em>–v. </em>to give support to</p>
<p><strong>upstanding </strong><em>–adj.</em> someone who is honest and respectable and is able to stand upright without shame or embarrassment</p>
<p><strong>abide </strong><em>–v.</em> to accept or live by a belief, rule or principle</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Traditional Seoul Village Hopes Curfew Brings Back Normal Life (2024/11/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/traditional-seoul-village-hopes-curfew-bring-back-normal-life.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>In South Korea's capital of Seoul, Bukchon Hanok Village's narrow winding alleyways date back hundreds of years to the Joseon <strong>Dynasty</strong>. The area has become a popular place to visit, especially after appearing in a television show about 10 years ago.</p>
<p>Foreign visitors and Koreans visit the neighborhood to see houses with wood <strong>columns</strong>, <strong>courtyards</strong> and tiled <strong>roofs</strong>.</p>
<p>The area attracted about 6 million visitors last year while the population of the area is around 6,100.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A large crowd of tourists walks through Bukchon Hanok Village in Seoul, South Korea, October 25, 2024. (REUTERS/Kim Soo-hyeon )" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a95baf70-efae-4d60-bac8-b64decaaeb02_cx0_cy1_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A large crowd of tourists walks through Bukchon Hanok Village in Seoul, South Korea, October 25, 2024. (REUTERS/Kim Soo-hyeon )</span></div>
<p>However, increasing numbers of visitors have become a problem for people who live there. They complain about noise, <strong>trash</strong>, bad behavior and invasion of privacy.</p>
<p>Some visitors have been caught on camera trying to enter private homes or looking inside without permission, creating conflict with locals.</p>
<p>Many local people have chosen to leave, leading to a 27.6 percent drop in the village's population over the past 10 years.</p>
<p>Village officials now want to set a curfew in the area. The curfew will limit visitors to certain areas of Bukchon from 5 p.m. to 10 a.m. local time. It will start as a <strong>trial</strong> in November and will be officially launched next March. Violators could pay fines of up to $72.</p>
<p>Chung Moon-hun is the head of Jongno district. Chung said the goal is to protect the rights of local people. Chung said the curfew can be changed if necessary to make it more effective. The area where curfew hours and fines will be in effect is about 34,000 square meters. That is about the size of five soccer fields.</p>
<p>Kwon Young-doo owns the private Asian Cultural Art Museum in Bukchon Hanok Village. Kwon is concerned about the curfew policy aimed at preventing visitors from overrunning the area.</p>
<p>"Who would want to visit?" asked Kwon who moved into the historic area 18 years ago. "They'll leave with a bad impression of South Korea."</p>
<p>Others do not believe the policy will be effective. They note measures such as <strong>exemptions</strong> for visitors staying overnight in traditional houses called hanok. Many of these hanok are now owned by businesses after officials loosened restrictions on overnight stays.</p>
<p>"People come for just a day to enjoy themselves, and the noise from parties is extremely loud," said Kim Eun-mee, who lives next to a hanok. Clearing trash in front of her home has become a task she has to perform several times a day.</p>
<p>"It's often difficult to maintain a normal daily <strong>routine</strong> due to <strong>disturbances</strong>.” She said people often make noise moving their suitcases around even in the early hours, which wakes her up.</p>
<p>Lee Dong-woo is head of the website BUTLER.LEE which is used to rent the hanoks. Lee said the business grew when owners who found it difficult to modernize or maintain old houses turned them over to businesses.</p>
<p>"These requests are driving the expansion, not because we are actively <strong>evicting</strong> current residents to operate hanok stays," Lee said. Lee oversees 17 hanok stays in Bukchon.</p>
<p>Visitors are divided over the curfew. Some agree locals' quality of life is important. Others are unhappy at the idea of getting fined for simply walking down a public street.</p>
<p>There are also questions about how the rules will be enforced; how to tell visitors from locals; how to make foreigners pay a fine, and how to deal with the language barrier.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter Jr.</p>
<p><em>Reuters reported on this story. Hai Do adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>dynasty </strong><em>–n.</em> a group of associated rulers who govern a country for a long time</p>
<p><strong>column </strong><em>–n. </em>a circular or square support for a building<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>courtyard </strong><em>–n.</em> an open area surrounded by buildings</p>
<p><strong>roof</strong><strong> </strong><em>–n.</em> the top of a house that protects the inside from rain and sun</p>
<p><strong>trash </strong><em>–n.</em> waste and unwanted materials</p>
<p><strong>trial </strong><em>–n.</em> a test</p>
<p><strong>exemption </strong>–n. freedom from having to observe a rule that everyone else must follow</p>
<p><strong>routine </strong>–n. something that is done regularly as a normal part of a day or week</p>
<p><strong>disturbance </strong>–n. a happening that is loud, surprising or that causes people to change what they would normally do</p>
<p><strong>evict </strong>–v. to remove someone from where they normally stay or live</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Practice Your Listening (2024/11/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/practice-your-listening.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Hello! This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Zekeriya in Turkiye about listening to English.</p>
<p><strong>Question</strong></p>
<p>Dear teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/0ef7bcc7-67f3-4ce9-be29-39b55cded8d4_w268_r1.jpg"/></div>
<p>When I practice listening, I <strong>focus</strong> a lot and do a lot of repetitions. After a while, I realized that I was actually <strong>memorizing</strong> the audio recording instead of practicing listening. How do you think I should do an <strong>ideal</strong> listening exercise?</p>
<p>Thank you,</p>
<p>Zekeriya</p>
<p><strong>Answer</strong></p>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Zekeriya.</p>
<p>There is not one ideal listening exercise. Instead, there are several good ways to improve your listening.</p>
<p>The repetitions you are doing can be necessary and helpful for you to understand what you hear. And repetitions likely help you remember new words and how to pronounce them. But let's look at more ways you can practice listening.</p>
<p><strong>Listening methods</strong></p>
<p>First, try to find listening material that is just a bit above your ability. This will help you learn new words without making it too difficult for you.</p>
<p>It is best to listen to English material that has words written either in <strong>captions</strong> or in the body text, such as a VOA Learning English article. This will help check your listening.</p>
<ul>
<li>You can test yourself by first listening to parts of the audio without reading the words.</li>
<li>Note the main ideas and the things you clearly understood.</li>
<li>Then, listen to it again and try to understand more details. This is when you can do shorter repetitions.</li>
<li>Next, you can check how much you understood by reading the words as you listen to the audio again.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Transcribing</strong></p>
<p>One of the best ways to practice listening is by writing every word you hear. This is called transcribing. Even with audio examples as short as one minute, you can learn a lot of English using this method. For example, if you are transcribing an <strong>interview</strong>, you might notice differences between spoken English and written English.</p>
<p>By transcribing, you can notice and learn new expressions, grammar rules and spelling. This method also helps make new words stay in your memory when you read them. That is because you are discovering the answer to a problem you have already tried to solve through listening.</p>
<p><strong>Other tips</strong></p>
<p>Try listening to English spoken at different speeds. Over time, you can follow spoken English at a faster speed. Many videos online let you increase or decrease the speed of playback.</p>
<p>Practice listening to English spoken in different foreign <strong>accents</strong>. This is a useful skill because English is spoken in so many places around the world.</p>
<p>Center your listening on specific sounds or grammatical points. For example, preposition use in English can be difficult. Try listening for prepositions and the words they connect with. This can help you use them correctly in your speaking and writing.</p>
<p>Remember that, like any skill, you can improve listening by practicing often and having detailed plans for the methods you will use.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? We'd like to hear from you. Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please include where you are from in your email, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>focus</strong><strong> </strong><em>–v. </em>to center one's attention on something</p>
<p><strong>memorize </strong><em>–v. </em>to learn something so you remember it exactly</p>
<p><strong>ideal </strong><em>–adj. </em>having the qualtiy of being exaclty what you want or the highest quality</p>
<p><strong>captions </strong><em>–n. </em>words that show on screen in a video that match the words being spoken</p>
<p><strong>interview </strong><em>-n. </em>a conversation in which a journalist asks questions to someone such as a famous person or government official.</p>
<p><strong>accent </strong><em>–n. </em>a way of pronouncing words that shows what country or background a person comes from</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers Discover Large, Ancient Mayan City (2024/11/8)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/researchers-discover-large-ancient-mayan-city.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">07 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Researchers in Mexico have discovered a large, lost Mayan city.</p>
<p>The major <strong>urban</strong> settlement, named Valeriana, is hidden deep in the southern forest of Campeche.</p>
<p>The discovery adds to existing knowledge about ancient Mayan settlements.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A Lidar image shows what archeologists say is a newly discovered Mayan city in the jungle of Campeche, Mexico. Handout released October 29, 2024. (Cambridge University Press on behalf of Antiquity Publications Ltd/Handout via REUTERS) " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/bb4abd87-d803-488e-b3e2-dedc41e4675b_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A Lidar image shows what archeologists say is a newly discovered Mayan city in the jungle of Campeche, Mexico. Handout released October 29, 2024. (Cambridge University Press on behalf of Antiquity Publications Ltd/Handout via REUTERS) </span></div>
<p>Valeriana was discovered by chance thanks to Lidar, or Light Detection and Ranging. It is a technology that uses lasers to map the Earth's surface.</p>
<p>The data used for the study came from around 122 square kilometers of high-quality Lidar data collected in 2013.</p>
<p>The work, led by the Nature Conservancy in Mexico, was part of a forest <strong>monitoring</strong> project called Alianza. The project aimed to reduce emissions from tree cutting, or deforestation, and land damage.</p>
<p>Researchers wrote in the study, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/antiquity/article/running-out-of-empty-space-environmental-lidar-and-the-crowded-ancient-landscape-of-campeche-mexico/FFDB435047017853F26CFC5D8804B08D" target="_blank">published by Cambridge University Press,</a> that "The discovery of Valeriana <strong>highlights</strong> the fact that there are still major gaps in our knowledge of the existence or absence of large sites within as-yet unmapped areas of the Maya Lowlands.”</p>
<p>Lidar technology revealed a major settlement, filled with buildings and agricultural <strong>infrastructure</strong>.</p>
<p>The classical-era Maya civilization dates back to around 1800 to 1100 years ago. At the time, the Maya civilization grew its control over present-day southern Mexico and what are now Belize, El Salvador, Guatemala and Honduras.</p>
<p>In the study, the researchers identified a total of 6,764 structures, suggesting a populous ancient city.</p>
<p>The researchers will carry out further detailed study of the dataset – both remotely and in the field. The discovery serves as a way to better understand ancient Mayan urbanization and settlements.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Raul Cortes reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><em>_______________________________________________</em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>urban</strong> <em>– adj.</em> of, relating to, characteristic of, or constituting a city</p>
<p><strong>monitor</strong> <em>-- v. </em><strong> </strong>to watch, keep track of, or check usually for a special purpose</p>
<p><strong>highlight</strong><em> – v. </em>to constitute a significant or especially interesting part of; to center attention on</p>
<p><strong>infrastructure</strong> <em>– n.</em> the resources (such as buildings, roads, irrigation, or equipment) required for an activity</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Europe’s Space Agency Is in Talks with SpaceX to Cut Space Junk (2024/11/8)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/europe-s-space-agency-is-in-talks-with-spacex-to-cut-space-junk.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">07 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The European Space Agency (ESA) is reportedly in talks with America's SpaceX to cooperate in efforts to reduce the growing amount of space <strong>junk</strong>.</p>
<p>The talks, reported by Reuters news agency, aim to get the California-based space company to join an international agreement that pushes for policies to fight space <strong>debris</strong>. It has been estimated that SpaceX satellites represent about two-thirds of spacecraft currently in low-Earth orbit.</p>
<p>Space debris is anything that humans have put into space that is no longer in use. This could include satellites, equipment, parts of rockets or spacecraft.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket is launched, carrying 23 Starlink satellites into low Earth orbit in Cape Canaveral, Florida, U.S., May 6, 2024. (REUTERS/Joe Skipper/File Photo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/8b68390c-9001-4833-a446-00cd973c5f20_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket is launched, carrying 23 Starlink satellites into low Earth orbit in Cape Canaveral, Florida, U.S., May 6, 2024. (REUTERS/Joe Skipper/File Photo)</span></div>
<p>Space junk orbits hundreds of kilometers above Earth. It can circle Earth at speeds of about 25,000 kilometers per hour in low-Earth orbit. And it can cause major damage if it hits a space station, satellite or spacecraft.</p>
<p>The International agreement that ESA wants SpaceX to join is called the Zero Debris Charter. It seeks to stop any new orbital junk from being created by 2030. The 22 members of ESA have been seeking new members to join the agreement since the agency announced it in 2023.</p>
<p>ESA Director General Josef Aschbacher told Reuters that more than 100 countries and organizations have so far joined the agreement. When asked about SpaceX's possible involvement, Aschbacher said ESA was “in discussion” with the company to possibly sign up.</p>
<p>Aschbacher did not provide further details. But he said that work on the charter is moving forward, and ESA is continually raising the issue of space junk with nations and organizations.</p>
<p>Reuters reported that SpaceX did not respond to a request for comment on the matter. The news agency said that out of about 10,300 active satellites in space, an estimated 6,300 are part of SpaceX's fast-growing Starlink internet service system. Reuters said that information came from the U.S. Space Force.</p>
<p>Other organizations and nations are also launching their own large satellite collections. China has done so in an attempt to compete with SpaceX, Reuters reported. In addition, American-based Amazon expects to launch more than 3,000 satellites for its Kuiper internet service over the next 10 years.</p>
<p>Jonathan McDowell is a Harvard University astronomer who follows such objects. He has estimated there are nearly 19,000 pieces of trackable space junk in orbit.</p>
<p>McDowell said he thinks it is important to have members of industry publicly support this kind of charter. "So, I'm glad to know SpaceX is considering it," he said.</p>
<p>There are no international laws on space debris. But in recent years countries have begun to create plans and national rules for fighting the problem.</p>
<p>"We are not a <strong>regulatory</strong> body; we are a technical space agency," Aschbacher said. "But the fact that we have put the charter around the table, which was <strong>elaborated</strong> with all the other partners, and that they signed up to it is very encouraging," he added.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Reuters reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>junk </strong><em>– n. </em>old things that no longer have much value</p>
<p><strong>debris </strong><em>– n.</em> broken pieces of something</p>
<p><strong>regulatory </strong><em>– adj. </em>controlling an activity or process, especially by using rules and laws</p>
<p><strong>elaborate </strong><em>–v.</em> to talk for a long time about something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Approves Apple AirPods to Be Used as Hearing Aids (2024/11/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/us-approves-apple-airpods-to-be-used-as-hearing-aids.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The American government has approved the use of Apple AirPods as hearing aids.</p>
<p>The United States Food and Drug Administration (FDA) recently <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.fda.gov/news-events/press-announcements/fda-authorizes-first-over-counter-hearing-aid-software">announced</a> it had approved new hearing aid software created for some AirPods devices. An Apple software release this week launched the system on the devices.</p>
<p>Apple <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.apple.com/airpods-pro/hearing-health/">said</a> its AirPods Pro 2 are equipped with the software. The company added that the design will permit users to turn their AirPods into a medical-strength hearing aid device.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A pair of Apple AirPods Pro 2 are displayed on a table at Brooklyn College's audiology clinic in New York on Oct. 22, 2024. (AP Photo/Mary Conlon)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/925df86d-5516-4a8a-b44d-b1094805cd10_cx0_cy6_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A pair of Apple AirPods Pro 2 are displayed on a table at Brooklyn College's audiology clinic in New York on Oct. 22, 2024. (AP Photo/Mary Conlon)</span></div>
<p>The system aims to increase <strong>specific</strong> sounds in real-time, including parts of speech and elements within a users' environment. Apple says another goal of its software release is to get more people to try hearing aids.</p>
<p>An estimated 30 million Americans – about 1 in 8 Americans over the age of 12 — have hearing loss in both ears. Millions could see improvements from hearing aids. But most have never tried them, the National Institute on Deafness and Other Communication Disorders says.</p>
<p>Many others have tried assistive devices, but choose not to use them. The reasons include high cost, poor quality, poor fit, how the devices look or other reasons. But in recent years, there has been a push in the U.S. to get more people to try them.</p>
<p>In 2022, federal rules changed to permit some kinds of hearing aids to be sold without a doctor's order, or <strong>prescription</strong>. Such moves aimed to bring better and less costly models to patients.</p>
<p>The highest-quality hearing aids can cost from $1,000 to $2,500, or even more. But some over-the-counter models sell for between $400 and $500, said Elizabeth Stangl, a hearing expert at the University of Iowa. She spoke to The Associated Press.</p>
<p>Stangl said some of the less costly models are only effective at raising sound levels. But they lack the personal settings and noise blocking tools that can make hearing aids most helpful. AirPods cost $249 on Apple's website, and sometimes less from other sellers.</p>
<p>The launch of the software is part of a series of health tools Apple has released over the years. Most of them were built for the Apple Watch. <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.apple.com/healthcare/apple-watch/">These include</a> several tools for checking heart and oxygen levels.</p>
<p>Apple's software release also includes built-in tests to help users find out if they have hearing loss and, if so, how severe it is. Those who do have hearing loss can then set specific <strong>amplification</strong> levels.</p>
<p>Experts say there are other, similar headphone devices on the market that could also be used to increase sound levels for people with hearing loss. But many agree the AirPods addition is a good one, largely because of the way it could help normalize hearing aids for the public.</p>
<p>Barbara Kelley is the director of the Hearing Loss Association of America. She told the AP that AirPods are considered “<strong>mainstream</strong>” and already widely used. This could get people to try the devices if they have been resistant to the look of traditional hearing aids.</p>
<p>Kelley noted that many health conditions have been linked to hearing loss. These include <strong>depression</strong>, <strong>dementia</strong> and greater risk of falls. The majority of people with hearing loss are over age 60, but it can affect younger people as well, including those who suffered a hearing damaging event.</p>
<p>“Everything we do, all our relationships, whether it's personal or in our work life, involve hearing <strong>conversation</strong>,” Kelley said. “We're finding now that the sooner that people can pay attention to their hearing health, the better.”</p>
<p>The University of Iowa's Stangl noted the AirPods solution does come with possible issues some people may not like. Fit and comfort during long use might be one of these. And while other hearing aids are built to last through a whole day or more, she said the <strong>battery </strong>life of the AirPods does not permit for that. She also said that wearing AirPods might send a message to others that the person does not want to be <strong>disturbed</strong> or spoken to.</p>
<p>“But we're hoping that more people will try it and realize, ‘Yeah, these do help,'” Stangl said.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters, Agence France-Press and Apple.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>specific </strong><em>– </em><em>adj.</em><strong> </strong>restricted to a particular individual, situation, effect, or reaction</p>
<p><strong>amplify </strong><em>– v.</em> to make louder</p>
<p><strong>mainstream </strong><em>– adj. </em>the beliefs or way of living accepted by most<em> </em>people</p>
<p><strong>dementia </strong><em>– n.</em> a mental illness suffered especially by older people</p>
<p><strong>conversation </strong><em>– n. </em>a discussion between two or more people</p>
<p><strong>battery </strong><em>– n. </em>a device that chemically stores electricity so it can be used as direct current in electrical circuits such as computers and motors</p>
<p><strong>disturb </strong><em>– v.</em> to interrupt what someone is doing</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Mpox Cases in DRC Might Be Decreasing (2024/11/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/mpox-cases-in-drc-might-be-decreasing.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Some health officials say mpox cases in the Democratic Republic of the Congo appear to be “<strong>stabilizing</strong>.” The observation is a possible sign that the <strong>epidemic</strong> might be declining.</p>
<p>Mpox is also known as m<i><i>onkey</i></i>pox. The United States Centers for Disease Control and Prevention <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cdc.gov/poxvirus/mpox/index.html">says</a> the viral disease was first identified by scientists in 1958 when outbreaks of a “pox-like” disease appeared in m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s. Until recently, most human cases involved people in central and West Africa who had contact with infected animals.</p>
<p>Last August, the World Health Organization (WHO) <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/who-calls-for-donations-after-declaring-mpox-a-health-emergency-/7744040.html">declared mpox</a> in Africa a "public health emergency of international concern.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Emile Miango, 2, who has mpox, lies in a hospital, in Kamituga, South Kivu province, Sept. 4, 2024, in the Democratic Republic of Congo. (AP Photo/Moses Sawasawa, file)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/03e90655-a011-4641-bc58-47c0e7cd3d49_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Emile Miango, 2, who has mpox, lies in a hospital, in Kamituga, South Kivu province, Sept. 4, 2024, in the Democratic Republic of Congo. (AP Photo/Moses Sawasawa, file)</span></div>
<p>In recent weeks, the WHO says the Democratic Republic of the Congo, or DRC, has reported about 200 to 300 confirmed mpox cases every week. That number is down from nearly 400 cases a week in July. A decrease has also been reported in Kamituga, where the new, more infectious <strong>variant</strong> of mpox first appeared.</p>
<p>But the U.N. health agency said last week that only about half of suspected infections in the DRC were being tested. And the agency noted that the virus is continuing to spread in some parts of the country and elsewhere, including Uganda.</p>
<p>While doctors are hopeful about the drop in infections in some parts of the DRC, they still do not know what kinds of physical contact are driving the outbreak. Health experts are also concerned about the low number of vaccines the Central African nation has received. The WHO estimates that only 50,000 people have been vaccinated in the DRC, which has a population of about 110 million.</p>
<p>Scientists also say there needs to be an urgent effort to vaccinate all of Africa to halt mpox's spread and avoid worse variants.</p>
<p>“If we miss this opportunity, the likelihood of another significant outbreak increases <strong>substantially</strong>,” said Dr. Zakary Rhissa, who heads operations in the DRC for the nonprofit group ALIMA.</p>
<p>This year, there have been 43,000 suspected cases in Africa and more than 1,000 people have died, mostly in the DRC.</p>
<p>Rhissa added, “We've seen how past outbreaks, such as the one in Nigeria in 2017, can lead to larger global events if not effectively contained.” The 2017 mpox epidemic affected more than 100 countries.</p>
<p>Rhissa said the decline in cases in Kamituga — where mpox initially spread among sex workers and miners — is an opening to put more programs in place for vaccination, <strong>surveillance</strong> and education.</p>
<p>Georgette Hamuli is an 18-year-old sex worker. Hamuli said she did not know about mpox until vaccination teams arrived in Goma recently. “The vaccine is also necessary,” she said. “I think we're now protected.”</p>
<p>The Africa Centers for Disease Control and Prevention has estimated the DRC needs at least 3 million mpox vaccines to stop the virus, and another 7 million for the rest of Africa. So far, the WHO and partners have provided 900,000 vaccines to nine African countries affected by mpox and expect 6 million vaccines to be available by the end of this year.</p>
<p>Mpox epidemics in Burundi, Kenya, Rwanda and Uganda are believed to have started in the DRC. Several mpox cases affecting travelers have also been identified in Sweden, Thailand, Germany, India and Britain.</p>
<p>Dr. Salim Abdool Karim is an infectious diseases expert at South Africa's University of KwaZulu-Natal. He said mpox outbreaks usually rise and then disappear quickly because of how the virus spreads. This time, however, he said the virus continues to spread through sex and infected animals.</p>
<p>“We're in new territory with mpox this time,” he added. “We're never going to solve this until we vaccinate most of our people.”</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Maria Cheng and Ruth Alonga reported this story for the Associated Press. Hai Do adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>stabilize</strong>–v. to not get worse; to even out or establish a normal level</p>
<p><strong>epidemic</strong> <em>–n. </em>when an infectious disease spreads quickly over a large area</p>
<p><strong>variant</strong> <em>–n.</em> a version of an infectious agent that is a little but different from the earlier one</p>
<p><strong>substantially </strong>–adv. to a large degree</p>
<p><strong>surveillance </strong>–n. closely observing something over a period to see if something bad is happening or going to happen</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Trump Wins US Presidential Election (2024/11/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/trump-wins-us-presidential-election.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Former U.S. President Donald Trump defeated Vice President Kamala Harris to earn a new four-year term as the country's leader.</p>
<p>Trump secured at least 277 of the 538 available electoral votes in Tuesday's election. In the U.S. system, the presidential vote is counted in the states. Trump's victories in Pennsylvania, Georgia, North Carolina and Wisconsin gave him a majority of Electoral College votes, which decide the U.S. presidency. Trump becomes the first U.S. leader to win two terms that are not <strong>consecutive</strong> since Grover Cleveland in 1892.</p>
<p>Trump claimed victory early Wednesday as he thanked his supporters at a campaign event in Florida.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Former President Donald Trump gestures as he walks with former first lady Melania Trump at an election night watch party at the Palm Beach Convention Center, Wednesday, Nov. 6, 2024, in West Palm Beach, Fla. (AP Photo/Evan Vucci)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/b72f8cd7-2831-4e6f-aa04-4360c6c9c669_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Former President Donald Trump gestures as he walks with former first lady Melania Trump at an election night watch party at the Palm Beach Convention Center, Wednesday, Nov. 6, 2024, in West Palm Beach, Fla. (AP Photo/Evan Vucci)</span></div>
<p>"This was a movement like nobody's ever seen before, and, frankly, this was, I believe, the greatest political movement of all time," Trump said.</p>
<p>He promised to "fix our borders" and "fix everything in our country."</p>
<p>Trump also said he would work to provide a "strong, safe and <strong>prosperous</strong> America."</p>
<p>A Harris campaign official told a crowd of her supporters in Washington that she would not speak to the gathering but would speak later Wednesday.</p>
<p>Republican Party wins Tuesday extended to Congress. The party won a majority in the Senate with at least 51 of 100 seats. Control of the House of Representatives, which is currently held by Republicans, was not yet clearly decided early Wednesday.</p>
<p><strong>World leaders offer congratulations</strong></p>
<p>World leaders offered congratulations to Trump after news media <strong>projections</strong> showed that he had secured a clear victory in the 2024 U.S. presidential election.</p>
<p>Early Wednesday, many world leaders expressed their opinions on social media service X.</p>
<p>Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu was one of the first leaders of U.S. allies to send a message of support. He praised Trump's “historic return,” saying it would strengthen “the great alliance between Israel and America.”</p>
<p>Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi offered Trump the “Heartiest congratulations.”</p>
<p>Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelenskyy praised Trump's policy of “peace through strength.” He added, “This is exactly the <strong>principle</strong> that can practically bring just peace in Ukraine closer.”</p>
<p>NATO chief Mark Rutte said he was looking forward to working with Trump to “<strong>advance</strong> peace through strength” through the military alliance.</p>
<p>French President Emmanuel Macron offered congratulations, saying he is “ready to work together as we did for four years...with your conviction and mine.”</p>
<p>British Prime Minister Keir Starmer promised to stand “shoulder to shoulder” with the U.S. leader in defense of shared values of freedom, democracy and <strong>enterprise</strong>.</p>
<p>President of the EU Commission Ursula von der Leyen praised the “true partnership” between the European Union and the United States.</p>
<p>And Hungarian Prime Minister Victor Orban called Trump's victory the “biggest comeback in US political history.”</p>
<p>Trump is expected to be inaugurated for a new term on January 20.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted this report for VOA Learning English from reports from VOANEWS.COM. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>consecutive</strong> –adj. one after the other</p>
<p><strong>prosperous</strong> <em>–adj. </em>having continuing success, growth and finding favor</p>
<p><strong>focus</strong> <em>–v.</em> to center one's attention on something</p>
<p><strong>projection</strong><strong> </strong><em>–n.</em> an estimate of what will happen in the future</p>
<p><strong>principle</strong> <em>–n.</em> a moral rule about right and wrong</p>
<p><strong>advance </strong><em>–v.</em> to bring forward or support the development of something</p>
<p><strong>enterprise </strong><em>–n.</em> activity that involves hard work and is usually related to business activities and industry</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers Discover World’s Oldest Tadpole (2024/11/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/researchers-discover-world-s-oldest-tadpole.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Scientists in Argentina have discovered the oldest-known remains of the tadpole. The animal belonged to a large frog <strong>species</strong> that lived alongside dinosaurs about 161 million years ago.</p>
<p>The researchers said the 16-centimeter-long tadpole died during the larval period, or stage, of frog development. The discovery is providing new information about the development of frogs and toads.</p>
<p>The remains suggest tadpoles today are largely unchanged from their ancestors in the ancient time called the Jurassic period. The oldest-known frog remains date back even further, though no older tadpole <strong>fossils</strong> have been found.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A fossil of the world's oldest tadpole, which coexisted with dinosaurs about 165 million years ago, is pictured next to a 3D-printed representation of the tadpole and of a fully developed frog, in Buenos Aires, Argentina October 28, 2024. (REUTERS/Agustin Marcarian)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/dbb14714-caa3-40b4-ae88-d139aebc7214_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A fossil of the world's oldest tadpole, which coexisted with dinosaurs about 165 million years ago, is pictured next to a 3D-printed representation of the tadpole and of a fully developed frog, in Buenos Aires, Argentina October 28, 2024. (REUTERS/Agustin Marcarian)</span></div>
<p>The remains are in good condition. In fact, researchers say, the ancient tadpole has some soft tissues rarely seen in fossils. The tadpole's eyes and nerves, for example, appear as dark markings in the fossil.</p>
<p>Fossil hunters found the tadpole in 2020, during a dig for dinosaur remains on a ranch in the southern province of Santa Cruz. The fossil includes the tadpole's head and most of its body.</p>
<p>Frogs have a two-stage life cycle, with the tadpole larva developing into the adult form. This tadpole was in the late stages of development. Adults of this species are a similar length as the tadpole, the researchers said.</p>
<p>"It's not only the oldest tadpole in the world and amazingly <strong>preserved</strong>, but it also tells us about the size of one of the few frog species known from that time," said biologist Mariana Chuliver of Fundación Azara-Universidad Maimónides.</p>
<p>Chuliver was the lead writer of the study that appeared recently in the scientific publication <em>Nature</em>.</p>
<p>Chuliver said the soft tissue remains are important because they permit researchers to "know the diet and lifestyle of these organisms."</p>
<p>The remains, Chuliver added, show that the form and structure of tadpoles have "remained almost unchanged over the last 160 million years."</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Miguel Lo Bianco reported on this story for Reuters. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>species </strong><em>– n.</em> a class of animals having common attributes and designated by a common name</p>
<p><strong>fossil </strong><em>– n.</em> the remains of an organism of past geologic ages that has been preserved in the earth's crust</p>
<p><strong>preserve</strong> <em>– v.</em> to keep intact or free from decay</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Protecting Bulbs from Animals and Cold Weather (2024/11/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/protecting-bulbs-from-animals-and-cold-weather.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>It would not be autumn without planting advice from Associated Press gardening expert Jessica Damiano.</p>
<p>Damiano recently wrote about her experience planting garlic <strong>cloves</strong>. She was concerned not just about protecting them from low winter temperatures. She was worried that animals would dig up her <strong>bulbs</strong> and eat them.</p>
<p>Tulips, daffodils and garlic, for example, produce bulbs that <strong>bloom</strong> in the spring in places that have four seasons and cold winters.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This Oct. 21, 2024, image provided by Jessica Damiano shows bird netting installed over a garden bed on Long Island, N.Y. (Jessica Damiano via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/84b313e9-91de-4b99-8140-ae805242dbe1_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This Oct. 21, 2024, image provided by Jessica Damiano shows bird netting installed over a garden bed on Long Island, N.Y. (Jessica Damiano via AP)</span></div>
<p>To keep away animals, Damiano put netting over the soil and covered it with straw<strong> </strong>to a thickness of 10 centimeters.</p>
<p>She said this is good to do with any bulbs, especially ones like garlic, tulips and crocuses. That is because animals like to eat the bulbs of these plants.</p>
<p><strong>Protecting bulbs</strong></p>
<p>Netting or a kind of fencing called chicken wire can serve as a physical barrier that prevents animals from digging up plants. Such barriers do not block sunlight and water from reaching the soil. Damiano said they can be secured to the ground with pieces of wood or rocks. They can be removed in the spring.</p>
<p>Straw is a good mulch material that helps keep the temperature of the soil from changing too much. That can help avoid damage to plants caused by freezing and <strong>thawing </strong>conditions. It also keeps the soil from drying out. Protecting soil is important during the winter when cold dry weather can damage even the strongest plants.</p>
<p><strong>Straw, hay, what is the difference?</strong></p>
<p>Damiano said it is important to use straw, not hay, in your garden. Hay is animal feed. It contains tall grass, alfalfa, clover and other seeds that will cause problems in your garden.</p>
<p>She said straw is leftover material from crop harvesting. It is better because it has fewer seeds.</p>
<p>Damiano also said straw is less likely to contain chemicals used for insect control on crops. Straw is also good for other purposes around your house, the gardening expert noted.</p>
<p><strong>Fertilizers and repellants</strong></p>
<p>Damiano does not like to use some popular fertilizers such as bone meal, blood meal or fish fertilizers. She said hungry animals might find such fertilizers appealing.</p>
<p>She also advises not to leave parts of bulbs on the ground in your garden because they might be a sign to animals that there is food nearby.</p>
<p>There are many products meant to keep away animals that eat bulbs, which include squirrels, rabbits, chipmunks and others. Damiano does not use <strong>repellants</strong> because they must be must be replaced often. She said she does not like doing garden work when it is cold outside.</p>
<p>Some repellants can be used to treat bulbs before planting. But, she said, they wear off over time. Damiano considered a physical barrier like netting or chicken wire to be the best defense.</p>
<p>But, she added, the repellants and other methods can be effective so long as you are <strong>diligent</strong>.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Jessica Damiano reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>clove </strong><em>–n</em>. a segment, or part, of a plant bulb</p>
<p><strong>bulb</strong> <em>–n. </em>the underground part of certain plants that produces leaves and flowers</p>
<p><strong>bloom</strong> <em>–v.</em> to produce a fully developed flower</p>
<p><strong>thaw </strong><em>–v.</em> to melt from a frozen state</p>
<p><strong>repellant </strong>–n. a substance that keep an animal such as an insect or a larger animal away because of some chemical property</p>
<p><strong>diligent </strong>–adj. showing care, hard work and continuous effort</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Uncertain Time for Immigrants’ Children in School (2024/11/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/uncertain-time-for-immigrants-children-in-school.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>On the first day of seventh grade in Aurora, Colorado, this past August, Alisson Ramirez worried about making friends and not understanding lessons taught in English.</p>
<p>"I was nervous that people would ask me things and I wouldn't know how to answer," the Venezuelan teen says. "And I would be <strong>ashamed</strong> to answer in Spanish."</p>
<p>But it was not what she had expected. Her teachers had translated words from their lessons into Spanish. They gave out written instructions in Spanish. Some teachers even asked in Spanish if students had finished or had questions.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Alisson Ram&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;237;rez uses a laptop to work on an assignment during science class Wednesday, Aug. 28, 2024, in Aurora, Colorado. (AP Photo/Godofredo A. V&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;225;squez)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/22a32a8d-9a6f-44fd-aed9-76df79b0dea5_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Alisson Ram<i>&amp;#</i>237;rez uses a laptop to work on an assignment during science class Wednesday, Aug. 28, 2024, in Aurora, Colorado. (AP Photo/Godofredo A. V<i>&amp;#</i>225;squez)</span></div>
<p>"That made me feel better," says Alisson. The 13-year-old is among the 3,000 new students, mostly from Venezuela and Colombia, at the Aurora public school system.</p>
<p><strong>City officials and false claims</strong></p>
<p>While teachers have been working hard to educate children of immigrants, outside the classrooms, city officials are not as welcoming. They promised not to spend any money helping newcomers and tried to keep them from coming to the area.</p>
<p>One city official even claimed that criminals from Venezuela had occupied buildings in Aurora. The police investigated and found it was not true. But the false claim continued to spread.</p>
<p>Maria Angel Torres is Alisson's mother. The family had left Venezuela to escape lawlessness and violence. They left behind a food truck business after being attacked for not paying protection money. The family then crossed the dangerous Darien Gap on foot to head north and seek asylum in the United States.</p>
<p>Torres said she did not believe criminals had <strong>taken over</strong> buildings. But she worried that bad reports about Venezuelans would affect her and her family. Some organizations and <strong>churches</strong> wanted to help her family. But others are deeply afraid.</p>
<p>Torres told the Associated Press, “I don't look like a threat. But people here act like they feel terrorized.”</p>
<p><strong>Times have changed in Aurora</strong></p>
<p>Aurora is used to educating children of immigrants.</p>
<p>The 2020 <strong>census</strong> reported that more than a third of people in Aurora speak a language other than English at home. Immigrants and refugees have been moving to Aurora because it is close to Denver and it has a lower cost of living.</p>
<p>However, some schools in the area were not ready for the sudden arrival of many non-English-speaking students from Venezuela and Colombia. Before, a teacher might have had one or two new students in her class. Now, teachers in some schools have as many as 10, or a third of their classroom.</p>
<p><strong>Translanguaging</strong></p>
<p>Marcella Garcia is the head of Aurora Hills Middle School. She observed that some new students were not talking in classrooms where only English was spoken. So, the school system advised teachers to use a method called "translanguaging." That means using Spanish or the home language at times to help new students understand English lessons and discussions happening around them.</p>
<p>The method has helped Alisson feel more at ease.</p>
<p>One day in September, Alisson and her friends spoke Spanish among themselves as their teacher spoke to the class in English about a drawing he was showing in front of the class.</p>
<p>It was a drawing of an ancient Egyptian marketplace. “What do you think this <strong>dude</strong> here is doing with the <strong>basket</strong>?” the teacher asked the class. One girl who had been in Aurora schools longer than the rest <strong>translated</strong> for Alisson and the other new students.</p>
<p>Before the school began using this new method, teachers may have stopped the new students from talking among themselves. Now, they permit students to help each other in any language they can.</p>
<p>So far, there appears to be little public criticism in the area against this method. It generally requires more work for teachers, who have to translate materials or their talks in real-time.</p>
<p><strong>Rumors of violence</strong></p>
<p>Recently, Alisson's mother received messages from Aurora Public Schools that there have been <strong>rumors</strong> of bomb threats at its schools and others across the state. The schools said there was no truth to the rumors.</p>
<p>But that does not make Torres feel better. She said in Venezuela, the country is in trouble, but no one there would think of threatening children at school.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Bianca Vázquez Toness reported</em><em> this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>ashamed</strong> – <em>adj</em>. not wanting to do something because of shame or embarrassment</p>
<p><strong>take</strong> <strong>over</strong> – <em>phrasal verb</em>. to take control of something</p>
<p><strong>church </strong>–<em> n</em>. place of religious worship</p>
<p><strong>census</strong> –<em> n</em>. the official process of counting the number of people in a country, city, or town and collecting information about them</p>
<p><strong>dude </strong>–<em> n</em>. <em>informal.</em> a man — used especially by young people</p>
<p><strong>basket </strong>–<em> n</em>. a container usually made by weaving together long thin pieces of material</p>
<p><strong>translate</strong> –<em> v</em>. to change words from one language into another language</p>
<p><strong>rumor </strong>–<em> n</em>. information or a story that is passed from person to person but has not been proven to be true</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Health Officials Call for Shots Against Pneumonia (2024/11/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/us-health-officials-call-for-shots-against-pneumonia.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>American health officials say people age 50 and older should get vaccinated against bacteria that cause pneumonia and other dangerous diseases.</p>
<p>Pneumonia is an infection that affects the lungs. It makes breathing difficult and can cause a rise in body temperature. Pneumonia can also lead to a <strong>cough</strong> that produces yellow, green or bloody substances.</p>
<p>The advice, or recommendation, was offered by a group of scientific advisors and approved by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). The former age recommendation for adult vaccinations was 65 and older.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This electron microscopic image provided by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention shows two, round-shaped, Gram-positive, Streptococcus pneumoniae bacteria. (Janice Haney Carr/CDC via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/7d634f36-6b28-40d4-9cf1-fcae90210c66_cx0_cy7_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This electron microscopic image provided by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention shows two, round-shaped, Gram-positive, Streptococcus pneumoniae bacteria. (Janice Haney Carr/CDC via AP)</span></div>
<p>CDC Director Mandy Cohen said in a statement, “Now is a great time to get vaccinated against pneumococcal disease in preparation for the winter <strong>respiratory</strong> season.”</p>
<p>The advisors voted 14-1 to change the age recommendation during an October meeting in Atlanta, Georgia, home of the CDC headquarters. Doctors widely follow the agency's guidance.</p>
<p>Pneumococcal shot recommendations are sometimes called the most complex vaccination guidance that the government issues.</p>
<p>The <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cdc.gov/pneumococcal/hcp/vaccine-recommendations/index.html">CDC currently recommends</a> shots for children younger than five and adults 50 or older, as long as they have never been vaccinated against pneumococcal disease. Officials also recommend the shots for children and adults at increased risk for pneumococcal disease, such as those with diabetes, liver disease or a weakened immune, or defense, system.</p>
<p>There are more than 100 known kinds of pneumococcal bacteria. They can cause serious infections in the lungs and other parts of the body. Each year, the U.S. sees about 30,000 cases of pneumococcal disease, which includes blood infections, brain and spine inflammation, and other problems. About 30 percent of cases are among people aged 50 to 64.</p>
<p>The first pneumococcal vaccine was licensed in the U.S. in 1977. Since then, drugmakers have been coming up with newer versions that target several bacteria in a single shot.</p>
<p>There are four vaccines now in use. They include Prevnar 20 from Wyeth-Pfizer, and Vaxneuvance and Pneumovax 23 made by Merck. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration this year also approved Merck's Capvaxive, which can cost around $300 a treatment. The new shot can protect against 21 kinds of bacteria, including eight not included in other pneumococcal vaccines. A Merck spokesperson said it is designed to help protect against the bacteria that cause the majority of severe disease in adults aged 50 and older.</p>
<p>In June, the CDC advisors recommended the vaccine as a possible shot for adults at higher risk. At the time, the group also talked about the possibility of lowering the age recommendation for older adults. They noted that infections causing sickness <strong>peak </strong>at age 55 to 59 among Black Americans — a lower age than found among white Americans.</p>
<p>Some scientists have concerns about the CDC recommendation. They say a second treatment, called a booster, may be necessary in about 15 years. And some new vaccines in development could force another update to the recommendations.</p>
<p>Dr. Jamie Loehr is the chair of the committee's pneumococcal working group. He was the only person to vote against the proposal.</p>
<p>He said, “Pneumococcal has been a very <strong>confusing </strong>recommendation for many, many years and it's hard to have a new recommendation every two or three years.”</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Hai Do adapted this story for VOA Learning English based on reporting from The Associated Press and information from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>cough</strong> - v. to force air through your throat with short, loud noise because you are sick.</p>
<p><strong>respiratory</strong> - adj. of or relating to breathing</p>
<p><strong>peak</strong> - n. the highest level</p>
<p><strong>confusing</strong> - adj. difficult to understand</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>American Music Legend Quincy Jones Dies at 91 (2024/11/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/american-music-legend-quincy-jones-dies-at-91.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>One of the biggest names in America's music industry – Quincy Jones – has died at the age of 91. A family statement said Jones passed away Sunday night surrounded by family members at his home in the Bel Air neighborhood of Los Angeles.</p>
<p>Jones is known for working with many top names in the music industry, including superstars Michael Jackson, Frank Sinatra and Ray Charles. Throughout his 65-year career, he worked with hundreds of other music artists.</p>
<p>Jones' publicist Arnold Robinson said in a statement, “Tonight, with full but broken hearts, we must share the news of our father and brother Quincy Jones' passing.” It added, “And although this is an incredible loss for our family, we celebrate the great life that he lived and know there will never be another like him.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Music producer Quincy Jones poses for a portrait to promote his documentary " ap="" by="" chris="" during="" festival="" file="" film="" in="" invision="" on="" pizzello="" quincy="" sept.="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/3942d3ab-85cf-4f68-938c-6c6529fe13c1_w268_r1.jpg" the="" toronto="" toronto.=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Music producer Quincy Jones poses for a portrait to promote his documentary "Quincy" during the Toronto Film Festival on Sept. 7, 2018, in Toronto. (Photo by Chris Pizzello/Invision/AP, File)</span></div>
<p>Born in Chicago in 1933, Jones said an early music influence was the <strong>hymns </strong>his mother used to sing around the house. Early on, he played music, the trumpet, and led others in band music.</p>
<p>As a very young man, Jones used to run with <strong>gangs</strong> on the South Side of Chicago. But he later rose to the top of show business, becoming one of the first Black business leaders in Hollywood. Later, he established himself as a major <strong>composer</strong> and producer.</p>
<p>Jones shaped recordings by jazz greats such as Miles Davis and produced hits for Sinatra and Ella Fitzgerald. And he helped organize the 1985 money-raising event for Africa that resulted in the song <em>We Are the World</em>. The song went on to become one of the biggest hits of its time.</p>
<p>Jones composed music for <em>Roots</em> and <em>In the Heat of the Night</em>. He also organized President Bill Clinton's first inaugural celebration in 1993. Jones also wrote several movie <strong>scores</strong> and co-produced the film <em>The Color Purple</em>. In addition, he co-produced the highly successful 1990s television show <em>The Fresh Prince of Bel-Air</em>, which launched the career of Will Smith.</p>
<p>Jones's work with superstar Michael Jackson still represents one of his most lasting successes. He and Jackson made three wildly popular albums: <em>Off the Wall</em> in 1979, <em>Thriller</em> in 1982, and <em>Bad</em> in 1987.</p>
<p><em>Thriller</em> sold more than 20 million copies in 1983 alone. It helped Jackson become the first major Black artist to have a video played on MTV and influenced countless other performers. Jones later explained, “Michael had the look and the voice, and I had every sound you can think of.”</p>
<p>Jones was known for keeping company with presidents and foreign leaders, movie stars and musicians, <strong>philanthropists</strong> and business leaders. His circle of friends included some of the most famous people of the 20th century, including artist Pablo Picasso, Pope John Paul II and Nelson Mandela.</p>
<p>The list of Jones' honors and awards fills 18 pages in his 2001 autobiography <em>Q</em>. The book made him a best-selling writer. He won a total of 27 Grammy Awards, as well as two honorary Academy Awards and an Emmy for the television series <em>Roots</em>.</p>
<p>Jones also received France's Legion d'Honneur, the Rudolph Valentino Award from the Republic of Italy and a Kennedy Center honor for his influence over American culture. He was the subject of a 1990 documentary called "<em>Listen Up: The Lives of Quincy Jones,</em>" as well as the 2018 film <em>Quincy</em>, directed by his daughter, Rashida Jones.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press, Reuters and VOA News reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>hymn </strong><em>– n. </em>a song sung by Christians to praise God</p>
<p><strong>gang </strong><em>– n.</em> a group of young people who spend time together, often fighting with other groups and behaving poorly</p>
<p><strong>composer </strong><em>– n. </em>a person who writes music</p>
<p><strong>score </strong><em>– n.</em> a printed piece of music</p>
<p><strong>philanthropist </strong><em>– adj. </em>someone who gives money to people who need hel</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Harris, Trump Make Final Push for Votes on Election Day (2024/11/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/harris-trump-make-final-push-for-votes-on-election-day.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Vice President Kamala Harris and former President Donald Trump are making a final push for votes on the day before Election Day in the United States.</p>
<p>Harris is spending the day in the state of Pennsylvania, looking to win its 19 Electoral College votes. In addition to Pennsylvania, Trump holds campaign events in North Carolina and Michigan.</p>
<p>About 77 million Americans have already voted early. The total is nearly half of the 158 million who voted through Election Day in 2020. Harris and Trump are now pushing for the votes of remaining supporters and undecided voters as voting ends on Election Day, Tuesday, November 5.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="File photos show Democratic presidential nominee Vice President Kamala Harris (L) at a campaign rally Erie, Pa., on Oct. 14, 2024, and Republican presidential nominee former President Donald Trump at a campaign rally in Uniondale, N.Y., on Sept.18, 2024. (AP File Photos)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/4bd6b4a7-c57f-4dfe-ab7b-12050978114b_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">File photos show Democratic presidential nominee Vice President Kamala Harris (L) at a campaign rally Erie, Pa., on Oct. 14, 2024, and Republican presidential nominee former President Donald Trump at a campaign rally in Uniondale, N.Y., on Sept.18, 2024. (AP File Photos)</span></div>
<p><strong>Electoral College</strong></p>
<p>In U.S. presidential elections, the candidate who captures 270 or more Electoral College votes is the winner, regardless of the popular vote.</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.fec.gov/introduction-campaign-finance/election-results-and-voting-information/federal-elections-2016/">In 2016</a>, Democrat Hillary Clinton received nearly 3 million votes more than Trump nationwide. But Trump won 304 Electoral College votes and the presidency. <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.fec.gov/introduction-campaign-finance/election-results-and-voting-information/federal-elections-2020/">In 2020</a>, Democrat Joe Biden received 7 million votes more than Trump and also won 306 Electoral College votes.</p>
<p>This year, the race comes down to results from seven states, called battleground or swing states, because of changing results from election to election. The states are Nevada, North Carolina, Wisconsin, Georgia, Pennsylvania, Michigan and Arizona.</p>
<p>Trump won Arizona, Georgia, Pennsylvania, Michigan, and Wisconsin in 2016 but lost all five states to Biden in 2020. This year, opinion studies from all seven states suggest that Harris and Trump are basically tied.</p>
<p>The vice president became the Democratic candidate after President Biden withdrew from the race in July. The <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/democrats-back-harris-as-biden-leaves-presidential-race/7708239.html">81-year-old Biden said he would not seek reelection</a> after a poor performance debating Trump in June.</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/a-short-history-of-attacks-on-us-presidents-candidates/7698894.html">Trump survived an assassination attempt</a> in Butler, Pennsylvania, also in June when a bullet struck his right ear. The gunman was killed after firing several shots. One other person was killed and two were injured at the Trump campaign event.</p>
<p><strong>Trump on the issues</strong></p>
<p>Trump launched his third campaign for the White House by renewing his “Make America Great Again” message and calling for a severe policy on illegal immigration. He promised to deport, or expel, 15 to 20 million illegal immigrants from the country.</p>
<p>Trump blamed Biden and Harris for the inflation that came after the worldwide pandemic. He said his administration would increase taxes, called tariffs, on imported goods, cut taxes for Americans, open more lands for oil and gas exploration and reduce <strong>regulations</strong> for businesses.</p>
<p>On foreign policy, Trump has criticized NATO and suggested that the U.S. should step back from other defense treaties. Trump has not said whether he would send more military aid to Ukraine and claimed that he could end the war in the country. Trump said he supports Israel in its war in Gaza and Lebanon. He condemned pro-Palestinian protests in the U.S. and told <em>Time</em> magazine that the two-state solution might not be possible.</p>
<p><strong>Harris on the issues</strong></p>
<p>Harris, at the age of 60, is <strong>projecting</strong> her campaign against the 78-year-old Trump as a generational change saying, “We're not going back.”</p>
<p>Harris brings attention to her support for <strong>abortion</strong> rights after the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/us-high-court-overturns-roe-v-wade-ending-abortion-right/6632104.html">Supreme Court's 2022 decision</a> overturning the earlier Supreme Court decision known as <em>Roe v. Wade</em>. Harris said that she “will sign a law restoring and protecting reproductive freedom in every state.” While president, Trump appointed three conservative justices to overturn <em>Roe v. Wade</em>, and he said the issue belongs to the states.</p>
<p>On immigration, Harris has spoken of her support for a bipartisan proposal for border security that would increase officers to deal with asylum seekers among other things.</p>
<p>On the economy, Harris said she supports higher taxes for companies and wealthy Americans and lower taxes on people making less than $400,000 a year. She calls Trump's proposed tariffs a tax increase on everyday Americans. Some tariffs put in place during Trump's term in office have remained in place under Biden.</p>
<p>On foreign policy, Harris supports an active role for the U.S. in NATO and other military alliances. She supports continuing U.S. aid to Ukraine against the Russian invasion there. Harris has said that Israel has a right to defend itself against Hamas's terrorist attacks. She has called for a cease-fire so that all hostages can be released and has described the situation in Gaza as a “humanitarian <strong>catastrophe</strong>.” She also supports a two-state solution for Israelis and Palestinians.</p>
<p>A Trump victory would make him the first incoming president to have been indicted and convicted of a felony in a New York trial. Trump denied any wrongdoing and is appealing the verdict.</p>
<p>A Harris victory would make her the first woman, the first Black woman and the first person of South Asian ancestry to win the U.S. presidency.</p>
<p>And now it is up to the American people.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr.</p>
<p><em>Hai Do wrote this story for VOA Learning English with additional information from VOA News, The Associated Press, and the Federal Election Commission.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>regulation </strong>–n. a rule or law especially for industries that says how something should or should not be done</p>
<p><strong>projecting</strong> <em>–n. </em>to believe or imagine that (your ideas, feelings, etc.) are shared by (another person)</p>
<p><strong>abortion</strong> <em>–n.</em> to end a pregnancy by killing the fetus</p>
<p><strong>catastrophe </strong>–n. a disaster or horrible event</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>NASA to Launch Instruments to Study Water on Moon (2024/11/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/nasa-to-launch-instrument-to-study-water-on-moon.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The American space agency NASA is preparing to launch a spacecraft to seek more detailed information on water sources on the moon.</p>
<p>The spacecraft is an orbiter called Lunar Trailblazer. It is set to launch later this year, or in early 2025. A SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket will carry the orbiter to space. That rocket will also transport another moon exploring spacecraft.</p>
<p>In a recent statement, NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.jpl.nasa.gov/news/how-nasas-lunar-trailblazer-could-decipher-the-moons-icy-secrets/">said</a> Lunar Trailblazer passed a series of important operational tests. It is currently completing additional software testing designed to <strong>simulate</strong> different elements of the trip, or mission.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This artist's concept shows NASA's Lunar Trailblazer in lunar orbit about 100 kilometers from the surface of the Moon. The 200 kilogram spacecraft measures about 3.5 meters wide with its solar equipment open. (Image Credit: Lockheed Martin Space/NASA)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1e8e8542-b126-41b7-8ef9-5de7b928f5b9_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This artist's concept shows NASA's Lunar Trailblazer in lunar orbit about 100 kilometers from the surface of the Moon. The 200 kilogram spacecraft measures about 3.5 meters wide with its solar equipment open. (Image Credit: Lockheed Martin Space/NASA)</span></div>
<p>NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL) is leading the mission, in cooperation with the California Institute of Technology (Caltech) in Pasadena, California. Lockheed Martin Space provided the spacecraft, linked it with the flight system, and supports operations as part of a contract with Caltech.</p>
<p>The spacecraft will use two science instruments to carry out its mission. Both instruments are designed to map the moon in search of areas containing water, as well as what forms the water is in. The two instruments use infrared technology to produce highly detailed mapped images.</p>
<p>Lunar Trailblazer weighs about 200 kilograms and measures 3.5 meters with its solar equipment fully deployed. The spacecraft is set to orbit the moon about 100 kilometers from the lunar surface.</p>
<p>Several past studies have provided strong evidence that water exists on the moon. But the evidence has not included exact details on where it is and what forms it might take. Scientists believe most of the water is solid, in the form of ice. But there could be areas where water exists in liquid form, or as a gas in the atmosphere.</p>
<p>One <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.21voa.com/a/study-water-sources-on-moon-more-widespread-than-thought/7800840.html">study</a> released last month suggested that existing water on the moon is more widespread than previously thought. That study was based on new examinations of data collected by India's Chandrayaan-1 orbiting spacecraft.</p>
<p>NASA has said its search for water on the moon is important because it is seen as a necessary resource for future exploration activities. Astronauts could process it for drinking water, to cool equipment, to create breathable oxygen or even to make rocket fuel.</p>
<p>NASA said Lunar Trailblazer will make it easier for future human or robotic science investigators to use the water to see where it first came from.</p>
<p>For example, the presence of ammonia in ice could suggest it came from <strong>comets</strong>, NASA said. The presence of sulfur, on the other hand, could show it rose to the surface from deep inside the lunar interior when the moon was young and volcanically active.</p>
<p>One of the instruments, the High-resolution Volatiles and Minerals Moon Mapper, was developed by the JPL. The other, called the Lunar Thermal Mapper, was built by a team at the University of Oxford in Britain.</p>
<p>Neil Bowles is an instrument scientist for the Lunar Thermal Mapper. He said in a statement the instrument would center on producing detailed maps of lunar surface temperatures. He added that the other instrument will look for a series of signs, called signatures, of water molecules.</p>
<p>“Both instruments will <strong>allow</strong> us to understand how surface temperature affects water, improving our knowledge of the presence and <strong>distribution</strong> of these molecules on the moon,” Bowles said.</p>
<p>The orbiter is designed to provide scientists with new information about how much movement there is of water molecules on the moon. Such movements can be linked to how much sun specific areas receive. “Understanding whether water molecules move freely across the surface of the moon or are locked inside rock is also scientifically important,” NASA said in a statement.</p>
<p>Rachel Klima is an investigator for the Lunar Trailblazer spacecraft and its systems at the Johns Hopkins Applied Physics Laboratory in Laurel, Maryland.</p>
<p>She said data collected by the instruments can help provide information about where the moon's water first came from. Klima compared such examinations to those involving <strong>glaciers</strong> that help scientists learn about Earth's ancient history. Ice on the moon, she said, “could provide <strong>clues</strong> as to where that water came from and how and when it got there.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from NASA. </em></p>
<p><strong>_________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>simulate </strong><em>– v. </em>to do or make something that behaves or looks like something real but is not</p>
<p><strong>comet </strong><em>– n.</em> an object in space that leaves a bright line behind it in the sky</p>
<p><strong>allow </strong><em>– v. </em>to permit<em> </em></p>
<p><strong>distribute </strong><em>– v. </em>to give something out to people or places</p>
<p><strong>glacier </strong><em>– n.</em> a large mass of ice that moves very slowly, usually down a hill or valley</p>
<p><strong>clue </strong><em>– n.</em> a sign or a piece of information that helps to solve a problem or answer a question</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Climate Extremes Continue, Bringing Floods to Spain (2024/11/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/climate-extremes-continue-bringing-floods-to-spain.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Even for a period of extreme weather, this autumn has had more than the usual weather disasters.</p>
<p>The Spanish province Valencia has seen the latest incident of massive and deadly flooding in Europe. Heavy downpours also hit France, Austria and Czechia this fall. Italy has had two major floods, once in September and then again in October.</p>
<p>More than 200 people have been killed in the flooding in Spain. At the same time, over half of the United States experiences an almost rain-free October.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Damaged cars are seen along a road affected by torrential rains that caused flooding, on the outskirts of Valencia, Spain, October 31, 2024. (REUTERS/Eva Manez)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/c43a90b7-3b6a-493b-960c-8bbefb845afb_cx0_cy5_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Damaged cars are seen along a road affected by torrential rains that caused flooding, on the outskirts of Valencia, Spain, October 31, 2024. (REUTERS/Eva Manez)</span></div>
<p>Scientists studying the recent weather say the heavy rains are probably connected to climate change in two ways. They say a warmer atmosphere holds and then releases more <strong>moisture</strong>. The other connection is possible changes in the jet stream that could cause extreme weather. The jet stream is the river of air above land that moves weather systems around the planet.</p>
<p>Several climate scientists and <strong>meteorologists</strong> said the immediate cause of the flooding is a cut-off lower pressure storm system that came from an unusually wavy and slowed jet stream.</p>
<p>In the United States, the slow movement caused a sunny, high-pressure system with no moisture to cover the country and keep storms away.</p>
<p>"If we're getting all the dryness, somebody else is getting all the rain," said Yale Climate Connection meteorologist Jeff Masters, co-founder of Weather Underground.</p>
<p>"The same extremely wavy jet stream that is causing the U.S. <strong>drought</strong> is also responsible for the horrific flooding in eastern Spain," said climate scientist Jennifer Francis. She is with the Woodwell Climate Research Center in Cape Cod, Massachusetts.</p>
<p>Francis is an early developer of the theory that connects a wavier and slower-moving jet stream to climate change. The theory is that the Arctic is warming so much; it is now not much colder than the rest of the planet. That theory is gaining more acceptance, but it is not fully accepted by the climate science community.</p>
<p>Climate scientist Erich Fischer is with the university ETH Zurich in Switzerland. He does not fully accept the wavy jet stream theory. But then he lists the storm systems that have slowed and flooded Europe this fall: one in France and two in Italy in September and October and flooding in Austria and the Czech Republic in September.</p>
<p>And then there were the October floods in the Balkans, although Fischer said he is not sure they are similar enough. The European climate service Copernicus says parts of Poland, Germany and the Czech Republic got three months of rain in just five days in September.</p>
<p>Fischer also spoke of the floods in Europe during the summer. "Starting with Bavaria, southern Germany in June, and then it was something like six events in Austria and Switzerland in the mountains, extreme thunderstorms, and now this autumn.”</p>
<p>He said it was an unusual period in which the systems, especially in Spain, France and Austria, stopped in one place and "the rain did not move" from the same valleys for hours.</p>
<p>Even without the changes to the jet stream, several scientists said they are sure that basic <strong>physics</strong> are making storms like this wetter.</p>
<p>It holds that every degree Celsius the air warms, it can hold seven percent more moisture. The world has warmed 1.3 degrees Celsius because of greenhouse gases, so it has about nine to 10 percent heavier rain, at the least, said Imperial College London climate scientist Friederike Otto. She helps run an organization called World Weather Attribution. It checks for human causes of extreme weather, sometimes finding them, sometimes not.</p>
<p>She said it is very clear that climate change is linked to the rain event in Valencia.</p>
<p>The Mediterranean Sea had its warmest surface temperature on record in mid-August, with a mean temperature of 28.47 Celsius, said Carola Koenig of the Centre for Flood Risk and Resilience at Brunel University of London.</p>
<p>She said that means more moisture is in the air, “resulting in more rain when the atmosphere starts to cool in the autumn.” She warned there may be more heavy rain after this week's storm.</p>
<p>There may be different ways of counting and <strong>attributing</strong> climate change and the problems it causes, Otto said, but one thing is for certain: "Burning fossil fuels causes climate change and climate change causes death and destruction."</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter. And I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Seth Borenstein reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>jet stream</strong> – <em>n</em>. a strong current of fast winds high above the Earth's surface</p>
<p><strong>moisture</strong> – <em>n</em>. a small amount of a liquid (such as water) that makes something wet or moist</p>
<p><strong>meteorologist</strong> – <em>n</em>. a science that deals with the atmosphere and with weather</p>
<p><strong>drought</strong> –<em> n</em>. a period with no rain</p>
<p><strong>physics </strong><em>– n. </em>a science that deals with matter and energy and the way they act on each other in heat, light, electricity, and sound</p>
<p><strong>attribute </strong> - <em>v. </em>to say that (something) is because of (someone or something)</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>At 2.4 Meters, Rioux Is World’s Tallest Teenager (2024/11/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/at-2-4-meters-rioux-is-world-s-tallest-teenager.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Hai Do</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>Canadian Olivier Rioux is the world's tallest teenager.</p>
<p>At 2.4 meters tall, he has a place in the Guinness World Records as the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/news/2021/9/canadian-confirmed-as-tallest-teenager-in-the-world-675836">world's tallest living teenager</a>.</p>
<p>Soon, he will make basketball history when he plays for the University of Florida.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Olivier Rioux, back center, a 2.4-meter-tall college basketball player at Florida, gathers with coaches and teammates at the team's practice, Friday, Oct. 18, 2024, in Gainesville, Fla. (AP Photo/John Raoux)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/ae79c81c-0bd5-42b3-9451-54f2ab3aadda_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Olivier Rioux, back center, a 2.4-meter-tall college basketball player at Florida, gathers with coaches and teammates at the team's practice, Friday, Oct. 18, 2024, in Gainesville, Fla. (AP Photo/John Raoux)</span></div>
<p>Known as “Oli,” he will become the tallest person to play college basketball. Rioux is about 5 centimeters taller than former professional basketball players in the National Basketball Association (NBA) like Gheorghe Muresan and Manute Bol. And he is nearly 8 centimeters taller than former NBA player Yao Ming of China.</p>
<p>When he walks from his college housing to classes at the University of Florida, Rioux stops a lot -- sometimes hundreds of times a day -- to take pictures with people.</p>
<p>“You don't have a single three seconds to yourself when you're outside, which I was fine with because my brother and my dad are tall. And, as a family, we used to go out. That's just how it was, and you can't change that because people are <strong>curious,</strong>” Rioux said.</p>
<p>His college teammates have already gotten used to it.</p>
<p>“It's really weird looking up to someone,” said teammate Micah Handlogten who is 2.2 meters tall. “People normally ask me, ‘You're so tall. Do you play basketball?' No one says a word to me (now). Everyone just looks at him. It's kind of crazy. He doesn't <strong>shy away from</strong> it,” he added. </p>
<p>Rioux actually enjoys it. He welcomes the looks, the questions and all the picture requests.</p>
<p>“You just get used to it,” he said. “Talking to people is nice because they are curious, and you can't change that.”</p>
<p>Rioux has worked hard to prepare for college basketball at the top level. The team expects Rioux to be a fan favorite. Coach Todd Golden said, “About 95 percent of my <strong>conversations</strong> with <strong>random</strong> people about our team are about him. It's the first time we've been ranked since 2019 and it's like, ‘Hey, Coach, we're really excited to see Oli out there this year.' And I get it, man. He's a very unique individual.”</p>
<p>Rioux grew up in Terrebonne, Quebec. At an early age, he was already taller than most of his teachers. He was 1.8 meters tall by age 8 and reached more than 2 meters before middle school.</p>
<p>Rioux started playing basketball at age 5. But he is still learning the game at the college level. Rioux can dunk the ball in the basket without leaving his feet. He wears No. 32 because of his affection for former NBA greats Magic Johnson and Shaquille O'Neal, another 2-meter-tall player.</p>
<p>Rioux would like to model his game after French superstar Victor Wembanyama.</p>
<p>Most people have the same reaction when seeing Rioux for the first time. Just about every picture taken of him goes viral.</p>
<p>“He doesn't seek the attention, but he also doesn't get annoyed at the people that ask,” teammate Handlogten said. “He <strong>embraces</strong> it because it's part of him, and he loves that...”</p>
<p>I'm Ashley Thompson.</p>
<p><em>Mark Long reported this story for The Associated Press. Hai Do adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>curious</strong> - adj. having desire to learn</p>
<p><strong>shy away from</strong> - <em>phrasal verb</em>, to try to avoid (something) because of nervousness, fear, dislike, etc.</p>
<p><strong>conversation</strong> - n. a talk involved two or more people</p>
<p><strong>random</strong> - adj. done without a particular pattern</p>
<p><strong>embrace</strong> - v. to accept something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>For When You Do Something Wrong: Mea Culpa (2024/11/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/for-when-you-do-something-wrong-mea-culpa.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories</em> from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>We all make mistakes. So, we have the expression <u>to err is human</u>.</p>
<p>People who accept responsibility or blame will often say “I'm sorry,” or “I was wrong.” Others might say, "It's my fault” or “I apologize." Often friends use expressions like “That was on me” or “My bad.”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Pope Francis apologizes to Indigenous peoples for abuses committed by missionaries during a visit at Maskwaci, the former Ermineskin Residential School, Monday, July 25, 2022, in Maskwacis, Alberta. In other words, he offered a mea culpa. (AP Photo/Eric Gay/File photo)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/31fb9d01-d1a7-4b5a-b417-298ba1d91db5_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Pope Francis apologizes to Indigenous peoples for abuses committed by missionaries during a visit at Maskwaci, the former Ermineskin Residential School, Monday, July 25, 2022, in Maskwacis, Alberta. In other words, he offered a mea culpa. (AP Photo/Eric Gay/File photo)</span></div>
<p>But there is another way to say that you accept responsibility or admit that you made a mistake. Some English speakers may say <u>mea culpa</u>.</p>
<p>If that does not sound like English, that's because it isn't.</p>
<p>American dictionary publisher <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/mea%20culpa"><em>Merriam-Webster</em> says</a> that <u>mea culpa</u> means "through my fault" in Latin. The phrase comes from a prayer of <strong>confession</strong> in the Catholic Church. By itself, the expression is used to mean "It was my fault" or "I apologize."</p>
<p><u>Mea culpa</u> is also a noun.</p>
<p>People caught doing something wrong often give, or issue, a <u>mea culpa</u>. For example, when an official is caught doing something wrong, she might issue a statement that includes a <u>mea culpa</u>.</p>
<p>Let's hear an example:</p>
<p><em>The mayor's <u>mea culpa</u> did not change the minds of voters, and she lost the election.</em></p>
<p><u>Mea culpa</u> is one of many English terms that come from the Latin word <u>culpa</u> which means guilt. Other examples include <strong>culpable</strong>, <strong>culprit,</strong> and <strong>exculpate</strong>.</p>
<p>When someone deserves blame for something, especially something harmful, we say he is <u>culpable</u> for the outcomes. For example:</p>
<p><em>Investigators said that the carmaker was <u>culpable</u> for thousands of accidents because of faulty brakes.</em></p>
<p>A <u>culprit</u> is a person guilty of a crime or a fault. That is why police officers often call a person guilty of crime a <u>culprit</u>.</p>
<p>And the word <u>exculpate</u> means to clear someone from suspected fault or guilt. Here's an example:</p>
<p><em>The husband was <u>exculpated</u> of his wife's death when she was found alive living in Paris under a fake name. </em></p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>.</p>
<p>Until next time ... I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Stories</h2>
<p><strong>confession </strong><em>– n. </em>a statement admitting guilt<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>culpable </strong><em>– adj. </em>meriting condemnation or blame especially as wrong or harmful</p>
<p><strong>culprit </strong><em>– n. </em>one accused of or charged with a crime</p>
<p><strong>exculpate </strong><em>– v. </em>to clear from alleged fault or guilt</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>In Burundi, Women Learn Old Way to Say Hello (2024/11/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202411/in-burundi-women-learn-an-old-way-to-say-hello.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 November, 2024</span><br/>
<p>The <strong>hug</strong> between the two women lasted a long time.</p>
<p>An 85-year-old woman put her arms around a younger woman she had not seen for months. She asked her a series of questions in a song-like way.</p>
<p><em>How are you? How is your husband? How are the kids? How are your cows? Are you on good terms with your neighbors?</em></p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/d3fa0568-86ae-45de-b6a6-f8336aa3465e_cx7_cy4_cw88_w100_r1.png"/></div>
<p>Prudencienne Namukobwa stopped the song to permit the younger woman to answer. The pattern is familiar to her because she has been doing it for many years.</p>
<p>"Ego," Emelyne Nzeyimana answered over and over in the local Kirundi language. "Yes."</p>
<p>The two women were performing a greeting of their ancestors.</p>
<p>A group of neighbors watched with surprise. Many were seeing their first performance of the traditional form of musical greeting, known to Burundians as <em>akazehe</em>. It is performed only by women.</p>
<p><em>Akazehe</em> is becoming less common. But cultural officials, teachers and others say the greeting is worth keeping.</p>
<p>During disease outbreaks, public health officials urged people to limit close contact. Such recommendations affected the greeting.</p>
<p>Among young people in Burundi, it is hard to find those who know what <em>akazehe</em> means. It is even harder to find someone who can perform it.</p>
<p>Sandrine Kitonze is a culture advisor in the office of the governor of Ngozi province. She said people stopped doing the greeting, even though <em>akazehe</em> "made you feel that the person who greets you loves you."</p>
<p>Some experts have noted <em>akazehe</em> could help lead to a feeling of unity in Burundi. The country is now largely peaceful following a period of deadly civil war and political unrest.</p>
<p>Annonciate Baragahorana is a teacher in the province of Bujumbura. She told the Associated Press that when she visited the central plateau area as a young girl, she was surprised and a little uneasy when women hugged and greeted her in this song-like way. "I wanted her to finish quickly, even if it was sweet words to hear."</p>
<p>Baragahorana said she feared <em>akazehe</em> may disappear because of the fear of spreading diseases. Now, she said, "people greet each other from a distance.”</p>
<p>Namukobwa lives in Ngozi a hilly province in Burundi's north. On a recent morning, she was sitting on a mat outside when she saw Nzeyimana, the visiting daughter of a former neighbor. She rose and welcomed the woman as if she were her own daughter.</p>
<p>"I felt that the first love she had when I was just a girl is kept until now," said Nzeyimana, a broadcaster in Ngozi. "This means that I am still her daughter."</p>
<p>Isaac Nikobiba is an <strong>anthropologist</strong> in Bujumbura. He said a custom such as <em>akazehe</em> should be kept <strong>at all costs</strong> because of its role in protecting families. Among communities that practice it, women could tell elder women about any problems at home. That could bring support from the extended family, he said.</p>
<p>Nikobiba said the threat to <em>akazehe</em> is part of other effects of modernization.</p>
<p>He explained how the custom worked to help younger women. "Normally, before starting a home in traditional Burundi, the girl would first receive advice from her father's sister. She would tell the girl, 'I will come to greet you after a certain time.'”</p>
<p>Nikobiba added that during that greeting, the young woman could report any problems. Support from elders would help them develop better mental health for the young family, he said.</p>
<p>Floride Ntakirutimana was among the small group of women who gathered to watch Namukobwa greeting Nzeyimana. She said she grew up in a farming community where no mother could perform <em>akazehe</em>. She only heard of it through radio programs.</p>
<p>After watching, she wanted to learn <em>akazehe</em> herself. "I feel better, Ntakirutimana said, “and I saw that it was good.”</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Rodney Muhumuza and Gaspard Maheburwa </em><em>reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>hug</strong> – <em>n. </em>the act of putting your arms around someone or something as a way of showing love or friendship</p>
<p><strong>greeting</strong> –<em> n</em>. something that is said or done to show people that you are happy to meet or see them</p>
<p><strong>plateau</strong> – n. a large flat area of land that is higher than other areas of land that surround it</p>
<p><strong>anthropologist</strong> – <em>n.</em> a person who studies human races, origins, societies, and cultures</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
