<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>VOA Special English</title>
        <link>https://www.21voa.com/special_english/</link>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <itunes:category>ESL</itunes:category>
        <itunes:author>VOA</itunes:author>
        <description>美国之音（以下称VOA）的英语节目，按播音速度可分为两种：Standard English （标准英语）和 Special English（特别英语）。

Special English 又叫“慢速英语”，是VOA 专为全世界非英语国家初学英语的听众安排的一种简易、规范的英语广播节目。该节目创始于50年代末期，是VOA 的专家们研究如何与世界各地的英语学习者进行交际的产物。它正式开播于1959年10月。当时只面向欧洲和中东，但由于这个节目适合许多国家英语学习者的需要，所以它的广播对象不久就扩大到世界其他地区，并很快在全世界范围内产生了广泛的影响。现在这个节目对欧洲、非洲和拉丁美洲每晚广播一次，对加勒比地区每晚广播一次（星期天除外），对东南亚广播次数最多，每天上午两次，晚上三次。

30多年来，VOA 为了办好Special English节目，进行了大量的调查研究工作，对播音速度、内容及用词范围都作了具体规定，基本上达到了既能为英语学习者提供信息，又不损害英语本身风格的目的，使之成为VOA 独具特色，拥有最大量听众的节目。

美国著名词汇学家S. B. Flexmer 指明了Special English的三条标准，也就是它所“特别”的地方：

1、它是一种由美国人最常用的1500个基本单词为主体构成的美国英语；

2、它用简短、明晰的句子写作和广播；

3、它以每分钟90个单词的速度，即2/3的Standard English（标准英语）速度进行广播。

Special English的节目可分为两大类：一类是新闻节目；一类是专题节目。

1．新闻节目

VOA Special English 的新闻广播向听众提供世界范围内的政治、经济、军事、外交、国际关系、宗教、天气以及各种重大事件和珍闻奇事等各个方面的信息，每天向东南亚地区广播五次，早上两次，晚上三次，每逢半点播出。

Special English新闻节目每次长约十分钟，大都播出十条左右新闻，近一千个单词，每条新闻多为一分钟，但偶尔也有长达两分钟的要闻。除头条新闻外，每条新闻都由一个电头引导，这样显得结构分明，条理清晰，适宜初学英语的人收听。在节目结束之前，播音员常常用三四句话重播其中三条新闻的提要以加深听众对要闻的印象。

Special English新闻中70%左右的内容与同时整点播出的Standard English新闻相同，但相同新闻的先后次序有所变动。每次节目的开头和结尾大同小异，格式比较固定。

2．专题节目（一）

Special English的专题节目（Feature Programs）,从时间上看，可分为两大类：一是每五分钟一次的专题，二是每十五分钟一次的专题。本节先介绍每项五分钟一次的专题材节目。

Special English五分钟一次的专题材节目安排在Special English新闻节目之后和（或）每十五分钟一次的专题材节目之前播出，每星期播七次。根据内容，可分为三个小类，即：Science Report（科学报道），逢星期一、三、五播出，每天播六遍；Agriculture Report（农业报道），逢星期二、四播出，每天播六遍；Words And Their Stories（词语掌故），逢星期六和星期天播出，每天播五遍。这三个专题材各具特色，具有相对的独立性，听众每听完一个节目，都会获得一个完整的印象。

Science Report（科学报道）这一专题材节目每周向听众介绍三篇有关现代科学技术最新发展情况的报道，涉及物理、化学、天文至高无上理、生物、环卫、心理、教育、医学和计算机等方面。适宜理工科大学生和科技工作者收集信息，积累资料，学习科技英语。

Agriculture Report（农业报道） Agriculture Report是为农业科技工作者和生产者安排的一个专题。它专门报道世界各国，特别是美国现代农业生产的最新成文汇报总务科 学家对农业生产某一方面的研究进展，以及他们对影响农业生产的某一自然现象进行分析和研究的近况。此外，它还经常向听众介绍发展中国家家业生产的一些有益经验等内容。

Words And Their Stories（词语掌故）这一专题节目，旨在向学习英语的听众介绍美国英语中生动有趣的词语和惯用法，并从科学研究和通俗词源学的角度来解释它们的含意、产生的背景及其在使用过程中的演变情况等。它通过讲故事的形式讲解每一个词语。这是VOA Special English中的优秀节目之一，是学习美国英语的极好材料。通过收听这一节目，听众不仅能学到娓娓动听的掌故和地道的美国英语，而且能增加美国的社会文化背景知识，历史传统与现状的了解。

VOA 为了更好地办好这个节目，便于听众收听学习，于1978年编辑出版了一本名为Words And Their Stories的书，共收集一百篇故事，作者是Herbert Sutcliffe, Harold Bermen 及VOA 该节目的部分编辑人员。在每次的实际广播中，播音员都以此书为蓝本，再根据需要对原稿进行适当增删。按每周两个故事计算，此书的一百个故事还不能满足一年的播音需要。于是编辑们就是重播部分词语掌故的同时，不断增加许多新的词语掌故，及时将词源学家的最新研究成果和不断增加的新词汇介绍给听众。收听实践证明，初学者在收听过程中必然会遇到许多人名、地名和一些较难的句子，有时甚至在听完之后还很难理解所播词语的确切含义及其汉语意思，为此，听众可参看1983年由中国对外翻译出版公司出版的该书英汉对照本中的有关部分。

3．专题节目（二）

VOA Special English的专题节目，除上节谈的五分钟一次的以外，还有本节要介绍的每十五分钟一次的节目。这类节目共有七个不同的小专题，以星期为单位循环，每天分四次复播出一个专题，但星期日和星期六的两个专题材每晚只播三遍，每次节目约十分钟，继每次五分钟的专题节目之后播出。

这类专题节目的基本结构是，在特定的伴声中先报告当次节目的名称，并扼要介绍其主要内容，然后播送节目正文。最后，在伴乐声中报告节目主持人和撰稿人的姓名，以邀请听众在下周的这个时间继续收听该节目而结束。

People in America（美国人物志） 这是有关美国历史名人的一个专题节目，每逢星期天晚上播出。它向听众介绍在美国历史上产生过重大影响、起过重要作用、作出了突出贡献的科学、文学、政治、或其他各方面的历史人物。节目一般都对他们的生平事迹进行简要的叙述，对其贡献作出评介，类似人物小传。有的重要人物事迹很多，必须用两次或几次的节目时间进行联播。对这样的节目要坚持收听，才会获得完整的印象。

TThis is America（今日美国） This Is America向听众介绍美国人民的生活、学习、工作和娱乐情况，是英语学习者解美国社会的一条渠道。该专题大都一个节目一个整体，每逢星期一晚播出。

Science in the News（科学新闻） 这一专题材主要对新近的科学技术新闻进行综述或摘要广播。向听众介绍世界各国在自然、医学、疾病、原子能、航天等方面的科研动态、成果、突破性进展及存在的困难。涉及当今世界人们普遍关心的重大问题，如核事故、航天飞机爆炸、自然灾害、环境污染和爱滋病等等。每逢星期二播出，每次播一到五条新闻摘要。

Explorations（自然探索） 每逢星期三晚上，听众可以收听到Explorations这一专题节目。该专题既涉及人类遨游太空、探索原子、研究自身、改造自然的现代技术，也报道发展中国家开发新资源，利用新工艺改善人民生活等方面的成就，其侧重点在各种科技实验和简易实用技术方面。该节目一般安排一段时间播一个系列，每次播出一个主题，以便能将某项新技术的研究和应用的全过程介绍给听众，电台还乐意为感兴趣的听众提供所需的文字材料。

The Making of a Nation（建国史话） 这一专题节目向听众介绍美利坚合众国从十三个殖民地区域到现代工业国的孕育、诞生以及形成超级大国的历史过程，并以历史为线索，特定的历史时期为单位，以重大的历史事件为主题材来叙述各个党派、各届总统和政府的历史作用与贡献。这是每个英语学习者都应了解的基本知识。The Making of a Nation每逢星期四播出。这是个系列节目，坚持收听，则有助于系统了解美国的历史概况。

American Mosaic（美国万花筒） American Mosaic是一个radio magazine（广播杂志）节目。该节目题材广泛、内容丰，展示着美国社会文化生活中比较轻松愉快的生活画面；听众收听该节目就如同在阅读一本图文并茂的杂志。它每次有三到五个小节目，涉及音乐、图书、技术和教育等方面的内容。我们既可以从中欣赏到著名歌唱的优秀歌曲，对美国音乐有所了解，又可以获取一些生动有趣的现代美国社会生活知识，随着播音员那亲切悦耳的声音步入美国风景如画的大好河山；同时还能听到世界各地的听众提出的有关英语语方文学等方面的问题和电台的解答。

American Stories（美国故事） 这一专题材节目安排在每星期六晚上播出。这样能使听众在学习和工作之余，得以轻松一下头脑。我们可以通过这一美国文学的“窗口”，接触各种流派、各类名家的文学作品。了解美国英语的时代特色，欣赏、学习美国人民运用语方的技巧，并从那些佳作名篇中获得艺术享受。该节目对短篇故事采取一次播一篇的方式，对中、长篇小说则先进行简写加工，再分几次播出全文。在播出故事正文之前，播音员常常先介绍故事的主要情节。对需要分几次节目时间播出的中长篇，在播第二或以后各部分之前，主持人还先重述已播部分的故事梗概，以唤起听众的回忆，使故事听起来更加连贯。</description>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          <item>
            <title>What Does It Take to Be a 'Power Couple'?  (2025/2/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/what-does-it-take-to-be-a-power-couple.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>In American English, we use many expressions to describe when two people have a lot of similarities or are very close. Here are some examples.</p>
<p>If we say two people are <u>joined at the hip,</u> they are nearly always together. If we describe individuals as <u>thick as thieves</u>, it means they are very close. People considered <u>two peas in a pod</u> have many things in common. And we use the term <u>kindred spirits</u> to describe people who often share the same opinions and interests.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Tara Davis-Woodhall and husband Hunter Woodhall kiss after she won the silver medal for the U.S. in the women's long jump final at the World Athletics Championships in Hungary, Aug. 20, 2023. They have been called track and field's power couple. (AP Photo/Matthias Schrader, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/837bc8a7-a6c0-47de-8456-b5adc25c909d_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Tara Davis-Woodhall and husband Hunter Woodhall kiss after she won the silver medal for the U.S. in the women's long jump final at the World Athletics Championships in Hungary, Aug. 20, 2023. They have been called track and field's power couple. (AP Photo/Matthias Schrader, File)</span></div>
<p>These expressions can represent people who grew closer for different reasons. Maybe they <strong>complemented</strong> each other well in certain ways. Or maybe their situations brought them together for the purpose of completing something important or meaningful.</p>
<p>But today we are going to discuss a very special kind of relationship – one that involves two people who are <strong>romantically</strong> involved and very successful.</p>
<p>People in such relationships can be described as <u>power couples</u>.</p>
<p>There are many examples of famous power couples, including successful movie stars, musicians and others in the performing arts. But power couples can exist in many other industries and communities, as well. And, the two people do not have to work in the same industry.</p>
<p>If they do, however, that can make them even more powerful. For example, a well-known <strong>architect</strong> who builds homes could be partnered with a famous designer who <strong>decorates</strong> them. Or, one person in a power couple may be a music producer, while the other is a famous singer.</p>
<p>Even though power couples involve highly successful people, one person could describe their partner as <u>their better half</u>. This is a way to <strong>compliment </strong>their “other half” in the relationship. For example, one might say during a meeting with a friend, “Hello! How are you? And more importantly, how is your better half?”</p>
<p>Now, let's hear two friends use some of these expressions.</p>
<p><em>A: Hey, I'm not used to seeing you alone. Where's your <strong>sidekick</strong>?</em></p>
<p><em>B: Huh? Who are you talking about?</em></p>
<p><em>A: Ben. You guys have been joined at the hip for weeks. Looks like you're thick as thieves. </em></p>
<p><em>B: Well, the project is pretty important for the company. So, we're putting in a lot of hours. </em></p>
<p><em>A: Are you becoming kindred spirits from working so much together?</em></p>
<p><em>B: No. It's just keeping us both very busy. </em></p>
<p><em>A: Busy trying to become the new power couple in the office?</em></p>
<p><em>B: What are you talking about?? We're not thick as thieves or kindred spirits, and we're definitely not a power couple. We are just working hard on the same project! </em></p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>. Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>complement</strong> <em>-n. </em>something that fills up, completes, or makes better or perfect : <em>-v. </em>to complete or enhance by providing something additional</p>
<p><strong>romantically </strong><em>-adv. </em>done in a way that relates or is associated with love<em> </em>: <strong>romantic </strong><em>-adv. </em>of, relating to, or associated with love</p>
<p><strong>architect</strong> <em>-n. </em>a person who designs buildings and advises in their construction</p>
<p><strong>decorate</strong> <em>-v. </em>to make more attractive by adding something that is beautiful or becoming</p>
<p><strong>compliment</strong> <em>-n</em>. an expression of respect, affection, or admiration : <em>-v. </em>to make an expression of respect, affection, or admiration</p>
<p><strong>sidekick</strong> <em>-n. </em>a person closely associated with another as a subordinate or partner</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Norway Nears Goal to Sell only Electric New Cars  (2025/2/9)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/norway-nears-goal-to-sell-only-electric-new-cars.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">08 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Norway is very close to meeting its goal of selling only fully electric new vehicles starting this year.</p>
<p>The Norwegian Road Federation (OFV), an automotive industry group, estimates that nearly 96 percent of new cars registered in Norway in January were all-electric. No other country has such a high rate of electric car (EV) ownership.</p>
<p>The OFV noted that of the 9,343 new cars sold last month in Norway, 8,954 of them were all-electric. Of the 50 most-sold models, only two were non-electric. The first of those came in 33rd place among the 50 models, the federation said.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE: Electric cars are charged via a charging station on a street in the Norwegian capital Oslo on September 25, 2024. " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/8a75879d-727f-4cd8-ab54-b6b3e446d6da_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE: Electric cars are charged via a charging station on a street in the Norwegian capital Oslo on September 25, 2024. </span></div>
<p>The European Automobile Manufacturers' Association (ACEA) reported the share of electric cars in Europe was just 13.6 percent during 2024. That was the first recorded decrease since 2020.</p>
<p>OFV director Oyvind Solberg Thorsen said in a statement, "We've never seen this before...If the rest of the year continues like this, we will very soon be close to the 2025 goal." He noted that reaching 100 percent of the goal means to continue to offer the “<strong>incentives</strong> that make it profitable to choose an electric car over other models.”</p>
<p>Even though it is a major oil and gas producer, Norway aims to only sell "zero <strong>emission</strong>" new vehicles starting in 2025. That goal is 10 years ahead of the target set by the European Union (EU). Norway is not a member of the EU.</p>
<p>One difference between the EU and Norway's method is that Norway has not banned the sale of cars with engines that burn fuel. Instead, Norway offers a number of tax breaks to EV manufacturers and owners. On the other hand, the country heavily taxes gas-powered vehicles.</p>
<p>For example, Norwegian EV owners do not have to pay road<strong> tolls</strong> and receive free parking in public car parks. EVs are also permitted to use parts of roads normally saved for public transportation vehicles.</p>
<p><strong>Chargers everywhere</strong></p>
<p>While some tax breaks and incentives have been reduced over the years, EVs have still kept expanding across Norwegian roads.</p>
<p>Frode Hvattum is a 50-year-old father of three who owns two EVs. He told the French News Agency AFP he started buying EVs because of his concern for the environment and for the <strong>benefits</strong> of driving them.</p>
<p>He lives in an area near Oslo where the streets are full of Teslas, Audis and Volkswagens. Some less costly Chinese EVs are increasingly appearing too.</p>
<p>Many homes have a device to charge, or supply electricity to, their EV's <strong>battery</strong>. Norway also has a large national network of superfast charging stations.</p>
<p>Having a nationwide charging network was important for Hvattum, who, like many Norwegians, often travels by car to his second home in the mountains several hours outside Oslo. He said he finds it easy to plan and make trips with numerous charging stations available.</p>
<p>"You don't have to plan your trip as much as before," Hvattum said. He added that he uses the 15-to-20-minute charging breaks his vehicle needs to make it up to the mountains to shop for food.</p>
<p><strong>Meeting its goal</strong></p>
<p>Even if EV sales fail to meet the 100 percent mark this year, experts say Norway can still be seen as having met its goal.</p>
<p>Christina Bu heads the Norwegian Electric Vehicle Association. She told AFP, "We should finish the year at between 95 and 100 percent."</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Pierre-Henry Deshayes reported this story for Agence France-Presse.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>incentive</strong> – <em>n</em>. something that urges a person to act in a particular way</p>
<p><strong>emission</strong> <em>– n.</em> harmful substances released into the air by automobiles or factories burning oil or coal</p>
<p><strong>toll</strong> – <em>n</em>. an amount of money that you are required to pay for the use of a road or bridge</p>
<p><strong>benefit</strong> – <em>n</em>. a good result or effect</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What is the Super Bowl?  (2025/2/8)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/what-is-the-super-bowl.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By VOA</span><br/><span class="datetime">07 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>This Sunday, February 9, is not a holiday in the United States, but it might seem like one to Americans.</p>
<p>Many will be attending parties to watch Super Bowl LIX. The Super Bowl is the championship game of professional American football.</p>
<p>The National Football League, or NFL, has 32 teams mainly based in large cities across the U.S.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Kansas City Chiefs place kicker Harrison Butker (7) kicks the game-winning field goal in the second half of the NFL Super Bowl 57 football game, against the Philadelphia Eagles Sunday, Feb. 12, 2023, in Glendale, Ariz. (AP Photo/David J. Phillip, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/96945554-e6ae-401d-8bbd-0b73a46cc8d0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Kansas City Chiefs place kicker Harrison Butker (7) kicks the game-winning field goal in the second half of the NFL Super Bowl 57 football game, against the Philadelphia Eagles Sunday, Feb. 12, 2023, in Glendale, Ariz. (AP Photo/David J. Phillip, File)</span></div>
<p>The first professional <strong>league</strong> was formed in 1920, when representatives of four teams met in Canton, Ohio. The group first called itself the American Professional Football Association but changed the name two years later to the National Football League.</p>
<p>In 1960, Texas businessman Lamar Hunt pushed the effort to create the American Football League, or AFL. The two leagues competed with each other to sign top football players from universities around the country.</p>
<p>In 1965, established NFL players began negotiating to play for the competing league. So, officials of the two leagues decided to work together. This agreement established a championship game between the two leagues. It was officially called the AFL-NFL World Championship Game but became known as the Super Bowl.</p>
<p>The first Super Bowl was played in 1967 in Los Angeles, California. The Green Bay Packers defeated the Kansas City Chiefs. It was not a very <strong>exciting</strong> game. Many of the seats in the sports center were empty. That changed with the Super Bowl played two years later. Experts say the public finally accepted the new league when the New York Jets defeated the Baltimore Colts.</p>
<p>After that game in 1969, officials of the two leagues decided to create a new National Football League. They divided the teams into two competing conferences, the American Conference, or AFC, and the National Conference, NFC. Each year, the conference champions play in the Super Bowl.</p>
<p>Today, the Super Bowl is a major sporting event. Tens of thousands of people will be watching the game Sunday at the Superdome in New Orleans, Louisiana.</p>
<p>Tens of millions of other people around the world will be watching Super Bowl LIX. They will be watching to see if the AFC Kansas City Chiefs or the NFC Philadelphia Eagles become the champions of American football.</p>
<p>Both teams have had success in the Big Game. The Eagles are one-time NFL champions. They defeated the New England Patriots in Super Bowl LII. This Sunday will be the team's fifth NFL championship game appearance.</p>
<p>The Kansas City Chiefs have played for the championship six times. They have won four times, including the last two Super Bowls. The Chiefs are the first team in NFL history to have a chance to win a third Super Bowl <strong>in a row</strong>.</p>
<p>I'm <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_f4j55Zlw">Caty Weaver.</a></p>
<p><em>Caty Weaver wrote this report for VOA Learning English with contributing information from the Associated Press.</em></p>
<p>____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in this Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>league </strong>–n. sports teams that play each other and are linked by a business agreement and rules</p>
<p><strong>exciting</strong> <em>–adj.</em> something that causes excitement</p>
<p><strong>in a row </strong><em>–phrase</em> one following another in a series</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Regarding and Regardless  (2025/2/8)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/regarding-and-regardless.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">07 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em> we answer a question from Ramatoulaye in Senegal. Here is Ramatoulaye's question:</p>
<p>Dear teacher,</p>
<p>Thank you and all the VOA Learning English team for their great work! My question is: what is the difference between “regarding” and “regardless?”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Ask a Teacher: Regarding and Regardless" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/2593bf3f-7416-4990-8c7b-cdbb32887111_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Ask a Teacher: Regarding and Regardless</span></div>
<p>Thank you for your comments, Ramatoulaye. And I am happy to answer your question.</p>
<p>Both words are very useful in speaking and writing. That's because the words give us a quick way to connect to other ideas.</p>
<p>“Regarding” simply means what someone is talking or writing about. Consider the following two examples:</p>
<p><em>We have all the information we need about the project.</em></p>
<p><em>We have all the information we need regarding the project.</em></p>
<p>The word “regarding” in the second example means the same thing as the preposition “about” in the first example. We generally use the word “about” more than “regarding.” However, it is more common to use “regarding” in formal speech than in informal communication.</p>
<p>Also, the expression “in regard to” means the same thing as “regarding.” Here are some examples:</p>
<p><em><u>In regard to</u></em><em> the price, I think it was too expensive.</em></p>
<p><em><u>In regard to</u></em><em> what you said, I don't think we know all the facts yet.</em></p>
<p>Note that we use a noun, noun phrase, or noun clause after the expression “in regard to.” Also, you will sometimes hear native speakers say “in regards to” instead of “in regard to.”</p>
<p>Here is something you may find interesting when we compare the expression “in regard to” and the verb “regard.” The verb “regard” is a somewhat formal way to say, “look at.” So, just as we can direct someone's attention to something by having them look at it, the expression “in regard to” directs us to something we are talking about.</p>
<p><strong>Regardless</strong></p>
<p>The word “regardless” expresses the idea that one or more things do not affect the current situation or what we want to express now. When you look at the word, you will see that it ends with the suffix <em>-less</em>. This suffix means the same thing as the word “without.” So, “regardless” means “without regard to.”</p>
<p>Consider the following examples.</p>
<p><em><u>Regardless of</u> religion, all people want happiness.</em></p>
<p><em>All people want happiness, <u>regardless of</u> religion.</em></p>
<p>Notice that you can use the word “regardless” either before or after the sentence or phrase it <strong>modifies</strong>.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? Regardless of your level of English, we want to hear from you! Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please let us know where you are from, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>________________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>modify</strong> <em>-v. </em>in grammar, to limit or specify the meaning of another word</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study: Millions of Europeans Could Die from Heat by 2100  (2025/2/7)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/study-millions-of-europeans-could-die-from-heat-by-2100.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">06 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>A new study warns that millions of Europeans could die from heat-related causes by the end of the century.</p>
<p>The study was based on computer <strong>simulations</strong> of predicted climate activity in 854 different European cities. It found that extreme temperatures, mostly heat, could kill as many as 2.3 million people in Europe by 2100.</p>
<p>The researchers said the number of predicted deaths could be reduced if nations are able to find better ways of cutting carbon pollution levels and dealing with extreme heat.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this file photo, people watch a sunset sitting on a beach next to the Trafalgar Lighthouse in Los Ca&lt;I&gt;&amp;#&lt;/I&gt;241;os de Meca, Spain, on, July 29, 2020. (AP Photo/Emilio Morenatti, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/435c5886-5e72-42b0-90d6-6f75aae18b43_cx6_cy17_cw86_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this file photo, people watch a sunset sitting on a beach next to the Trafalgar Lighthouse in Los Ca<i>&amp;#</i>241;os de Meca, Spain, on, July 29, 2020. (AP Photo/Emilio Morenatti, File)</span></div>
<p>Currently, cold weather kills far more people in Europe than hot weather. But the study found that as temperatures continue to rise, deaths from cold weather will lessen over time. However, heat-related deaths are predicted to rise sharply.</p>
<p>Scientists at the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine led the research. The results appeared recently <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-00239-4#:~:text=An%20extra%202.3%20million%20people,the%20effects%20of%20rising%20temperatures.">in a study</a> in the publication <em>Nature Medicine</em>.</p>
<p>The researchers urged increased efforts to reduce greenhouse gases and expand indoor air-cooling systems and cooling centers in parts of Europe. Without such efforts, places in Italy, southern Spain and Greece are likely to see large increases in heat deaths related to climate change, the study found.</p>
<p>On the other hand, much of Scandinavia and Britain are predicted to see fewer temperature-related deaths, largely because low temperatures are expected to become more moderate.</p>
<p>Pierre Masselot studies the environmental effects of human health at the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine. He helped lead the research.</p>
<p>Masselot told the Associated Press that drops in cold deaths in northern parts of Europe are happening in areas not as populated as places further south. “The Mediterranean is a so-called climate hotspot," he said. "It's a <strong>region</strong> that is warming much quicker than the rest of the world. And Malta is right in the middle of it.”</p>
<p>The study predicts Malta's temperature-related deaths will increase by 269 people for every 100,000 individuals by the end of the century. On the other hand, Ireland's rate is expected to drop slightly to 15 per 100,000 people.</p>
<p>European officials reported several heat waves have killed thousands of people in recent years across the continent. The highest number was in 2003, when about 70,000 deaths were recorded.</p>
<p>Among the areas predicted to see the most deaths from future temperature rises is Barcelona, Spain. The study found almost 250,000 people could die from temperature-related causes in that city by 2100. And the study warned that Rome and Naples could have up to 150,000 deaths.</p>
<p>The study predicted that more than 5.8 million extra heat deaths would be linked to climate change. At the same time, the study found cold-related deaths would drop by 3.5 million.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>simulate </strong><em>– v. </em>do or make something that behaves or looks like something real but is not</p>
<p><strong>region </strong><em>– n. </em>a particular area in a country or the world</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Study Finds India’s Tiger Population Doubled in 12 Years  (2025/2/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/study-finds-india-s-tiger-population-doubled-in-12-years.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p class="MsoBodyText">A recent study says India has doubled its tiger population in 12 years.</p>
<p>Researchers said the gain came from efforts to protect the big cats from hunters, and to protect against the loss of tiger <strong>habitat</strong> and <strong>prey</strong>, among other things.</p>
<p>The National Tiger Conservation Authority said the number of tigers grew from an estimated 1,706 in 2010 to around 3,682 in 2022. Those numbers mean India is home to about 75 percent of the total tiger population.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Tigers interact at the Ranthambore National Park in Sawai Madhopur, India on April 12, 2015. (AP Photo/Satyajeet Singh Rathore, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/54dd38b3-b64e-42a3-9597-cfd4c8a2a9c4_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Tigers interact at the Ranthambore National Park in Sawai Madhopur, India on April 12, 2015. (AP Photo/Satyajeet Singh Rathore, File)</span></div>
<p>The research shows that a reduction in conflict between humans and wildlife also played a part in the population growth. The study credited efforts to improve economic conditions for communities near tiger habitats. The researchers said the growth in the tiger population also led to improvements in local economies through increased <strong>ecotourism</strong>.</p>
<p>The study appears in the publication <em>Science</em>. It said India's success demonstrates that wildlife protection can help both <strong>biodiversity</strong> and nearby communities.</p>
<p>“The common belief is that human densities <strong>preclude</strong> an increase in tiger populations," said Yadvendradev Jhala. Jhala is a scientist at Bengaluru-based Indian National Academy of Sciences and was the study's lead writer. “What the research shows is that it's not the human density, but the <strong>attitude</strong> of people, which matters more.”</p>
<p>Wildlife <strong>conservationists</strong> and ecologists welcomed the study. But they said making the source data available to a larger group of scientists would aid tigers and other wildlife in India. The study was based on data collected by Indian government-supported organizations.</p>
<p>Arjun Gopalaswamy is an ecologist who knows how to measure wildlife populations. He said that estimates from India's official tiger observation program have been undependable. He said some of the numbers in the study are much higher than past estimates of tiger populations from the same datasets. But he added that the study's findings seem to have corrected a data problem noted repeatedly by scientists since 2011 related to tiger population size and their <strong>range</strong>.</p>
<p>The study said tigers disappeared in some areas. These included habitats that were not near national parks or other protected areas, and areas of increased development, increased human use of forest resources and areas with armed conflict.</p>
<p>“Without community support and<strong> participation</strong> and community benefits, conservation is not possible in our country,” said Jhala.</p>
<p>That means local people need to see good results from their efforts to save tigers.</p>
<p>Tigers are spread across about 138,200 square kilometers of India. But just 25 percent of the area is rich in tiger prey and is protected. Another 45 percent of tiger habitat is shared with about 60 million people, the study said.</p>
<p>Jhala said strong wildlife protection legislation is the “backbone” of tiger conservation in India. “Habitat is not a <strong>constraint</strong>, it's the quality of the habitat which is a constraint,” he said.</p>
<p>Wildlife biologist Ravi Chellam, who did not take part in the study, praised the tiger conservation efforts as promising. But, he said, such efforts need to be extended to other wild animals to better care for the whole ecosystem in India.</p>
<p>Chellam said several kinds of Indian wildlife are “on the edge,” and need more attention.</p>
<p>I'm <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_f4j55Zlw">Caty Weaver.</a></p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>______________________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>habitat</strong> <em>–n.</em> the place or environment where a plant or animal naturally or normally exists</p>
<p><strong>prey </strong><em>–n.</em> an animal hunted or killed by another animal for food</p>
<p><strong>ecotourism </strong><em>–n.</em> people who travel to and visit a place to see its natural beauty and wildlife</p>
<p><strong>biodiversity </strong><em>–n.</em> biological variety in an environment as indicated by numbers of different species of plants and animals</p>
<p><strong>preclude </strong><em>–v.</em> to make impossible by necessary consequence</p>
<p><strong>attitude </strong><em>–n</em>. the visible behavior that shows how a person thinks or feels about something or someone</p>
<p><strong>conservationist </strong>–n. a person who works to preserve animals, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_iuIUpwMv">plants</a> and natural resources for future generations</p>
<p><strong>range </strong><em>–n.</em> the area where a plant or animal naturally lives and can be found</p>
<p><strong>constraint </strong><em>–n.</em> the state of being restricted</p>
<p><strong>participation </strong><em>– n.</em> the action or state of taking part in something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>New US Jet Breaks Sound Barrier in First Flight Test  (2025/2/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/new-us-jet-breaks-sound-barrier-in-first-flight-test.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>An experimental aircraft developed by a private American company broke the sound barrier during a recent flight test.</p>
<p>California-based company Boom Supersonic built the plane, named XB-1. The company said the aircraft reached a speed of Mach 1.05 during a test on January 28. The test flight operated from the Mojave Air &amp; Space Port in Mojave, California.</p>
<p>Any speed greater than Mach 1.0 breaks the sound barrier and is considered supersonic. The American space agency NASA <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/learning-resources/for-kids-and-students/what-is-supersonic-flight-grades-5-8/#:~:text=Vehicles%20that%20fly%20at%20supersonic,to%20the%20speed%20of%20sound.">explains</a> that at sea level, the speed of sound is estimated to be about 1,236 kilometers per hour.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="The Boom Supersonic's XB-1 aircraft breaks the sound barrier, Mach 1, during a test flight Tuesday, Jan. 28, 2025, over the Mohave Desert, Calif. (Boom Supersonic via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/2d899815-edd8-4ed9-91dc-03ace83020b5_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">The Boom Supersonic's XB-1 aircraft breaks the sound barrier, Mach 1, during a test flight Tuesday, Jan. 28, 2025, over the Mohave Desert, Calif. (Boom Supersonic via AP)</span></div>
<p>In a statement, Boom Supersonic said the XB-1 demonstrator aircraft climbed to more than 35,000 feet before reaching Mach 1.0. It recorded the speed within 11 minutes of taking off. The company also released a <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-qisIViAHwI">video feed</a> of the supersonic test flight.</p>
<p>The company said in a press release, “Historically, supersonic aircraft have been the work of nation states, developed by militaries and governments.” But the latest flight made the XB-1 “the world's first independently developed supersonic <strong>jet</strong>” to break the sound barrier, Boom Supersonic said.</p>
<p>The company's founder and chief executive officer, Blake Scholl, said, “XB-1's supersonic flight demonstrates that the technology for passenger supersonic flight has arrived.”</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" href="https://boomsupersonic.com/">Boom Supersonic</a> launched in 2014 “with the goal of making high-speed travel <strong>mainstream</strong> and <strong>enabling</strong> a new world of human connection.” With that in mind, the company has been working to develop a supersonic passenger airliner called Overture. The aircraft would carry up to 80 passengers.</p>
<p>Boom Supersonic is one of several American companies seeking to develop supersonic flight vehicles. NASA is also working on a supersonic aircraft in partnership with a U.S. contractor.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p>The last time supersonic travel was available to passengers was 2003. That is the year the Concorde – the world's first supersonic passenger jet aircraft – stopped service. Britain and France jointly operated the Concorde.</p>
<p>But the joint operation between British Airways and Air France suffered several business difficulties that led to the decision to stop flying the supersonic planes. Some of the difficulties were linked to publicity about a deadly Concorde crash in 2000. That incident involved an Air France airliner crashing shortly after taking off from Paris. The crash claimed a total of 113 lives.</p>
<p>Boom Supersonic says its planned Overture airliner will be designed to transport passengers from the U.S. East Coast across the Atlantic to Europe in about 3-and-a-half hours. The flight with normal passenger jets takes about eight hours.</p>
<p>Amy Marino Spowart is the president and chief executive officer at the National Aeronautic Association. She told The Associated Press the latest supersonic test flight suggests “the future of <strong>aviation</strong> is here and now.” Spowart added, “Not only is there hope for faster and better commercial flight, but Boom proves that it can be done <strong>sustainably</strong>.”</p>
<p>Boom Supersonic has said its planned supersonic airliner will be designed to run on up to 100 percent sustainable aircraft fuel. Such sustainable fuels are made from non-petroleum products, such as food waste or other biomass materials. Both XB-1 and Overture are made mostly from a carbon-based <strong>composite</strong> material to provide “a strong, lightweight structure,” the company said.</p>
<p>NASA's supersonic aircraft – built together with Lockheed Martin – is called X-59. It is also an experimental plane that is seeking to test the level of noise produced by supersonic travel. Currently, supersonic flights are banned over land because of the loud noise they produce.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
renderExternalContent("https://www.youtube.com/embed/eC3Fl7Bt4qQ?&amp;&amp;&amp;fs=1&amp;enablejsapi=1")



<p>NASA has <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/missions/quesst/quesst-mission/quesst-the-mission-description/">explained</a> it plans to carry out testing this year of the X-59 aircraft, which has been designed and engineered to operate at lower noise levels than other supersonic aircraft. The tests – to take place at supersonic test centers in California – are designed “to prove the quiet supersonic technology works as designed.”</p>
<p>NASA said that after that testing is done, the agency plans to begin community reaction studies, beginning in 2026. These will involve flying the X-59 over several cities and then asking people on the ground to share their thoughts on the level of noise they heard.</p>
<p>NASA has said the X-59 – which measures 30 meters long and nine meters wide – is expected to fly at 1.4 times the speed of sound. That is about 1,500 kilometers per hour.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press, Reuters and Boom Supersonic reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the reports for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>_______________________________________</strong></h2>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>mainstream </strong><em>– adj. </em>the beliefs or way of living that are accepted by most people</p>
<p><strong>enable </strong><em>– v. </em>to make something possible</p>
<p><strong>sustainable </strong><em>– adj. </em>method of energy production that cause little or no damage to the environment</p>
<p><strong>composite </strong><em>– adj. </em>made up of several different materials or parts</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Japan Launches New Satellite to Improve Navigation System  (2025/2/6)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/japan-launches-new-satellite-to-improve-navigation-system.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">05 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Japan's space agency says it successfully launched a <strong>navigation</strong> satellite on its new H3 rocket. The latest launch on February 2 took place as the country aims to develop a more <strong>precise</strong> positioning system.</p>
<p>The H3 rocket carrying the Michibiki 6 satellite lifted off from the Tanegashima Space Center on a southwestern Japanese island.</p>
<p>Makoto Arita oversees the H3 project for the Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency known as JAXA. Arita said everything went smoothly and the satellite successfully separated from the rocket as planned about 29 minutes after liftoff.</p><div class="contentImage"><img a="" alt="The H3 Launch Vehicle No. 5, carrying the " at="" center="" feb.="" in="" japan="" launch="" lifts="" michibiki="" no.="" off="" pad="" southern="" space="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/8068b7d6-2728-49af-a20b-c23c10b60066_w268_r1.jpg" sunday="" tanegashima=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">The H3 Launch Vehicle No. 5, carrying the "Michibiki No. 6," lifts off at a launch pad in Tanegashima Space Center in Tanegashima, southern Japan, Sunday Feb. 2, 2025.</span></div>
<p>Officials said it should reach its target orbit around Earth in the middle of February.</p>
<p>Japan's current system is called the <strong>quasi</strong>-<strong>zenith</strong> satellite system, or QZSS. It started operating in 2018 and has four satellites that serve a regional <strong>navigation</strong> system. The Michibiki 6 will be the fifth satellite in the network.</p>
<p>Michibiki's signals are used to <strong>supplement</strong> the American satellite system called the Global Positioning System (GPS). It will also improve positioning data for smartphones, car navigation, navigation at sea and <strong>drones</strong>.</p>
<p>Japan plans to launch two more navigation satellites to have a seven-satellite system by March 2026. The Japan Science and Technology Agency hopes that will create a more precise global positioning ability without depending on foreign services, including GPS. By the late 2030s, Japan plans to have an 11-satellite network.</p>
<p><strong>First launch not successful</strong></p>
<p>Sunday's launch was the fourth successful flight in a row for the H3 system. The first attempt to launch last year failed and the rocket had to be destroyed with its <strong>payload</strong>.</p>
<p>Japan considers the ability to regularly put satellites into orbit as important to its space program and national security. It has been developing two new leading rockets. One is the large H3 from Mitsubishi Heavy Industries. The other is a much smaller Epsilon system with the aerospace unit of IHI corporation. Japan hopes to meet the needs of companies for space launch services and improve its position in the growing satellite launch market.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Mari Yamaguchi reported this story for the Associated Press. Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>navigation</strong> – <em>n</em>. the act, activity, or process of finding the way to get to a place when you are traveling in a ship, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_QWvmxS9e">airplane</a> or car</p>
<p><strong>precise </strong><em>–adj.</em> exactly placed; exactly where something is supposed to be</p>
<p><strong>quasi </strong><em>– prefix</em> almost, nearly</p>
<p><strong>zenith </strong><em>– n. </em>to point in the sky directly above your head</p>
<p><strong>drone</strong> - <em>n</em>. a small aircraft that flies without a pilot and is controlled from the ground</p>
<p><strong>supplement </strong><em>– v.</em> to provide additional support</p>
<p><strong>payload</strong> <em>– n.</em> anything that someone is paying to have transported by a vehicle such as an airplane or rocket</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Huge Iceberg Could Threaten Penguins in the South Atlantic Ocean  (2025/2/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/huge-iceberg-could-threaten-penguins-in-the-south-atlantic-ocean.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Scientists are worried that a large <strong>iceberg</strong> heading toward an island in the South Atlantic Ocean could threaten wildlife there.</p>
<p>Researchers say the iceberg is the largest in the world. It is moving through the South Atlantic toward the island of South Georgia. The island is a British overseas territory that is about 1,400 kilometers east of the Falkland Islands.</p>
<p>Scientists say South Georgia is a main mating ground for wildlife, especially penguins and seals.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image provided by the Ministry of Defence shows the iceberg, known as A23a, on Nov. 25, 2024, off the coast of Antarctica. (Cpl Tom Cann RAF/Crown Copyright 2024 via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/52c90d07-ee3c-49bc-abf0-3215f1af247c_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image provided by the Ministry of Defence shows the iceberg, known as A23a, on Nov. 25, 2024, off the coast of Antarctica. (Cpl Tom Cann RAF/Crown Copyright 2024 via AP)</span></div>
<p>The iceberg is officially known as A23a and it measures about 3,500 square kilometers. It has existed since 1986, when it broke off from the Antarctic <strong>shelf</strong>.</p>
<p>Andrew Meijers is an oceanographer with the British Antarctic Survey. He told the French News Agency (AFP) that scientists have been using satellite imagery to follow the iceberg's movements.</p>
<p>Meijers said observations had shown the iceberg had not broken into smaller pieces like some other so-called "megabergs" that passed through the Southern Ocean. He added that predicting the iceberg's exact path is difficult. But ocean conditions suggest it should reach South Georgia in two to four weeks.</p>
<p>Meijers said he is worried the iceberg will get caught on the underground <strong>continental shelf</strong> around South Georgia. But he said it is also possible the large ice mass could miss the shelf and continue moving into open waters beyond South Georgia.</p>
<p>If the iceberg does get caught, or stuck, on the shelf, Meijers said it could remain there for months or it could break into pieces. Meijers is concerned that this could harm efforts by penguins and seals on the island to feed and raise their young. Icebergs that have grounded there in the past led to the deaths of young penguins and seals, he said.</p>
<p>Raul Cordero is a mechanical engineer from Chile's University of Santiago. He is also a member of the National Antarctic Research Committee. Cordero told AFP he thinks the iceberg will miss South Georgia.</p>
<p>"The island acts as an <strong>obstacle</strong> for ocean currents and therefore usually <strong>diverts</strong> the water long before it reaches the island," he said. "The iceberg is moved by that water flow, so the chances of it hitting are not that high." Cordero added, however, that some iceberg pieces could affect the island.</p>
<p>Soledad Tiranti is a <strong>glacier</strong> expert who is currently on an Argentinian exploration trip in the Antarctic. She told AFP that icebergs such as A23a "are so deep that before reaching an island or mainland they generally get stuck" on the seabed.</p>
<p>It is currently summer in South Georgia and penguins and seals from the area have been looking for food in the cold Antarctic waters to bring back to their young. Meijers said the animals might have to go around the iceberg if it gets stuck.</p>
<p>He added that if they had to move around it, this would take a lot of their energy, possibly leading to animal deaths. The seal and penguin populations on South Georgia have already been having a "bad season" with cases of bird flu, Meijers said.</p>
<p>Iceberg A23a remained stuck for 30 years before finally breaking free from the Antarctic shelf in 2020. Scientists watching its movements say the iceberg has followed nearly the same path as other large ice masses in the past.</p>
<p>The icebergs generally pass the east side of the Antarctic Peninsula through the Weddell Sea along a path known as "iceberg <strong>alley</strong>." They are pushed by the world's most powerful ocean current system, the Antarctic Circumpolar Current.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Agence France-Presse reported on this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>______________________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>iceberg </strong><em>– n. </em>a huge piece of ice that floats freely in the sea</p>
<p><strong>shelf</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> an area of relatively shallow water that surrounds a land mass</p>
<p><strong>continental shelf </strong><em>–n.</em> an area of relatively shallow water that extends from the world's great land masses and beyond which is the deep ocean</p>
<p><strong>obstacle </strong><em>– n. </em>something that makes it difficult or gets in the way of doing something; a barrier</p>
<p><strong>divert </strong><em>– v. </em>to<em> </em>send someone or something to a place other than where they had expected to go</p>
<p><strong>glacier</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n. </em>a large mass of ice that moves very slowly, usually down a hill or valley</p>
<p><strong>alley </strong><em>– n. </em>a narrow street or place where things are likely to pass</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How to Write a Good Email  (2025/2/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/how-to-write-a-good-email.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Gregory Stachel</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>
Email is one of the most important ways through which we communicate. It has become part of most everyone's day-to-day life.</p>
<p>Writing a good email can mean the difference between someone reading it and writing back, and someone ignoring it all together. Do you have questions on how to make your message more effective?</p>
<p>Today on <em>Education Tips, </em>we will answer the question, “How can I make my emails better?”</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Education Tips: How to Write a Good Email" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/5663032C-AEBD-4C48-BFC2-1BFC5947DC1C_w268_r1.png"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Education Tips: How to Write a Good Email</span></div>
<p>Emails are made up of four different parts:</p>
<ul style="margin-left:40px">
<li>the subject line,</li>
<li>the opening,</li>
<li>the body, and</li>
<li>the closing.</li>
</ul>
<p>Let us explore how to make each of these parts better.</p>
<p><strong>Subject line</strong></p>
<p>The subject line is what the other person, or receiver, will read first. The subject line is usually the most important part of an email. It should be short but contain enough details that the receiver recognizes the subject of the email. A good subject line sets the expectations for the email. A bad subject line can mean the receiver will not read the email.</p>
<p>Some people will add the word “important” to the subject line, but this does not provide enough information. Instead of writing “important,” two better choices for subject lines are:</p>
<p><em>Meeting Tomorrow at 10am to Discuss New Changes<br/>
Question About Future Classes</em></p>
<p><strong>Opening an email</strong></p>
<p>As in any form of writing, you should know your <strong>audience</strong>. The opening of an email depends on things like how <strong>formal </strong>the relationship is.</p>
<p>If you are sending an email to a friend or someone you work with, two good openings or greetings are:</p>
<p><em>Good Morning/Afternoon,<br/>
Hello, or Hello [name], </em></p>
<p>If you are sending the email to someone you do not know and it is a formal situation, some possible openings are:</p>
<p><em>Dear [name of department],<br/>
To Whom it May Concern,</em></p>
<p>In a formal situation, when you know the name of the person, a good opening is simply:</p>
<p><em>Dear [title] [family name],</em><br/>
As in, <em>Dear Mister Brown, </em></p>
<p><strong>Body</strong></p>
<p>The body of the email is where you ask for what you need or make clear your reason for writing the email. This could be asking them a question or keeping them informed. The body of the email should <strong>prioritize</strong> the most important information. It should be direct, and it is wise to keep it short.</p>
<p>If the person you are emailing does not know you, you should <strong>introduce</strong> yourself in the first few lines. You might write:</p>
<p><em>My name is Patricia Jones. I am sending this email to get some more information about the job you advertised.</em></p>
<p>After you have introduced yourself and given your reason for writing, you can follow this with the body of your email. The most important information should come first. This makes your email clear to your receiver and saves them time. Here is an example.</p>
<p><em>I wanted to know if you are currently accepting <strong>applications</strong>. If so, where can I send my information? Additionally, will you be meeting people in-person or online?</em></p>
<p>It is important to clearly explain yourself in as few words as possible. Try to keep your email short, but <strong>polite</strong>. This is important because you want to make yourself clear to your receiver.</p>
<p><strong>Closings</strong></p>
<p>The last part to a good email is the closing. It is usually one or two words that let the receiver know that this is the end of the email. The ending should include your name and tell the receiver where you work and what you do. A few different closings are:</p>
<p><em>Kind regards,<br/>
Best,<br/>
Thank you,</em></p>
<p>Some applications create an <strong>automatic signature</strong> for the sender. This is useful because it saves time when you are writing.</p>
<p><strong>Example email</strong></p>
<p>So, what does a completed email look like? Here is an example email:</p>
<p>If you follow these suggestions, you will find that you receive more <strong>responses</strong> to your emails. Effective email writing is important especially now when so much of what we do is online.</p>
<p>I'm Gregory Stachel.</p>
<p>And I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Gregory Stachel wrote this story for VOA Learning English. George Grow was the editor.</em></p><div id="bottom"><!-- 51-content-bottom -->
<ins class="adsbygoogle" data-ad-client="ca-pub-3585518775245612" data-ad-format="auto" data-ad-slot="9284795419" data-full-width-responsive="true" style="display:block; text-align:center;"></ins>
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></div>
<p>______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>audience </strong>– <em>n.</em> the people who watch, read, or listen to something</p>
<p><strong>formal</strong> – <em>adj.</em> <em>of language:</em> suitable for serious or official speech and writing</p>
<p><strong>prioritize</strong> – <em>v.</em> to make (something) the most important thing in a group</p>
<p><strong>introduce</strong> – <em>v.</em> to make (someone) known to someone else by name</p>
<p><strong>application</strong> – <em>n.</em> formal and usually written request for something (such as a job, admission to a school, a loan, or such</p>
<p><strong>polite</strong> – <em>adj.</em> having or showing good manners or respect for other people</p>
<p><strong>automatic</strong> – <em>adj.</em> <em>of a machine or device</em>: having controls that allow something to work or happen without being directly controlled by a person</p>
<p><strong>signature</strong> – <em>n.</em> a person's name written in that person's handwriting or, on an electronic message, the person's name and other contact information</p>
<p><strong>response</strong> – <em>n.</em> something that is said or written as a reply to something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>New Zealand Recognizes a Mountain as a Legal Person  (2025/2/5)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/new-zealand-recognizes-a-mountain-as-a-legal-person.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">04 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>New Zealand's parliament recently passed a law that gives a mountain all the rights and responsibilities of a human being.</p>
<p>The <strong>indigenous</strong> Māori people of New Zealand consider the mountain their ancestor.</p>
<p>The mountain is now known by its Māori name, Taranaki Maunga. The Māori people of New Zealand represent about 15 percent of the country's population.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A man takes a picture of his wife with Mount Taranaki, also known as Mount Egmont, in the background in New Plymouth, New Zealand, Sept. 26, 2011. (AP Photo/Dita Alangkara, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/7374aa6d-0b65-47f6-a124-0eaba2737c33_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A man takes a picture of his wife with Mount Taranaki, also known as Mount Egmont, in the background in New Plymouth, New Zealand, Sept. 26, 2011. (AP Photo/Dita Alangkara, File)</span></div>
<p>Taranaki Maunga is a <strong>dormant</strong> volcano on New Zealand's North Island. Snow covers the top of the 2,516-meter-high mountain. It is a popular place for <strong>tourism</strong>, hiking and snow sports.</p>
<p>The legal recognition of the mountain is one of the steps New Zealand's government has taken to make up for harm the indigenous population suffered in the past. The new law makes it known that the Taranaki area was stolen from the Māori after New Zealand was colonized.</p>
<p>The new law gives Taranaki Maunga all the rights, powers, duties, responsibilities and <strong>liabilities</strong> of a person. The law says a newly created group will be “the face and voice” of the mountain. Four members from local Māori tribes and four members appointed by the country's conservation minister will be in the group.</p>
<p>Paul Goldsmith is the lawmaker responsible for the legal settlements between the government and Māori tribes. In a speech to Parliament, he said, “The mountain has long been an honored ancestor, a source of physical, cultural and spiritual <strong>sustenance</strong> and a final resting place."</p>
<p>Britain colonized New Zealand in the 1700s and 1800s. In 1770, the British explorer Captain James Cook named the volcano Mount Egmont.</p>
<p>In 1840, Māori tribes and representatives of the British government signed the Treaty of Waitangi. The treaty promised the Māori would keep the rights to their land and resources. However, the British government began breaking parts of the treaty after that.</p>
<p>In 1865, the government took a large area of Taranaki land, including the mountain, to punish the Māori for rebelling against British rule. Over the next one hundred years, hunting and sports groups helped oversee how the land was used, but the Māori did not.</p>
<p>Goldsmith told the Associated Press that, in the past, Māori customs connected to the mountain were banned while the government supported tourism in the area.</p>
<p>The Māori protest movement of the 1970s and 1980s led to increased recognition of the Māori language, culture and rights in New Zealand's law. This has included billions of dollars to pay for the harm caused by breaking the Treaty of Waitangi.</p>
<p>The mountain's legal rights are in place to support its health and wellbeing. The law will support traditional uses of the land and calls for conservation work to protect the native wildlife. The mountain will remain open to the public.</p>
<p><strong>Are other landforms considered people?</strong></p>
<p>New Zealand was the first country in the world to recognize landforms as people. In 2014, a law gave personhood to Te Urewera, a large forest on the North Island. Government ownership ended and the Tūhoe tribe became its guardian.</p>
<p>And in 2017, New Zealand recognized the Whanganui River as a human, as part of a settlement with the tribe connected to the river.</p>
<p>All 123 lawmakers in Parliament supported the new law for Taranaki Maunga. The unity of the vote was a change from recent disagreements in New Zealand about proposed changes to the Treaty of Waitangi itself.</p>
<p>In November, about 40,000 people marched to Parliament to protest a new law with proposed changes to the treaty. The protesters said the new law would take away Māori rights and harm the progress that has been made during the last 50 years.</p>
<p>Most officials do not expect the bill with the proposed changes to become law.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Charlotte Graham-McLay wrote this story for The Associated Press. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>indigenous </strong><em>–n.</em> someone or something that is native to a place for a relatively long period of time</p>
<p><strong>dormant </strong><em>–adj. </em>not currently active</p>
<p><strong>tourism </strong><em>–n.</em> the activity of traveling to places for enjoyment or the industry that provides food, shelter and activity to tourists</p>
<p><strong>liability </strong><em>–n.</em> something that you are responsible for such as paying back a loan</p>
<p><strong>sustenance </strong>–n. something that gives support, help and strength; food</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists Find ‘Chorus Waves’ in Unexpected Part of Space  (2025/2/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/scientists-find-chorus-waves-in-unexpected-part-of-space.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p class="paragraph">International researchers recently released a study on bursts of energy in an unexpected area of space.</p>
<p>Scientists call the energetic activity “<strong>chorus</strong> waves” because they are said to move at the same <strong>frequency</strong> as sounds humans can hear. When the energy is turned into audio signals, the waves sound like birds <strong>chirping</strong>.</p>
<p>Researchers have known about chorus waves in space for many years. But the latest research has found the waves exist 100,000 kilometers from Earth. Chorus waves have never before been measured at such a big distance from a planet.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="NASA's four Magnetospheric Multiscale, or MMS, satellites at the Astrotech Space Operations facility in Titusville, Florida, March 2015. (NASA via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/84f639b0-d205-4ab1-aa8f-c1c89806bc6c_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">NASA's four Magnetospheric Multiscale, or MMS, satellites at the Astrotech Space Operations facility in Titusville, Florida, March 2015. (NASA via AP)</span></div>
<p>In an email, study writer Chengming Liu from Beihang University in Beijing wrote: “They are one of the strongest and most <strong>significant </strong>waves in space.”</p>
<p>Allison Jaynes is a space physicist at the University of Iowa who was not involved with the study. Speaking about the recent study, Jaynes said, “That opens up a lot of new questions about the physics that could be possible in this area.”</p>
<p>The newfound chorus waves were detected in an area where Earth's <strong>magnetic field</strong> is stretched out. Scientists said they did not expect to find <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_jRlu8izx">the waves</a> there. The discovery raises new questions about how the chirping waves form.</p>
<p>Jaynes added, “We definitely need to find more of these events.”</p>
<p>Scientists still are not sure how the waves develop. But they think Earth's <strong>magnetic field</strong> may have something to do with it.</p>
<p>For many years, radio <strong>antennas</strong> have picked up chorus waves. This includes receivers at an Antarctica research station in the 1960s. And NASA's two Van Allen Probes heard the chirping sounds from Earth's <strong>radiation belts</strong> at a closer distance than the newest observations.</p>
<p>The latest chorus waves were picked up by NASA's Magnetospheric Multiscale satellites. They were launched in 2015 to explore the Earth and the sun's magnetic fields.</p>
<p>Chorus waves have also been found near other planets including Jupiter and Saturn. The waves can produce high-energy electrons.<strong> </strong>That means they can threaten satellite communications.</p>
<p>The researchers said their findings suggest that chorus waves might be found everywhere in the magnetic fields of planets.</p>
<p>The study was released on January 22 in the scientific publication <em>Nature</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Adithi Ramakrishnan reported this story for the Associated Press from New York. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>chorus</strong> –n. a group of singers who sing together</p>
<p><strong>significant </strong>–adj. important, meaningful</p>
<p><strong>chirping </strong>–n. short, sharp sounds similar to the songs of certain birds</p>
<p><strong>frequency </strong>–n. the number of times a wave form repeats in a certain amount of time</p>
<p><strong>magnetic field</strong> –n. the area around a magnetized object that is influenced by its magnetism</p>
<p><strong>antenna</strong> –n. a device that carries radio waves to a receiver</p>
<p><strong>radiation belt </strong>–n. an area of charged particles around a planet that is formed largely because of its magnetic field</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Approves Treatment for Severe High Blood Pressure  (2025/2/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/us-approves-treatment-for-severe-high-blood-pressure.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Michael Garrity had dangerously high blood pressure for many years. And the medicines that doctors gave him could not control it.</p>
<p>But a new treatment targeting some nerves on his kidneys has helped the 62-year-old Garrity have normal blood pressure for the first time in years.</p>
<p>When some nerves from the kidneys send more signals than is normal, dangerously high blood pressure can result. The new treatment uses ultrasound, or high frequency sound waves, to reduce the signals the nerves send.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this photo provided by Massachusetts General Hospital, patient Mike Garrity, center, speaks with Drs. Joe Garasic, left, and Randy Zusman in Boston, on Sept. 25, 2024. (Jeffrey Andree/Massachusetts General Hospital via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/d1e31959-9ecc-41f6-a59b-ea925085c879_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this photo provided by Massachusetts General Hospital, patient Mike Garrity, center, speaks with Drs. Joe Garasic, left, and Randy Zusman in Boston, on Sept. 25, 2024. (Jeffrey Andree/Massachusetts General Hospital via AP)</span></div>
<p>“My blood pressure would <strong>spike</strong> and I'd run out of breath and feel tired, and that doesn't happen anymore,” said Garrity, who lives in the American state of Massachusetts. Garrity still takes medicine but at lower amounts. He said he is very happy with the results of his treatment.</p>
<p>About half of U.S. adults have high blood pressure. It increases the risk for heart attacks, <strong>strokes</strong>, kidney failure, and possibly <strong>dementia</strong>. Many people do not know they have high blood pressure until something goes wrong.</p>
<p>“Know your blood pressure, know the numbers,” said Dr. Randy Zusman of Massachusetts General Hospital. He treats difficult cases. He also said people who think they are healthy should still have their blood pressure measured once a year or more.</p>
<p>Only a small percentage of people with high blood pressure control the condition well. That might mean there is a need for new treatments. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration approved the new ultrasound treatment about a year ago.</p>
<p>Some hospitals are offering the treatment, but only for patients who might be likely to have good results.</p>
<p><strong>What is high blood pressure?</strong></p>
<p>Blood pressure is measured using two values. One value is called “systolic” pressure. It is the force blood puts on the walls of <strong>arteries</strong> as it is pumped out of the heart. The second value is called “diastolic” pressure. That number measures pressure in <strong>blood vessels</strong> between heartbeats.</p>
<p>The Associated Press reports that normal blood pressure is less than 120 over 80. However, blood pressure naturally changes throughout the day. It is higher when a person is physically active or experiences tension. But when it stays higher than, for example, 130 over 80 or higher, it might mean the heart is working too hard.</p>
<p><strong>Treatments for high blood pressure</strong></p>
<p>Instead of drugs, doctors advise lifestyle changes as the first step to reduce blood pressure. Changes can include losing weight, getting regular exercise, eating more fruits and vegetables, limiting salt and alcohol, and taking steps to deal with tension, or stress, in a healthy way.</p>
<p>However, if blood pressure reaches 140 over 90, taking medicine becomes necessary. Zusman said most patients need two or three drugs, sometimes more, along with healthier living.</p>
<p>The high blood pressure Garrity has struggled with resists treatment with drugs. He tried taking four to six drugs as well as eating healthy food and exercising. Still, his blood pressure regularly reached 150 over 100 or higher.</p>
<p>Dr. Joseph Garasic is a heart specialist at Massachusetts General Hospital. He performed Garrity's operation. He said doctors pass a small tube through blood vessels to reach the kidneys. Then they direct ultrasound through kidney arteries targeting the nerves. The operation takes about one hour.</p>
<p>The treatment is not a cure, and it does not help all patients. But Garasic said several studies show on average an eight to 10-point drop in blood pressure. This small decrease can still help some patients. Others, like Garrity, see bigger drops. This can help reduce the number of medications patients must take.</p>
<p>Studies connected to the new ultrasound treatment have only lasted a few years. That means doctors do not yet know if the nerves will grow back. The American Heart Association says people with high blood pressure and their doctors should have “thoughtful and informed discussions” to decide who might be the right patients to try the treatment.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Lauran Neergaard wrote this story for The Associated Press. Andrew Smith adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>spike </strong><em>–v.</em> to suddenly increase</p>
<p><strong>stroke </strong><em>–n.</em> when a blockage in a blood vessel stops blood flow to part of the brain</p>
<p><strong>dementia </strong><em>–n.</em> a brain disease affecting memory and behavior</p>
<p><strong>artery </strong><em>–n.</em> a blood vessel that carries blood containing oxygen away from the heart to the organs</p>
<p><strong>blood vessel </strong><em>–n.</em> any tube that carries blood to or from the heart</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Company Gives Over 18,000 Kilograms of Salmon to Food Bank  (2025/2/4)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/us-company-gives-over-18-000-kilograms-of-salmon-to-food-bank.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">03 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>A New York food bank was offered a large donation of fresh fish last month — but the gift came with a <strong>complication.</strong></p>
<p>LocalCoho, a New York salmon farm that was closing, wanted to give 18,100 kilograms of coho salmon to the Food Bank of Central New York. The high-quality protein could feed thousands of families.</p>
<p>However, the gift fish were still alive and swimming in the farm's large tanks. The organization needed to find a way to remove about 13,000 salmon from the tanks and, later, process them into food.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Stephen Zicari, an employee of Local Coho salmon fish farm in Auburn, N.Y., nets fish from one of the farm's tanks Friday, Jan. 24, 2025, that will be donated to the Food Bank of Central New York. (AP Photo/Craig Ruttle)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/d3a4c562-373d-47bb-af01-0e701c847d82_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Stephen Zicari, an employee of Local Coho salmon fish farm in Auburn, N.Y., nets fish from one of the farm's tanks Friday, Jan. 24, 2025, that will be donated to the Food Bank of Central New York. (AP Photo/Craig Ruttle)</span></div>
<p>And the food aid group needed to do all this quickly, before the business closed permanently at the end of January.</p>
<p>Thanks to many volunteers, the group was able to empty the tanks in time, place the fish in cold storage and transport them to a processer.</p>
<p>Brian McManus is the food bank's chief operations officer. He said that the short amount of time to complete the operation made activities difficult. But, he said, “I knew that we had the will. I knew we had the expertise.”</p>
<p>Food waste has been a big problem around the world for years. More than one-third of the food produced in the United States is never eaten and much of it ends up in <strong>landfills</strong>.</p>
<p>Christina Hudson Kohler was among the volunteers who got into the water to collect the fish and put them into the cold storage containers.</p>
<p>“It's a little bit different,” Kohler said during a break. “In the past, my volunteer work with the food bank has been sorting carrots or peppers....”</p>
<p>LocalCoho was a new company that had been developing a <strong>sustainable</strong> salmon farming system. The system employed <strong>recirculated</strong> water. The company had been supplying coho salmon to buyers, including restaurants, with the goal of building farms across the country.</p>
<p>But company officials said they could not raise enough money from investors to grow and become profitable. So, they decided to close the business.</p>
<p>Adam Kramarsyck was the salmon farm's<strong> manager</strong>. He said the company did not want the fish to go to waste so it sought a way to donate them.</p>
<p>Kramarsyck said of the effort, “It's ‘lemonade out of lemons.'” The expression means to create good from a bad situation.</p>
<p>The donation is expected to provide more than 26,000 servings of hard-to-source protein for the hungry.</p>
<p>“Protein, animal protein is very, very desirable. We know that people need it for nourishment and it's difficult to get. And so this is going to make a very large<strong> impact</strong>," said McManus, the food bank chief.</p>
<p>“I don't <strong>anticipate</strong> this being here very long,'' he added. "We've had salmon before, but not like this.”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Michael Hill reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>complication</strong> – n. something that makes a situation more complicated or difficult</p>
<p><strong>landfill </strong>– n. a system of trash and garbage disposal in which the waste is buried between layers of earth to build up low-lying land</p>
<p><strong>manager </strong>– n. a person who looks after and make decisions about a business, activity or other operation</p>
<p><strong>sustainable </strong>– adj. of or related to the use of natural resources in a way that does not deplete them</p>
<p><strong>recirculate </strong>– v to cause to circulate (or flow without obstruction) again and again</p>
<p><strong>impact </strong>– n. an important effect</p>
<p><strong>anticipate</strong> – v. to expect; to look forward to as sure or certain</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers: NASA Asteroid Samples Contain ‘Building Blocks’ of Life  (2025/2/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/researchers-nasa-asteroid-samples-contain-building-blocks-of-life.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Scientists examining material collected from an <strong>asteroid</strong> say it appears to contain some of the chemical building blocks of life.</p>
<p>The American spacecraft OSIRIS-REx collected the <strong>samples</strong> in 2020 from the asteroid Bennu. In 2023, the spacecraft sent the rock and dust material back to Earth in a special container that landed by parachute. Scientists from the American space agency NASA recovered the samples in the western state of Utah.</p>
<p>OSIRIS-REx is already on its way to another asteroid called Apophis. It is expected to reach that asteroid in 2029.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This artist's rendering made available by NASA on shows the Origins Spectral Interpretation Resource Identification Security - Regolith Explorer (OSIRIS-REx) spacecraft contacting the asteroid Bennu with the Touch-And-Go Sample Arm Mechanism." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0a00-0242-b549-08dbbcfddc4a_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This artist's rendering made available by NASA on shows the Origins Spectral Interpretation Resource Identification Security - Regolith Explorer (OSIRIS-REx) spacecraft contacting the asteroid Bennu with the Touch-And-Go Sample Arm Mechanism.</span></div>
<p>On Bennu, the spacecraft collected a total of 122 grams of material. This is believed to be the largest sample collected from beyond the moon. NASA has shared some of the material with international researchers.</p>
<p>Two research groups released studies last week describing results of their examinations of the asteroid material.</p>
<p>One <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41550-024-02472-9">study</a>, published in <em>Nature Astronomy</em>, suggested the samples contained a mixture of <strong>organic</strong> compounds. Organic compounds have one or more carbon atoms that attach to other elements, usually hydrogen, oxygen, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_j4YfOxMd">nitrogen</a> and sulfur. All life on Earth is based on carbon and is built from organic compounds.</p>
<p>The other study, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-08495-6">published</a> in <em>Nature</em>, provides evidence that a much larger object, which Bennu is believed to have broken off from, once held salty, liquid water.</p>
<p>The researchers said this suggests that in the early solar system, asteroids such as Bennu might have transported water and life-supporting chemicals to other planets and moons.</p>
<p>Researchers from both groups noted it was important that the samples they worked with came directly from the asteroid itself. Asteroid pieces that fall to Earth turn into meteorites, and chemicals inside the samples can be changed or lost.</p>
<p>In a statement, NASA said the findings do not provide direct evidence of life itself. However, the space agency said, “They do suggest the conditions necessary for the <strong>emergence</strong> of life were widespread across the early solar system.” This increases the chances that “life could have formed on other planets and moons,” the statement added.</p>
<p>The parent of Bennu is believed to be an icy body measuring about 100 kilometers across. Scientists believe the body formed in the outer solar system and was later destroyed, possibly 1 to 2 billion years ago. The pieces that broke off likely formed Bennu and other asteroids observed to be masses of <strong>loose</strong> material, rather than solid objects.</p>
<p>Nicky Fox is the associate administrator for NASA's Science Mission Directorate in Washington D.C. She praised the OSIRIS-REx mission, saying it was “already rewriting the textbook on what we understand about the beginnings of our solar system.”</p>
<p>Fox added that she hopes the samples can help scientists understand “what <strong>ingredients</strong> in our solar system existed before life started on Earth.”</p>
<p>Tim McCoy is a researcher at the U.S. Smithsonian Institution and was a lead writer of the <em>Nature</em> study. He told the Associated Press (AP) that the samples may provide details about "the kind of environment that could have been <strong>essential</strong> to the steps that lead from elements to life.”</p>
<p>He noted that combining the ingredients of life with an environment of sodium-rich water is “really the pathway to life.” He added the samples suggest the processes involving the chemical compounds “probably occurred much earlier and were much more widespread than we had thought before."</p>
<p>Yasuhito Sekine is with the Institute of Science in Tokyo. He did not take part in the new research. Sekine confirmed the findings were only made possible by examining samples “collected directly from the asteroid, then carefully <strong>preserved</strong> back on Earth."</p>
<p>Jason Dworkin is a project scientist for the OSIRIS-REx mission at NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center in Maryland. He told Reuters news agency that all biology is made up of organic compounds. And some of those may have survived 4.5 billion years.</p>
<p>Dworkin said the materials from OSIRIS-REx provide new details about a solar system that might have had the right elements to support life. But he added that one of the most interesting questions, still remains: “Why we, so far, only see life on Earth and not elsewhere.”</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from The Associated Press, Reuters, Agence France-<a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_VWMHoets">Presse</a> and NASA.</em></p>
<p><strong>_____________________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>asteroid </strong><em>– n. </em>an object made of rock and metal that orbit the sun, but are smaller than planets</p>
<p><strong>sample </strong><em>– n. </em>a small amount of something that gives you information about the thing it was taken from</p>
<p><strong>organic </strong><em>– adj. </em>from a living organism</p>
<p><strong>emerge </strong><em>– v. </em>to appear from somewhere</p>
<p><strong>loose </strong><em>– adj. </em>not firmly attached</p>
<p><strong>ingredient </strong><em>– n. </em>the different parts that make up something</p>
<p><strong>preserve </strong><em>– v. </em>to keep something the same or prevent it from becoming damaged</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Conflict Complicates Environmental Problems at the Dead Sea  (2025/2/3)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/conflict-complicates-environmental-problems-at-the-dead-sea.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">02 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>International visitors to Israel used to visit Ein Gedi, a popular beach on the Dead Sea.</p>
<p>The Dead Sea is the place on Earth's surface that is farthest below sea level.</p>
<p>Now, the beautiful desert area is in ruins beside the shrinking, salty lake.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Rock patterns formed by crystalised minerals are pictured along the Dead Sea shore near Kibbutz Ein Gedi in eastern Israel on December 30, 2024. (Photo by Menahem Kahana / AFP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/08711a45-26f3-408c-9fd1-f4b5fbc0f569_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Rock patterns formed by crystalised minerals are pictured along the Dead Sea shore near Kibbutz Ein Gedi in eastern Israel on December 30, 2024. (Photo by Menahem Kahana / AFP)</span></div>
<p>The beach has been closed to the public for five years, mainly because of the appearance of dangerous holes in the ground. These holes, known as sinkholes, are caused by the collapse of the surface layer.</p>
<p>The beach has been closed because the drop in the sea's level has made it difficult to reach its waters.</p>
<p>These environmental changes are not new. The Dead Sea, where Israeli, Jordanian and Palestinian territory meet, has been dying for years. With the current conflict in the Middle East, efforts to deal with the environmental problem have disappeared too.</p>
<p>Nadav Tal of the Israel office of Eco Peace, a non-profit group, told the French News Agency (AFP), "<strong>Regional </strong>cooperation is the key... to saving the Dead Sea." Tal added: "Because we are living in a conflict area, there is an <strong>obstacle</strong>." Tal described how the sea has been<strong> declining </strong>more than one meter per year since the 1960s.</p>
<p><strong>Environmental disaster </strong></p>
<p>The <strong>evaporation</strong> of the salty waters takes place partly because temperatures reach up to 50 degrees Celsius in the summer. The sea has also been affected by years of increasing water usage from the sea's main source, the Jordan River, and other smaller waterways which begin in Lebanon and Syria.</p>
<p>Local factories also use the water to get minerals -- potash, bromine, sodium chloride, and magnesium chloride, among others. Tal told AFP, "The<strong> consequences</strong> of this water <strong>diversion</strong> is what we see around us.”</p>
<p>He described it as an “ecological disaster," adding that "the declining of the Dead Sea is a disaster for Israeli tourism."</p>
<p><strong>Call for joint efforts </strong></p>
<p>Efforts to deal with the Dead Sea disaster include past agreements signed by Israel and Jordan. But the wars taking place in Gaza and beyond have brought tensions to an all-time high. As a result, cross-border environmental issues are no longer getting attention.</p>
<p>At Israel's environment ministry, Ohad Carny has been working on the Dead Sea issue for years. He said the government was looking into several solutions. They include building a <strong>desalination</strong> factory and making a <strong>canal </strong>from either the north or the south to deal with water shortages in the area including the Dead Sea. But, he said, "It doesn't make economic or environmental sense to desalinate water and bring it directly to the Dead Sea, because then it's a waste of drinking water and the region needs...more drinking water and more water for agriculture.”</p>
<p>Carny said that his attention was on the Israeli side. But he added, "We can't do it alone. It must be a joint effort. So only time will tell, and we won't do anything without an agreement together with the Jordanian side."</p>
<p>Back at the Dead Sea, 40-year-old bus driver Benny is at a place where people can still visit. Benny was getting some winter sun at one of the warm sinkhole pools.</p>
<p>He said the sea's changes were difficult. "But everything has a plus and minus. Because of what is happening here, we have water spots like this one."</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Ruth Eglash reported this story for Agence France-Presse (AFP). John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>regional </strong>–<em> adj.</em> of or relating to a geographic area distinguished by similar features</p>
<p><strong>obstacle</strong> <em>– n.</em> something that slows progress or development; something that slows forward movement</p>
<p><strong>decline<em> </em></strong><em>–v.</em> to decrease</p>
<p><strong>consequences </strong><em>–n. (pl.)</em> the results of an action or process</p>
<p><strong>diversion </strong><em>– n.</em> the act of turning from one course or use to another</p>
<p><strong>evaporation</strong><em> –n.</em> the process by which a liquid becomes a gas</p>
<p><strong>desalination </strong><em>– n.</em> the process of removing salt from water</p>
<p><strong>canal </strong><em>– n.</em> an artificial waterway for draining or irrigating land</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>‘Kitchen-Table’ Is a Type of Politics  (2025/2/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/what-are-kitchen-table-politics.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" name="_Hlk81395775">On this program we explore words and expressions in the English language. We give examples and notes on usage.</a></p>
<p>Today we talk about different kinds of politics.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="People eating at Gotham restaurant on December 14, 2021, in New York City. (AP Photo/Brittainy Newman)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/45F04E84-B302-45E9-B677-D6B0CAB30522_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">People eating at Gotham restaurant on December 14, 2021, in New York City. (AP Photo/Brittainy Newman)</span></div>
<p>We start with <u>kitchen-table politics</u>. The kitchen is often considered the hub, or center,<strong> </strong>of the home. It is where we gather to not only share a meal but to talk about the events of the day. We often discuss issues of importance with our family and friends around the <strong>dining</strong> room table.</p>
<p>So, kitchen-table issues are those that affect individuals and their families daily. A family might discuss these issues at the kitchen table during mealtimes.</p>
<p>Rising gas and food prices are two good examples of kitchen-table politics. These issues affect decisions we make day to day. They are sometimes also called <strong>dinner</strong>-table politics. Or we could describe them as bread-and-butter issues.</p>
<p>Merriam Webster dictionary defines bread-and-butter issues as “being as <strong>basic</strong> as the earning of one's <strong>livelihood</strong>.” The online Cambridge Dictionary defines a bread-and-butter issue as “a subject or problem that relates directly to most people's needs and interests.”</p>
<p>For example, <strong>affordable</strong> food prices and availability of good healthcare are the kinds of bread-and-butter political issues that people vote on.</p>
<p>The noun <u>bread and butter</u> means a way of making a living. For example, for a creative writer, her ideas are her bread and butter.</p>
<p>So, bread-and-butter political issues deal with our ability to provide for the needs of ourselves and our families.</p>
<p>Next, let's talk about <u>green politics</u>. These political issues deal with caring for the natural environment. Green politics can cover ideas such as environmental <strong>sustainability</strong>, <strong>recycling</strong>,<strong> </strong>and threats to wildlife. The natural world is central to green politics.</p>
<p><u>Identity politics</u> is more personal. This term means that a person's political views are formed by their experiences and understanding of themselves. Things like <strong>gender</strong>, age, social and economic position, and religious belief can inform identity politics.</p>
<p>Finally, we come to <u>gotcha politics</u>. This type of politics is centered on damaging opponents through public accusations of wrongdoing or misbehavior. Gotcha politics often involves investigation into the private lives, past and present, of politicians in search of <strong>negative</strong> information.</p>
<p>In gotcha politics, “Gotcha” is short for “I got you,” meaning, “I caught you!”</p>
<p>And that's the end of this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>.</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>dine </strong><em>-v. </em>to eat dinner</p>
<p><strong>dinner </strong><em>-n. </em>the main meal of the day</p>
<p><strong>basic </strong><em>-adj. </em>of, relating to, or forming the base or essence</p>
<p><strong>livelihood </strong><em>-n. </em>means of support<em> </em></p>
<p><strong>affordable</strong> <em>-adj. </em>having a cost that is not too high</p>
<p><strong>sustainability </strong><em>-n. </em>of, relating to, or being a method of harvesting or using a resource so that the resource is not depleted or permanently damaged</p>
<p><strong>recycling </strong><em>-n. </em>to process (something, such as liquid body waste, glass, or cans) in order to regain material for human use</p>
<p><strong>gender</strong> <em>-n. </em>the behavioral, cultural, or psychological traits typically associated with one sex<em> </em></p>
<p><strong>negative </strong><em>-adj. </em>not positive or helpful</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Last Four Monkeys Return to ‘Monkey Farm’ in South Carolina  (2025/2/2)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202502/last-four-monkeys-return-to-monkey-farm-in-south-carolina.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">01 February, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Officials in the southern U.S. state of South Carolina have recaptured the last of 43 m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s who escaped from a farm that raises m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s in early November.</p>
<p>The chief executive of Alpha Genesis research center, Greg Westergaard, said the final four recaptured m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s appeared to be in good health. The remaining m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s had spent weeks living in the woods and even experienced a rare snowstorm.</p>
<p>Alpha Genesis is a company that offers services to biomedical researchers. Some locals call it “the m<i><i>onkey</i></i> farm." The animals – all female rhesus macaque m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s – escaped from the grounds of the company on November 6.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A rhesus macaques m&lt;I&gt;&lt;I&gt;onkey&lt;/I&gt;&lt;/I&gt; observes kayakers along the Silver River in Silver Springs, Fla., Friday, Nov. 10, 2017." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/478fc63d-e6a9-4e91-ac9b-c0b1ec6cb89a_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A rhesus macaques m<i><i>onkey</i></i> observes kayakers along the Silver River in Silver Springs, Fla., Friday, Nov. 10, 2017.</span></div>
<p>Police who investigated the incident said the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s escaped when an employee did not fully secure their enclosure. Westergaard explained in November that workers were supposed to <strong>lock</strong> one <strong>gate</strong> before opening another, but all three gates were left unsecure.</p>
<p>Employees at Alpha Genesis tried to persuade the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s to return with offers of special foods. These included peanut butter and jelly sandwiches and "m<i><i>onkey</i></i> <strong>biscuits</strong>" – a high-protein food made specially for rhesus macaques.</p>
<p>Alpha Genesis employees kept an eye on the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s and set out <strong>humane</strong> traps. Most of the animals came back to eat the food.</p>
<p>Most of the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s did not go far. The animals are about the size of a cat, weighing around 3 kilograms. The m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s never represented a risk to public health, police and federal health officials said. During the time they were free, the area received its first snow in seven years, measuring up to 8 centimeters.</p>
<p>The Alpha Genesis company raises the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s to sell to medical labs and other researchers. Humans have been using the m<i><i>onkey</i></i>s for scientific research since the late 1800s. Scientists believe rhesus macaques and humans split from a common ancestor about 25 million years ago and share about 93 percent of the same DNA.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>This story was reported by staff of the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>lock </strong>– <em>n.</em> a device that keeps something (such as a door, window, or box) from being opened and that is usually opened by using a key</p>
<p><strong>gate</strong> - <em>n</em>. a place in a wall or a fence that has a movable part which can be opened or closed like a door</p>
<p><strong>biscuit</strong> – n. a small, light roll that is eaten as part of a meal</p>
<p><strong>humane</strong> - <em>adj</em>. kind or gentle to people or animals</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What is the Best Kind of Yoga for Beginners?  (2025/2/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/what-is-the-best-kind-of-yoga-for-beginners.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">31 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>The activity called yoga means different things to different people around the world. The word itself comes from the Sanskrit language and means “union.”</p>
<p>For some, yoga is an exercise centered on mindful breathing and slow movement. For others, it is a series of difficult body movements and positioning designed to improve health and fitness. Still others consider yoga a spiritual exercise. And there are many people for whom yoga is a combination of all or some of these things.</p>
<p>So, yoga takes many different forms around the world.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A woman sits in lotus prayer pose during the " at="" beach="" bruna="" copacabana="" de="" event="" in="" janeiro="" june="" on="" photo="" prado="" rio="" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1d2a1895-d66c-4288-b81e-41aeb3230ea0_w268_r1.jpg" sunrise="" the="" yoga=""/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A woman sits in lotus prayer pose during the "Yoga at the Sunrise" event on Copacabana beach, in Rio de Janeiro, on June 22, 2024. (AP Photo/Bruna Prado)</span></div>
<p>All kinds of yoga involve positions known as poses (asanas). But the positions and training can differ even under yoga methods, or styles, of the same name, including hatha, vinyasa, Iyengar and others.</p>
<p>So, what is the best kind of yoga training for a beginner?</p>
<p>“The best is the one that works for you,” said Tim Senesi, who has been teaching yoga in Orange County, California, for 22 years. “There are many different paths leading toward the same aim,” he added.</p>
<p><strong>The hatha/yin yoga styles </strong></p>
<p>Hatha, meaning “force,” describes any kind of yoga class involving asanas. A sun salutation, for example, is an important series of 12 asanas that begin many kinds of yoga classes.</p>
<p>Training under the hatha name, however, is usually gentler than others and more centered on breathing exercises, called pranayama. Poses are held for a few breaths and students usually move more slowly.</p>
<p>Hatha can be good for beginners who are looking to <strong>relax </strong>while improving <strong>flexibility </strong>and balance.</p>
<p>Another style, yin, pays even more attention to recovery by working to stretch the muscles' connective tissue. Students hold poses for 5 minutes or more, permitting the body to settle into a pose rather than pushing it.</p>
<p><strong>The vinyasa/ashtanga styles </strong></p>
<p>A more difficult, flowing form of yoga is known as vinyasa. It mixes movement with breath over a series of asanas. Some higher-level vinyasa classes move at a rate of one movement per breath.</p>
<p>In the United States, these classes are often called Flow or Power yoga. They can be good for people who are more athletic. Still, teachers suggest that even athletic students start with a beginner level.</p>
<p>“I wouldn't really <strong>encourage</strong> them to start in a higher level vinyasa flow class because they're not going to have the <strong>foundation</strong> to move safely through that,” said Anne Van Valkenburg, of Lanai, Hawaii. She has been training yoga teachers in a mix of methods for 18 years.</p>
<p>Ashtanga yoga is similar to vinyasa. However, ashtanga involves a set series of poses that students repeat day after day, often going at their own speed. As students get stronger and more skilled, they move up to a higher series with more difficult poses.</p>
<p><strong>The Iyengar style </strong></p>
<p>Iyengar style involves the same poses as vinyasa, but classes usually move at a slower pace. However, the poses are not necessarily easier. Iyengar yoga pays special attention to carefully moving or aligning parts of the body. Poses are held for longer and students often use supportive equipment during the exercise.</p>
<p>Iyengar is especially good for people recovering from injuries. It can also be a good fit for physically active people who want to get the basics of yoga before moving into different styles.</p>
<p><strong>Find a good fit </strong></p>
<p>These days, teachers often mix different yoga methods in a single class. And many classes are not named under any traditional method.</p>
<p>The AP suggests that if you are interested in starting to practice yoga, you should look for a beginner series. But if you cannot find one that is right, do not worry. Most teachers are happy to have beginners in their classes and will alter the training to meet the needs of students new to yoga.</p>
<p>Most of all, try a few classes until you find the method or teacher who is a good fit for you.</p>
<p>“I feel sad when someone tries yoga once or twice and they're like, ‘Eh, I don't like it,'” Van Valkenburg said, adding, “there's just so much out there that you might be missing...”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Albert Stumm reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>relax<em> </em></strong><em>– v. </em>to make or become less tense or worried</p>
<p><strong>flexibility</strong> <em>– n.</em> the ability of joints and muscles to move through a range of motion</p>
<p><strong>encourage </strong><em>– v.</em> to make someone want to do something<br/>
<br/>
<strong>foundation<em> </em></strong><em>– n.</em> a base upon which something stands or is supported</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Accountability, Responsibility, Liability  (2025/2/1)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/accountability-responsibility-liability.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">31 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Saeed in Iran about words that can express the idea of duty.</p>
<p>Here is Saeed's question:</p>
<p>Dear teacher,</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Ask a Teacher: Accountability, Responsibility, Liability" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/86e0a0ea-09ea-403a-8add-5a25cdcc43c7_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Ask a Teacher: Accountability, Responsibility, Liability</span></div>
<p>What is the difference between accountability, responsibility, and liability?</p>
<p>Especially from the point of view of law.</p>
<p>Sincerely, Saeed</p>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Saeed.</p>
<p>All three of the words you ask about express the idea of duty. A duty is what a person must do because it is right and just.</p>
<p>Let's begin with the noun “responsibility.” It is the most common word of the three, and we use it in everyday speech. However, when we talk about responsibility in legal terms, we are more likely to use the noun “duty.”</p>
<p>We often refer to a <strong>task</strong> when we use the word “responsibility” or its adjective form, “responsible.” The following examples show this:</p>
<p><em>It is a pilot's responsibility to safely fly the airplane. </em></p>
<p><em>A pilot is responsible for safely flying the airplane.</em></p>
<p>When we want to say that only one person or subject is responsible for something, we can use the adjective “sole,” spelled s-o-l-e, or the adverb “solely,” as in these examples:</p>
<p><em>Any mistakes are <u>the sole responsibility</u> of the writer. </em></p>
<p><em>The writer is <u>solely responsible for</u> what he or she posts on social media. </em></p>
<p>To express the idea that someone should agree to having a duty, we can use the expression “take responsibility for,” as in the following example:</p>
<p><em>People must <u>take responsibility for</u> their own actions. </em></p>
<p><strong>Accountability and liability</strong></p>
<p>We usually use the noun “accountability” to refer to possible <strong>penalties</strong> or bad results people may face if they do not do their duty. To do this, we use the verb “hold” before the adjective “accountable,” as in this example:</p>
<p><em>The problem was that no one in the office <u>was held accountable for </u>their actions. </em></p>
<p>We often use the noun “accountability” when discussing organizations. For example, if a business has a “system of accountability,” that means the company's leaders and workers likely face a penalty if they do not carry out their duties.</p>
<p>“Liability” is the most specific term of the three nouns. If someone or some group has legal liability, that means they have a duty that can be judged in a court of law. We use the adjective form, “liable,” to say that a person or group can face legal penalties because they were not as careful as they should have been. The following example shows this usage:</p>
<p><em>The company was <u>held liable for</u> failure to warn about the danger of its product. </em></p>
<p>Notice that we use the verb “hold” before the adjective “liable,” just like we do before the adjective “accountable.”</p>
<p>There is also a common use of the noun “liability” in everyday speech that is not linked to legal issues. We can say that something or someone is “a liability” if they make bad results more likely. The following example shows this usage:</p>
<p><em>That football player is getting old and is too slow. He has become a liability for the team.</em></p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? We want to hear from you! Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please let us know where you are from, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>task </strong><em>–n.</em> a piece of work or a job that needs to be done</p>
<p><strong>penalty </strong><em>–n.</em> anything that has the effect of punishing a person or group for what they have or have not done</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>In India, Sudden Sea Turtle Deaths Cause Concern  (2025/1/31)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/in-india-sudden-sea-turtle-deaths-cause-concern.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">30 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Over 400 dead sea turtles have been found on India's east coast near the city of Chennai in the last two weeks. Those numbers have not been seen in more than 20 years.</p>
<p>The <strong>species</strong> of turtle is known as olive ridley. The animals travel thousands of kilometers for ideal places to lay their eggs along India's coast. But that process, called nesting, has become more difficult because undisturbed beaches are becoming harder to find around the world. And, mass deaths like these can be caused by fishing <strong>nets</strong> that can catch and harm the species.</p>
<p>Shravan Krishnan is a volunteer with Chennai-based Students Sea Turtles <strong>Conservation</strong> Network. He told The Associated Press that in a usual year, there are between 100 to 200 adult turtle deaths on the city's coast. "This year, we've already crossed 200 dead turtles in a little more than two weeks," he said.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - An olive ridley turtle drags sand to cover its nest after laying it at the Rushikulya River in Ganjam, India, March 13, 2015." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/3ef18e6a-495d-413b-a6f8-d6da9fbfc89f_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - An olive ridley turtle drags sand to cover its nest after laying it at the Rushikulya River in Ganjam, India, March 13, 2015.</span></div>
<p>Krishnan is also concerned about the low number of turtles nesting on shore. He and other conservationists walk along the city's beaches at night to collect and move turtle nests. They do so to prevent the eggs from being eaten by dogs or damaged by people walking along the coast. "We have found only four nests so far, which is also really worrying," Krishnan said.</p>
<p><strong>Highest turtle deaths in the last twenty years</strong></p>
<p>Environmentalists and forest department officials have been seeing at least ten dead turtles every day for the past few days, sometimes many more. That is the highest number officials have seen since 2014. Experts say the deaths are most likely caused by large fishing nets that are pulled along the ocean floor.</p>
<p>Manish Meena is in charge of the city's wildlife. He said groups have been actively trying to inform people involved in fishing to release turtles that might get caught in nets. They have also asked the coast guard to watch for illegal fishing activity.</p>
<p>Fishing boats using giant nets that catch everything on the ocean floor are barred by a local government order from operating within five <strong>nautical miles</strong> of the coastline during the turtle nesting season. The law also requires the use of devices that can help turtles escape nets.</p>
<p>Shantanu Kalambi is an ocean animal specialist with the conservation organization ReefWatch. He said that when the turtles get caught in nets, they are unable to come up to the surface for air. And environmentalists say the crews of fishing boats do not always use the devices to help turtles escape, since they reduce how many fish they can catch.</p>
<p><strong>A number of threats</strong></p>
<p>Olive ridley turtles are considered an endangered species. Just like most sea turtles, their eggs need two months to <strong>hatch.</strong> This places them at higher risk because of coastal land activity, warmer temperatures and pollution from light.</p>
<p>Farther up India's east coast, over 500,000 turtles nest every year. But only one in about 1,000 turtle babies that hatch survives to adulthood.</p>
<p>Experts say the turtles are important to the balance of the ocean <strong>ecosystem. </strong></p>
<p>"As a species, they are millions of years old and they play an <strong>essential</strong> role in the food chain," Kalambi said.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Sibi Arasu reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>species </strong>-<em>n</em>. <em>biology</em>. a group of animals or plants that are similar and can produce young animals or plants</p>
<p><strong>net</strong> <em>– n</em>. a device that is used for catching or holding things or for keeping things out of a space and that is made of pieces of string, rope, wire, etc., woven together with spaces in between</p>
<p><strong>conservation </strong>– <em>n</em>. the protection of animals, plants, and natural resources</p>
<p><strong>nautical mile</strong> – <em>n</em>. a unit of distance equal to 1,852 meters that is used for sea and air travel</p>
<p><strong>hatch</strong> – <em>v. of a bird, insect, fish.</em> to come out of an egg : to be born by coming out of an egg</p>
<p><strong>ecosystem</strong> – <em>n</em>. everything that exists in a particular environment</p>
<p><strong>essential </strong>– <em>adj</em>. necessary</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Is the Pink Substance Dropped on LA Fires Safe?  (2025/1/30)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/is-the-pink-substance-dropped-on-la-fires-safe.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">29 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>The efforts to battle widespread fires across Los Angeles included aircraft drops of a bright red and pink substance.</p>
<p>The material covered forests, homes, cars, and other things in the path of the wind-fueled fires. Because the substance was dropped in many <strong>residential</strong> areas, some people have wondered how safe it is.</p>
<p>The material is a fire <strong>retardant</strong>. The kind dropped around Los Angeles was mostly a product called Phos-Chek. The substance has been used by the U.S. Forest Service to fight fires since the 1960s.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="An air tanker drops retardant while working to contain the Eaton Fire in Altadena, Calif., Monday, Jan. 13, 2025." src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1bebe65d-a252-4781-8b96-0678d9f00565_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">An air tanker drops retardant while working to contain the Eaton Fire in Altadena, Calif., Monday, Jan. 13, 2025.</span></div>
<p>Jason Colquhoun is a 53-year-old pilot with HeliQwest, an aircraft company specializing in firefighting activities. He told the French news agency Agence France-Presse (AFP) that using the Barbie-pink material makes his job easier. "You can see it so easily ... it's <strong>amazing</strong>," he said.</p>
<p>Daniel McCurry is an associate professor of civil and environmental engineering at the University of Southern California. He said that in recent weeks, Phos-Chek had been dropped in residential areas more than ever before. That fact has led many to question its safety.</p>
<p>Phos-Chek is sold by fire protection equipment supplier Perimeter Solutions. It is a mixture of mostly ammonium phosphate or ammonium polyphosphate. These substances are also used to produce fertilizer. Other chemicals are added to the mixture to give it color. Perimeter told AFP the substance is designed to be one color. But it can look different depending on time of day, lighting, or smoke.</p>
<p>The bright pink color helps pilots as they try to make sure they have covered a whole area, Colquhoun explained. He noted that when pilots drop water from the air, they have to search for "the shine and the darkness" to know where to make the next drop. The colorful retardant, however, is "so much easier to spot," Colquhoun said.</p>
<p>McCurry said another reason it is better than water is that it keeps working even after the water it is mixed with dries. Phos-Chek is made thick so the wind does not blow it away and to ensure that it covers the desired area.</p>
<p>McCurry explained the substance works by forming a <strong>coating</strong> that will not burn. After the water dries up, the retardant keeps working until rain washes it into the ground. McCurry said a former firefighter told him that in a high-intensity fire the substance is "not much use." He added that the high winds driving the fires in Los Angeles may have limited its effectiveness.</p>
<p>U.S. Forest Service spokesperson Wade Muehlhof said the agency only uses retardants that meet U.S. government rules for not being harmful to animals, humans, or things living in water. He told AFP the Forest Service usually does not drop the retardant in waterways and areas home to endangered animals -- unless the fire is threatening human life or public safety. But accidents do happen, he said, and the wind may blow it into such areas.</p>
<p>McCurry said he believes Phos-Chek is “likely not harmless to the environment” now. But, he added, "On the other hand, the human health <strong>impact</strong> is still a little unclear." He noted that it would take "a lot" of retardant to poison, say, a large body of water.</p>
<p>But he said that as firefighters battled the Los Angeles fires, the substance was dropped on a lot of neighborhoods in “<strong>unprecedented</strong>”<strong> </strong>amounts. McCurry said Phos-Chek is more often used further from populated areas, or in lesser amounts. "So, who knows," he added.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Huw Griffith and Sarah Titterton reported this story for Agence France-Presse.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>residential </strong>– <em>adj</em>. an area where people live</p>
<p><strong>retardant</strong> – <em>n</em>. something that is able to slow down the progress or development of something</p>
<p><strong>amazing</strong> – <em>adj</em>. causing great surprise or wonder</p>
<p><strong>coating</strong> – <em>n</em>. a thin layer of material that covers the surface of something</p>
<p><strong>impact </strong>– <em>n.</em> a powerful or major influence or effect</p>
<p><strong>unprecedented </strong>– <em>adj</em>. never having happened before</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Scientists with Disabilities Seek Changes to Improve their Work  (2025/1/29)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/scientists-with-disabilities-seek-changes-to-improve-their-work.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/>
<span class="datetime">28 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Disabled researchers often face barriers while carrying out their work. So some scientists with disabilities are seeking to increase attention about the problem and come up with workable solutions.</p>
<p>Anita Marshall is a geologist with the University of Florida. She recently told The Associated Press (AP) that while she faces some limitations, it does not mean she cannot do her job. “Just because you can't do it like someone else doesn't mean you can't do it,” she said.</p>
<p>Marshall recently led an outing of disabled researchers to a natural lake in Southern California's San Bernadino National Forest.</p>
<div class="contentImage"><img alt="Taormina Lepore, foreground, who has low vision, walks with a white cane during the accessible field trip Sept. 26, 2024, in San Bernadino, Calif. (AP Photo/Ryan Sun)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/52f9daf9-6d6d-40df-8faa-0fd4f56d6862_cx0_cy8_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/>
<span class="imagecaption">Taormina Lepore, foreground, who has low vision, walks with a white cane during the accessible field trip Sept. 26, 2024, in San Bernadino, Calif. (AP Photo/Ryan Sun)</span></div>
<p>The group included scientists and students with disabilities related to sight, hearing and mobility. They visited Lost Lake, which sits along the area's San Andreas Fault. The fault contains two <strong>tectonic plates</strong> that can cause earthquakes.</p>
<p>The trip was organized by Marshall's group, called the International Association for Geoscience Diversity. It aims to demonstrate the difficulties, or challenges, disabled researchers often face. Other groups also aim to improve <strong>access </strong>to field and laboratory work so those with disabilities feel welcome and stay.</p>
<p>Taormina Lepore is a Western Michigan University paleontologist who went on the trip. She told the AP that one problem is that many scientists seem to value a single, traditional way of doing their work. This makes it more difficult to get changes for disabled researchers.</p>
<p>On the trip to Lost Lake, everyone got to see the lake even if they could not get there physically. Some attendees saw the surroundings on video taken by a drone.</p>
<p>Lepore, who also researches science education, said an important part of the process is for scientists to think about what might help other scientists they work with. “It's really about <strong>empathy</strong>, as much as it is about science.”</p>
<p>The National Science Foundation said in 2021 that disabled people make up about three percent of the science, technology, engineering, and math workforce.</p>
<p>Scientists with disabilities say the low percentage is partly because labs, classrooms and field areas are not designed for disabled individuals.</p>
<p>Mark Leddy used to oversee disability-related <strong>grants </strong>for the National Science Foundation. He noted that some students and <strong>faculty </strong>are still told they cannot work in a lab or do research safely.</p>
<p>The Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 does set rules for new buildings and labs. These include requiring <strong>ramps </strong>and walkways that can be used by people in wheelchairs. But making changes to older labs can be costly and difficult.</p>
<p>Alyssa Paparella is working on her doctorate degree in biology at Baylor College of Medicine in Texas. She founded an online community for disabled scientists. Paparella said a science building at one of her former schools did not have the needed buttons to open the doors. “That's the front door that they're not even able to get in.”</p>
<p>Leddy said researchers with disabilities are invaluable because of their life experiences. They have to come up with creative ways to get past barriers in their lives — a problem-solving skill that is needed in a lab.</p>
<p>Jennifer Piatek is a professor of Earth and Space Sciences at Central Connecticut State University. She uses a wheelchair but was able to see through drone video.</p>
<p>Piatek said it was nice to be part of a community that took her needs into account. You can learn a lot from images and maps, “but really you need to get to the space to be in it.”</p>
<p>Western Michigan's Lepore is a <strong>neurodivergent</strong> person with low vision. She noted, “Nature is not <strong>inherently </strong>accessible.”</p>
<p>Bushra Hussaini works at New York City's American Museum of Natural History. She told the AP that by going on field trips, she learns new ways to support <strong>interns </strong>and volunteers who visit the museum. She said the supportive community of geologists is what keeps her coming back. “We learn from each other and we help each other.”</p>
<p>As a doctoral student, Marshall went on field trips with other students. But she often had to wait in the car because the organizers had not thought about her disabilities. Marshall wants things to be different for the next generation of scientists. “The whole point of these little day trips is to just plant that seed out there...that there's another way forward,” she said.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter Jr. And I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Adithi Ramakrishnan reported this story for the Associated Press. Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>tectonic plate</strong> <em>–n.</em> one of the parts of the earth's surface that move in relation to each other</p><p>
<strong>access</strong> <em>–n.</em> the ability to use or do an activity or take part in a program</p><p>
<strong>empathy</strong> <em>–n.</em> the belief that you can feel what others feel</p><p>
<strong>grant </strong><em>–n.</em> an amount of money that is given by an organization to an individual or group to do a specific task or service and which does not need to be paid back</p><p>
<strong>faculty</strong> <em>–n.</em> a group of teachers at a school or a college</p><p>
<strong>ramp</strong> <em>–n.</em> a structure that lets wheeled vehicles or wheelchairs get up stairs or steep ground</p><p>
<strong>neurodivergent</strong> <em>–adj.</em> having a condition that causes the brain to process information differently than most individuals</p><p>
<strong>inherently</strong> <em>–adv.</em> belonging to a person's nature or way of being</p><p>
<strong>intern</strong> <em>–n.</em> a young person who works in an organization to learn skills for future employment</p></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>How to Protect Against Increased Viral Spread in Winter  (2025/1/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/how-to-protect-against-wintertime-viruses.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">27 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p class="MsoBodyText">Influenza, or the flu, COVID-19, norovirus and the common cold easily spread throughout the winter season.</p>
<p>Knowing what these infections are and how they spread can help us avoid them. The Associated Press has listed some things anyone can do to keep healthy and to know more about these infections:</p>
<p><strong>Cold, flu, or COVID?</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A flu vaccine is displayed at a pharmacy in New York, on Tuesday, Sept. 24, 2024. (AP Photo/Mary Conlon, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1b9b0c9f-5a06-4670-aadc-dd16870c7d70_cx0_cy3_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A flu vaccine is displayed at a pharmacy in New York, on Tuesday, Sept. 24, 2024. (AP Photo/Mary Conlon, File)</span></div>
<p>Some signs, or symptoms, of a cold, the flu, COVID-19 or norovirus are similar. This can make it hard to know what is making us sick.</p>
<p>However, some symptoms are unmistakable.</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cdc.gov/norovirus/about/index.html">Norovirus</a> spreads through polluted food, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_QgPoTeZo">water</a> and surfaces, including the skin. The virus causes <strong>vomiting</strong>, <strong>diarrhea</strong>, and stomach pain. The sickness can last for about one to three days.</p>
<p>The <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cdc.gov/common-cold/about/index.html">common cold</a> can be caused by several different kinds of viruses and can include several symptoms. These include a runny nose, <strong>congestion</strong>, <strong>cough</strong>, <strong>sneezing</strong>, and pain in the throat, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_VBZd1fld">head</a> and other parts of the body. It can also cause higher than normal body temperature, or a fever. The common cold usually lasts less than a week.</p>
<p>The <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cdc.gov/flu/signs-symptoms/index.html">flu</a> is caused by influenza viruses that are always changing. Infection leads to fever, cough, sore throat, runny nose, body <strong>aches</strong>, headaches and feeling tired. Flu symptoms usually hit more quickly than cold symptoms. They can last from a few days to two weeks.</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cdc.gov/covid/signs-symptoms/index.html">COVID-19</a> can cause fever, <strong>chills</strong>, cough, congestion, tiredness and throat and head pain. Other signs of COVID are the loss of smell or taste, difficulty breathing, nausea, or vomiting. The sickness can last for several days.</p>
<p>The respiratory syncytial virus, or <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cdc.gov/rsv/symptoms/index.html">RSV</a>, can make people sick for one or two weeks. The signs include runny nose, congestion, coughing, sneezing, breathing problems, fever, and a loss of <strong>appetite</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Wash your hands</strong></p>
<p>So how can we avoid infections? Experts say people should wash their hands carefully and often with a cleanser such as soap. Clean hands are very important to reducing the spread of norovirus, colds, flu and COVID-19.</p>
<p>The United States Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) says this is especially true after using the bathroom, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_vYnFPopf">eating</a> or preparing food.</p>
<p>Make sure you take enough time to wash your hands. It should take at least 20 seconds to complete the job.</p>
<p>If you do not have soap and water available, cleansers called hand sanitizers are a good substitute. The sanitizer must be at least 60 percent alcohol to be effective against most of these viruses. An exception is norovirus which requires a stronger sanitizer.</p>
<p><strong>Cleaning surfaces can remove viruses</strong></p>
<p>To avoid norovirus, you must immediately clean surfaces that have come in contact with infected food or bodily fluids. The CDC advises disinfecting things with a chlorine bleach solution or <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-registration/epas-registered-antimicrobial-products-effective-against-norovirus-feline">one of the products listed on the Environmental Protection Agency website</a>.</p>
<p>Do not forget to wash any clothing that has come in contact with vomit or other bodily waste. Use hot water and soap. Then, wash your hands again.</p>
<p>With colds and flu, it is best to repeatedly clean surfaces that are touched or used often. These include doorknobs, light switches, kitchen workspaces, children's playthings, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_BaPXCDc6">cellphones</a> and other objects around the home.</p>
<p>Use household cleaning products that contain soap or detergent and follow up with a sanitizer. <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cdc.gov/hygiene/about/when-and-how-to-clean-and-disinfect-your-home.html#:~:text=Clean%20first%20and%20clean%20regularly,viruses%20or%20bacteria%20from%20surfaces.">The CDC has more advice on how to clean</a>.</p>
<p>COVID-19 spreads through the air in small drops and particles. The CDC says there is low risk of getting the virus from surfaces.</p>
<p><strong>Keeping your hands off your face can keep viruses out</strong></p>
<p>Viruses can spread through talking, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_98beP7cn">coughing</a> and sneezing, so cover your mouth with a tissue when you sneeze or cough. Then, wash your hands.</p>
<p>Do not touch your face. If you have viruses on your unwashed hands and touch your face, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_NHfUg1Ij">eyes</a> or nose, they can get into your body. Your likelihood of getting sick will increase.</p>
<p><strong>Consider a vaccine (if there is one)</strong></p>
<p>You might consider a vaccine if one is available.</p>
<p>Updated COVID-19 vaccines are available. <a class="wsw__a" href="https://apnews.com/article/covid19-flu-rsv-vaccines-shots-ad33f4fe23f4c293ab87415b6449d9ad">Yearly flu shots</a> for people 6 months and older are also available. For adults 60 and older or people who are pregnant, you might want to get the <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.cdc.gov/rsv/about/prevention.html">RSV vaccine</a>.</p>
<p>There is no vaccine for norovirus or the common cold.</p>
<p><strong>Another way to keep your defenses against viruses up: Rest</strong></p>
<p>Your immune system may not work as well if you are lacking enough sleep, water or are experiencing high levels of tension. Rest. <a class="wsw__a" href="https://apnews.com/article/sleep-stress-anxiety-caffeine-alcohol-35dfa5725a0fdefae0b18d5442e55cb3">Sleep</a>. And drink enough water.</p>
<p><strong>Stay at home</strong></p>
<p>If you do get sick, you can take a test to find out if you have COVID-19 or influenza. It is important to know if you have a virus that could be treated with available medicines. The drug Paxlovid treats COVID-19. Tamiflu is used to treat flu.</p>
<p>Above all, if you have symptoms of any of these sicknesses, stay at home and away from other people. This will help stop the spread of viruses.</p>
<p>To treat a cold, flu or COVID-19, rest and drink fluids. You can take pain medicine to lower a fever or to ease pain. Humidifier machines, which increase the amount of water in the air, can also help ease symptoms.</p>
<p>There is no medication for norovirus. You need to replace fluids lost because of <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_Y8uzUGms">the sickness</a>. Drink as much water and other liquids as possible. Seek medical help if you notice you have a dry mouth and throat, are not expelling liquid waste easily, or feel <strong>dizzy</strong> when standing.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver. And I'm Mario Ritter Jr.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press produced this report. Caty Weaver adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>vomiting </strong><em>–n.</em> expelling what is inside your stomach through your mouth</p>
<p><strong>diarrhea </strong><em>–n.</em> a sickness that can cause an infected person to pass waste and fluid often</p>
<p><strong>congestion </strong><em>–n.</em> blockage in the area of the nose caused by fluid</p>
<p><strong>cough </strong><em>–n.</em> involuntarily expelling air through the throat in a quick action</p>
<p><strong>sneezing </strong>–n. suddenly expelling air through the nose and throat</p>
<p><strong>ache </strong>–n. physical and lasting pain in a part of the body</p>
<p><strong>chill </strong>–n. a feeling of being cold with involuntary shaking</p>
<p><strong>appetite </strong>–n. the desire to eat food</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Using Real Trees to Bring Nature Indoors  (2025/1/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/using-real-trees-to-bring-nature-indoors.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">27 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>There is a growing movement worldwide to use plants in building design to establish closer connections with nature and soften hard city <strong>styles</strong>. The movement also seeks to improve designs to help protect the environment and increase personal wellness.</p>
<p>Many of the efforts by <strong>architects</strong> and designers have centered on one natural element: trees.</p>
<p>Examples of such design can be found in many places, including New York City. A building in Manhattan that houses the Ford Foundation has a 12-story light-filled entrance area, or atrium. It is also filled with plants and flowers including magnolias, eucalyptus, jacaranda, cryptomeria, iron bark and pear trees.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This photo provided by KAA Design Group shows the Tree House's primary suite private courtyard with Japanese wood soaking tub and reflecting pool. (KAA Design Group via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/0b7cabf1-745d-4ca8-96e4-686baef461fe_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This photo provided by KAA Design Group shows the Tree House's primary suite private courtyard with Japanese wood soaking tub and reflecting pool. (KAA Design Group via AP)</span></div>
<p>Another example sits within New York City's Brookfield Place shopping center. The center's main atrium includes a collection of 12-meter-tall Washingtonia palm trees.</p>
<p>In Singapore, the city-state's Jewel Changi airport offers travelers an inviting environment. It has 2,500 trees native to nations including Madagascar, Australia, Malaysia and Indonesia. The airport includes a 2.4-hectare indoor forest with walking paths.</p>
<p>Some <strong>apartments</strong> and mixed-use buildings are also putting trees and other greenery into their designs. Such buildings are sometimes called “greenscrapers,” a term that comes from the word “<strong>skyscraper.”</strong></p>
<p>In Milan, Italy, architect Stefano Boeri designed Bosco Verticale, a 44-story building with 800 trees and other greenery. In the Netherlands, he also built the Trudo Vertical Forest. This is a low-income apartment building with trees growing on all sides.</p>
<p>Similar changes are also happening inside private homes. In some, trees are brought right indoors. In others, outdoor trees are carefully placed as important partners in the building plan.</p>
<p>Some architects even build homes around existing trees. Others plant one or more trees inside the home. And some architects or designers imagine natural settings indoors by using parts of trees. These designs are meant to create the look and feel of real wood, while bringing feelings of peace and calm.</p>
<p><strong>A calm heart of the home</strong></p>
<p>Ryoko Okada is an architect at New York City's Oda Architecture. She told The Associated Press that she and her co-workers aim to bring outdoor elements indoors as often as they can.</p>
<p>“There's nothing more calming than being surrounded by nature...” Okada said. She added that a living tree indoors can bring peace and happiness as people watch it grow and change.</p>
<p><strong>Framing the views with existing trees</strong></p>
<p>Another design example came from KAA Design Group in Los Angeles. A team from the company created a modern home that uses the property's existing trees, such as cork oaks, rare Torrey pines, and magnolias.</p>
<p>One very large, old cork oak sits in the center of the property. At first, the owners did not like the look and said they wanted the tree gone. One of the company's partners, Grant Kirkpatrick, had to persuade the homeowners to keep it. Kirkpatrick explained he succeeded by pointing out that the tree was “a 300-year-old <strong>antique</strong> that should be <strong>featured </strong>rather than removed.”</p>
<p>The driveway on that property also offers a calming design. A black pine tree rises up from the driveway like a piece of natural art. In addition, views from almost every window in the house feature the beautiful nature outdoors.</p>
<p><strong>Things to consider</strong></p>
<p>Okada says she suggests people do not plant a full-size tree in their home without first seeking expert advice. She notes that a living tree will only do well if certain conditions – such as air, light and soil – are right.</p>
<p>Okada added that a living tree “...needs to be supported by proper <strong>infrastructure</strong> to stay alive and avoid home damage.” She also urges people to heavily research a tree's natural environment to avoid drawing in unwanted <strong>pests</strong>.</p>
<p>Kirkpatrick noted that planting a tree indoors can be difficult. He explained that at least 1.2 meters of soil depth is needed, along with lots of natural light and the right temperature.</p>
<p><strong>Other ways to use trees besides having a live one</strong></p>
<p>Kirkpatrick said he worked on one property that experienced a serious fire in 2016. His team decided to use parts from one of the burned manzanita trees in the interior design. The piece was painted black and placed inside the property. He said it now represents an eye-catching, natural art piece.</p>
<p>I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Kim Cook reported this story for the Associated Press from New York, New York. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>skyscraper </strong><em>-n.</em><strong> </strong>a very tall building<br/>
<strong>style </strong><em>-n. </em>a particular manner or technique by which something is done, created, or performed</p>
<p><strong>architect </strong><em>-n. </em>a person who designs buildings and advises in their construction</p>
<p><strong>apartment </strong><em>-n. </em>a room or set of rooms used as a dwelling</p>
<p><strong>antique </strong><em>-adj. </em>being in the style or fashion of former times</p>
<p><strong>feature </strong><em>-n. </em>a part or detail that stands out</p>
<p><strong>infrastructure</strong> <em>-n. </em>the underlying foundation or basic framework</p>
<p><strong>pest </strong><em>-n. </em>a plant or animal harmful to human beings or human concerns</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>The American South Gets ‘Once-in-a Lifetime’ Snow and Cold  (2025/1/28)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/the-american-south-gets-once-in-a-lifetime-snow-and-cold.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">27 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>People in the southern U.S. state of Florida are used to warm, sunny weather. But on January 21, Floridians saw a rare sight: snow on their beaches. A cold weather system brought snow to several southern states in what many are calling a once-in-a-lifetime event.</p>
<p>So much snow fell across the American South that snowballs flew on Bourbon Street in New Orleans, Louisiana, and children and parents used any kind of plastic they could find to slide down snow-covered hills along the Mississippi River.</p>
<p>The Associated Press reported that 24.9 centimeters of snow fell near the small town of Milton, Florida. That breaks the snowfall record of 10.1 centimeters from 1954.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="An ice covered fountain sits in front of a Mardi Gras festooned skeleton the day after a rare and record setting snowstorm in River Ridge, La., a suburb of New Orleans, Wednesday, Jan. 22, 2025. " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f02d36d4-0a04-4a0e-8af1-7b62d1203c79_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">An ice covered fountain sits in front of a Mardi Gras festooned skeleton the day after a rare and record setting snowstorm in River Ridge, La., a suburb of New Orleans, Wednesday, Jan. 22, 2025. </span></div>
<p>"It's an incredible, incredible event," said Michael Mugrage. Mugrage is a meteorologist at the National Weather Service office in Mobile, Alabama. That is where many of the highest snowfall numbers from the South were reported. "It puts it in <strong>perspective</strong> how rare this is."</p>
<p>Milton is northeast of Pensacola, Florida, where 22.6 centimeters broke the city's previous all-time snow record of 7.6 centimeters set in 1895.</p>
<p>Here are some places reporting rare snowfall events:</p>
<p><strong>New Orleans, Louisiana</strong></p>
<p>The National Weather Service reported that in some parts of New Orleans, 25 centimeters of snow fell. That broke the city's record of 6.8 centimeters from 1963.</p>
<p><strong>Houston, Texas</strong></p>
<p>In Texas, up to 10 centimeters of snow fell in the Houston area. The area reportedly does not own any trucks with snow-moving equipment known as snowplows.</p>
<p><strong>Charleston, South Carolina</strong></p>
<p>More than 10 centimeters of snow fell in and around Charleston, South Carolina, where snow closed the airport.</p>
<p><strong>Mobile, Alabama</strong></p>
<p>At Mobile Regional Airport in Alabama, 15.7 centimeters of snow was recorded, breaking the city's one-day snowfall record of 12.7 centimeters. The record was set on January 24, 1881, the weather service said. A reported snowfall total of 28 centimeters in the small town of Babbie in southern Alabama was among the highest nationwide for the day.</p>
<p><strong>Cold and snowy</strong></p>
<p>It was very cold in Mobile, too. The National Weather Service said a low of <strong>minus</strong> 14 Celsius tied the third-coldest low temperature record for the city, set in 1899. In Louisiana, all-time records for low temperatures were reported in the cities of New Iberia and Lafayette. Wednesday's low of minus 17 Celsius in New Iberia broke a record that had stood since 1962. Lafayette's low of minus 16 Celsius broke a record that dates back to 1899.</p>
<p>Across several southern states, flights were cancelled, and some highways were closed.</p>
<p><strong>Europe's climate agency reports record high temperatures</strong></p>
<p>The record snowfall and low temperatures did not affect the entire world. The AP reports Europe's Copernicus climate service data shows the first 20 days of January 2025 had the highest average temperature worldwide recorded for the first 20 days of any year.</p>
<p>So far this year, U.S. weather has set or equaled 697 daily records for coldest temperatures. That is close to the 629 daily records that have been reported so far this year for warmest temperatures. The National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration said that in the past 365 days, U.S. weather stations have recorded five times as many heat records as cold records.</p>
<p>Scientists say they seem to be seeing more cool air but not cooler weather. Some scientists hold the theory that warm temperatures in the Arctic area are displacing cold air which is pushed further south.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jill Robbins adapted this story from Associated Press reports for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>perspective</strong> –<em> n</em>. a way of thinking about and understanding something (such as a particular issue or life in general)</p>
<p><strong>minus</strong> – <em>adj. </em>having a value that is below zero, negative</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Astronauts Stay Busy on International Space Station Awaiting Flight Home  (2025/1/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/astronauts-stay-busy-on-international-space-station-awaiting-flight-home.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Two American astronauts awaiting their return flight from the International Space Station (ISS) have stayed busy carrying out a series of scientific experiments.</p>
<p>The U.S. space agency NASA has said the pair – Butch Wilmore and Suni Williams – will remain at the ISS until late March or early April. When they arrived at the orbiting laboratory in June 2024, the astronauts expected to stay in space for just one week.</p>
<p>Their trip was a test flight of Boeing's Starliner spacecraft. While Starliner safely transported the two to the ISS, the spacecraft had several problems that persuaded NASA to send it back to Earth for further testing without the astronauts onboard.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="In this photo provided by NASA, Boeing Crew Flight Test astronauts Butch Wilmore, left, and Suni Williams pose inside the International Space Station's Harmony module and Boeing's Starliner spacecraft on June 13, 2024. (NASA via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/01000000-0aff-0242-6a80-08dc96f4ac8c_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">In this photo provided by NASA, Boeing Crew Flight Test astronauts Butch Wilmore, left, and Suni Williams pose inside the International Space Station's Harmony module and Boeing's Starliner spacecraft on June 13, 2024. (NASA via AP)</span></div>
<p>NASA's current plan calls for Wilmore and Williams to fly back on a SpaceX spacecraft in late March at the earliest. NASA has been using SpaceX's Crew Dragon to regularly carry astronauts and supplies to the ISS since 2020.</p>
<p>The astronauts have been using their extended mission to carry out experiments. In addition, Williams stepped out of <a class="wsw__a" href="https://blogs.nasa.gov/spacestation/">the space station</a> earlier this month to complete a spacewalk.</p>
<p>Another NASA astronaut, Nick Hague, joined Williams on the spacewalk on January 16, the agency <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/image-article/suni-williams-conducts-spacewalk/#:~:text=NASA%20astronaut%20Suni%20Williams%20is,and%20the%20eighth%20for%20Williams.">said</a> in a statement.</p>
<p>The two repaired a piece of equipment that helps guide the movements of the ISS. The spacewalk also included work on an X-ray telescope, as well as maintenance activities for other ISS systems. NASA noted it was the fourth spacewalk for Hague and the eighth for Williams.</p>
<p>The space agency <a class="wsw__a" href="https://blogs.nasa.gov/spacestation/">said</a> Williams was preparing for another spacewalk planned for January 30. Wilmore is expected to join Williams on that spacewalk, which NASA estimates will last about six-and-a-half hours. The two will be aiming to remove <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_FkQDXp0z">a radio</a> <strong>antenna </strong>structure. They will also be “searching for microbes” around the ISS for use in experiments.</p>
<p>Here is a look at other experiments Wilmore and Williams have completed during their stay:</p>
<p><strong>New methods to grow food</strong></p>
<p>NASA said Wilmore and Williams have tested different methods for growing crops in space. Such methods could support humans who have longer stays in space in the future.</p>
<p>One experiment is called the Plant Water Management investigation. NASA said this experiment “uses the physical properties of fluids...to overcome the lack of gravity and provide <strong>hydration</strong> to plants.” The experiment aims to help NASA develop <strong>hydroponic</strong> systems to support future space missions.</p>
<p>Another experiment examines a new way to grow vegetables, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_4036MWWQ">plants</a> and flowers inside the ISS to provide nutrition and beauty. As part of this experiment, Wilmore <strong>installed</strong> a new light <strong>meter</strong> inside the ISS. The device is designed to measure available light and to help crew members improve growing operations.</p>
<p><strong>Robot assistants</strong></p>
<p>NASA also said that throughout the current mission, Williams had deployed and observed three free-flying robots called Astrobee. This robotic experiment seeks to examine how such robots could assist astronauts with daily duties and <strong>maintenance</strong> work.</p>
<p>The agency <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/mission/station/research-explorer/facility/?#id=1891">said</a> the square-shaped robots are designed to help scientists and engineers develop and test new robotic technologies for use in microgravity environments. The assistants are also designed to help astronauts with daily tasks “and give ground controllers additional eyes and ears on the space station.”</p>
<p>Williams tested the robots' ability to map the inside of the space station and Astrobee's flight abilities.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p><strong>Image captures from space</strong></p>
<p>NASA astronauts visiting the ISS have a long history of capturing images of Earth from space. And this is another activity Wilmore and Williams have carried out. The ISS gives astronauts a “window to the world” as they orbit 400 kilometers above their home planet.</p>
<p>During their mission, NASA said the two astronauts had “captured hundreds of photographs of Earth, ranging from <strong>auroras</strong>, land, sea, orbital sunrises and sunsets, and more.”</p>
<p><strong>Radio connections with Earth </strong></p>
<p>Another space station tradition is for U.S. astronauts to connect with students and other interested individuals during their stay in space. They have <strong>virtual</strong> visits with people back on Earth who can ask the astronauts how it feels to live in space and can learn about NASA's experiments aboard the ISS.</p>
<p>In early August, Williams used <strong>ham radio</strong> technology to connect with students from Banda Aceh, Indonesia. NASA explained that students get the chance to communicate with the astronauts when the ISS passes overhead. The students can ask about research on the ISS as well as the radio wave technology that makes <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_vqekhKzO">the communication</a> possible.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from NASA and The Associated Press. </em></p>
<p><strong>___________________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>antenna </strong><em>– n. </em>a device used to send or receive communications signals</p>
<p><strong>hydration </strong><em>– n. </em>the process of making the body take in water or other liquid</p>
<p><strong>hydroponic </strong><em>– adj. </em>relating to or grown using a method of growing plants in water, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_s8ok1cjU">sand</a> or gravel</p>
<p><strong>install </strong><em>–v.</em> to put a piece of equipment in place so that it can do what it is designed to do</p>
<p><strong>meter </strong><em>–n.</em> any device either analog or digital that measures a value in the physical world</p>
<p><strong>maintenance</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n. </em>the work needed to keep something operating in good condition</p>
<p><strong>aurora </strong><em>– n. </em>a natural appearance of colored lights in the sky</p>
<p><strong>virtual </strong><em>– adj. </em>happening using digital communications and not taking place physically</p>
<p><strong>ham radio</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n. </em>an activity that sends and receive radio messages as a hobby</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Birdwatchers Photograph Prized Waterbirds in Alabama  (2025/1/27)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/birdwatchers-photograph-prized-waterbirds-in-alabama.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">26 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>In flooded agricultural fields near the Tennessee River, tens of thousands of birds called sandhill cranes search for food such as berries, corn, seeds and insects.</p>
<p>The Cranes come to the Wheeler National Wildlife Refuge Center in northern Alabama during the winter. The yearly movement, or migration, of sandhill cranes brings many birdwatchers who want to see the tall birds up close.</p>
<p>The birdwatchers also come to see the rare and endangered whooping cranes that migrate in much smaller numbers to Wheeler. Many other birds can be seen, including geese, ducks, bald eagles, kestrels and hawks.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Rob Broeren takes pictures of sandhill cranes at the Wheeler National Wildlife Refuge, Monday, Jan. 13, 2025, in Decatur, Ala. (AP Photo/George Walker IV)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/c30c8162-eff9-46e9-80b1-895371d27902_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Rob Broeren takes pictures of sandhill cranes at the Wheeler National Wildlife Refuge, Monday, Jan. 13, 2025, in Decatur, Ala. (AP Photo/George Walker IV)</span></div>
<p>Park ranger David Young described the area as “a birder's paradise,” meaning it is a perfect place for birdwatchers.</p>
<p>The cranes fly from the Great Lakes, an area far to the north, to Alabama each year.</p>
<p>The sandhill cranes started migrating to Wheeler for the winter in the mid-1990s. Their numbers increased by a lot in the mid-2000s, Young said. Last year, the migratory sandhill population reached a new record of 30,000 cranes.</p>
<p>The refuge has become a popular place for birdwatchers who bring hand-held telescopes called binoculars. Birdwatchers can even get closer to the 1.2-meter-tall cranes as visitors stay hidden behind photography <strong>blinds</strong> and a two-level observation center. A yearly Festival of the Cranes in January brings more attention and visitors.</p>
<p>The cranes put on a fun show, dancing on their thin legs, moving their wings and putting their long beaks in the air to make different sounds.</p>
<p>Diana Maybury-Sharp regularly comes to Wheeler with friends to <strong>hike</strong> and look at birds.</p>
<p>“It's pretty<strong> extraordinary</strong>. I've seen them in other parts of the country where there were just a few,” Maybury-Sharp said. “They're not<strong> vocal</strong> like they are here. There's so many here that it's an unusual experience.”</p>
<p>The whooping cranes are part of the eastern migratory population that comes from the north-central state of Wisconsin. Young said they started coming to Alabama in 2004. Their population is between 12 and 20 each winter.</p>
<p>Whooping cranes nearly died out in the early 1900s because of hunting and farming. The International Crane Foundation says recovery and reintroduction efforts have slowly increased their wild and captive populations to more than 800.</p>
<p>The whooping cranes are sometimes hard to see among the sandhills, but their height and white feathers help them stand out. Young said the migration patterns of the cranes might change depending on the climate of both their <strong>nesting </strong>places to the north and their winter homes in the south.</p>
<p>Rob Broeren brought along his camera and a long telephoto lens and found a good place to work on his wildlife photography skills. He comes to the refuge about twice a month each year to photograph the birds and ducks.</p>
<p>“You just need to be patient and wait for them to do something interesting and make their calls,” Broeren said. “You get that cool shot and that's a good day.”</p>
<p>The sandhill cranes will start leaving the refuge in mid-February. Young said he notices a lot more activity when the birds are showing they are ready to travel back to their nesting grounds.</p>
<p>“It's usually on a day when we have some sort of a south wind," Young said. "They're smart and they will ride the wind back to their breeding grounds whenever it's most <strong>convenient</strong> for them.”</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Kristin M. Hall reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>blind </strong><em>–n. </em>something to block sight or keep out light</p>
<p><strong>hike </strong><em>–v. </em>to walk through nature on trails for a fair distance</p>
<p><strong>extraordinary</strong> <em>– adj.</em> going beyond what is normal or regular</p>
<p><strong>vocal </strong><em>– adj.</em> of or relating to the voice</p>
<p><strong>nest<em> </em></strong><em>– v.</em> to occupy or build a nest – a place where a bird lays its eggs</p>
<p><strong>convenient </strong><em>– adj. </em>suited to easy performance; suited to a situation</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Get Ready for Spring Planting in Winter  (2025/1/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/get-ready-for-spring-planting-in-winter.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the <em>Health &amp; Lifestyle</em> report.</p>
<p>In many parts of the world, winter brings cold temperatures and, in some places, snowfall. For people who like planting things, gardening may seem far away.</p>
<p>However, during winter weather, there are still things a gardener can do to prepare for the spring. Gardening expert Jessica Damiano recently wrote about such preparatory <strong>tasks</strong> for the Associated Press. We can also call these tasks "prep work."</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Snow covers the yard of a home in the Grant Park neighborhood of Portland, Oregon, Feburary 23, 2023. (AP Photo/Drew Callister)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/04537a8f-10d8-4bfb-94bf-d5193765e81b_cx0_cy12_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Snow covers the yard of a home in the Grant Park neighborhood of Portland, Oregon, Feburary 23, 2023. (AP Photo/Drew Callister)</span></div>
<p><strong>Testing seeds</strong></p>
<p>First let's talk about seeds.</p>
<p>If you have seed <strong>packets</strong>, she suggests checking their <strong>expiration</strong> date. That is the date by which they go “bad” or will not grow. Damiano says the seeds are usually considered “fresh” within a year of being <strong>packaged</strong>. But they can be used for longer than that.</p>
<p>However, you cannot be sure if the seeds are still good just by looking at a date. She suggests testing them.</p>
<p>To do this, she places several seeds on a wet paper towel and then puts that into a plastic container. In about 10 days, she will look to see how many seeds have <strong>sprouted. </strong></p>
<p>This gives her an idea of how many seeds to use to get the desired number of plants. However, if less than 50 percent of the seeds sprout, she throws them away.</p>
<p>Damiano tests her old seeds in the winter before the busy spring gardening season. That is when seed and plant stores, or nurseries, can run out of seeds.</p>
<p><strong>Inspect and care for equipment</strong></p>
<p>She also inspects her gardening equipment.</p>
<p>For example, if you use grow lights — lights especially made for plants — make sure they still work. You might have to buy new <strong>bulbs</strong>.</p>
<p>Damiano brings out her grow lights and inspects each bulb. If necessary, she will order replacement bulbs. That way she is prepared to plant at any time, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_xunw7UCS">even</a> six to eight weeks in the future.</p>
<p>She also makes sure she has <strong>sterile</strong> seed-starting potting mix. This is special soil for planting in containers.</p>
<p>Damiano sharpens her cutting tools, such as pruning shears. Larger tools like lawnmowers should be inspected every year. Like nurseries, places that service lawn equipment might be busier in the spring. You can get ahead of the crowd by getting your tools fixed early.</p>
<p>Clean your gardening hand tools, like trowels and spades. Cover them lightly with oil. This will help keep them in good working order.</p>
<p>Inspect things like hoses, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_cHp8ajPN">sprinklers</a> and other water systems for damage. Make a list of anything you may need to replace or repair.</p>
<p>Damiano says that you could wait until spring to take care of all these things—but why? Once spring arrives, you will have these tasks done.</p>
<p>And that's the Health &amp; Lifestyle report. I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Jessica Damiano reported this story for The Associated Press from New York. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>__________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>task </strong><em>–n.</em> a job or work that needs to be done</p>
<p><strong>packet </strong><em>–n.</em> a paper envelope that contains small things like seeds</p>
<p><strong>expiration </strong><em>–n. </em>the point at which something is no longer usable</p>
<p><strong>package </strong><em>–v.</em> to put a product in any one of many kinds of containers for sale to the public</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_kiLqyYlu"><strong>sprouted </strong></a><em>–adj.</em> a seed that has begun to send out early leaves</p>
<p><strong>bulb </strong><em>–n.</em> a round lighting device</p>
<p><strong>sterile </strong><em>–adj. </em>something that does not have any microorganisms in it</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Sometimes We 'Spread Ourself Too Thin'  (2025/1/26)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/sometimes-we-spread-ourself-too-thin.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">25 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>Today we talk about our busy lives. Many people have family and work responsibilities. We might have religious or community activities. Taking care of our health is also important. And let's not forget about our personal projects, our interests, and our friendships.</p>
<p>With everything <u>on our plate</u>, it is easy to feel <strong>overwhelmed</strong>, overextended, and <strong>overcommitted</strong>.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="During the coronavirus pandemic, many resources were spread very thin. Pictured here, medical workers screen people arriving at a special COVID-19 testing site in Boston, Saturday, March 28, 2020. (AP Photo/Michael Dwyer)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/8468D3AA-5CD8-4282-B4E5-88E51CB1404D_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">During the coronavirus pandemic, many resources were spread very thin. Pictured here, medical workers screen people arriving at a special COVID-19 testing site in Boston, Saturday, March 28, 2020. (AP Photo/Michael Dwyer)</span></div>
<p>However, if we try to do too much, we may <u>spread ourselves too thin</u>. This expression means we have taken on too much. We are <u>pushed to the limit</u>.</p>
<p>People who are<u> spread too thin</u>, take on too many jobs, projects, or goals. The heavy load requires more energy or attention than they possess.</p>
<p>If we work on many projects simultaneously, or at the same time, it is possible that none will get done well, if they get done at all. And it is possible such <strong>multitasking</strong> could <strong>stress </strong>us out.</p>
<p>Being spread too thin can also be described as <u>biting off more than we can chew</u>. When we bite off more than we can chew, we attempt to do more than is possible.</p>
<span class="c-sticky-element__close-el c-sticky-element__swipe-el ta-c" title="close">
<span class="ico ico-close m-0"></span>
</span>
<p><small>Here is a VOA Learning English <em>English in a Minute</em> video explaining the idiom "to bite off more than you can chew."</small></p>
<p>Now, let's hear these some of these terms and expressions used in a <strong>conversation</strong>.</p>
<p><em>A: So, how are your classes going?</em></p>
<p><em>B: Not great. Many of my best students are failing my course. They all missed an important deadline for a project. </em></p>
<p><em>A: That's strange. What else do they have going on?</em></p>
<p><em>B: A lot! They are all performing in the same play. So, they have had <strong>rehearsals</strong> every night for the past month. And many have part-time jobs as well. </em></p>
<p><em>A: Sounds like they've spread themselves too thin. They've got too much going on. </em></p>
<p><em>B: I think you're right. </em></p>
<p><em>A: So, what are you going to do?</em></p>
<p><em>B: Well, first I'll extend the deadline. And then I'm going to warn them about biting off more than they can chew. </em></p>
<p>And that's all the time we have for this <em>Words and Their Stories</em>.</p>
<p>Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>overwhelmed</strong> – <em>adj.</em> overcome or overpowered by force, number, thought or feeling</p>
<p><strong>overcommitted </strong>– <em>adj. </em>to be obligated to something beyond the ability for fulfillment</p>
<p><strong>multitasking </strong>– <em>n.</em><strong> </strong>the performance of several tasks at one time</p>
<p><strong>stress </strong>– <em>v. </em>to subject to physical or psychological pressure</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" name="_Hlk187918566"><strong>conversation </strong></a>– <em>n.</em><strong> </strong>talking or a talk between two or more people</p>
<p><strong>rehearsal </strong>– <em>n.</em> a private performance or practice session in preparation for a public appearance</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers Uncover a Bathhouse Complex in Ancient Pompeii  (2025/1/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/researchers-uncover-a-bathhouse-complex-in-ancient-pompeii.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Caty Weaver</span><br/><span class="datetime">24 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p class="MsoBodyText">Archeological research has uncovered another treasure of the ancient Roman city of Pompeii: a large private <strong>bathhouse</strong>.</p>
<p>The explosion of Mount Vesuvius in 70 AD buried Pompeii in thick ash, wreckage, and lava, or hot liquid rock. Archeologists are continuing to find remains of the city under the ground.</p>
<p>The bathhouse was part of a large private house, the scientists said. The bathhouse holds a series of rooms that would have provided hot, warm, or cold conditions. The art and design of the complex, including <strong>mosaic</strong> works, also suggest the owner was wealthy.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A picture released by the Pompeii Archeological Park Press Office, Friday, January 17, 2025, showing a private bathhouse recently discovered in the Pompeii archeological site. (Archeological Park of Pompeii Press Office Via AP, HO)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/96299b57-85eb-4fda-8898-d763bc865f64_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A picture released by the Pompeii Archeological Park Press Office, Friday, January 17, 2025, showing a private bathhouse recently discovered in the Pompeii archeological site. (Archeological Park of Pompeii Press Office Via AP, HO)</span></div>
<p>“We have here perhaps the largest<strong> thermal</strong> complex in a private house in Pompeii,” said Gabriel Zuchtriegel, director of the Pompeii Archaeological Park.</p>
<p>He explained that Pompeii's powerful and wealthy set up large spaces at their homes to hold major gatherings for ceremonies and other purposes.</p>
<p>“It was an <strong>opportunity</strong> to show the wealth in which they lived and also to have a nice thermal treatment," he said.</p>
<p>The baths were unearthed in the so-called Regio IX, a large central area of Pompeii Park that is still unexplored.</p>
<p>Recently, archeologists working in the same area found a <strong>bakery</strong>, a <strong>laundry</strong> and two homes. They also found the bones of three people who died in the volcanic burst.</p>
<p>Pompeii was not the only city destroyed in the explosion. It also buried the city of Herculaneum.</p>
<p>Zuchtriegel said wealthy citizens of Pompeii often would first take a bath and then attend a banquet, or a big meal. The private thermal complex permitted them to do so together at the home where the banquet was held.</p>
<p>“There is room for about 30 people who could do the whole <strong>routine</strong>, and that could also be done in public baths. So there is the caldarium, a very warm environment, and also a large <strong>tub</strong> with cold water,” he said.</p>
<p>I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Caty Weaver adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p><strong>______________________________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2">Words in This Story</h2>
<p><strong>bathhouse </strong><em>– n. </em>a building equipped for bathing</p>
<p><strong>mosaic </strong><em>–n.</em> the covering of a wall that is made of main small pieces and which shows a picture or design</p>
<p><strong>thermal </strong><em>– adj.</em> of, relating to, or caused by heat</p>
<p><strong>opportunity </strong><em>– n.</em><strong> </strong>a favorable combination of circumstances, time, and place</p>
<p><strong>bakery </strong><em>– n.</em><strong> </strong>a place for baking or selling baked goods</p>
<p><strong>laundry </strong><em>– n. </em>a business where clothes or linens are washed</p>
<p><strong>routine</strong> <em>– n. </em>a standard or regular way of doing something</p>
<p><strong>tub </strong><em>–n.</em> a large, round container big enough to clean clothes or to take a bath in</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Minimal Pairs for Pronunciation  (2025/1/25)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/minimal-pairs-for-pronunciation.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">24 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em> we answer a question from Doraemon in Japan. Here is Doraemon's question:</p>
<p><em>Hi VOA,</em></p>
<p><em>For me, as an English learner, words like clash, crash, and crush sound like the same word.<br/>
Can you help me to tell one word from others?<br/>
Thank you.</em><em> </em></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Ask a Teacher: Minimal Pairs for Pronunciation" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/c708a5b5-901a-473a-884f-4201ea6b2eeb_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Ask a Teacher: Minimal Pairs for Pronunciation</span></div>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Doraemon.</p>
<p>When a foreign language contains sounds that do not exist in a person's native language, it can be difficult for learners to hear those sounds.</p>
<p>The reason you have difficulty hearing the difference between “crash” and “clash” is because the Japanese language does not have the consonant sounds “r” or “l.” And when English speakers are talking quickly, the difference between the sounds of “r” and “l” becomes very small. As a result, those two consonants can sound the same to a native Japanese speaker.</p>
<p>Some vowel sounds can also be difficult to hear or pronounce depending on the vowels a person's native language has. For example, consider the difference between the following two words:</p>
<p><em>hit heat</em></p>
<p>The Spanish language has the vowel sound in the word “heat,” but it does not have the vowel sound in the word “hit.”</p>
<p>As a result, Spanish speakers will sometimes pronounce words like “hit,” “bit,” and “little” with an “ee” sound. For example, the two words “hit” and “heat” will both sound like “heat” when spoken with a Spanish <strong>accent</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Train your ears using minimal pairs</strong></p>
<p>You can learn to hear the difference between sounds in a foreign language by careful <strong>practice</strong> using minimal pairs. Minimal pairs are two words that differ from each other by only one sound.</p>
<p>For example, the two words “hit” and “heat” differ from each other by only one sound.</p>
<p>Here are some tips for using minimal pairs:</p>
<p>Find lists and recordings of minimal pairs through a Google search or on YouTube. For Japanese speakers, find minimal pairs that differ between the sounds of “r” and “l.” Be sure to include minimal pairs that place the two sounds at the beginning, middle, and end of words. Here are examples:</p>
<p><em>rake lake</em></p>
<p><em>correct collect</em></p>
<p><em>hair hail</em></p>
<p>Carefully listen to the pronunciation of the minimal pairs. At first, it might be difficult for you to hear the difference between them. But over time you will start hearing the difference.</p>
<p>Also practice pronouncing these sounds. Learning to pronounce them can help you hear them. To pronounce them, you need to practice putting your tongue in the correct position.</p>
<p>The tongue is a muscle. Just as we can train our muscles to play a sport, we can train our tongue to move to the correct positions for pronouncing a foreign language. This <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=94MMQ1av_-s">How to Pronounce video</a> from VOA Learning English shows the tongue positions you need to pronounce the letters “r” and “l” correctly.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? We want to hear from you! Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please let us know where you are from, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>accent</strong> – <em>n. </em>a way of speaking typical of a particular group of people and especially of the natives or residents of a region</p>
<p><strong>practice</strong> – <em>v. </em>to perform or work at repeatedly so as to become proficient</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>US Solar Farms Put Hungry Sheep to Work  (2025/1/24)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/us-solar-farms-put-hungry-sheep-to-work.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">23 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>A group of sheep on farmland in the American state of Texas work together to complete a job: eating the grass growing beneath hundreds of<strong> solar panels.</strong></p>
<p>Sheep have become a<strong> symbol </strong>of a growing solar industry as large-scale solar farms appear across the United States.</p>
<p><strong>Solar grazing </strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Sheep walk near solar panels on a solar farm owned by SB Energy on Tuesday, Dec. 17, 2024, in Buckholts, Texas. (AP Photo/Ashley Landis)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/a524fb24-ab1f-4d74-b382-0600d7b1c1c9_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Sheep walk near solar panels on a solar farm owned by SB Energy on Tuesday, Dec. 17, 2024, in Buckholts, Texas. (AP Photo/Ashley Landis)</span></div>
<p>In Milam County, Texas, SB Energy operates the fifth-largest solar project in the country. It can produce 900 megawatts of power across 1,618 hectares.</p>
<p>So, how does the company deal with all the grass that grows on such a large piece of land? It deploys about 3,000 sheep that keep the grass cover low. Sheep, unlike devices such as lawnmowers, can fit between small spaces and work in all kinds of weather conditions.</p>
<p>The work of the sheep, and sometimes other animals, is called solar grazing. It is considered part of the larger idea of agrivoltaics --- the use of land for both solar energy production and agriculture.</p>
<p>The <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.climatehubs.usda.gov/hubs/northeast/topic/agrivoltaics-coming-soon-farm-near-you#:~:text=Agrivoltaics%20is%20the%20use%20of,workers%20on%20hot%20summer%20days." target="_blank">U.S. Department of Agriculture</a> suggests that solar grazing may help the environment in several ways. These include making grassy areas safer for wild animals, like nesting ground birds, and by reducing fuel use and air pollution.</p>
<p>Agrivoltaics is on the rise with more than 60 solar grazing projects in the U.S., the National Renewable Energy Laboratory says. The American Solar Grazing Association says 27 states take part in solar grazing.</p>
<p><strong>A sunny opportunity </strong></p>
<p>Putting the animals to work on solar fields also provides some help to the sheep and <strong>wool</strong> market, which has struggled in recent years. The number of sheep and lambs in Texas fell to 655,000 in January 2024, a 4 percent drop from the year before. That information comes from the most recent data from the U.S. Department of Agriculture.</p>
<p>Because solar fields use sunny, flat land that is often good for animals to eat grass on, the power plants have been used in cooperation with farmers rather than against them.</p>
<p>Sheep farmer JR Howard accidentally found himself in the middle of Texas' move to clean energy. In 2021, he and his family began working with solar farms. Howard's sheep ate the grass on these large areas of land.</p>
<p>What was once a small business has turned into a larger operation with more than 8,000 sheep and 26 employees.</p>
<p>“Just the growth has been kind of crazy for us,” said Howard, who named his company Texas Solar Sheep. “It's been great for me and my family.”</p>
<p><strong>Following the herd </strong></p>
<p>Some agriculture experts say Howard's success shows how solar farms have become a big help for some <strong>ranchers</strong>.</p>
<p>Reid Redden is a sheep farmer and solar <strong>vegetation</strong> manager in San Angelo, Texas. Redden said a successful sheep business requires agricultural land that has become increasingly hard to find.</p>
<p>“Solar grazing is probably the biggest <strong>opportunity</strong> that the sheep industry had in the United States in several generations,” Redden said.</p>
<p>Redden suggested that people in the rural communities near where he raises sheep have been very positive about solar grazing.</p>
<p>Agrivoltaics itself is not new. Solar farms use a lot of land and require a lot of space that could be used for food production.</p>
<p>Agrivoltaics helps with the problem by permitting the two industries to coexist, whether growing food or caring for livestock.</p>
<p>There is a lot still unknown about the full effects of solar grazing, said Nuria Gomez-Casanovas of Texas A&amp;M University.</p>
<p>Not enough studies have been done to know the long-term environmental effects, such as how good the soil will be for future agriculture. However, Gomez-Casanovas suspects solar grazing may improve sheep productivity.</p>
<p>“We really have more questions than answers,” Gomez-Casanovas said.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Nadia Lathan reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>solar panel </strong><em>– n. </em>a battery of solar cells</p>
<p><strong>symbol</strong> <em>– n.</em> something that stands for or suggests something else by reason of relationship, association, convention, or accidental resemblance</p>
<p><strong>wool </strong><em>– n.</em> the soft and usually thick undercoat of hairy mammals (especially sheep)</p>
<p><strong>rancher</strong> <em>– n. </em>one who owns or works on a large farm that raises sheep, cows, horses, etc.</p>
<p><strong>vegetation </strong><em>– n.</em> plant cover or plant life</p>
<p><strong>opportunity </strong><em>– n.</em> a good chance for advancement or progress</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers: Female Family Ties Important to Social Networks  (2025/1/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/researchers-female-family-ties-important-to-social-networks.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>A recent study suggests that female family ties were central to social networks in ancient Celtic society before the Roman invasion.</p>
<p>Genetic evidence from a late Iron Age cemetery in Britain shows that women were closely related. At the same time, unrelated men were more likely to come into the community from other places, likely after marriage.</p>
<p>For the study, researchers examined ancient DNA from 57 burial places in Dorset in southwestern England. People used the cemetery from around 2100 years ago to around 1800 years ago.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This photo provided by Bournemouth University in January 2025 shows burials being investigated at an Iron Age Celtic cemetery as part of the Durotriges tribe project dig in Dorset, southwest England. (Bournemouth University via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/06785e4f-fca7-41a3-9537-b62600ac24ec_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This photo provided by Bournemouth University in January 2025 shows burials being investigated at an Iron Age Celtic cemetery as part of the Durotriges tribe project dig in Dorset, southwest England. (Bournemouth University via AP)</span></div>
<p>The results showed that two-thirds of the individuals descended from a single maternal lineage.</p>
<p>Lara Cassidy of Trinity College Dublin was one of the study's co-writers. Cassidy suggested to the Associated Press (AP) that the results were surprising, or in her words, “jaw-dropping.”</p>
<p>She said that such a finding had “never been observed before in European prehistory.”</p>
<p>The study appeared recently in the scientific publication <em>Nature.</em></p>
<p>The research suggests that women stayed in the same circles throughout life. They kept social networks and likely inherited or managed land and property.</p>
<p>Cassidy told the AP that the findings suggest, “it's your husband who is coming in as a relative stranger, dependent on a wife's family for land and livelihood.”</p>
<p>Such a way of living is called matrilocality. The researchers said it is historically rare.</p>
<p>Guido Gnecchi-Ruscone is with the Max Planck Institute in Germany. Gnecchi-Ruscone was not part of the study.</p>
<p>He said researchers studying burial places in Britain and Europe have only discovered the opposite behavior. He said in those communities, women left their homes and families to join their husband's family group.</p>
<p>He said such a way of living, known as patrilocality, has been observed in other ancient time periods. These include the Neolithic period which started more than 10,000 years ago to the early Medieval period more than 1000 years in the past.</p>
<p>Cassidy said in studies of pre-industrial societies from around 220 years ago to the present, researchers found that men join their wives' extended family households only eight percent of the time.</p>
<p>But researchers already knew there was something special about the role of women in Iron Age Britain. A group of tribes with closely related languages and art that is often described as Celtic lived in England before the Roman invasion about 2000 years ago.</p>
<p>Valuable objects have been found buried with Celtic women. Roman writers, including Julius Caesar, wrote with disrespect about their relative independence and fighting abilities.</p>
<p>The network of strong female family connections that the researchers found does not necessarily mean that women also held official positions of political power.</p>
<p>Study co-writer Miles Russell of Bournemouth University in England researches ancient societies. He said the findings do suggest that women had some control of land and property and strong social support. Such a situation made Britain's Celtic society more “egalitarian” than the Roman world, Russell said.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Christina Larson reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>____________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>cemetery </strong><em>– n.</em> a burial ground</p>
<p><strong>descended from </strong><em>–v. (phrasal)</em> to be related by birth to an ancestor</p>
<p><strong>maternal </strong><em>– adj. </em>of or related to the mother</p>
<p><strong>lineage</strong> <em>– n. </em>a group of individuals descending from a common ancestor</p>
<p><strong>inherit</strong> <em>–v.</em> to receive property or something of value because of a family relationship</p>
<p><strong>manage </strong><em>–v</em>. to oversee or look over</p>
<p><strong>extended family</strong> <em>– n.</em> a large group of people who are related by blood or marriage who consider themselves as a large family</p>
<p><strong>egalitarian </strong><em>–adj.</em> aiming to make people in a society more equal than they are</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Meta Ends Third-party Fact-Checking, Adds ‘Community Notes’ System  (2025/1/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/meta-ends-third-party-fact-checking-adds-community-notes-system.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Facebook parent company Meta recently announced changes to the way it tries to identify misinformation and harmful material published on its social media services.</p>
<p>Meta chief Mark Zuckerberg <a class="wsw__a" href="https://about.fb.com/news/2025/01/meta-more-speech-fewer-mistakes/">explained</a> in a video that the company had decided to make the changes because the old system had produced “too many mistakes and too much <strong>censorship</strong>.”</p>
<p><strong>Issues with Meta moderation</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - The Facebook logo is seen on a cell phone in Boston, USA, Friday, Oct. 14, 2022. (AP Photo/Michael Dwyer, File)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/2ac5b816-9f18-48ba-9521-fb24fec5d49b_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - The Facebook logo is seen on a cell phone in Boston, USA, Friday, Oct. 14, 2022. (AP Photo/Michael Dwyer, File)</span></div>
<p>Zuckerberg said the <strong>moderation</strong> system Meta had built needed to be “complex” to examine huge amounts of <strong>content</strong> in search of material that violated company policies.</p>
<p>However, he noted the problem with such systems is they can make a lot of errors. The Meta chief added about such systems, “Even if they accidentally censor just one percent of posts, that's millions of people.”</p>
<p>So, he said the company had decided to move to a new system centered on “reducing mistakes, simplifying our policies, and restoring free expression.”</p>
<p><strong>“Community Notes” system</strong></p>
<p>The new method turns over content moderation duties to a “Community Notes” system. The company said this system aims to “empower the community” to decide whether content is acceptable or needs further examination.</p>
<p>The changes will be effective for Meta's Facebook, Instagram and Threads services. Meta said the new system would become available first to U.S. users in the coming months.</p>
<p>Meta's former moderation system involved the use of independent, third-party fact-checking organizations. Many of these were large media companies or news agencies. The efforts included digital tools as well as human workers to fact-check content and identify false, <strong>inappropriate</strong> or harmful material.</p>
<p>Meta said the third-party moderation method ended up identifying too much information for fact-checking. After closer examination, a lot of content should have been considered “<strong>legitimate</strong> political speech and debate.”</p>
<p>Another problem, the company said, was that the decisions made by content moderators could be affected by their personal beliefs, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_6ywWHIXG">opinions</a> and <strong>biases</strong>. One result was that “a program intended to inform too often became a tool to censor.”</p>
<p>Meta's new Community Notes system is similar to the method used by the social media service X. A statement by Meta <a class="wsw__a" href="https://about.fb.com/news/2025/01/meta-more-speech-fewer-mistakes/">said</a> changes to this system will have to be made by users, not anyone from the company.</p>
<p>Meta said, “Just like they do on X, Community Notes will require agreement between people with a <strong>range</strong> of <strong>perspectives</strong> to help prevent biased ratings.” The company also invited any users to register to be among the first to try out the system.</p>
<p><strong>How did fact-checkers react to Meta's change?</strong></p>
<p>The International Fact-Checking Network (IFCN) criticized Meta's latest decision. It said the move threatened to "undo nearly a <strong>decade</strong> of progress."</p>
<p>The group rejected Zuckerberg's claim that the fact-checking program had become a "tool to censor" users. It noted, that "the freedom to say why something is not true is also free speech."</p>
<p>Milijana Roga<i></i>269; is executive editor of the Serbian fact-checking outlet Istinomer. She told Reuters news agency that she thinks Meta's decision would end up hurting the media industry. Roga<i></i>269; noted that research suggests that many citizens use Meta services as their main source for information. Removing independent fact-checkers “further <strong>hinders</strong> access to <strong>accurate</strong> information and news," Roga<i></i>269; said.</p>
<p><strong>How effective are Community Notes?</strong></p>
<p>Not a lot of research has been done on how effective Community Notes systems are. But one effort carried out by the University of California and Johns Hopkins University found in 2024 that community notes entered on X for COVID-19 misinformation were accurate. The research showed the notes used<strong> </strong>both moderate and high-quality sources and were attached to widely read posts.</p>
<p>However, the number of people taking part in that study was small. Also, the effects the system had on users' opinions and behavior is unknown.</p>
<p>A 2023 study, from the <em>Journal of Online Trust and Safety,</em> said it was harder for users to agree when they examined content related to political issues.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story, based on reports from Meta, The Associated Press and Reuters.</em></p>
<p><strong>____________________________________</strong>_________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>censorship </strong><em>– n. </em>the system or practice of censoring information contained in books, movies, the internet, etc.</p>
<p><strong>moderate</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v.</em> to make sure the rules of an internet discussion are not broken</p>
<p><strong>content </strong><em>–n.</em> writing, audio and visual material found online</p>
<p><strong>inappropriate </strong><em>–adj</em>. something that is not right in a particular situation and which depends on people's opinions</p>
<p><strong>legitimate </strong><em>– adj. </em>something real</p>
<p><strong>bias </strong><em>– adj. </em>a situation in which you support or oppose something in an unfair way because you are influenced by personal opinions</p>
<p><strong>range </strong><em>–n.</em> all elements of a series of objects or numbers</p>
<p><strong>perspective</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n. </em>the way person thins about something</p>
<p><strong>decade </strong><em>– n. </em>a period of 10 years<em> </em></p>
<p><strong>hinder </strong><em>– v. </em>to make it difficult to do something</p>
<p><strong>accurate </strong><em>– n. </em>true or correct<em> </em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Red Coloring Linked to Cancer Risk Banned in US Foods  (2025/1/23)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/red-coloring-linked-to-cancer-risk-banned-in-us-foods.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">22 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has banned a chemical widely used to color some food products red. The ban of the coloring chemical, called dye, came nearly 35 years after it was removed from skin products because of a possible cancer risk.</p>
<p>A group of food safety and health supporters issued a <strong>petition</strong> in 2022 seeking to have the FDA ban Red No. 3 in food.</p>
<p>The earlier ban was ordered in 1990, after two studies showed Red No. 3 caused cancer in male rats eating high levels of the chemical. At the time, however, the FDA only acted to ban the coloring mixture in products put on the skin or in drugs taken by mouth.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - This image shows a pile of candy corn in Westchester County, N.Y., Oct. 23, 2023. " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/180ce991-0d5d-4e08-bc3a-8f328f0a5d77_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - This image shows a pile of candy corn in Westchester County, N.Y., Oct. 23, 2023. </span></div>
<p>Health activists had long sought FDA approval to expand the ban to food products. In November, nearly two dozen members of Congress sent a letter demanding that FDA officials ban Red No. 3.</p>
<p>Some of the most common products containing Red No. 3 include sweets, icing, strawberry milk, maraschino cherries, strawberry protein drinks, as well as some gummy vitamins and medications.</p>
<p>The FDA said food manufacturers will have until January 2027 to remove the dye from their products.</p>
<p>Other countries still permit certain uses of the dye. But any imported products will still have to meet the new U.S. requirement. Red No. 3 is already banned for food use in Europe, Australia and New Zealand, except in certain kinds of cherries.</p>
<p>The dye will be banned in California starting in January 2027. And lawmakers in Tennessee, Arkansas and Indiana have also proposed limits on certain dyes, especially from foods offered in public schools.</p>
<p>Jim Jones is the FDA's deputy commissioner for human foods. He <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.fda.gov/food/hfp-constituent-updates/fda-revoke-authorization-use-red-no-3-food-and-ingested-drugs">noted</a> that even though the agency had established the new ban, “the way that FD&amp;C Red No. 3 causes cancer in male rats does not <strong>occur</strong> in humans." FDA officials said the ban was enacted because of a U.S. rule called the Delaney Clause. This legal policy requires the FDA to ban any additive found to cause cancer in people or animals.</p>
<p>Dr. Peter Lurie is director of the <strong>consumer</strong> activist group the Center for Science in the Public Interest. He helped lead the latest effort to remove Red No. 3 from food products. Lurie told The Associated Press, "This is a welcome, but long <strong>overdue</strong>, action from the FDA.”</p>
<p>The International Association of Color Manufacturers has repeatedly said Red No. 3 is safe in levels usually taken in by humans. The group pointed to research carried out by scientific experts from the United Nations and the World Health Organization. One study, released in 2018, confirmed the safety of Red 3 in food.</p>
<p>Some food manufacturers have already changed their products to remove Red No. 3. One example is Sensient Food Colors, a St. Louis-based supplier of food colors and flavorings. In its place, the company uses beet juice, a dye made from insects and other coloring mixtures.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Jonel Aleccia reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>petition </strong>–<em> n.</em> an official request for someone in authority to do something</p>
<p><strong>occur</strong> – <em>v. </em>to happen</p>
<p><strong>consumer</strong> –<em> n. </em>a person who buys goods or services</p>
<p><strong>overdue</strong> – <em>adj</em>. not appearing or presented by a stated, expected, or required time</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Make a Memory Palace to Improve Your English  (2025/1/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/improve-your-english-with-a-memory-palace.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Alice Bryant</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>
Sherlock Holmes is an imaginary private detective created by British writer Arthur Conan Doyle in the late 1880s. Doyle's stories about the detective have been turned into movies and television shows.</p>
<p>One of Sherlock Holmes' great skills is a powerful memory. In a recent BBC television series, the character uses a memory technique called a “mind <strong>palace</strong>” or “memory palace.”</p>
<p>On one show, for example, Holmes has been severely wounded in a shooting and retreats into his mind to search for ways to survive. He visits rooms in his mind palace, looking for helpful memories. In one room, he finds his childhood dog, and the memory helps calm the detective.</p><div class="contentImage"><img src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/142EFFF5-F4C5-4CAE-A8C1-C76F629E3DD6_w268_r1.png"/></div>
<p>The memory palace idea was not a BBC creation. The method for remembering has existed for thousands of years. Many language educators today teach their students how to use the method to improve their language skills.</p>
<p>But what exactly is a memory palace? It is a real structure, such as a home or building, that you can picture in your head. You then imagine placing things you want to remember inside the structure.</p>
<p>You can use a memory palace to remember words, <strong>phrases</strong>, facts, or even the order of events. If you can see the inside of a house or building in your mind, you can make your own memory palace. On today's Education Tips, we will show you how.</p>
<p><strong>Making your palace</strong></p>
<p>Start with a list of words or phrases that you want to remember. Then, close your eyes and choose a physical space that you know well, such as your home, a school you attended, or a current or former workplace. If your chosen space has only one or two rooms, do not worry. You can also use things like doors, passageways, steps or other permanent places along the physical path.</p>
<p>The next step is to imagine walking through the space using the path that you would normally take through it. As you walk through, put objects that you want to remember at specific places along the path. Leave the objects there to pick up later when you visit your memory palace.</p>
<p>Now, let's try this technique by using six <strong>ingredients</strong> for a pizza: flour, water, dry yeast, tomato sauce, cheese and basil.</p>
<p>Close your eyes and picture a home.</p>
<p>First, you open the front door and see a bag of flour on the floor. The bag is broken and some of the flour has spilled. You are worried that you might <strong>slip</strong>, so you carefully step over the area.</p>
<p>Second, you walk into your bedroom. On top of your bed sits a cup of water. The cup is shaped like an upside-down piece of pizza. You think about how funny that is and laugh about it.</p>
<p>Third, as you enter the living room, you see a very large <strong>spoon</strong> of dry yeast sitting on the <strong>sofa</strong>. The spoon is watching a cooking show on television.</p>
<p>Fourth, while standing in the living room, you notice the room has a strange smell to it. You look above the television and see a block of cheese hanging on the wall.</p>
<p>Fifth, you walk into the <strong>kitchen</strong> and see two tomatoes chasing each other around the room. Suddenly, they crash and explode, covering the floor in red.</p>
<p>And sixth, you open the back door and go outside. There, you see a group of very tall green basil plants. In a funny voice, the tallest plant says, “Choose me! Choose me!”</p>
<p>Did you notice anything strange about the palace? It was full of extraordinary and humorous imagery. We will say more about that in a few minutes.</p>
<p>But first, let's check how well our technique worked. See if you can answer these questions:</p>
<p>1-What was on the wall above the television?</p>
<p>2-Where were the tomatoes and what were they doing?</p>
<p>3-Which object was sitting on the bed?</p>
<p>4-Where was the yeast and what was it doing?</p>
<p>5-Which ingredient spoke and what did it say?</p>
<p>6-What did you see when you opened the front door?</p>
<p>My <strong>guess</strong> is that you remembered everything in our memory palace. That's good news.</p>
<p><strong>Make memory strong</strong></p>
<p>Experts offer some advice for making strong memory palaces.</p>
<p>For instance, if you want to remember a lot of words, memory trainer Anthony Metivier suggests first <strong>drawing</strong> a simple map of your memory palace. Then, number the places along your path where you will put the things that you want to remember. You can put more than one thing in each room or area. Later, you will add the mental imagery.</p>
<p>English teacher James, of the YouTube channel JamesESL English Lessons, has additional advice. In his video on memory palaces, he says that there are three <strong>keys</strong> to a strong memory palace. They are: emotion, movement, and connections between the object and something permanent.</p>
<p>Both he and Metivier say imagining things in a humorous or crazy way improves your ability to remember them. These experts also agree that connecting images to actions or movement will create lasting memories. For instance, the tomatoes were chasing each other and the basil spoke.</p>
<p>And finally, teacher James suggests placing the objects next to or on something permanent in your palace. Beds, sofas, floors, walls, doors – all of these are permanent. The block of cheese was on the wall, for example.</p>
<p>Now, it's your turn. Pick a list of English words or phrases that you have trouble remembering and try this method on your own.</p>
<p>Let us know how it goes.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell. And I'm Alice Bryant.</p>
<p><em>Alice Bryant wrote this story for Learning English. Caty Weaver was the editor. </em></p>
<p>_________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>palace</strong> – n. a very large and impressive house</p>
<p><strong>ingredient</strong> – n. one of the things that are used to make a food or product</p>
<p><strong>slip</strong> – v. to lose your balance, especially on a slippery surface</p>
<p><strong>phrase</strong> – n. a group of two or more words that express a single idea but do not usually form a complete sentence</p>
<p><strong>spoon</strong> – n. an eating or cooking tool that has a small shallow bowl attached to a handle</p>
<p><strong>sofa</strong> – n. a long and comfortable piece of furniture on which a person can sit or lie down</p>
<p><strong>kitchen</strong> – n. a room in which food is cooked</p>
<p><strong>guess</strong> – n. an attempt to give an answer about something when you do not know much about it or are not sure about it</p>
<p><strong>key</strong> – n. something that is necessary in order to do or achieve something</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Nepal Supreme Court Bans Large Business Development in Protected Areas  (2025/1/22)</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/nepal-supreme-court-bans-large-business-development-in-protected-areas.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">21 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Nepal's Supreme Court has struck down disputed laws that permit waterpower centers,<strong> </strong>visitor housing such as hotels, and other business development in protected natural areas. Environmental defenders say the January 15 ruling is a victory for efforts to protect the country's natural areas.</p>
<p>Nepal has recognized one fifth of its territory as protected natural areas. The country has 12 national parks and six conservation areas. They include lowland areas such as Chitwan National Park. The park is home to many wild animals such as tigers and rhinos. Other protected areas include Sagarmatha National Park, home to Mount Everest.</p>
<p>Waterpower, or hydropower, and <strong>tourism</strong> represent major economic sources for Nepal. Last year, its government passed laws to permit development of large projects in some parts of national parks, forests and other protected areas.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - Nepalese mahouts walk their elephants through the Rapti River from Chitwan National Park in Sauraha, Chitwan, 170 kilometers (106 miles) south from Katmandu, Nepal, Monday, Dec. 26, 2011. (AP Photo/Niranjan Shrestha)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/d2b7f940-ad4b-4cf5-9896-01131f6606fb_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - Nepalese mahouts walk their elephants through the Rapti River from Chitwan National Park in Sauraha, Chitwan, 170 kilometers (106 miles) south from Katmandu, Nepal, Monday, Dec. 26, 2011. (AP Photo/Niranjan Shrestha)</span></div>
<p>Padam Bahadur Shrestha is a Nepalese environmental activist who took legal action against the laws. He told Agence France Press that the laws' passage showed that the government lacked <strong>insight</strong> and was only seeking to please business investors.</p>
<p>Shrestha praised the Supreme Court's ruling, saying it "<strong>preserves </strong>ecology and <strong>biodiversity</strong>.”</p>
<p>Nepal is recognized worldwide for its actions to protect its wild animal and plant life.</p>
<p>Nepal's environmental protection laws have helped the local tiger population increase from 121 animals in 2010 to 355 in 2023. And while only about 100 one-horned rhinos were living in Nepal in the 1960s, their number increased to 752 in 2021.</p>
<p>Nepal also increased its tree cover by almost 100 percent between 1992 and 2016. Wood industry activities, or logging, had deforested many areas of the country for tens of years earlier.</p>
<p>Rampreet Yadav is a former <strong>conservation</strong> officer of Chitwan National Park, Nepal's largest protected area. He said the recent laws “should never have been passed."</p>
<p>"If development projects are <strong>allowed</strong> in protected areas, they will destroy our nature and animal habitats," he added.</p>
<p>The Nepalese government wants to develop its hydropower industry, especially along rivers in the Himalayan mountains. Last October, it signed agreements with India and Bangladesh to export thousands of <strong>megawatts</strong> of hydropower.</p>
<p>Nepal also earns much money from tourism. Last year, around one million foreign visitors came to Nepal, and the government has been spending money on the development of its airports.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.</p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith adapted this story based on reporting from Agence France Press. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>tourism </strong>– <em>n. </em>the practice of traveling for recreation</p>
<p><strong>insight </strong>– <em>n. </em>the power or act of seeing into or understanding a situation</p>
<p><strong>preserve </strong>– <em>v.</em> to keep safe from injury, harm, or destruction</p>
<p><strong>biodiversity </strong>– <em>n.</em> biological variety in an environment as indicated by numbers of different species of plants and animals <strong>conservation</strong> – <em>n.</em> planned management of a natural resource to prevent exploitation, destruction, or neglect</p>
<p><strong>allow </strong>– <em>v. </em>to permit; to let</p>
<p><strong>megawatt </strong>– <em>n.</em> one million watts</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>No Soil Needed to Grow Air Plants at Home  (2025/1/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/no-soil-needed-to-grow-air-plants-at-home.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">20 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>If you are looking for houseplants that do not take up a lot of space and are easy to grow, air plants might be the right choice.</p>
<p>There are more than 500 different <strong>species </strong>of air plants. Officially they are known as Tillandsia. These plants are native to places in<strong> </strong>North and South America that support year-round plant growth. Air plants belong to the same family as the pineapple.</p>
<p>Instead of soil, these plants attach themselves to things like trees, rocks and buildings. They do not cause problems for the objects they grow on. Air plants do not have roots. They depend on specialized cells – called trichomes – to permit their leaves to take in water and nutrients.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image provided by Drift in Air Plants shows a Tillandsia xerographica air plant in Bakersfield, California. (Jennifer Tuttle/Drift in Air Plants via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/38950b6c-8cd1-4636-8a34-17153f9148cb_cx0_cy9_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image provided by Drift in Air Plants shows a Tillandsia xerographica air plant in Bakersfield, California. (Jennifer Tuttle/Drift in Air Plants via AP)</span></div>
<p>Associated Press gardening writer Jessica Damiano has experimented with air plants and offers these guidelines for people wanting to grow them.</p>
<p><strong>Sunlight</strong></p>
<p>Air plants require bright, indirect light. So, they should be placed near an east- or west-facing window, but not directly in front of it. Direct sunlight can burn the plant's leaves.</p>
<p><strong>Watering</strong></p>
<p>In homes with average <strong>humidity</strong> levels, put air plants in a bowl of room-temperature water once a week for 30 to 60 minutes. In homes with drier air, this process can be repeated when needed.</p>
<p>Lightly shake the plants to remove extra water. Then, place them upside-down on a cloth to dry for several hours. This step is necessary to prevent water from collecting on the plant's leaves, which can cause damage.</p>
<p>If using chlorinated water, it is best to let the liquid sit for 12 to 24 hours to permit the chemical to <strong>dissipate</strong> before watering plants. Air plants are especially sensitive to chlorine.</p>
<p><strong>Feeding the plants</strong></p>
<p>Growers should feed their air plants with any all-purpose houseplant, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_eTz32nqz">bromeliad</a> or orchid fertilizer. The substance should be added to the soaking water monthly to provide added nutrients. Use about half the amount suggested by the fertilizer manufacturer.</p>
<p><strong>Life cycle</strong></p>
<p>Air plants <strong>bloom</strong> only once. The resulting pink, coral, purple or white flowers are a signal that the plants are nearing death. However, air plants produce offshoots, known as “pups.” These can be separated into new plants once they grow to about one-third the size of the parent.</p>
<p><strong>So many choices</strong></p>
<p>Notable air plants include Spanish moss which can be found hanging from large trees in tropical or subtropical areas. In the home, Spanish moss is grown in a humid environment, such as a bathroom.</p>
<p>Another kind is Tillandsia <em>ionantha</em>, which is also known as the sky plant. It is a <strong>shaggy</strong>-looking plant with green bracts. Bracts are leaf-like structures that grow from the area just beneath a flower. The tops of <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_lnnkCrAw">bracts</a> can turn pink or purple before flowering.</p>
<p>Tillandsia <em>caput-medusae</em> is named for its similarity to the snake-haired head of Medusa, from Greek mythology. The plant is popular because of its long, wavy leaves that grow upward from a fat, round base.</p>
<p>Perhaps the most unusual species of Tillandsia is the <a class="wsw__a" name="_Hlk187660007">Xerographic</a> air plant. This kind is known as the King of Air Plants. It can grow up to about one-half meter. The plant's long, thin silver leaves <strong>curl </strong>downward to produce a round shape that sets it apart from other air plants.</p>
<p><strong>How to show your Tillandsia</strong></p>
<p>You can place air plants in just about any spot that provides the required sunlight and good air flow.</p>
<p>Glass containers or <strong>terrariums</strong> are popular choices. But growers can also put air plants inside seashells or on rocks. One could even create a floating Tillandsia garden by hanging several plants from <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_dYc5qcDC">fishing</a> line.</p>
<p>The plants can also be attached to natural wood pieces with wire or glue. Some choose to grow them inside hanging <strong>frames</strong>. When choosing placement possibilities, the main thing to keep in mind is to make sure you are fully meeting all the plant's needs.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>The Associated Press reported this story. Bryan Lynn adapted the report for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p><strong>______________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>species </strong><em>– n. </em>a group of animals or plants that are similar and can produce young animals or plants</p>
<p><strong>humidity</strong><strong> </strong><em>– n.</em> a measurement of how much water is in the air</p>
<p><strong>dissipate </strong>–v. to dry up, disappear through evaporation or by becoming less and less dense</p>
<p><strong>bloom </strong><em>– v. </em>when a flower fully opens</p>
<p><strong>shaggy </strong><em>– adj. </em>having or covered with long, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_yT73SHaK">rough</a> and messy hair</p>
<p><strong>curl</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v. </em>when something moves in a circular direction</p>
<p><strong>terrarium </strong><em>– n. </em>a container, often made of glass, that is used to keep small plants in</p>
<p><strong>frame </strong><em>– n. </em>a border that surrounds and supports a picture, <a class="wsw__a" name="_Int_rJDKPMgA">door</a> or window</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Learn to Have Better Balance and Prevent Falls as You Age  (2025/1/21)</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/learn-to-have-better-balance-and-prevent-falls-as-you-age.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Jill Robbins</span><br/><span class="datetime">20 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>To age well, doctors say we should remember the importance of good balance. It matters when you wash yourself, put clothing on and, generally, move around in your home and elsewhere. As we age, good balance permits us to live more independently.</p>
<p>Difficulties with balance can be dangerous. The United States Centers for Disease Control reports that three million older people in America seek medical care for fall-related injuries each year. But we can prevent some falls, said Roopa Anmolsingh. She is a geriatrician, a doctor who specializes in treating old people. She is also the creator of the balance class program at Cleveland Clinic in Ohio. She said that "Some people have a <strong>misconception</strong> that part of getting old is, you're going to fall. That's not true. You can control how you fall, or if you fall."</p>
<p>To prevent falls, geriatricians say people should start asking themselves questions about their balance as early as 50 years old. Here are the questions:</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="FILE - A couple walk on a sidewalk in Santiago, Chile, Wednesday on May 3, 2017. " src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/e26a4513-386c-4b2e-b739-68d383c6ac29_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">FILE - A couple walk on a sidewalk in Santiago, Chile, Wednesday on May 3, 2017. </span></div>
<p><strong>Do I ever feel unsteady?</strong></p>
<p>If you feel<strong> </strong>unsteady, or lose balance, from time to time, ask your doctor to check all your body systems that can affect balance. Along with muscle and bone problems, unsteadiness can also result from poor blood pressure, inner-ear problems, nervous system issues and more.</p>
<p>Maybe you do not have unsteadiness but wonder about your skill at balancing. You can test yourself easily and at home to find out if you need any medical intervention.</p>
<p>Stand next to a wall or something that can provide support if needed. Raise one leg. Can you hold that position for 10 seconds? Now try the other leg. If you can stand on each leg alone for 10 seconds, you should be fine, said Greg W. Hartley, a professor of physical therapy specializing in geriatrics at the University of Miami in Florida.</p>
<p>"If you can't do that, then you should probably go see a physical therapist," he said. A physical therapist treats people with conditions or injuries that affect body movement.</p>
<p>Another at-home test is called TUG, for "timed up and go." Hartley suggests doing this test with supervision. You begin the test from a seated position. Then, stand up and start a timer immediately. Walk three meters, turn and walk back to your seat. Stop the timer as soon as you sit down. If the test takes you longer to complete than 15 seconds, your risk for falling is very high. But, if you do it in 12 seconds or less, your fall risk is almost zero.</p>
<p>Also, <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.ncoa.org/tools/falls-free-checkup/">The National Council on Aging offers an online set of questions</a> to predict your risk of a fall.</p>
<p><strong>What can I do to improve balance?</strong></p>
<p>Because muscle mass lessens in most people during their 30s, geriatricians say the best way to keep good balance is to stay physically active throughout life. Anmolsingh says it is never too late to act on that advice.</p>
<p>Activities including<strong> tai chi</strong> and <strong>yoga </strong>are good for older adults because they involve controlled movements while <strong>shifting</strong> body weight. There also are simpler exercises people can work into their everyday lives.</p>
<p>Anmolsingh says standing on one foot while waiting in line at a store is good. Or, at home, sit down and stand up several times straight without using a support. Another easy exercise is the three-way leg lift. Hold on to a support, then lift a leg to the front, then to the side and then to the back.</p>
<p><strong>How often should I do the exercises?</strong></p>
<p>The National Institute of Aging says people should spend at least 150 minutes per week in general physical activity to improve balance and overall health.</p>
<p>Hartley said exercises done on a usual basis help train the brain to react correctly when you start to fall.</p>
<p>"Just like an athlete needs to do repetition to train for a sport, you're doing repetition to train for everyday balance activities," he said.</p>
<p>I'm Jill Robbins.</p>
<p><em>Albert Stumm reported this story for the Associated Press.</em><em> Jill Robbins adapted it for Learning English. </em></p>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>misconception</strong> – <em>n</em>. a wrong or mistaken idea</p>
<p><strong>tai chi </strong>- <em>n</em>. a Chinese form of exercise that uses very slow and controlled movements</p>
<p><strong>yoga</strong> – <em>n</em>. a system of exercises for mental and physical health</p>
<p><strong>shift</strong> – <em>v</em>. to move or to cause (something or someone) to move to a different place, or position</p>
<p><strong>athlete</strong> – <em>n</em>. a person who is trained in or good at sports, games, or exercises that require physical skill and strength</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Researchers Use Lasers to Study Ancient Peruvian Mummies   (2025/1/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/researchers-use-lasers-to-study-ancient-peruvian-mummies.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>For more than 5,000 years, humans have covered themselves with permanent artistic designs known as tattoos.</p>
<p>In a recent study, researchers used lasers to uncover highly complex designs of ancient tattoos on <strong>mummies </strong>from Peru.</p>
<p>The skin of the mummies and the black liquid, or ink, used to make the tattoos permitted researchers to observe fine details. These marks are not <strong>visible</strong> to the human eye, said study co-writer Michael Pittman of the Chinese University of Hong Kong.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This August 2024 photo provided by researchers shows a mummified human from Peru's Chancay culture. (Tom Kaye via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/ba4e6410-471c-4273-9ddd-20ed618142ee_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This August 2024 photo provided by researchers shows a mummified human from Peru's Chancay culture. (Tom Kaye via AP)</span></div>
<p>The researchers examined around 100 mummies dating to around 775 years ago. The mummies were from coastal Peru's Chancay culture, which grew and developed before the Inca empire and the arrival of Europeans.</p>
<p>All the individuals had some form of tattoos on the back of their hands, knuckles, arms or other body parts. The study paid careful attention to four individuals with “<strong>exceptional</strong> tattoos” — designs of shapes such as triangles and diamonds, said Pittman.</p>
<p>It was not clear how the tattoos were created. But they are “of a quality that stands up against the really good electric tattooing of today,” said Aaron Deter-Wolf of the Tennessee Division of Archaeology. Deter-Wolf was not involved in the research.</p>
<p>The study results appeared recently in the publication <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.2421517122" target="_blank">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</a>.</p>
<p>Using lasers that make skin <strong>glow</strong>, “we basically turn skin into a <strong>light bulb</strong>,” said study co-writer Tom Kaye of the nonprofit Foundation for Scientific Advancement based in Sierra Vista, Arizona.</p>
<p>The findings were “helpful to learn about new non-destructive technologies that can help us study and document sensitive archaeological materials,” such as mummies, said Deter-Wolf.</p>
<p>The oldest known tattoos ever discovered are on the remains of a Neolithic man who lived in the Italian Alps around five thousand years ago. Many mummies from ancient Egypt also have tattoos, as do remains from cultures around the world.</p>
<p>People have used tattooing for many reasons throughout history. The marks can show cultural or individual identity, social standing, and more. Tattoos also have been used for protection against disease or to deepen relationships with spirits or gods, suggested Lars Krutak. Krutak, who works at the Museum of International Folk Art in Santa Fe, New Mexico, was not involved in the research.</p>
<p>Designs on ancient <strong>textile</strong> and stone products are more commonly found in good condition for study than are ancient tattoos. But ancient tattoos when studied can provide information about art forms that would not otherwise be available, suggested Martin Smith of Bournemouth University. Smith was not involved in the recent study.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Christina Larson reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>mummy</strong><em> – n.</em> human remains that are in good condition or very well preserved</p>
<p><strong>visible</strong> <em>– adj.</em> capable of being seen</p>
<p><strong>exceptional</strong> <em>– adj.</em> superior, rare, much better than average</p>
<p><strong>glow</strong> <em>– v. </em>to shine as if filled with light</p>
<p><strong>light bulb</strong><em> – n.</em> an electric lamp</p>
<p><strong>textile</strong> <em>– n</em>. woven cloth, fibers, or yarn</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Two New Private Spacecraft Launch to the Moon  (2025/1/20)</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/two-new-private-spacecraft-launch-to-the-moon.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Bryan Lynn</span><br/><span class="datetime">19 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Two private spacecraft are on their way to the moon to carry out separate <strong>missions</strong>.</p>
<p>The landers launched January 15 from the American government's Kennedy Space Center in Florida. The private company SpaceX used its Falcon 9 launch vehicle to fly the landers into space. The two separated from Falcon 9 about one hour into the flight.</p>
<p>Mission leaders said the launch went exactly as planned, with no problems reported. The trip to the moon will take some time. One spacecraft is expected to land on the <strong>lunar</strong> surface in early March, while the other should touch down in late May or early June.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket lifts off from pad 39A with a payload of a pair of lunar landers at the Kennedy Space Center in Cape Canaveral, Fla., Wednesday, Jan. 15, 2025. (AP Photo/John Raoux)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/f1a72312-cf15-428d-85fe-f619ae15b872_cx0_cy2_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket lifts off from pad 39A with a payload of a pair of lunar landers at the Kennedy Space Center in Cape Canaveral, Fla., Wednesday, Jan. 15, 2025. (AP Photo/John Raoux)</span></div>
<p>In February 2024, the first private spacecraft completed the first U.S. moon landing in more than 50 years. The lander, called Odysseus, was developed by the Texas-based company Intuitive Machines. The spacecraft experienced some technical problems but was able to carry out several science experiments before powering down permanently on the moon in late March.</p>
<p>For this current mission, Texas-based Firefly Aerospace developed Blue Ghost, one of the two landers launched. The other, named Resilience, belongs to Japanese company ispace. Both are designed to collect data and materials to support several planned moon missions – some including astronauts – in coming years.</p>
<p>The Blue Ghost lander is targeting a landing site near a volcanic structure called Mons Latreille. It is a 480-kilometer basin that sits in the northeast quarter of the near side of the moon.</p>
<p>The American space agency NASA says the 2-meter-tall Blue Ghost is carrying 10 NASA science and technology instruments. They aim to “gather valuable scientific data studying Earth's nearest neighbor,” the agency said.</p>
<p>NASA's Artemis program aims to send astronauts to the moon for the first time since the Apollo 17 mission in 1972. The next planned flight in that program is <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.nasa.gov/mission/artemis-ii/">Artemis II</a>, which is set to launch in April 2026. In that mission, four astronauts will fly NASA's Orion spacecraft more than 400,000 kilometers on a trip around the moon.</p>
<p>Nicola Fox is the associate administrator for NASA's Science Mission Directorate in Washington D.C. She said in a statement the agency's cooperation with private companies is “a critical part of bringing humanity back to the moon.”</p>
<p>Fox added that NASA chose the new experiments partly because of information learned from NASA's Apollo space program, which began in the 1960s. She said the current mission seeks to ensure “the safety and health of our future science instruments, spacecraft, and, most importantly, our astronauts on the lunar surface.”</p>
<p>Blue Ghost's equipment includes a tool to collect dirt and another to dig a hole for measuring temperatures below the lunar surface. The spacecraft is also carrying a device built to measure light <strong>reflections</strong> to be used with lasers to better measure the distance between Earth and the moon.</p>
<p>In addition, Blue Ghost is carrying instruments to examine the structure and density of areas beneath the lunar surface. Other equipment will seek to capture X-ray images of the edge of Earth's magnetic field.</p>
<p>The ispace lander Resilience is carrying an exploring vehicle, called a rover, to the moon. The five-kilogram rover is designed to collect lunar soil and other materials from the surface.</p>
<p>Resilience is also <a class="wsw__a" href="https://ispace-inc.com/news-en/?p=6795">carrying equipment and instruments</a> to complete several experiments for Japanese companies and other organizations. One of the experiments will test an <strong>electrolysis</strong> device designed to separate water into hydrogen and oxygen. Such a device could help future astronauts better use water resources on the moon and produce rocket fuel.</p>
<p>Other experiments set for the Resilience mission include food production tests and the deployment of a “deep space radiation probe.” The instrument is designed to collect detailed measurements of <strong>ionizing</strong> radiation in space.</p>
<p>NASA has said it is paying $101 million to Firefly for the mission and another $44 million for the experiments. Officials from ispace did not report how much its mission would cost.</p>
<p>It is the second moon mission for ispace. During the last one, Japan's space agency JAXA successfully launched its SLIM spacecraft to the moon in January 2024. But the lander touched down imperfectly, causing some communication and power problems.</p>
<p>However, Japanese space officials reported they had stayed in communication with SLIM through late April. During this time, they said the spacecraft was able to collect valuable data about the landing and surrounding area.</p>
<p>I'm Bryan Lynn.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Lynn wrote this story for VOA Learning English, based on reports from NASA, The Associated Press and Agence France-Press</em></p>
<p><strong>______________________________________</strong></p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>mission </strong><em>– n. (space exploration) </em>the flight of a spacecraft to its target along with tasks expected to be carried out</p>
<p><strong>lunar </strong><em>– n. </em>of, relating to, or resembling the moon</p>
<p><strong>reflect </strong><em>– v. </em>if a surface reflects heat, light, etc., it sends the light, etc. back and does not absorb it</p>
<p><strong>electrolysis </strong><em>– n. </em>use of an electric current to cause chemical change in a liquid</p>
<p><strong>ionize</strong><strong> </strong><em>– v. </em>to cause to form an ion: an atom or small group of atoms that has an electrical charge because it has added or lost one or more electrons</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Knee Jerk and Gut Reactions: When We Are Not in Control  (2025/1/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/knee-jerk-when-you-are-not-in-control.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>And now, <em>Words and Their Stories, </em>from VOA Learning English.</p>
<p>In life, some of our decisions and actions are well thought out. They involve research, examination, and time for thought. And other decisions and actions are not well thought out. We make them quickly, without thinking, almost like a pure physical reaction.</p>
<p>We can call these decisions, actions or reactions <u>knee-jerk</u><strong>.</strong></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Liberty Barros holds her Guinness World Records' certificate for achieving the fastest 20-meter back bend knee-lock walk in 22.53 seconds, in London, Britain, November 10, 2022. (REUTERS Photo/Maja Smiejkowska)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/000b0000-0aff-0242-eba6-08dac35060f3_cx0_cy10_cw0_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Liberty Barros holds her Guinness World Records' certificate for achieving the fastest 20-meter back bend knee-lock walk in 22.53 seconds, in London, Britain, November 10, 2022. (REUTERS Photo/Maja Smiejkowska)</span></div>
<p>This term comes from a medical process. Meriam Webster defines the noun "knee jerk" as “an <strong>involuntary </strong>forward kick produced by a light blow on the tendon below the kneecap.” It is an involuntary action. It's <strong>automatic.</strong></p>
<p>The words “involuntary” and “automatic” are important when understanding the term “knee jerk” and when to use it. Knee-jerk reactions seem to happen automatically without a decision-making process.</p>
<p>We often use “knee jerk” as an adjective.</p>
<p>Like hitting your kneecap to move your leg, knee-jerk reactions or statements also seem like an involuntary <strong>reflex</strong>.</p>
<p>"Knee jerk" also describes predictable<strong> </strong>behavior. Again, hit the knee, the leg will kick every time. So "knee jerk" describes someone who always reacts quickly and without enough thought.</p>
<p>For example, let's say you are on a team with someone who never faces responsibility for their mistakes in the game. If brought to account, the player always blames the dropped ball on other teammates. You can say that player is having a knee-jerk reaction to criticism. They have a <u>go-to</u> response. It's like a reflex they can't control.</p>
<p>We often use knee-jerk in a criticizing or <strong>negative </strong>way.</p>
<p>Now, a <u>gut reaction</u> also happens without thinking. But it is a bit different than a knee-jerk response. A gut reaction is a feeling. When we have a gut reaction, our <strong>instincts </strong>are telling us that something may not be right. Gut reactions are instinctual warnings.</p>
<p>So, we also use this expression a bit differently than "knee jerk." We usually talk about our own gut reactions or impulses, not others.</p>
<p>Here is an example:</p>
<p>One day, I was hiking on a mountain in California. I had hiked for about two hours and was near the top. The view, I was told, was truly beautiful. I couldn't wait to see it! Then, suddenly, I had a strange feeling. Something just didn't feel right. I can't explain why, but my gut instinct was to turn around and head back down the mountain. I later found out that a dangerous bear had been sighted in the same area that I had fled. I am so thankful I listened to my gut instinct.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Words and Their Stories</em>. Until next time, I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Anna Matteo wrote this story for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>__________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>involuntary </strong><em>-adj. </em>not normally under the control of the will</p>
<p><strong>automatic</strong> <em>-adj.</em> largely or wholly involuntary :acting or done without conscious thought or intention</p>
<p><strong>reflex </strong><em>-n. </em>an automatic response to a stimulus in which a nerve message passes from a sense organ to the spinal cord and then to a point of action (as a muscle or gland) often without first passing to the brain</p>
<p><strong>negative </strong><em>-adj. </em>not positive or helpful</p>
<p><strong>instinct </strong><em>-n. </em>behavior that is based on automatic actions</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>The Inauguration of the US President Through Time  (2025/1/19)</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/the-inauguration-of-the-us-president-through-time.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Mario Ritter, Jr.</span><br/><span class="datetime">18 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>On January 20, the United States president is sworn into office in Washington D.C.</p>
<p>The inauguration is an important ceremony that officially marks the start of an administration. As part of the event, the incoming president speaks to the nation and announces U.S. policy goals.</p>
<p>This year, expanded security measures will stretch across much of Washington. The city's mayor, Muriel Bowser, announced major street closures and special transportation measures to increase security during inauguration events.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Security fencing surrounds Capitol Hill as snow blankets the region ahead of a joint session of Congress to certify the votes from the Electoral College in the presidential election, in Washington, Monday, Jan. 6, 2025. (AP Photo/J. Scott Applewhite)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/15bad3a6-524d-44d4-8c40-b9fd009973b9_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Security fencing surrounds Capitol Hill as snow blankets the region ahead of a joint session of Congress to certify the votes from the Electoral College in the presidential election, in Washington, Monday, Jan. 6, 2025. (AP Photo/J. Scott Applewhite)</span></div>
<p>The Associated Press reports Washington D.C.'s National Guard will deploy 7,800 soldiers to help with security. The Secret Service is reportedly under additional pressure because of two attempts on the life of incoming President Donald Trump last year. In one of those attempts, Trump received minor injuries.</p>
<p>The Library of Congress has saved many historical documents and objects from past ceremonies. Here are some facts and firsts about U.S. presidential inaugurations:</p>
<p><strong>Inaugural firsts: </strong></p>
<p>George Washington did not take the <strong>oath </strong>to become the first U.S. president in January nor was the event held in Washinton, D.C. His first inaugural <strong>address </strong>was given to a joint session of Congress gathered in Federal Hall in New York City, on April 30, 1789. New York City was the nation's first capital.</p>
<p>Washington began a tradition that stood for many years of kissing The Bible after taking the oath of office. The Museum of the Bible <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.museumofthebible.org/book-minute/washingtons-inauguration" target="_blank">says</a> on its website that four other presidents – Warren Harding,</p>
<p>Dwight Eisenhower, Jimmy Carter and George H. W. Bush – used Washington's Bible in their ceremonies. Bush had hoped to use Washington's Bible for his first inauguration in 2001, but weather delayed shipping so he ended up using a family Bible instead.</p>
<p>Washington's second inaugural address set another mark: it was the shortest at 135 words.</p>
<p>For 144 years, the inauguration was not held in the winter, but mostly in March.</p>
<p>John Adams, the nation's second president, was the first to receive the oath from the Chief Justice of the U.S. Supreme Court. His swearing in took place in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, the nation's second capital.</p>
<p>Thomas Jefferson was the first president to be inaugurated in Washington, D.C. He walked to and from the ceremony instead of riding in a <strong>carriage</strong>. The U.S. Marine Band played at the event for the first time and has done so in every ceremony since.</p>
<p>In 1825, John Quincy Adams, son of John Adams, broke with tradition. He was the first president to long wear pants instead of traditional shorter pants with stockings. The man who replaced Adams, Andrew Jackson, was the first to receive the oath on the East Portico of the Capitol Building. John Quincy Adams refused to attend.</p>
<p>In 1837, Martin Van Buren was the first of a new generation of presidents to not have British ancestry. His parents were Dutch and he was born a citizen of the United States.</p>
<p>William Henry Harrison set an unhappy first: On Inauguration Day in 1841, he gave the longest-ever speech without wearing warm clothes. He became sick and died weeks into his term.</p>
<p>Abraham Lincoln gave his first inaugural speech surrounded by heavy security as the nation neared war between the North and South. His second address, in 1865, was shortly after the end of the U.S. Civil War. He urged Americans “With <strong>malice</strong> towards none; with <strong>charity</strong> for all” to “<strong>bind up</strong> the nation's wounds.” In 2009 and 2013, Barrack Obama took his oath on Lincoln's Bible.</p>
<p>In 1909, William Howard Taft's inauguration was notable for taking place inside the Senate Chamber because of a huge snowstorm. It took about 6,000 men to clear snow for the parade.</p>
<p>The inaugural ceremony of Calvin Coolidge in 1925 was the first to be broadcast on radio. And the first president to have a televised inaugural ceremony was Harry Truman in 1949.</p>
<p>Franklin D. Roosevelt's second inauguration was the first to take place on January 20th. The 20th Amendment to the Constitution moved the event's date because of improved transportation methods.</p>
<p>In 1953, Dwight Eisenhower broke the tradition of kissing The Bible and instead gave a prayer.</p>
<p>Robert Frost was the first poet to every speak at an inaugural event. Frost <strong>recited</strong> his poem <em>The Gift Outright</em> for John Kennedy's 1961 swearing-in. Kennedy was the first Roman Catholic president. Joe Biden was the second.</p>
<p>After Jimmy Carter's inauguration, he and first lady Rosalynn Carter walked down Washington D.C.'s Pennsylvania Avenue to the White House instead of riding inside a car.</p>
<p>Ronald Reagan's inaugurations set two marks that may also never be equaled. At noon on Reagan's first inauguration, the temperature was nearly 13 degrees Celsius. That was the warmest Inauguration Day ever. Then, on his second in January 1985, the temperature was nearly minus 14 degrees Celsius – the coldest day ever for the event.</p>
<p>This year, January 20 will mark only the second time a U.S. president has been inaugurated for a second term that did not follow the first. Donald Trump first took the oath of office in 2017. He joins Grover Cleveland, who was inaugurated in 1885 and 1893. Cleveland is known as the 22nd and 24th President. Trump is set to be both the 45th and 47th President of the United States.</p>
<p>I'm Mario Ritter, Jr. And I'm Caty Weaver.</p>
<p><em>Mario Ritter, Jr. adapted this story for VOA Learning English from Library of Congress materials. </em></p>
<p>_______________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>oath</strong> <em>–n.</em> a public promise by a government official to fulfill his or her duty</p>
<p><strong>address </strong><em>–n.</em> a speech before a lot of people for a major event in public life</p>
<p><strong>carriage</strong> <em>–n.</em> a vehicle with wheels that is pulled by horses</p>
<p><strong>malice</strong> <em>–n.</em> a desire to cause harm to others</p>
<p><strong>charity</strong> <em>–n. </em>the willingness to give to others with a good heart</p>
<p><strong>bind up </strong><em>–v. (phrasal)</em> to wrap a wound in cloth or a bandage so it will heal</p>
<p><strong>recite</strong> <em>–v.</em> to give a speech or reading of a written work from memory and not to read it</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>What Is Art Deco and Why Is It Popular Again?  (2025/1/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/what-is-art-deco-and-why-is-it-popular-again.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>Art Deco is an international artistic <strong>style</strong> that was popular in the 1920s and 1930s.</p>
<p>Now, interest in the style and its qualities is growing. A new generation is enjoying the style's roots and turning it into something new.</p>
<p>A public showing, or exhibition, at the Museum of the City of New York provides a look at the style that helped define the city 100 years ago.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt=" This image provided by the Museum of the City of New York shows a postcard featuring the Empire State Building, from left, the RCA Building, and the Chrysler Building. (Museum of the City of New York via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/109dd6c2-c5fb-4357-ac6b-7c78d81c96af_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption"> This image provided by the Museum of the City of New York shows a postcard featuring the Empire State Building, from left, the RCA Building, and the Chrysler Building. (Museum of the City of New York via AP)</span></div>
<p>Famous Art Deco buildings include the Chrysler Building, the Empire State Building, Rockefeller Center and Radio City Music Hall.</p>
<p>The public showing, called “Art Deco City: New York Postcards from the Leonard A. Lauder Collection,” also has clothing and film clips from the time.</p>
<p>In London, the Victoria and Albert Museum has a collection of day and evening clothing, jewelry and more. The collection comes from Les Ballets Russes, a dance company that had a major effect on <strong>fashion</strong>.</p>
<p>And in Paris, organizers of the 2024 Olympics created Art Deco <strong>posters</strong> last year to celebrate the games and mark the one hundred years since the 1924 Olympics, which Paris also hosted.</p>
<p><strong>A style of the 1920s and 30s </strong></p>
<p>Experts have different opinions about Art Deco. Design writer Arricca Elin Sansone, for example, said last year in Elle Décor magazine: “Ask three historians to define the term Art Deco, and you'll likely get three <strong>varying</strong> answers.”</p>
<p>Appearing after World War I, the first Art Deco era had a spirit of creativity and freedom. With the aim of appearing modern, the style became one of the most important forms of design in the 1920s and early 1930s.</p>
<p>The Art Deco style is believed to have first appeared at the 1925 International Exhibition of Modern Decorative and Industrial Arts, in Paris.</p>
<p>The early 1930s saw the development of the style in Miami where South Beach's Art Deco District is popular with visitors and a center for design.</p>
<p>In some large cities, low-rise buildings of two or three floors turned into landscapes of high-rise skyscrapers. Public and private spaces showed <strong>themes</strong> involving geometrical designs and luxurious materials.</p>
<p>In transportation, faster cars and better trains suggested a new age while jazz music urged people to celebrate.</p>
<p><strong>“A fashionable renaissance” </strong></p>
<p>The same energy can be found in today's fashion shows and red-carpet events for stars. Some of today's colorful clothing suggests the Jazz Age, another name for the period when Art Deco was popular. Stars like Zendaya, Gigi Hadid, Beyoncé and Demi Lovato have used elements of the Deco era in new ways.</p>
<p>“The aesthetic of the 1920s is enjoying a fashionable renaissance,” said Kirsty Thatcher of the Australian fashion magazine Russh. A “renaissance” represents a rebirth of something from the past.</p>
<p>New York-based interior designer Vanessa DeLeon told the Associated Press, “The boldness and elegance of Art Deco are what appeals to me.”</p>
<p>Jamie Watkins and Tom Kennedy of the London design company Divine Savages include Art Deco elements in their collections of products for the home. Watkins suggested: “It's no wonder we're drawn to it again.”</p>
<p>Lynda Klich is the co-organizer or curator of the exhibition at the Museum of the City of New York. Klich noted that postcards were the social media of their day. Travelers at the time busily wrote messages to friends and family. New York's famous Art Deco buildings appear in over 250 postcards. There is also a selection of clothing from the 1920s, shoes and other objects.</p>
<p>“Art Deco was the look that sold the city to the world,” said co-curator Lilly Tuttle.</p>
<p>The exhibition in New York City runs through February 17.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Kim Cook reported on this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>style </strong><em>–n. </em>a particular form of design that is repeated through a period because it is popular</p>
<p><strong>fashion </strong><em>– n.</em> the popular or dominant style (as in clothing or dress) during a particular time</p>
<p><strong>poster</strong> <em>–n.</em> a large picture that is often used to advertise for a show or movie</p>
<p><strong>vary</strong> <em>– v. </em> to have or show differences between items or things</p>
<p><strong>theme </strong><em>– n.</em> a special quality or characteristic; a subject or topic of artistical representation</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>Apply and Application  (2025/1/18)</title>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/apply-and-application.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Andrew Smith</span><br/><span class="datetime">17 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>This week on <em>Ask a Teacher</em>, we answer a question from Krystyna in Poland. Here is Krystyna's question:</p>
<p><em>Dear Teacher,<br/>
I would like to know of different ways to use words such as “apply” and “application” for getting jobs or other purposes.</em></p>
<p><em>Thank you, </em><em>Krystyna</em><em>.</em></p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="Ask a Teacher: Apply and Application" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/2ca81581-0bba-4ddd-b3f5-fd0855406dac_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">Ask a Teacher: Apply and Application</span></div>
<p>I'm happy to answer this question, Krystyna.</p>
<p>The word “apply” is a verb, and the word “application” is a noun. We can use both words when discussing the process of looking for a job.</p>
<p>We say we “apply for a job” when we go through the official process of asking an employer for work. To do this, we usually have to complete a job application. The application is a <strong>form</strong>, either online or on paper, that gives the employer information about the person applying for the job.</p>
<p>We commonly use the phrasal verb “fill out” to express the act of completing an application. Consider the following examples:</p>
<p><em>You must fill out this application first. </em></p>
<p><em>Did you fill out the application?</em></p>
<p>While we say “apply for” when trying to get a job, we say “apply to” when we are trying to get accepted into a school or other program, as in the following example:</p>
<p><em>She applied to three medical schools in California. </em></p>
<p>However, we say “apply for” when we are trying to get financial aid or special awards.</p>
<p>The expression “apply to” also has another meaning. It can mean that something relates to something else, or that something is true for all people or things. Listen to the following examples:</p>
<p><em>The new rule only applies to people who work more than 40 hours each week.</em></p>
<p><em>The right of freedom of speech should apply to all citizens. </em></p>
<p>The word “application” has other meanings besides a form people fill out. Among these is a computer program that does a specific task, or kind of work. From this meaning, we get the term “Apps,” which we use in our smartphones and computers.</p>
<p>There also is another expression with the verb “apply.” If you “apply yourself,” that means that you are working hard over a period of time to complete a project or develop a skill.</p>
<p>For our readers and listeners, what are your questions about American English? Are you applying yourself to your study of English? We want to hear from you! Send us an email at <a class="wsw__a" href="21voa.com">21voa.com</a>. And please let us know where you are from, too.</p>
<p>And that's <em>Ask a Teacher</em>.</p>
<p>I'm Andrew Smith.<em> </em></p>
<p><em>Andrew Smith wrote this lesson for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>form </strong>–n. a document or application that people add information to for official use</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>People in China Swim in Freezing River for Health, Happiness  (2025/1/17)</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/people-in-china-swim-in-freezing-river-for-health-happiness.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By Anna Matteo</span><br/><span class="datetime">16 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>From VOA Learning English, this is the Health &amp; Lifestyle report.</p>
<p>Even as temperatures kept dropping in China's northeastern “ice city” of Harbin, excitement rose among a group of swimmers who enjoy jumping into freezing waters.</p>
<p>The daily event, known as ice swimming, is a winter tradition in Harbin. Swimmers train daily throughout the year to get their bodies ready for the unusual swim. Reporters from The Associated Press recently visited the city and spoke with some of the swimmers.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="A woman jumps into a pool cut from the ice on the Songhua River in Harbin in northeastern China's Heilongjiang province, Tuesday, Jan. 7, 2025. (AP Photo/Andy Wong)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/6d1a4494-79e3-42ba-ab34-b82c042182c8_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">A woman jumps into a pool cut from the ice on the Songhua River in Harbin in northeastern China's Heilongjiang province, Tuesday, Jan. 7, 2025. (AP Photo/Andy Wong)</span></div>
<p>To create a pool in the Songhua River, the swimmers first had to break a 10-centimeter thick cover of ice. Then they removed the ice pieces, took off all clothes except bathing suits and prepared to enter. One by one, they jumped into a freezing, 10-meter-long pool.</p>
<p>Some of the swimmers reported that their legs and arms quickly went <strong>numb</strong> after entering the water. The outside temperature was about minus 13 degrees Celsius and the water temperature remained near freezing.</p>
<p>One of the swimmers was Chen Xia. She came from Zhejiang province about 1,700 kilometers <strong>further </strong>south. She decided to jump into the river even though she had a cold. Chen said the winter waters where she lives are warmer than those in Harbin.</p>
<p>She said the experience strengthened her <strong>confidence</strong> in winter swimming. She has been taking part in the activity for about 20 years.</p>
<p>The 56-year-old Chen said the freezing waters made her skin feel like small <strong>pins </strong>were attacking her body. But, she added that the experience still brought her happiness. “I felt <strong>prickling</strong> all over my body. But it still made me feel <strong>blissful,</strong>” she said.</p>
<p>Yu Xiaofeng lives in Harbin, a city that sits near the border with Russia. The 61-year-old said winter swimming in the city dates back to the 1970s. At that time, locals saw Russian Orthodox religious believers being <strong>baptized </strong>in the river. Later in 1983, an official winter swimming group was established in Harbin.</p>
<p>The city also holds an ongoing winter celebration known for its huge, detailed ice and snow <strong>sculptures.</strong></p>
<p>Winter swimming is considered a sport in China. But it gained popularity much faster in Harbin than in other parts of the country. Today, Yu said the city is considered a “holy land” for winter swimming.</p>
<p>Yu said the winter swimmers appear to have better health than others. She added that she has felt a great sense of family and joy in the community during her 30 years of winter swimming.</p>
<p><a class="wsw__a" name="_Hlk187425130">While the AP reporters did not <strong>quote</strong> medical experts for this story, some of the swimmers said they believe ice swimming is good for their health. During the COVID-19 pandemic, the group even came up with a new saying to describe the experience. They would rather “suffer through winter swimming than line up at the hospital,” Yu said. </a></p>
<p>You Decang is a 76-year-old winter swimmer who said he believes the activity helps keep him healthy. He noted that he has never caught a cold. You added, “If I go just one day without winter swimming, I feel quite <strong>uncomfortable</strong>.”</p>
<p>And that's the Health &amp; Lifestyle report. I'm Anna Matteo.</p>
<p><em>Andy Wong reported this story for The Associated Press. Olivia Zhang and Caroline Chen contributed to this report. Anna Matteo adapted it for VOA Learning English.</em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story</strong></h2>
<p><strong>numb </strong><em>–v. </em>to cause (a part of the body) to lose sensation</p>
<p><strong>further </strong><em>–adj.</em> going or extending beyond</p>
<p><strong>confidence </strong><em>-n. </em>a feeling or consciousness of one's powers or of reliance on one's circumstances</p>
<p><strong>pin </strong><em>–n. </em>a piece of wood, metal, or plastic used especially for fastening things together or for hanging one thing from another</p>
<p><strong>prickling</strong> <em>–v. </em>to cause or feel a slight stinging or tingling sensation : <strong>prickle</strong> <em>–n. </em>a tingling sensation</p>
<p><strong>blissful </strong><em>–adj.</em> full of, marked by, or causing complete happiness</p>
<p><strong>baptize </strong><em>–v. </em>to dip in water or sprinkle water on as a part of the ceremony of receiving into the Christian church</p>
<p><strong>sculpture </strong><em>–n. </em>a three-dimensional work of art (such as a statue)</p>
<p><strong>quote </strong><em>–v. </em>to speak or write (a passage) from another usually with credit acknowledgment</p>
<p><strong>uncomfortable </strong><em>–adj.</em> feeling discomfort</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
          <item>
            <title>European and Japanese Spacecraft Examines Mercury’s Pole   (2025/1/16)</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure type="audio/mpeg" url="https://files.21voa.com/audio/202501/european-and-japanese-spacecraft-examines-mercury-s-pole.mp3"/>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content"><span class="byline">By John Russell</span><br/><span class="datetime">15 January, 2025</span><br/>
<p>A spacecraft recently sent back some of the best close-up pictures yet of the planet Mercury's north pole.</p>
<p>The European and Japanese robotic explorer went as close as 295 kilometers above Mercury's night side before passing directly over the planet's north pole.</p>
<p>The European Space Agency (ESA) released images that show craters with deep <strong>shadows</strong> on our solar system's smallest planet.</p><div class="contentImage"><img alt="This image provided by European Space Agency shows close-up photos of Mercury showing northern plains taken by the European-Japanese spacecraft BepiColombo. (European Space Agency via AP)" src="https://files.21voa.com/gdb/1b134ccd-29d1-420d-ba79-2a92b79db447_w268_r1.jpg"/><br/><span class="imagecaption">This image provided by European Space Agency shows close-up photos of Mercury showing northern plains taken by the European-Japanese spacecraft BepiColombo. (European Space Agency via AP)</span></div>
<p><a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.esa.int/Science_Exploration/Space_Science/BepiColombo/Top_three_images_from_BepiColombo_s_sixth_Mercury_flyby" target="_blank">ESA noted</a> that the edges, or rims, of the <strong>craters</strong> called Prokofiev, Kandinsky, Tolkien and Gordimer create permanent shadows. As a result, these unlit craters are some of the coldest places in the Solar System even though Mercury is the closest planet to the sun.</p>
<p>Cameras also took images of neighboring volcanic plains known as Borealis Planitia. <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.esa.int/Science_Exploration/Space_Science/BepiColombo/Top_three_images_from_BepiColombo_s_sixth_Mercury_flyby" target="_blank">ESA noted</a> that these are “Mercury's largest <strong>expanse</strong> of ‘smooth plains' and were formed by the widespread <strong>eruption</strong> of...lava 3.7 billion years ago.”</p>
<p>Also appearing in the images released by ESA is Mercury's largest impact crater, the Caloris Basin, which covers more than 1,500 kilometers.</p>
<p>This was the sixth and final flyby of Mercury for the BepiColombo spacecraft since its launch in 2018. The recent move put the spacecraft on a path to enter orbit around Mercury late next year. The spacecraft holds two orbiters, one from Europe and the other from Japan, that will circle the planet's poles.</p>
<p>In a statement <a class="wsw__a" href="https://www.esa.int/Science_Exploration/Space_Science/BepiColombo" target="_blank">on its website</a>, ESA noted that Mercury, a small, dry planet, is “the least explored planet of the inner Solar System. Learning more about Mercury will<strong> shed light</strong> on the history of the entire Solar System.”</p>
<p>The spacecraft is named for the late Giuseppe (Bepi) Colombo, an Italian mathematician. Colombo played a part in NASA's Mariner 10 mission to Mercury in the 1970s and, 20 years later, in the Italian Space Agency's special satellite project that flew on the U.S. Space Shuttle.</p>
<p>I'm John Russell.</p>
<p><em>Marcia Dunn reported this story for the Associated Press. John Russell adapted it for VOA Learning English. </em></p>
<p>___________________________________________</p>
<h2 class="wsw__h2"><strong>Words in This Story </strong></h2>
<p><strong>shadow </strong><em>– v. </em>to cast a shadow (a dark figure cast upon a surface when a body blocks the rays of a light)</p>
<p><strong>crater</strong> <em>– n.</em> a low area or depression formed by an impact</p>
<p><strong>expanse </strong><em>– n.</em> a great extent or distance of something that is spread out</p>
<p><strong>erupt</strong> <em>– v. </em>to force out or release suddenly (often lava or steam that is pent up)</p>
<p><strong>shed light </strong><em>–idiom </em>to expand or increase knowledge</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
          </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
